<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Translation of the Dunhuang Star Chart (Or.8210/S.3326)</title><author>Imre Galambos</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First edition</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>International Dunhuang Project</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>2009</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Electronic</p><bibl><ref>Galambos_2009</ref></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc>Translation</projectDesc></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><head><p>This is a translation of the text of the manuscript Or.8210/S.3326. It starts from the first entry which contains continuous text and ends with the author’s note at the end of this section. The second part is the technical text accompanying the astronomical charts. The parts where the manuscript is worn and illegible are marked in square brackets; I marked such places with missing text dots inside the brackets: [...]. Where the missing text could be reconstructed on the basis of the context, I
 included the translation within the brackets.</p></head><body><msDescription n="1"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">Or.8210/S.3326</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><q lang="eng"><p>Whenever [...] day, at midnight examining the four directions; when
                                this cloud is present, the land will be inundated with great water
                                and the hundred rivers will overflow. Wu Xian says that this is the
                                vapour of the essence of the sea. When the sea moves its vapour, in
                                the place where following this the cloud is seen, there will
                                inevitably be a great flood, the hundred rivers will overflow, the
                                people will lose their homes, the dead will outnumber the living,
                                their white bones will fill the gullies and ravines.</p><p>Whenever this vapour is present in villages and towns, those who see
                                it will inevitably go through a great mourning; troops and weapons
                                will fill the land, blood will flow like a river. Fan Zeng says that
                                this is the vapour of the cruel general. If it is seen, underneath
                                troops will inevitably gather.”</p><p>Whenever this vapour is present in [villages] and towns, those who
                                see it will not move [...], and underneath it will be the one is to
                                rise to the throne. Wu Xian says that his land will inevitably
                                produce one of the highest ministers or someone from here will
                                receive the title of a prince.</p><p>Whenever a five-colour vapour is seen above someone’s house and it
                                remains there steadily during the last days of the month, the first
                                day of the following one [...] morning, and if [the vapour above]
                                the house has mostly greenish-blue, this is the vapour of a dead
                                body; if mostly red, it is the vapour of gold and jade; if mostly
                                yellow, this house will go through extensive renovation works; if
                                mostly white, this land has copper and iron; if mostly black, this
                                house will serve as the abode of the divine spirit (shen).</p><p>Whenever there is an irregular vapour over [...], there will
                                inevitably be a treasure underneath. The five colours [...] — the
                                [...] colour means metal and copper; red means jade; [...] colour
                                means [...], [...] colour means the presence of golden treasure
                                hidden underneath the house, not deeper than three zhang and [not
                                shallower] than eight chi. [If looked for it,] the treasure will
                                certainly be found.</p><p>Whenever there is a five-colour vapour inside [...], and it appears
                                mostly greenish-blue, this means a dragon; mostly red means a
                                thousand [...] as odd; mostly yellow means that a dragon is hidden
                                inside it; mostly white means death and mourning. Chen Ping says
                                that whosoever’s family is about to be annihilated, his gates will
                                mostly have black colour: his home will be exterminated by robbers
                                and bandits within one year.</p><p>Lü Buwei said that whenever you approach a mound on a plain and there
                                is vapour in the shape of a thousand zhang long staff reaching high
                                up into the sky, straight and vertical; if it is yellow, it is the
                                colour of the Son of Heaven; blue, red, white and black all mean
                                that there shall be tears and grief. Your servant Chunfeng says that
                                such towns will inevitably produce dukes and knights. If its colour
                                is greenish-blue it means illness; white means that a war will break
                                out; black means that the towns will be flooded with robbers and
                                thieves.</p><p>Whenever vapours are present in towns, the examiner may divine them
                                according to their colour. If it is mostly greenish-blue, this is
                                the vapour of the highest ministers; if mostly red, the vapour of
                                the prefect (taishou); if mostly yellow, the vapour of [...]. If it
                                has more white, then underneath there is a great worthy or saint. If
                                it has more black, then beneath there is a hidden dragon and if it
                                does not come out, in one hundred days there will be a flood
                                disaster.</p><p>Whenever there a white vapour is present at common people’s houses,
                                and it appears inside the house, this is a scattered vapour and
                                means that grave illness will strike; if its colour is murky black
                                and it covers the top of the house, then someone from the family
                                will die in battle. If not, then the whole family will be
                                annihilated.</p><p>Whenever a vapour is present inside someone’s home and garden, and it
                                is in the form of a leaping or crouching wolf or tiger, the family
                                will certainly bear a son who will become a general and will be
                                conferred a rank of nobility. This will happen within three
                                years.</p><p>Whenever a man travels traverses rivers and uncultivated territories
                                and this vapour is present, if he sees a red vapour in the shape of
                                a [...], this means an old tomb of a monarch: it definitely cannot
                                be crossed. This vapour means certain death within three years.</p><p>When in the wilderness this vapour is seen, shaped like a pagoda,
                                underneath there inevitably be a cache of silver, not deeper than
                                three zhang and not shallower than two zhang.</p><p>If between the trees of the forest a red vapour is seen in the shape
                                of vines creeping up the tree, this is a creeping vapour. It has
                                already been discussed by Fan Zeng who says that wherever it creeps
                                up, underneath this place there is copper; if not, then coins. Mozi
                                says that this is a vapour of golden treasure.</p><p>Whenever you proceed through a forest at the hill of a mountain,
                                there may be a white vapour rolling in and out. This has already
                                been discussed by Mozi, according to whom this means that underneath
                                this place are jade ornaments. Lü Buwei says that there are jade
                                objects underneath. Chen Ping says that there is gold
                                underneath.</p><p>Whenever somebody traverses a mountain and sees that a white vapour
                                is present in the shape of a person, he definitely should not pass
                                through. This vapour will affect the man and straight away kill him.
                                He should wait for the day with a correct vapour and then the
                                destruction can be averted. Underneath there inevitably be some
                                treasure, which is also called [...]. See this in Chen Ping’s
                                Zhoulun.</p><p>If when traversing a mountain you see a black vapour as if covering
                                the place from the top, underneath there will be a hidden current:
                                the spring will be not deeper than two zhang and not shallower than
                                eight chi. If you search for it, you will inevitably find a spring.
                                Fan Zeng says that what is explained here is that underneath there
                                is a non-flowing spring. See this in Mozi.</p><p>Whenever a man traverses a mountain and sees that a white vapour is
                                present in the shape of a sword, there will inevitably be weapons
                                underneath. You will certainly find them if you look for them. See
                                this also in Lü Buwei.</p><p>I have formerly joined together the above forty-eight entries on
                                vapour divination. My own experiments showed them to be reliable,
                                this is why I recorded them. I did not dare to include in this
                                scroll the ones I have not tested for divination. Disregarding my
                                ignorance and incapacity, with foolish enthusiasm I dared to collect
                                and record these, all in the same manner as earlier entries. [...]
                                My apologies, this is all my fault!</p></q></msItem><msItem n="2"><q lang="eng"><p>From Nü 8° to Wei 15°. This is associated with the terrestial branch
                                zi, and is called Xuanxiao, or Dark Emptiness. Dark means black,
                                this is the colour of North; Emptiness means exhaustion. In the 11th
                                month the Yang vapours descend and the Yin vapours ascend, the
                                myriad things are dominated by darkness and death, there is no
                                living thing around, Heaven and Earth are bare and empty. This is
                                why it is called Dark Emptiness. This division corresponds to the
                                Kingdom of Qi.</p><p>From Wei 16° to Kui 4°. This is associated with the terrestial branch
                                hai, and is called Zouzi. Zouzi means to sigh. This division
                                corresponds to the Kingdom of Wei. From Kui 4° to Wei 6°. This is
                                associated with the terrestial branch xu, and is called Jianglou, or
                                Descending Warp. This division corresponds to the Kingdom of Zeng.
                                From Wei 7° to Bi 11°. This is associated with the terrestial branch
                                you, and is called Daliang, or Great Beam. Beam means strength. In
                                the 8th month the autumn dew starts to descend and the myriad things
                                because of this are solid, mature and strong. This is why it is
                                called Great Beam.</p><p>From Bi 12° to Jing 15°. This is associated with the terrestial
                                branch shen, and is called Shichen, or Full Sinking. In the 7th
                                month the myriad things are fully prospering, the Yin vapours are
                                heavy and sink downward, permeating the myriad things. This is why
                                it is called Full Sinking. This division corresponds to the Kingdom
                                of Wei. From Jing 16° to Liu 8°. This is associated with the
                                terrestial branch wei, and is called Chunshou, or Quail Head. The
                                seven southern constellations have the shape of a bird, with the
                                eight stars of the Jing signifying the head and the Liu the beak.
                                Head here refers to the [bird’s] head. This is why it is called
                                Quail Head. This division corresponds to the Kingdom of Qin.</p><p>From Liu 9° to Zhang 17°. This is associated with the terrestial
                                branch wu, and is called Chunhuo, or Quail Fire. The fire
                                corresponds to the South. In the 5th month the Yang vapours begin to
                                prosper, the Fire Star (i.e. Mars) obscures the seven central stars
                                at the place of the Vermillion Bird. This is why it is called Quail
                                Fire. This division corresponds to the Kingdom of Zhou.</p><p>From Zhang 18° to Zhen 1° (correctly should be 11°). This is
                                associated with the terrestial branch si, and is called Chunwei, or
                                Quail Tail. In the seven southern constellations forming the
                                Vermillion Bird, Zhen represents the tail. This is why it is called
                                Quail Tail. This division corresponds to the Kingdom of Chu.</p><p>From Zhen 12° [to Di 4°]. This is associated with the terrestial
                                branch chen, and is called Shouxing, or Life Star. In the 3rd month
                                the myriad things begin penetrating the Earth, the spring vapours
                                spread around and nurture the myriad things, and thus each fulfils
                                its inborn nature, without violating [the rules of] Heaven. This is
                                why it is called the Life Star. This division corresponds to the
                                Kingdom of Zheng.</p><p>From Di 5° to Wei 9°. This is associated with the terrestial branch
                                mao, and is called Dahuo, or Great Fire. East corresponds to wood,
                                and the Heart Star is associated with mao -- fire comes forth from
                                the heart (i.e. inside) of wood, this is why it is called Great
                                Fire. This division corresponds to the Kingdom of Song.</p><p>From Wei 10° to Dou 12° (correctly should be 11°). This is associated
                                with the terrestial branch yin, and is called is Simu, or Split
                                Wood. Wei in the East represents the end of the Wood constellation,
                                Dou in the North represents the beginning of the Water
                                constellation. This station is between the two of them, separating
                                water from wood, this is why it is called Split Wood. This division
                                corresponds to the Kingdom of Yan.</p><p>From Dou 12° to Xunü 7°. This is associated with the terrestial
                                branch chou, and is called Xingji, or Star Register. Star Register
                                refers to keeping track of the [beginning and] end of the myriad
                                things. This is why it is called Star Register. This division
                                corresponds to the Kingdom of Yue.</p></q></msItem></msContents></msDescription></body></text></TEI.2>
