<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title lang="eng">Twenty Favourite Things</title>
                <editor id="SW">Susan Whitfield</editor>
                <editor id="VS">Vic Swift</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>International Dunhuang Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                <date>2014</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>First edition</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Electronic</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>Catalogue</projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <head><p>As part of IDP's 20th anniversary celebrations in 2013–14 we asked twenty of our
                friends and supporters to select their favourite item from the IDP collections. All
                twenty contributions are reproduced here.</p></head>
        <body>
            <msDescription n="1">
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>Paris</settlement>
                    <repository>Bibliothèque nationale de France</repository>
                    <collection>Pelliot</collection>
                    <idno type="current">Pelliot chinois 4524</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <msItem n="1">
                        <author><name lang="eng">Victor H. Mair</name></author>
                        <note><p>Victor H. Mair is Professor of Chinese Language and Literature at
                                    the <link url="http://www.upenn.edu">University of
                                    Pennsylvania</link> in Philadelphia, USA. He has been teaching
                                there since 1979, before which he taught at <link
                                    url="http://www.harvard.edu">Harvard University</link>.
                                Professor Mair's interest in Central Asia stems mainly from his
                                studies of Dunhuang popular narratives, about which he has written
                                three books and dozens of articles. Developing out of his research
                                on Dunhuang <term lang="chi-Latn">biànwén</term> <term lang="chi-Hant">變文</term> (transformation
                                texts), he gradually moved into archaeological investigations on the
                                Bronze Age and Early Iron Age mummies of eastern Central Asia. In
                                conjunction with the latter extended project, he has travelled to
                                Xinjiang many times, hosted a major exhibition entitled <title
                                    lang="eng">Secrets of the Silk Road</title> in 2011 at the <link
                                    url="http://www.penn.museum">University of Pennsylvania
                                    Museum</link>, and has published numerous books and articles
                                about the mummies and their associated artefacts.</p>
                                </note>
                        <note><p>Victor H. Mair writes:</p>
                            <q><p>The picture scroll depicting the contest of magical conjurations
                                    between Śāriputra and the Six Heretics is my favourite of all
                                    objects from Dunhuang for many reasons. The most immediate
                                    reason is simply its innate charm, the pictures vividly
                                    capturing the excitement of the competition and the details of
                                    the individual scenes.</p><p>Above all, however, is the fact
                                    that this unique scroll holds the key to unlocking the
                                    relationship between pictorial and textual narrative that became
                                    a hallmark of popular fiction and drama in succeeding centuries.
                                    What we find is that the verses on the verso of <link
                                        url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=Pelliot%20chinois%204524"
                                        >Pelliot chinois 4524</link> match the verse portions of the
                                    prosimetric transformation text about Mulian (Maudgalyāyana)
                                    saving his mother from the suffering of the underworld.</p><p>To
                                    show how the picture scroll relates to the transformation text,
                                    I have devoted one entire book <title lang="eng">Painting and
                                        Performance: Chinese Picture Recitation and Its Indian
                                        Genesis</title>, parts of two other books <title lang="eng"
                                        >Tun-huang Popular Narratives</title> and <title lang="eng"
                                        >T'ang Transformation Texts</title>, and several major
                                    articles e.g. ‘Śāriputra Defeats the Six Heterodox Masters:
                                    Oral-Visual Aspects of an Illustrated Transformation Scroll
                                        (P4524),’ <title lang="eng">Asia Major</title>; 3rd series,
                                    8.2 (1995 [actually published in September, 1997]), 1–52, plus
                                    three plates.</p></q></note>
                        <note><p><link
                                    url="http://idpuk.blogspot.co.uk/2013/11/a-few-of-our-favourite-things-1-victor.html"
                                    >Link to original post on IDP blog.</link></p></note>
                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
            </msDescription>
            <msDescription n="2">
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>Budapest</settlement>
                    <repository>Library and Information Centre of the Hungarian Academy of
                        Sciences</repository>
                    <collection>Stein</collection>
                    <idno type="current">653/1-2</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <msItem n="1">
                        <author><name lang="eng">Agnes Kelecsényi and Kinga Dévényi</name></author>
                        <note><p>Agnes Kelecsényi and Kinga Dévényi are curators in the Oriental
                            Collection of the <link url="http://www.mtak.hu/index.php">Library and Information Centre of the Hungarian
                                Academy of Sciences</link> in Budapest, where Stein’s bequest is preserved.
                                They have been strongly involved in disseminating knowledge about
                                this collection including various digitisation and cataloguing
                                projects with IDP. Their chosen item is Aurel Stein's manuscript of
                                    the <title lang="eng">Sand-buried Ruins of
                            Khotan</title>.</p>
                            </note>
                        <note><p>Agnes Kelecsényi and Kinga Dévényi write:</p>
                            <q><p>The two volume manuscript, bound in brown leather, consists of
                                    two parts: The text of the Preliminary Note in Stein’s
                                    pagination Vol.1.:434 ff. and Vol. 2.: 435-812 ff. completed in
                                    London, 6 February 1903. At the end of the manuscript two parts
                                    are inserted from his diary written during his return journey to
                                    Europe: Osh, 8 June 1901 (13 ff.); and Samarkand, 15 June 1901
                                    (6 ff.).</p><p>This manuscript was donated to the Hungarian
                                    Academy of Sciences by Stein as a part of his first donation of
                                    books to the Academy of his native land.</p><p>It is our
                                    favourite item because his neat handwriting and scarce
                                    amendments reflect his scholarly way of composing and his well
                                    disciplined character. While the dried flowers put among the
                                    leaves of the manuscript, and which are from the Mohand Marg,
                                    his mountain retreat in Kashmir, are a sign of his tender heart,
                                    love of nature, and spirituality.</p></q></note>
                        <note><p><link
                                    url="http://idpuk.blogspot.co.uk/2013/11/a-few-of-our-favourite-things-2-agnes.html"
                                    >Link to original post on IDP blog.</link></p></note>
                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
            </msDescription>
            <msDescription n="3">
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>London</settlement>
                    <repository>The British Library</repository>
                    <collection>Stein</collection>
                    <idno type="current">IOL Tib N 1103</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <msItem n="1">
                        <author><name lang="eng">Tsuguhito Takeuchi</name></author>
                        <note><p>Tsuguhito Takeuchi is Professor of Linguistics at <link url="http://www.kobe-cufs.ac.jp/index.html">Kobe City
                                University of Foreign Studies</link>. His research field is the linguistic
                                analysis of Old Tibetan documents from Central Asia. He is the
                                author of <title lang="eng">Old Tibetan Manuscripts from East
                                    Turkestan in the Stein Collection of the British
                                Library</title> and he is currently cataloguing the Tibetan woodslips
                                in the Stein Collection.</p><p>His chosen item is <link
                                    url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=IOL Tib N 1103"
                                    >IOL Tib N 1103</link> (M.Tagh.002) in the Stein Collection of
                                    the <link url="http://www.bl.uk/">British Library</link>, a Tibetan woodslip unearthed from Mazār Tāgh by
                                Aurel Stein.</p></note>
                        <note><p>Tsuguhito Takeuchi writes:</p>
                            <q><p>This is a particular type of tally stick. One side is painted
                                    red with several short and long notches cut into it. A wedge is
                                    cut away at the bottom right. On the left side is written a
                                    place name, ending with <term lang="tib-Latn">rtse</term> ‘mountain peak.’ This is a
                                    place for <term lang="tib-Latn">ri-zug</term> or hill-stationing of watchmen, a unit of
                                    four men, consisting of Tibetan soldiers and Khotanese cooks.
                                    They were sent from the Mazār Tāgh fort to hill stations in the
                                    desert. When they set out, they brought the cut-out wedge as a
                                    tally to receive provisions (barley) later from a courier who
                                    carried this master woodslip bearing the name of the
                                    hill-station. At the time of receiving provisions, both short
                                    and long notched served for identification: the short notches
                                    represented the amount of grain, while the long ones served for
                                    matching-up.</p><p>Although each <term lang="tib-Latn">ri-zug</term> slip appears to
                                    contain scarce information, closer examinations reveal how they
                                    actually functioned. They attest the sophisticated logistic
                                    system of the Tibetan military administration, a key for
                                    understanding how a small number of Tibetans controlled the vast
                                    colonial empire.</p><p>These slips together with paper documents
                                    also vividly indicate the harshness of the lives of local
                                    peoples. How were they recruited and sent to stations? They tell
                                    of the escape and execution of Khotanese, etc. Seemingly humble
                                    finds yield much information!</p></q></note>
                        <note><p><link
                                    url="http://idpuk.blogspot.co.uk/2013/11/a-few-of-our-favourite-things-3.html"
                                    >Link to original post on IDP blog.</link></p></note>
                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
            </msDescription>
            <msDescription n="4">
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>Berlin</settlement>
                    <repository>Berlin Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and Humanities</repository>
                    <collection>Turfan Collection</collection>
                    <idno type="current">M 4a</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <msItem n="1">
                        <author><name lang="eng">Desmond Durkin-Meisterernst</name></author>
                        <note><p>Desmond Durkin-Meisterernst works in Berlin on the edition of
                                Iranian fragments in the Berlin Turfan Collection at the <link
                                    url="http://www.bbaw.de">Berlin Brandenburg Academy of Sciences
                                    and Humanities</link>. The project is called ‘<link
                                    url="http://pom.bbaw.de/turfan/start.php?aufl=1920"
                                    >Turfanforschung</link>’ (Turfan Studies) and is an IDP partner.
                                His chosen item is<link
                                    url="http://idp.bbaw.de/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=M%204a">M
                                    4a</link>.</p></note>
                        <note><p>Desmond Durkin-Meisterernst writes:</p>
                            <q>One of my favourite items in the Berlin Turfan Collection is the
                                    bifolio <link
                                    url="http://idp.bbaw.de/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=M%204a">M
                                    4a</link> and in particular the right-hand side on which a small
                                hymn is preserved entirely. The bifolio is an exquisite example of
                                Manichaean book art. The scribe used an elaborate headline and
                                initial letter extending into the upper right margin to create a
                                very pleasing design. The short text is framed within rubrics in red
                                that identify its beginning and end. It is in Parthian, a language
                                from the north of Iran which probably died out in the seventh
                                century but which has survived because it was still used by
                                Manichaeans in far-away Turfan on the Silk Road in the tenth
                                century.</q></note>
                        <note><p><link
                                    url="http://idpuk.blogspot.co.uk/2013/11/a-few-of-our-favourite-things-4-desmond.html"
                                    >Link to original post on IDP blog.</link></p></note>
                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
            </msDescription>
            <msDescription n="5">
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>London</settlement>
                    <repository>The British Library</repository>
                    <collection>Stein</collection>
                    <idno type="current">Or.8210/S.6168</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <msItem n="1">
                        <author><name lang="eng">Vivienne Lo</name></author>
                        <note><p>Vivienne Lo is the director of the <link
                                    url="http://www.ucl.ac.uk/chinahealth">UCL China Centre for
                                    Health and Humanity</link>. She has also been a restaurateur and
                                professional acupuncturist for many decades and combines her
                                historical and contemporary interests in the history of food, qi
                                exercises and Chinese medicine. She has been teaching the History of
                                Asian Medicine and Classical Chinese medicine at BSc and MA level
                                    at <link url="http://www.ucl.ac.uk">University College
                                    London</link> (UCL) since 2002. Her research concerns the social
                                and cultural origins of acupuncture and therapeutic exercise. She
                                translates and analyses manuscript material from Early and Medieval
                                China and the transmission of scientific knowledge along the
                                so-called Silk Roads through to the modern Chinese medical diaspora.
                                Her chosen item is medical manuscript <link
                                    url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=Or.8210/S.6168"
                                    >Or.8210/S.6168</link>.</p></note>
                        <note><p>Vivienne Lo writes:</p><q><p><link
                                        url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=Or.8210/S.6168"
                                        >Or.8210/S.6168</link>is the earliest illustration of
                                    moxibustion practice, the therapeutic treatment that uses
                                    artemesia punk and other cautery techniques to treat illnesses.
                                    It pre-dates the earliest Chinese bronze acupuncture models used
                                    for teaching in the Song period by at least a century and
                                    represents a pervasive medical culture in evidence at both the
                                    centre and periphery of Chinese administration. I have called
                                    this culture 'quick and easy Chinese medicine', because the
                                    charts provide everything you need to know: the locations of the
                                    points, symptoms of the illnesses, numbers of cautery to place
                                    and burn on the points with little reference to the kind of
                                    theory that requires a classical education. It is therefore a
                                    'householder' treatment for everyday symptoms. It can be
                                    compared and contrasted to Tibetan manuscripts in the Pelliot
                                    collection which reveal the cross-cultural transmission of
                                    medicine in the Dunhuang area.</p><p>I love this mansuscript and
                                    sponsored it in the name of my late father, Kenneth Lo. When I
                                    first began researching medicine in early and medieval
                                    manuscript cultures I had no idea there was such a treasure just
                                    down the road from my office. Both in my work as an
                                    acupuncturist and as an historian I have been intrigued by what
                                    makes an acceptable home treatment and what is properly in the
                                    domain of the professional. In the history of Chinese therapy
                                    moxibustion has been much more prevalent than acupuncture.
                                    Artemesia grows everywhere and is easy to prepare into moxa.
                                    Even though in the Chinese context historically, and in some
                                    places still today, the moxa is applied until the skin blisters
                                    so there is a danger of infection, in most parts of the world it
                                    has become a much gentler practice and, in my view, is safe to
                                    use at home with very little instruction.</p></q></note>
                        <note><p><link
                                    url="http://idpuk.blogspot.co.uk/2013/11/a-few-of-our-favourite-things-5.html"
                                    >Link to original post on IDP blog.</link></p></note>
                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
            </msDescription>
            <msDescription n="6">
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>St Petersburg</settlement>
                    <repository>Hermitage</repository>
                    <collection>Oldenburg</collection>
                    <idno type="current">DH-1</idno>
                    <idno type="current">DH-2</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <msItem n="1">
                        <author><name lang="eng">Maria Menshikova</name></author>
                        <note><p>Maria Menshikova is Curator of the Dunhuang collection in the <link
                                    url="http://www.hermitagemuseum.org/html_En/index.html">State
                                    Hermitage Museum</link>. She started work at the Hermitage over
                                forty years ago and while there studied art history. Her interest in
                                Dunhuang dates back to childhood as her father, Professor Lev
                                Menshikov, was a renowned Chinese scholar and curator and cataloguer
                                of the Dunhuang Chinese manuscripts at the <link
                                    url="http://www.orientalstudies.ru/eng/">Institute of Oriental
                                    Manuscripts</link>. She has recently curated an exhibition of
                                Sergei Oldenburg’s expedition to Dunhuang at the Hermitage. 
                                Her chosen item is a pair of seated guardians <link
                                    url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=DH-1"
                                    >DH-1</link> and <link
                                    url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=DH-2"
                                    >DH-2</link>.</p></note>
                        <note><p>Maria Menshikova writes:</p><q><p>It so happened that through my
                                    visual memory I always remember the images from Dunhuang. In my
                                    childhood my father, Lev Nikolaevitch Menshikov, showed me the
                                    pictures of the ceiling ornaments, books with the reproductions
                                    and photographs of the Mogao Thousand Buddhas caves. And on
                                    Sundays papa took me to the museums and of course to the
                                    Hermitage and the rooms with the Dunhuang collection. Maybe it
                                    was my childish impression but in the exhibition the most
                                    attractive for me were the fantastic beasts, the dogs that sat
                                    in the middle of the room in the glass cages. I was not afraid
                                    of them but thought they were looking at me breathing and
                                    smiling as the real pets can.</p><p>Two sculptures of the
                                    fantastic animals were brought from Dunhuang to St. Petersburg
                                    in 1915 by the second Russian Turkestan Expedition, led by
                                    academician Sergei Feodorovitch Oldenburg. No other such beasts
                                    from Dunhuang are known or have survived. They must be the pair
                                    of seated guardians at the entrance to the Buddhist cave. One of
                                    them is shown with the open mouth like roaring, the second with
                                    the closed mouth but tentative. They are vigorous and listen to
                                    the sounds of the world. Any moment they are ready to protect
                                    the Buddhist faith from any evil.</p></q></note>
                        <note><p><link
                                    url="http://idpuk.blogspot.co.uk/2013/12/a-few-of-our-favourite-things-6-maria.html"
                                    >Link to original post on IDP blog.</link></p></note>
                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
            </msDescription>
            <msDescription n="7">
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>London</settlement>
                    <repository>The British Library</repository>
                    <collection>Stein</collection>
                    <idno type="current">Or.8212/98</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <msItem n="1">
                        <author><name lang="eng">Hans van Roon</name></author>
                        <note><p>Hans van Roon is a Dutch chartered accountant and financial
                                specialist who in 1987 read Peter Hopkirk’s <title lang="eng">Foreign
                                    Devils on the Silk Road</title> and never stopped reading again.
                                This was the beginning of his own personal Silk Road journey. He
                                publishes on a regularly basis the latest news about the Silk Road
                                and anything related to IDP on his blog <link
                                    url="http://mongolschinaandthesilkroad.blogspot.nl">Mongols
                                    China and the Silk Road</link>.</p><p>His favourite object is
                                the third of five nearly complete Sogdian letters from the beginning
                                of the fourth century, discovered in 1907 by Aurel Stein some 90 km
                                west of Dunhuang.</p></note>
                        <note><p>Hans van Roon writes:</p><q>Many readers will be familiar with this letter but this one is
                                special to me as:<lg>
                                    <l>• This was found by Aurel Stein;</l>
                                    <l>• These letters are the most ancient monuments of the Sogdian
                                        language;</l>
                                    <l>• This one is almost complete and full of drama with an
                                        abandoned wife in the middle of nowhere while, we as readers
                                        know her cry for help never arrived at its destination;</l>
                                    <l>• It is written by a woman and the length of the letter
                                        suggests that it is not her first and only letter. It ends
                                        with the famous bitter words of anger to her husband: ‘I
                                        would rather be a dog’s or a pig’s wife than yours!’</l>
                                    <l>• It makes you feel that you are in direct contact with someone
                                        from the fourth century, which is something magical!</l>
                                </lg></q></note>
                        <note><p><link
                                    url="http://idpuk.blogspot.co.uk/2013/12/a-few-of-our-favourite-things-7-hans.html"
                                    >Link to original post on IDP blog.</link></p></note>
                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
            </msDescription>
            <msDescription n="8">
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>London</settlement>
                    <repository>The British Library</repository>
                    <collection>Stein</collection>
                    <idno type="current">Photo 1280/1(1)</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <msItem n="1">
                        <author><name lang="eng">Helen Wang</name></author>
                        <note><p>Helen Wang is Curator of <link
                                    url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/about_us/departments/staff/coins_and_medals/helen_wang.aspx"
                                    >East Asian Money at the British Museum</link>. In addition to
                                    researching <title lang="eng"><link
                                        url="http://www.britishmuseumshoponline.org/money-on-the-silk-road/invt/cmc18062"
                                        >Money on the Silk Road</link></title> (2004) and <title
                                    lang="eng"><link
                                        url="http://journals.cambridge.org/action/displayIssue?jid=JRA&amp;volumeId=23&amp;seriesId=3&amp;issueId=02&amp;etoc=Y"
                                        >Textiles as Money on the Silk Road</link></title> (2013),
                                she’s worked collaboratively with lots of IDP friends to produce
                                important reference works on the collections of Sir Aurel Stein.
                                These include the <title lang="eng"><link
                                        url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/publications/research_publications_series/2008/handbook_stein_collection.aspx"
                                        >Handbook to the Collections of Sir Aurel Stein in the
                                        UK</link></title> (1999, revised 2008); <title lang="eng"
                                        ><link
                                        url="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Aurel-Stein-Times-Helen-Wang/dp/1872843298"
                                        >Sir Aurel Stein in The Times</link></title> (2002); <title
                                    lang="eng">Catalogue to the Collections of Sir Aurel Stein in
                                    the Library of the Hungarian Academy of Sciences</title> (2002)
                                and its <title lang="eng">Supplement</title> (2007); and <title
                                    lang="eng"><link
                                        url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/publications/research_publications_series/2012/sir_aurel_stein.aspx"
                                        >Sir Aurel Stein, Colleagues and
                                Collections</link></title> (2012). Her chosen item is a photograph of
                                Stein’s assistant <link
                                    url="http://journals.cambridge.org/action/displayAbstract?fromPage=online&amp;aid=5349248"
                                    >Miss Lorimer</link><link
                                    url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=Photo%201280/1(1)"
                                    >Photo 1280/1(1)</link>.</p></note>
                        <note><p>Helen Wang writes:</p><q><p>I’ve chosen Miss Lorimer (Stein’s
                                    Recording Angel, or R.A.) in recognition of her outstanding
                                    commitment and contribution to Sir Aurel Stein’s projects and
                                    undertakings. Miss Lorimer worked with Stein for thirteen years,
                                    spending nine years at the British Museum, and four years in
                                    India. Although Stein was an exceptionally competent keeper of
                                    records and accounts (if in doubt, take a look at his <link
                                        url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/pdf/16_Diamond-Rogers-Fletcher.pdf"
                                        >papers in the Bodleian Library</link>), it’s quite clear
                                    that he preferred the open air to the office. After all, how
                                    many ‘Education Officers’ are able to spend months on
                                    expeditions away from their desks? And how many archaeologists
                                    of no fixed abode are able to keep such close tabs on their
                                    recording team?</p><p>When the shipments arrived in London, it
                                    was the small team of Mr Andrews and Miss Lorimer who set to
                                    work on the collection. Stein joined them when he could. At the
                                    British Museum, the Stein Collection had its own space, with its
                                    own lock and key, and it was here that Andrews and Lorimer
                                    unpacked the finds, stored them safely, and created the slips.
                                    These were long strips of paper, once used like index cards in
                                    the museum, and now superseded by spreadsheets and databases.
                                    Each object had its own slip, which typically recorded the
                                    object’s ‘Stein number’ (his unique system, combining upper and
                                    lower case letters, and Roman and Arabic numerals to indicate
                                    the precise context of a site find, purchase or gift), its
                                    measurements and a description. The slips served as the basis
                                    for the thousands of object descriptions published in Stein’s
                                    publications, and they were essential for managing the
                                    collection. Some parts of the collection travelled, and Miss
                                    Lorimer, in particular, had to keep track of everything. For
                                    example, in 1911 over 400 Chinese manuscripts were <link
                                        url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/pdf/12_Wood%20(Tentative%20listiing).pdf"
                                        >sent to Paul Pelliot in Paris</link>for cataloguing, and
                                    remained there throughout the First World War.</p><p>The Stein
                                    Collections are phenomenally important — for the wonderful
                                    objects and manuscripts, of course, but also for the meticulous
                                    recording of the contexts in which they were found. This does
                                    not happen by itself. Without the painstaking efforts of people
                                    like Miss Lorimer, who mostly work behind the scenes and are
                                    seldom acknowledged, our understanding of the Silk Road would be
                                    so much the poorer.</p></q></note>
                        <note><p><link
                                    url="http://idpuk.blogspot.co.uk/2013/12/a-few-of-our-favourite-things-8-helen.html"
                                    >Link to original post on IDP blog.</link></p></note>
                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
            </msDescription>
            <msDescription n="9">
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>London</settlement>
                    <repository>The British Library</repository>
                    <collection>Stein</collection>
                    <idno type="current">IOL San 482</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <msItem n="1">
                        <author><name lang="eng">Seishi Karashima</name></author>
                        <note><p>Seishi Karashima has been a Professor of Sino-Indian Buddhist
                                Philology at <link url="http://iriab.soka.ac.jp/orc/english.html">The
                                    International Research Institute for Advanced Buddhology</link>,
                                Soka University, Tokyo, since 1997, where he has been carrying out
                                philological research on early Mahāyāna scriptures and early Chinese
                                Buddhist translations. He has published twelve books and more than a
                                hundred articles on these themes, including: <title lang="eng">The
                                    Study of the Chinese Versions of the Saddharmapuṇḍarīkasūtra ––
                                    in the light of the Sanskrit and Tibetan Versions</title>; <title
                                    lang="eng">A Glossary of Dharmarakṣa’s Translation of the Lotus
                                    Sutra</title>;<title lang="eng">A Glossary of Kumārajiva's
                                    Translation of the Lotus Sutra</title>; <title lang="eng">A
                                    Glossary of Lokakṣema’s Translation of the Aṣṭasāhasrikā
                                    Prajñāpāramitā</title>; <title lang="eng">A Critical Edition of
                                    Lokakṣema’s Translation of the Aṣṭasāhasrikā
                                    Prajñāpāramitā</title>.</p><p>In the 1990s, he realised that the
                                old Sanskrit manuscripts and fragments from Central Asia were
                                indispensable sources for allowing scholars to draw nearer to the
                                original features of early Mahāyāna scriptures and therefore, since
                                then, he has been engaged in publishing photographs and
                                transliterations of those manuscripts and fragments, now preserved
                                at the <link url="http://www.bl.uk/">British Library</link> and <link url="http://www.orientalstudies.ru/">Institute of Oriental Manuscripts</link> in St.
                                Petersburg. He has also been in the process of publishing a series
                                    of <title lang="eng">Buddhist Manuscripts from Central Asia: The
                                    British Library Sanskrit Fragments</title>(BLSF) (2 vols. so
                                far) and that of <title lang="eng">The St. Petersburg Sanskrit
                                    Fragments</title>(StPSF) (in preparation) in collaboration with
                                K. Wille, M. I. Vorobyova-Desyatovskaya and other
                                scholars.</p><p>His chosen item is the Sanskrit manuscript <link
                                    url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=IOL%20San%20482"
                                    >IOL San 482</link>.</p></note>
                        <note><p>Seishi Karashima writes:</p><q><p>The manuscript of the <title lang="san-Latn">Saddharmapuṇḍarīkasūtra</title> (IOL San 482–515), or the <title lang="eng">Lotus Sutra</title>,
                                    was discovered by Aurel Stein in Farhād-Bēg-Yailaki, near
                                    Khadalik, during his second expedition and is kept at present in
                                    the British Library. 35 folios, written on paper, are preserved.
                                    This incomplete manuscript, whose script is the Early Turkestan
                                    Brāhmī, type b, probably dates back to the fifth or sixth
                                    century AD. Both its language (Buddhist Sanskrit) and the
                                    content (from the eleventh to the beginning of the fifteenth
                                    chapter of the <title lang="eng">Lotus Sutra</title>) also show its antiquity. Owing to
                                    its particular importance to the study of the <title lang="eng">Lotus Sutra</title>, a
                                    black-and-white facsimile edition, though of very low quality,
                                    was published as early as 1949 in Japan, from which the late
                                    Prof. Hirofumi Toda made a transliteration.</p><p>When I saw the
                                    actual manuscript with my own eyes at the British Library in
                                    December 2004, I was struck by its beautiful calligraphy and its
                                    absolute clearness, which unfortunately the facsimile edition
                                    lacks. Thus, I decided to transliterate the manuscript anew by
                                    using newly-taken coloured photographs and, at the same time,
                                    persuaded our university to support IDP financially by
                                    digitising the entire collection of the Sanskrit manuscript
                                    fragments from Central Asia. I am happy to know that, now, this
                                    ten-year digitisation project has been completed.</p></q></note>
                        <note><p><link
                                    url="http://idpuk.blogspot.co.uk/2014/01/a-few-of-our-favourite-things-9-seishi.html"
                                    >Link to original post on IDP blog.</link></p></note>
                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
            </msDescription>
            <msDescription n="10">
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>London</settlement>
                    <repository>The British Library</repository>
                    <collection>Stein</collection>
                    <idno type="current">IOL Tib J 308</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <msItem n="1">
                        <author><name lang="eng">Agnieszka Helman-Ważny</name></author>
                        <note><p>Agnieszka Helman-Ważny (<link
                                    url="http://www.uni-hamburg.de/index_e.html">University of
                                    Hamburg</link>, <link url="http://www.arizona.edu/">University of
                                    Arizona</link>) is a paper scientist. Her main research area is
                                the history of paper and books in Tibet and Central Asia, and the
                                development of methods for their examination and conservation. Since
                                2005, she has studied the early history of paper in Central Asia and
                                aimed to create a typology of paper based on a systematic study of
                                manuscript collections found along the Silk Road. She detected a
                                broad range of paper types for these early manuscripts written in
                                Chinese, Tibetan and other languages. By using the technological and
                                microscopic study of paper combined with codicological and textual
                                information, her research undertaken in collaboration with the IDP
                                team has aimed to explore the possibilities for dating this material
                                and recovering the histories of its regional production and usage.
                                Her chosen item is a Tibetan manuscript, <link
                                    url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=IOL%20Tib%20J%20308"
                                    >IOL Tib J 308</link>, written possibly with blood on fine
                                quality paper.</p></note>
                        <note><p>Agnieszka Helman-Ważny writes:</p><q><p><link
                                        url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=IOL%20Tib%20J%20308"
                                        >IOL Tib J 308</link> was primary selected for our research
                                    because of the unusual ink colour and the fine paper quality.
                                    The manuscript is typical of the Tibetan pothi book format: 9 x
                                    43 cm with one string hole. The leaf proportions and string hole
                                    resemble Indian palm leaf books. The hole, with its abraded
                                    edges, suggests that the book was well used and that its leaves
                                    were string-joined. The Tibetologist Sam van Schaik describes
                                    the copying of the text on this manuscript as a meritorious
                                    activity associated with the achievement of a long life. During
                                    the 830s–840s, many hundreds of copies of this text were made at
                                    the behest of the Tibetan emperor; however, the present copy is
                                    different from these in format and writing style. The script in
                                    this manuscript is in a brown ink easily distinguished from
                                    black carbon-based inks. It is possible that the ink colour is
                                    evidence of the practice of writing with blood, which is also
                                    attested by results of Renate Nöller’s XRF and VIS spectroscopy
                                    examinations.</p><p>This manuscript's paper was produced from
                                    ramie and hemp derived from textile waste. It was made with a
                                    movable type of papermaking mould equipped with a bamboo sieve.
                                    Thus this paper represents laid, regular paper with a sieve
                                    print characterized by 16 laid lines in 3 cm; the laid lines are
                                    horizontal and parallel to the text. The exceptionally good
                                    quality of fibre struck my attention when I was looking at it
                                    under the microscope. My study confirmed that this simple
                                    manuscript without any fancy elements was written on paper made
                                    from high quality textiles. I could envision the raw materials
                                    beaten gently by hand during the papermaking process, to prevent
                                    shortening of the fibres. Those fibres visible on the photograph
                                    above are exceptionally long and well preserved.</p><p>This type
                                    of rag paper, made with one of the oldest papermaking techniques
                                    known and adapted later in Europe, has been found in the
                                    majority of manuscripts from Central Asia produced in the first
                                    millennium but hardly ever later. Thus this Tibetan manuscript,
                                    a common sutra, a scripture from the Buddha, was probably
                                    locally produced at Dunhuang with extreme sincerity and
                                    devotion. It makes me wonder what wish was laid bare by this
                                    person who wrote on such gently-made paper, possibly with the
                                    addition of his own blood. Unfortunately we will never know who
                                    was its creator…</p></q></note>
                        <note><p><link
                                    url="http://idpuk.blogspot.co.uk/2014/01/a-few-of-our-favourite-things-10.html"
                                    >Link to original post on IDP blog.</link></p></note>
                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
            </msDescription>
            <msDescription n="11">
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>London</settlement>
                    <repository>Victoria and Albert Museum</repository>
                    <collection>Stein</collection>
                    <idno type="current">LOAN:STEIN.344</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <msItem n="1">
                        <author><name lang="eng">Helen Persson</name></author>
                        <note><p>Helen Persson has been at the <link
                                    url="http://www.vam.ac.uk/content/articles/a/asian-department/"
                                    >Victoria and Albert Museum</link>, London, since 2001 and is
                                curator of Chinese textiles and dress, in the Asian Department. Her
                                first degree is in archaeology from the <link url="http://www.su.se/">University of Stockholm</link> and
                                her second is in History of dress from the <link url="http://www.courtauld.ac.uk/index.shtml">Courtauld Institute of Art</link>,
                                London.</p><p>Helen’s interests in Central Asia focus in particular
                                on the exchange in textiles; in motifs and technologies during the
                                first millenium and how the textiles can help us understand the
                                societies where they were made and used. Her interests also include
                                fashion and identity. She has lectured and published extensively on
                                textiles from the Silk Road, among others <title lang="eng">Textiles
                                    from Dunhuang in UK Collections</title>, edited by Zhao Feng
                                (2007), and most recently on Chinese silks for the Mamluk market in
                                a Centre for Textile Research publication (forthcoming).</p><p>Her
                                chosen item is a <link
                                    url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=LOAN:STEIN.344"
                                    >hemp shoe</link> found by Stein in the Limes watchtowers, north
                                of Dunhuang.</p></note>
                        <note><p>Helen Persson writes:</p><q><p>Well, I do like shoes and this peculiar
                                    looking and old shoe is very special. Although the shoe's
                                    original functions were practical and protective, there is a
                                    clear design element to it. The utilitarian everyday object has
                                    decorative features as well, showing human's desire to embellish
                                    even the simplest of artefacts. The shoe was discovered in a
                                    refuse heap, discarded most likely because of worn holes in the
                                    heel and the ball of the toes. The upper is made of two or more
                                    thicknesses of strong plain woven hemp or cotton, bound together
                                    by even rows of hemp string, producing a pattern of dots all
                                    over. The process of sewing two or more layers of materials
                                    together to make thicker padded material is like quilting and
                                    just as in quilting, the stitching has become both functional
                                    and decorative. A drawstring is threaded around the upper edge,
                                    which by a clever method of crossing near the instep restricts
                                    the size of the opening and draws up the slack of the fabric
                                    over the toes into a sort of point. This has created a curious
                                    profile of the shoe, like a horn. The thick sole has warp of
                                    hemp cord placed lengthways with weft of string plaited in a
                                    ‘wrapped-twined’ manner. Furthermore, the entire sole is covered
                                    with tight knots of string, which would have the effect of the
                                    hob-nailed military sandals of the Romans or the climbing nails
                                    in a modern boot. The knots would have made walking on the sand
                                    in the Taklamakan Desert much easier. This type of sole can also
                                    be seen in the footwear of the terracotta soldiers from Xi’an,
                                    showing that this sort of footwear is not a single occurrence
                                    but most likely had a long tradition. It would most likely have
                                    been worn as an outer shoe, i.e. over a thinner cloth
                                    shoe.</p><p>This shoe was recovered from the site known as the
                                    Limes Watchtowers, which actually include several different
                                    sites of fortified encampments north of Dunhuang in northwest
                                    China, along the edges of the Taklamakan Desert. They were
                                    designed to ensure the safe transit of goods across the area and
                                    served as a base for expansion into Central Asia. Within the
                                    towers Stein found an astounding range of artefacts, which
                                    provide a glimpse of garrison life and military operations under
                                    the Han empire, including bronze mirrors, coarse pottery, tools,
                                    leather armour, weapons, shoes, and clothing. Ancient documents
                                    included personal letters on silk and wood; military directives
                                    and supply lists; and treatises on a range of subjects,
                                    including medicine and astrology. This shoe was found at the
                                    garrison station named by Stein as T.VI.b, where many Chinese
                                    documents dating from 68–56 BCE were found — indicating that
                                    this artefact is among the oldest shoes in the V&amp;A
                                    collection.</p><p>This shoe is one of my favourite Stein
                                    objects, as it is an everyday object which basic form is
                                    functional, but been created with ingenuity and some decorative
                                    elements. It contributes to the story of Central Asian life
                                    during the Han dynasty.</p></q></note>
                        <note><p><link
                                    url="http://idpuk.blogspot.co.uk/2014/01/a-few-of-our-favourite-things-11-helen.html"
                                    >Link to original post on IDP blog.</link></p></note>
                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
            </msDescription>
            <msDescription n="12">
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>London</settlement>
                    <repository>The British Museum</repository>
                    <collection>Stein</collection>
                    <idno type="current">1919,0101,0.6</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <msItem n="1">
                        <author><name lang="eng">Fan Jinshi</name></author>
                        <note><p>Fan Jinshi is Director of the <link url="http://www.dha.ac.cn"
                                    >Dunhuang Academy</link> in China. Her research interests are on
                                Chinese Central Asia — known historically in China as ‘The Western
                                Regions’. This is part of the ancient ‘Silk Road’ where trade and
                                culture flourished and where diverse civilisations met. In the rich
                                cultural legacy that remains in the region we can glimpse the
                                history of a thousand years of interaction between these
                                civilisations. Buddhism had a far-reaching impact in its journey
                                from India through Central Asia to China and East Asia. The Dunhuang
                                Mogao caves are a direct result of this, showcasing this mix of
                                cultures. Having been involved for many years with research on and
                                protection of the caves, Professor Fan Jinshi has a strong interest
                                in the cultural connections between Dunhuang and Central
                                Asia.</p><p>Her chosen item is the painting <link
                                    url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=1919,0101,0.6"
                                    >1919,0101,0.6</link>.</p></note>
                        <note><p>Fan Jinshi writes:</p><q><p>The painting has several
                                    interesting features. Firstly, the heads of the three younger
                                    disciples are very round with round faces and cute expressions.
                                    Second, the painting is very similar to murals found in Dunhuang
                                    Mogao Caves dating from the early Tang period. For example, the
                                        complex <term lang="chi-Latn">lingzhi</term> mushroom (<term lang="chi-Hant"
                                        >灵芝</term>) design depicted on the canopy and the lotus seat
                                    is identical to that shown in the preaching scene on the east
                                    wall of Mogao Cave 329, dating to the early Tang. Third, the
                                    composition is very similar to the Pure Land and preaching
                                    scenes depicted in early Tang caves such as Mogao 321 and 329.
                                    This type of composition is thought to have originated from the
                                    preaching scene in the Sui-period Mogao Cave 390. These
                                    similarities indicate a close relationship between this piece
                                    and the murals of the same period at Dunhuang Mogao.</p></q></note>
                        <note><p><link
                                    url="http://idpuk.blogspot.co.uk/2014/01/a-few-of-our-favourite-things-12-fan.html"
                                    >Link to original post on IDP blog.</link></p></note>
                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
            </msDescription>
            <msDescription n="13">
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>Paris</settlement>
                    <repository>Bibliothèque nationale de France</repository>
                    <collection>Pelliot</collection>
                    <idno type="current">Pelliot chinois 2583</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <msItem n="1">
                        <author><name lang="eng">Stephen F. Teiser</name></author>
                        <note><p>Stephen F. Teiser teaches history of religions at <link url="http://www.princeton.edu/main/">Princeton
                                University</link>, where he is D.T. Suzuki Professor in Buddhist Studies
                                and Director of the <link url="http://eastasia.princeton.edu">Program
                                    in East Asian Studies</link>. He is interested in the
                                interaction between Buddhism and indigenous Chinese traditions,
                                brought into focus through the wealth of sūtras, non-canonical
                                texts, and artistic evidence unearthed on the Silk Road. An updated
                                edition of his 1994 book on concepts of hell (<title lang="eng">The
                                    Scripture on the Ten Kings and the Making of Purgatory in
                                    Medieval Chinese Buddhism</title>) will soon be published in
                                Chinese translation. His current research, tentatively
                                    entitled <title lang="eng">Curing with Karma</title>, focuses on
                                Buddhist liturgical manuscripts from Dunhuang.</p><p>His chosen item
                                    is <link
                                    url="http://idp.bnf.fr/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=Pelliot%20chinois%202583"
                                    >Pelliot chinois 2583</link>, a Chinese scroll from the
                                collections of the <link
                                    url="http://www.bnf.fr/fr/acc/x.accueil.html">Bibliothèque
                                    nationale de France</link>.</p></note>
                        <note><p>Stephen F. Teiser writes:</p><q><p><link
                                        url="http://idp.bnf.fr/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=Pelliot%20chinois%202583"
                                        >Pelliot chinois 2583</link>is a scroll composed of thirteen
                                    sheets of paper originally written one at a time. Each sheet was
                                    a liturgy accompanying a single ritual act of donation on behalf
                                    of Dunhuang’s nuns, monks, and laypeople. Some of the rites were
                                    intended for healing sickness; others were documents used in
                                    memorial observances or the distribution of nuns’ clothing after
                                    death. Most of the prayers are short, occupying less than half a
                                    sheet. The detail of the page shown here (verso, sheet 4) opens
                                    by listing the type and amount of items offered: 'One piece of
                                    purple hanging silk (crossed out and corrected: cotton), one set
                                    consisting of official robe and silk skirt, one silk
                                    side-buttoning blouse.' The next two lines contain the liturgy
                                    proper, explaining that a nun named Mingqian has been sick,
                                    dedicating the donation’s merit to her cure, and asking that
                                    chanting accompany the rite. The fourth line records the donor’s
                                    name, the date, and a benediction. The last line seems to be the
                                    signature of the monastic official responsible for the
                                    disposition of the gift, a monk Huiyan.</p><p>Both sides of this
                                    fourteen-foot long scroll are fascinating. The side now labeled
                                    verso by the <link
                                        url="http://www.bnf.fr/fr/acc/x.accueil.html">Bibliothèque nationale</link> was actually composed first,
                                    each sheet a written artifact of a ritual performance. The rites
                                    were undertaken on behalf of otherwise unknown local people
                                    during the period of Tibetan rule (786-848). The prayers provide
                                    refreshingly concrete, direct witness to the worries and hopes,
                                    the simple words and possessions of the performers. Later,
                                    someone collected all thirteen liturgies and pasted them
                                    end-to-end in scroll format, whose verso side (now labeled
                                    recto) was used for recording two more texts. The first, main
                                    text is a Chinese-language commentary authored by the most
                                    prolific bilingual monk at Dunhuang (Tibetan name: Gö Chödrup,
                                    Chinese name: Wu Facheng), on a Buddhist scripture on causality
                                    and the Four Noble Truths, <title lang="eng">The Rice Stalk
                                        Sūtra</title> (Skt.: <title lang="eng"
                                        >Śālistambhaka-sūtra</title>). The second, shorter text on
                                    this side of the manuscript is a partial calendar for the year
                                    821, written upside-down and beginning from the end of the
                                    manuscript. For each day the almanac lists reigning deities;
                                    correlates for cycles of weather, sun, and moon; types of
                                    activities deemed lucky or unlucky; and so on.</p><p>The
                                    ensemble of the scroll’s two sides makes this my favorite
                                    manuscript in the Dunhuang collection. The texts offer
                                    elaborations of core Buddhist teachings plus hemerological
                                    calculation of lucky and unlucky days, all constructed on the
                                    back side of humble liturgies transferring merit to nuns, monks,
                                    and laypeople.</p></q></note>
                        <note><p><link
                                    url="http://idpuk.blogspot.co.uk/2014/01/a-few-of-our-favourite-things-13.html"
                                    >Link to original post on IDP blog.</link></p></note>
                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
            </msDescription>
            <msDescription n="14">
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>London</settlement>
                    <repository>The British Library</repository>
                    <collection>Stein</collection>
                    <idno type="current">Or.8212/95</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <msItem n="1">
                        <author><name lang="eng">Nicholas Sims-Williams</name></author>
                        <note><p>After studying Old and Middle Iranian languages and related
                            subjects at <link url="http://www.cam.ac.uk/">Cambridge</link>, Nicholas Sims-Williams has spent his whole
                                career at the <link url="http://www.soas.ac.uk">School of Oriental
                                    and African Studies</link>, University of London, where his
                                teaching has covered seven Iranian languages (Avestan, Old Persian,
                                Middle Persian, Parthian, Choresmian, Bactrian, Sogdian and
                                Khotanese) and occasionally Syriac. Although he has published on all
                                of these languages, he has concentrated on the Middle Iranian
                                languages of Eastern Iran and Central Asia, in particular Sogdian
                                and Bactrian. He is equally interested in the languages themselves,
                                with their Indo-European roots, and in their Central Asian setting,
                                with its stimulating mixture of languages, cultures and religions.
                                In addition to a two-volume edition of Sogdian inscriptions from
                                Northern Pakistan and a three-volume edition of Bactrian documents
                                from Northern Afghanistan, his books include studies of many
                                manuscripts in the IDP, such as documents in mixed Sogdian and Old
                                Turkish from the London and Paris collections and Christian Sogdian
                                and New Persian manuscripts in the Berlin Turfan
                                collection.</p><p>His chosen item is Sogdian Letter No. 2 <link
                                    url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=Or.8212/95"
                                    >Or.8212/95</link>, Stein site id. T.XII.a.ii.2.</p></note>
                        <note><p>Nicholas Sims-Williams writes:</p><q><p>In 1907 Aurel Stein
                                    discovered a cache of early paper documents at the site T.XII.a
                                    to the west of Dunhuang, a guard-post on the wall protecting the
                                    western border of China. These are known as the ‘Ancient
                                    Letters’ because they are among the earliest documents written
                                    in Sogdian, a language of the Iranian family formerly spoken in
                                    Sogdiana, the region around Samarkand in present-day Uzbekistan,
                                    and in the numerous trading colonies established by the Sogdians
                                    along the route to central China. The Ancient Letters represent
                                    the contents of a postbag lost in transit from China to the
                                    west, perhaps confiscated by the Chinese authorities. Written by
                                    Sogdians in Xinjiang and Gansu and addressed to their
                                    compatriots in Sogdiana or Loulan, the letters provide a unique
                                    glimpse into the lives of the Sogdian merchants on the so-called
                                    ‘Silk Road’.</p><p>Several of these letters could easily have
                                    qualified as my favourite item — no. 6 (<link
                                        url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=Or.8212/97"
                                        >Or.8212/97</link>), the only one which actually mentions
                                    silk, or nos. 1 (<link
                                        url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=Or.8212/92.1"
                                        >Or.8212/92.1</link>) and 3 (<link
                                        url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=Or.8212/98"
                                        >Or.8212/98</link>), two letters written by a woman
                                    abandoned in Dunhuang by her husband — but I have finally
                                        chosen Letter no. 2 (<link
                                        url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=Or.8212/95"
                                        >Or.8212/95</link>). This letter was written
                                    by Nanai-vandak, a Sogdian agent stationed somewhere in Gansu,
                                    possibly in Jincheng, and addressed to his partners in
                                    Samarkand, the capital of Sogdiana, over 2,000 miles to the
                                    west. Perhaps because of the distance it had to travel, it was
                                    protected by an inner wrapper of brown silk and an outer
                                    envelope of coarse fabric which bears instructions for the
                                    delivery of the letter. The letter, which was probably written
                                    in June or July 313 AD contains news of momentous events in
                                    China: a severe famine in the capital Luoyang; fighting between
                                    the Huns (Xiongnu) and the Chinese; the flight of the emperor;
                                    and the sack of the cities of Ye (in 307) and Luoyang (in
                                    311).</p><p>While the main importance of this letter lies in the
                                    historical data it contains, what I find particularly affecting
                                    are the paragraphs with which it ends, a poignant last will and
                                    testament. Nanai-vandak regards the events described as bringing
                                    to an end the world as he knows it and foresees nothing but ruin
                                    and death for himself and the other Sogdian merchants in China.
                                    Since he does not expect to return home, he asks his
                                    correspondents in Samarkand to look after a large sum of money
                                    which he had left on deposit there, to invest it on behalf of
                                    the orphan Takhsich-vandak, presumably his son, who is still a
                                    minor, and to find him a wife when he comes of age. But of
                                    course his letter never reached its destination, so it is
                                    unlikely that its provisions were ever carried out. We can only
                                    speculate as to what became of the father and his son: did
                                    Nanai-vandak survive and return home? and did his partners find
                                    a wife for Takhsich-vandak and hand over his
                                inheritance?</p></q></note>
                        <note><p><link
                                    url="http://idpuk.blogspot.co.uk/2014/02/a-few-of-our-favourite-things-14.html"
                                    >Link to original post on IDP blog.</link></p></note>
                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
            </msDescription>
            <msDescription n="15">
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>Berlin</settlement>
                    <repository>Museum of Asian Art</repository>
                    <collection>Central Asia</collection>
                    <idno type="current">MIK III 8426</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <msItem n="1">
                        <author><name lang="eng">Hans-Ulrich Seidt</name></author>
                        <note><p>Hans-Ulrich Seidt is currently Director-General for Culture and
                            Communication in the <link url="http://www.auswaertiges-amt.de/EN/Startseite_node.html">Federal Foreign Office</link> in Berlin. His interest
                                in Central Asia goes back to the late 1980s when he was working as a
                                young diplomat at the West German embassy in Moscow. At that time he
                                had the opportunity to visit the Central Asian republics of the
                                former Soviet Union. It was a fascinating experience and he has
                                returned to Central Asia many times.</p><p>His chosen item is the
                                    wallpainting <link
                                    url="http://idp.bbaw.de/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=MIK%20III%208426"
                                        >MIK III 8426</link> from the collections of the <link url="http://www.smb.museum/museen-und-einrichtungen/museum-fuer-asiatische-kunst/home.html">Museum of Asian Art, Berlin</link>.</p></note>
                        <note><p>Hans-Ulrich Seidt writes:</p>
                            <q><p>The object I have chosen for the webpage of the International
                                    Dunhuang Project is not from the area of the former Soviet
                                    Union. It comes from China and is today part of the collections
                                    of the Museum of Asian Art in Berlin-Dahlem. The mural was
                                    brought to Berlin during the first decade of the twentieth
                                    century by the German expedition to Turfan. In my eyes this
                                    unique piece of art not only demonstrates the general wealth and
                                    prosperity along the ancient silk roads but also the
                                    multi-ethnic character of their urban trade
                            centres.</p></q></note>
                        <note><p><link
                                    url="http://idpuk.blogspot.co.uk/2014/02/a-few-of-our-favourite-things-15-hans.html"
                                    >Link to original post on IDP blog.</link></p></note>
                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
            </msDescription>
            <msDescription n="16">
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>London</settlement>
                    <repository>The British Library</repository>
                    <collection>Stein</collection>
                    <idno type="current">IOL Khot W 1</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <msItem n="1">
                        <author><name lang="eng">Oktor Skjærvø</name></author>
                        <note><p>Prods Oktor Skjærvø, a former Norwegian, is now an American
                                citizen. During his Sanskrit studies in Oslo, he acquired an
                                interest in Old Iranian languages in general and Khotanese in
                                particular, following in the footsteps of his compatriot Sten Konow,
                                one of the pioneers of Indic epigraphy and Khotanese language. His
                                work on the Khotanese collections in India Office Library and the
                                British Library (now both in the <link url="http://www.bl.uk/">British Library</link>) from the early
                                1980s onward culminated in an edition of the Khotanese <title
                                    lang="eng">Suvarṇabhāsottama-sūtra</title> and a complete
                                Catalogue of the British Library collection (which will be online in
                                2014). He later began concentrating on the eighth-century secular
                                documents in their social and political context, housed mainly in
                                the British Library, Hedin collection (Stockholm), and the Petrovsky
                                collection (St Petersburg), a work that is now being continued, he
                                is happy to say, by his students Zhang Zhan and Wen Xin. His chosen
                                item is <link
                                    url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=IOL%20Khot%20W%201"
                                    >IOL Khot W 1</link>, a wooden tablet from
                            Dandān-Uiliq.</p></note>
                        <note><p>Oktor Skjærvø writes:</p>
                            <q><p>This is a double wooden tablet ‘envelope’ consisting of a bottom
                                    with three raised edges and a top (cover) with a handle that
                                    slides into the bottom part. The top has a raised middle part in
                                    which a square hole has been carved out, in which there is a
                                    hole piercing both tablets through which a string was drawn. The
                                    square hole was then filled with clay on which a seal impression
                                    was made. The clay, seal impression, and a piece of the string
                                    are still extant. On the inside surfaces of the closed tablet is
                                    recording of a legal case dated in year one of ‘<q type="translation" lang="eng">the gracious
                                    lord, great king of kings of Khotan, Viśya Sīhya</q>’, formerly
                                    unknown. The case concerns the sale (lease) of a man’s brother
                                    to do state work on behalf of the villagers of Birgaṃdara to
                                    help pay their debt. The cover contains a summary of the legal
                                    decision, as the complete decision could only be read by
                                    breaking the seal. This tablet was reused, however, to record
                                    another legal decision on its underside.</p><p>There are two
                                    other similar double wooden tablets in the British Library
                                    collection, that had been long known and published, but this
                                    object had been stored away and was brought to my attention by
                                    Michael O’Keefe during one of my visits. It turned out to herald
                                    a new era of discoveries of such objects. About the same time,
                                    one was published in <title lang="eng">China
                                    Pictorial</title> 1981 that was also dated in the year of Viśya
                                    Sīhya and concerning the sale of a brother’s son (published by
                                    R.E. Emmerick). A few years later, on a visit to Urumqi and
                                    Turfan, I was told of a tablet in the Xinjiang Institute of
                                    Archaeology in Urumqi (no. WBH 01), which I was kindly allowed
                                    to inspect. This tablet recorded the sale by a monastery of a
                                    woman and her son (published by Professor Duan
                                    Qing).</p><p>Since then, a number of such tablets have come to
                                    light in China (now being published by Professor Duan Qing),
                                    which are shedding welcome new light on the history of Khotan in
                                    the late seventh to early eighth centuries.</p><p>To me,
                                        however, it seems like <link
                                            url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=IOL%20Khot%20W%201"
                                            >IOL Khot W 1</link> was what started this new
                                    spate of discoveries. That is why I choose it as my favourite
                                    object.</p></q></note>
                        <note><p><link
                                    url="http://idpuk.blogspot.co.uk/2014/02/a-few-of-our-favourite-things-16-oktor.html"
                                    >Link to original post on IDP blog.</link></p></note>
                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
            </msDescription>
            <msDescription n="17">
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>St Petersburg</settlement>
                    <repository>Institute of Oriental Manuscripts</repository>
                    <collection>Oldenburg</collection>
                    <idno type="current">F-32/4</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <msItem n="1">
                        <author><name lang="eng">Irina Popova</name></author>
                        <note><p>Irina Popova has been the Director of the <link
                                    url="http://www.orientalstudies.ru/eng/">Institute of Oriental
                                    Manuscripts</link>, Russian Academy of Sciences (RAS), since 2003. She is also Professor of
                                Chinese History and Language at <link url="http://eng.spbu.ru">St
                                    Petersburg State University</link>, the Faculty of Oriental
                                Studies. She was admitted to Leningrad State University in 1978 in
                                the Faculty of Oriental Studies, History of China Section. In
                                November 1983, she started her doctoral studies at the Leningrad
                                Branch of the Institute of Oriental Studies. Three years later, she
                                joined the staff of the Institute as a junior researcher. In 1988
                                she received her Ph.D. for the thesis on the Theory of the Rulership
                                in the Early Tang China and received her Habilitation in 2000. Her
                                major research areas are political thought, government and the
                                administrative system of medieval and especially Tang China, as well
                                as the study of Dunhuang and Chinese manuscripts held at the
                                Institute and archival documents on Russian Sinology.</p><p>Irina
                                Popova’s chosen item is <link
                                    url="http://idp.orientalstudies.ru/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=F-32/4"
                                    >F-32/4</link> from the collections of the <link
                                    url="http://www.orientalstudies.ru/eng/">Institute of Oriental
                                    Manuscripts</link>.</p></note>
                        <note><p>Irina Popova writes:</p><q><p>The manuscript of the ‘Library Document’ (<link
                                        url="http://idp.orientalstudies.ru/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=F-32/4"
                                        >F-32/4</link>) was discovered by the Second Russian
                                    Turkestan Expedition headed by Sergey Oldenburg in Dunhuang and
                                    became part of the collection of The Asiatic Museum (now
                                        The <link url="http://www.orientalstudies.ru/eng/">Institute
                                        of Oriental Manuscripts</link>, RAS) with all the other documents on September 1, 1915. The separate sheet of white
                                    paper (30 x 17.2 cm) was registered as a ‘Postscript to <title lang="san-Latn">Prajñāpāramitā Sūtra</title>’.</p><p>The text states that the ruler of
                                    Dunhuang Cao Zongshou and his wife Lady Fan issued an order to
                                    make cloth wrappers for Buddhist sutras and to supplement the
                                    lacunae in the library of Baoen Monastery. The document was
                                    dated the 15th day under the sign <term lang="chi-Latn">renyin</term> of the 7th month of the
                                    5th year under the reign of Universal Peace (<term lang="chi-Latn">Xianping</term>) of the
                                    Song Dynasty, which corresponds to August 25, 1002. This 4-line
                                    document therewith became one of the pearls of Russian
                                    collection, for the clear reason that there are not too many
                                    documents from the Library Cave bearing a full date. And it is
                                    remarkable and even unique, as it represents a long forgotten
                                    type of document that reflects the daily life of Chinese
                                    society in a provincial town located close to the state’s
                                    frontier.</p><p>Moroever, in the course of the research and
                                    print and on-line publication of the Dunhuang collections from
                                    all over the world no other document with a full date from later
                                    than this has come to light, even if there is circumstantial
                                    evidence that such documents may exist. So then, this
                                    unpretentious short manuscript <link
                                        url="http://idp.orientalstudies.ru/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=F-32/4"
                                        >F-32/4</link> retains its complete timeless
                            value.</p></q></note>
                        <note><p><link
                                    url="http://idpuk.blogspot.co.uk/2014/02/a-few-of-our-favourite-things-17-irina.html"
                                    >Link to original post on IDP blog.</link></p></note>
                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
            </msDescription>
            <msDescription n="18">
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>London</settlement>
                    <repository>The British Library</repository>
                    <collection>Stein</collection>
                    <idno type="current">1919,0101,0.139</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <msItem n="1">
                        <author><name lang="eng">Dan Waugh</name></author>
                        <note><p>Daniel C. Waugh is Professor Emeritus at the <link
                                    url="http://www.washington.edu">University of
                                Washington</link> (Seattle, USA), where in the mid-1990s, his
                                interests shifted from his original specialization, pre-modern
                                Russia, to Central Asia. The watershed from which has flowed ‘the
                                rest of his life’ was his commitment in 1998 to start teaching a
                                course on the Silk Roads, in preparation for which he enrolled in a
                                summer program at the Mogao Caves, co-sponsored by the <link url="http://www.silkroadfoundation.org/toc/index.html">Silkroad
                                    Foundation</link> and the <link ur="http://www.dha.ac.cn/">Dunhuang Academy</link>. In subsequent years, he was the
                                founding director of <link url="http://depts.washington.edu/silkroad"
                                    >Silk Road Seattle</link>, which sponsored a series of
                                educational programs and created an extensive set of Internet
                                resources. In 2003 he became editor of the <link
                                    url="http://www.silk-road.com/toc/newsletter.html">Silkroad
                                    Foundation’s journal</link>, which has now grown from a thin
                                newsletter to a substantial annual. Projects to develop and share
                                educational resources on the Silk Roads with the IDP are ongoing.
                                His chosen object is the Dunhuang silk banner <link
                                    url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=1919,0101,0.139"
                                    >1919,0101,0.139</link>.</p></note>
                        <note><p>Dan Waugh writes:</p><q><p>In 2009, I was in London examining
                                    the objects in the <link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org"
                                        >British Museum</link> which had been donated by C. P. Skrine
                                    after he had served as British Consul General in Kashgar in the
                                    early 1920s. Skrine’s modest collection included fragments of
                                    early Buddhist paintings and manuscripts which he had acquired
                                    in Khotan. The article I co-authored with Ursula Sims-Williams
                                    on the Skrine material and the antiquities market in Khotan then
                                    appeared in my journal <link
                                        url="http://www.silkroadfoundation.org/newsletter/vol8/srjournal_v8.pdf"
                                            ><title lang="eng">The Silk Road</title>, Vol.
                                    8</link>(PDF), and has since been published in Chinese
                                    translation.</p><p>On that trip to London, I was fortunate to be
                                    included in a private viewing of some of the Dunhuang banners,
                                    which Roderick Whitfield had organized for a colleague. When
                                    asked there in the storage rooms of the British Museum whether
                                    there were any of the banners from Mogao Cave 17 that I
                                    particularly wanted to see, with little hesitation I chose <link
                                        url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=1919,0101,0.139"
                                        >1919,0101,0.139</link>, a late ninth-century painting on
                                    silk depicting a bodhisattva holding a glass bowl. Why that
                                    painting? In the first instance for the bowl, which to my mind
                                    embodies much of what the ‘Silk Roads’ are all about. It is one
                                    of the Middle Eastern cut glass bowls (numerous in the Sassanian
                                    period) which traveled along the Silk Roads all the way to Japan
                                    where one is in the collection of the Shōsō-in at Nara. When
                                    found in archaeological contexts these bowls usually have a
                                    rough patina and no longer are transparent, but here one can see
                                    through the bowl the hand that is holding it. In a recent
                                    addition to its display of such Sassanian glass, the British
                                    Museum has included a replica (2007.6004.1) made by Japanese
                                    glass artist Tami Ishida to give a sense of how their facets
                                    would have sparkled when new.</p><p>That Dunhuang banner also
                                    evokes memories for me. When at the Mogao Caves for the first
                                    time in 1998, I was particularly struck by Cave 196, dated to
                                    893–4, that is, approximately the same time as the banner. Cave
                                    196 is distinctive in that, unlike most of the other Mogao
                                    caves, it has preserved its original entrance hall and also some
                                    of its statues in their original position on the large U-shaped
                                    altar platform of the main hall. The best known of these is a
                                    bodhisattva of great beauty in the position of 'royal ease',
                                    whose features remind us of the bodhisattva depicted on the
                                    banner.</p><p>Cave 196 is an early example of the the design of
                                    some of the largest and most impressive of the Mogao caves, best
                                    known from the ones commissioned by the Cao family in the tenth
                                    century. Among them is Cave 61, constructed about half a century
                                    after Cave 196, which contains the famous depiction of Mt. Wutai
                                    on the west wall and the numerous donor images of the Cao family
                                    in the lower register at the east side of the room. The
                                    imposing, larger-than-life statuary, which would have occupied
                                    the central altar platform in those caves, is no longer extant.
                                    Cave 196 thus offers a rare sense of what the devotee of the
                                    ninth or tenth century might actually have experienced upon
                                    entering such a cave, as though re-born in Paradise in the
                                    actual presence of the Buddhist divinities. The devotee of my
                                    imagination might well have earned merit by commissioning a
                                    banner whose elaborately garbed subject bears what would have
                                    been considered a most precious offering.</p><p>When we
                                    contemplate Dunhuang, our gaze tends to be directed inward, to
                                    the treasure trove of manuscripts, banners, murals and statuary
                                    which have so transformed our understanding of the Silk Roads.
                                    It is easy to get lost in the details. For many over the
                                    centuries down to the present, to visit the Mogao Caves has been
                                    a life-changing experience, with some of the most vivid memories
                                    the result of turning the gaze outwards. Remember that the
                                    founding of the caves is associated with a vision experienced at
                                    sunrise over the Sanwei Mountain to the east: Mogao is special
                                    not in the least for its extraordinary natural setting. Too few
                                    visitors today climb the hills to see the fragile strip of green
                                    below in its starkly beautiful desert setting and experience the
                                    landscape turning purple at sunset. Even fewer would spend a
                                    night (as I did in 1998) at the temple on the top of Sanwei
                                    Mountain with its curious ‘folk’ image of Guanyin, watching the
                                    moon rise and awakening next morning to a rosy-fingered
                                    dawn.</p></q></note>
                        <note><p><link
                                    url="http://idpuk.blogspot.co.uk/2014/03/a-few-of-our-favourite-things-18-dan.html"
                                    >Link to original post on IDP blog.</link></p></note>
                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
            </msDescription>
            <msDescription n="19">
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>London</settlement>
                    <repository>The British Library</repository>
                    <collection>Stein</collection>
                    <idno type="current">Neg 1240(90)</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <msItem n="1">
                        <author><name lang="eng">John Falconer</name></author>
                        <note><p>John Falconer is Lead Curator of Visual Arts at the <link url="www.bl.uk/">British
                                Library</link>. This includes the Library's photographic collections, which
                                are particularly strong on historical collections of India, his
                                specialism. However, he has also been working on the Stein and other
                                Central Asian photographic collections for over twenty years, having
                                catalogued those at the <link url="http://www.bl.uk/">British Library</link> and the <link url="http://www.mtak.hu/index_en.php">Library and
                                Information Centre of the Hungarian Academy of Sciences</link>. He has also
                                travelled and worked in the field, including on IDP Field Trips to
                                the Taklamakan: many of his own photographs are now in the Library's
                                collections and were on display at the <link
                                    url="http://idp.bl.uk/events/RGS2014/intro.html">IDP20
                                    photographic exhibition</link> at the <link url="http://www.rgs.org/HomePage.htm">Royal Geographical Society</link>.
                                He has also curated photographic exhibitions in Afghanistan, Sri
                                Lanka, Myamar, China and elsewhere. His chosen item is a photograph
                                taken by Robert Byron.</p></note>
                        <note><p>John Falconer writes:</p><q><p>In the decade before his untimely death in the early days of the
                                    Second World War, Robert Byron (1905–41) established an enduring
                                    reputation as an art and architectural historian. His travels
                                    through Iran and Afghanistan in search of the purest examples of
                                    Islamic architecture in the early 1930s are described in his
                                    best-known work, <title lang="eng">The Road to
                                    Oxiana</title> (1937). While frequently displaying the casual
                                    racism and snobbery common to so many upper-middle class
                                    Englishmen of his generation, the book remains a perceptive and
                                    often hilarious account of a difficult and sometime dangerous
                                    journey. Despite radically personal and often idiosyncratic
                                    opinions on architecture — he notes approvingly of the
                                    Gumbad-i-Alaviyan at Hamadan that it '<q type="transcription" lang="eng">wipes the taste of the
                                        Alhambra and the Taj Mahal out of one’s mouth … I came to
                                        Persia to get rid of that taste</q>' — he was a passionate
                                    devotee of the arts of Central Asia.</p><p>His extensive
                                    collection of photographs (British Library shelfmark: Neg 1240)
                                    is among the most enduring and valuable of his legacies,
                                    providing a unique record of the buildings encountered and
                                    described on his travels, many of them now inaccessible, altered
                                    or entirely destroyed. The image selected here is rare in
                                    including a human presence: in contrast to his prose, Byron was
                                    not significantly concerned in his photographs with evoking
                                    atmosphere or creating artistic images. His purpose was to
                                    provide an accurate visual record for his own writings and for
                                    future historians of architectural form. In his wanderings
                                    around the monuments of Herat, a city that has seen massive
                                    damage to its historic fabric in recent decades, he writes of
                                    feeling as one '<q type="transcription" lang="eng">who has lighted on the lost books of Livy, or
                                        an unknown Botticelli</q>'. His photographs preserve, however
                                    inadequately, something of this heritage.</p><p>Coincidentally,
                                    the Byron collection forms a further link with another important
                                    archive of photographs in the British Library. Byron nursed an
                                    unrequited passion for the traveller and writer Desmond Parsons
                                    until the latter’s death in 1937, and had lived with him in
                                    Peking in 1934. Parsons’ own photographs recording his visit to
                                    the Dunhuang Caves in 1935 (BL shelfmark: Photo 1275), were
                                    recently presented to the British Library and are also available
                                    for study on the <link url="http://idp.bl.uk">IDP
                                    website</link>.</p></q></note>
                        <note><p><link
                                    url="http://idpuk.blogspot.co.uk/2014/03/a-few-of-our-favourite-things-19-john.html"
                                    >Link to original post on IDP blog.</link></p></note>
                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
            </msDescription>
            <msDescription n="20">
                <msIdentifier>
                    <settlement>London</settlement>
                    <repository>The British Library</repository>
                    <collection>Stein</collection>
                    <idno type="current">Or.8210/S.3753</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                    <msItem n="1">
                        <author><name lang="eng">John Cayley</name></author>
                        <note><p>John Cayley — now teaching at <link url="http://www.brown.edu/">Brown University</link> in the guise of a
                                pioneering practitioner and theorist of digital language arts — was
                                once, in the late 1980s, a curator in the Chinese Section of
                                    the <link url="http://www.bl.uk">British Library</link>. There,
                                he had experience with research relating to items in the Dunhuang
                                collection and, moreover, had the high privilege, occasionally, of
                                examining some of this material firsthand. Chinese calligraphy
                                remains a research interest for Cayley. The calligraphy of the major
                                part of the Dunhuang collection is a wonder of calligraphic art on a
                                global scale, but this ‘major part’ chiefly represents the art of
                                the religiously motivated scribe rather than that of the
                                scholar-artist, the Chinese person (usually man) of letters.
                                Nonetheless, the collection—as we will see from the item Cayley has
                                sponsored and which is also one of his very ‘favourite things’ —
                                does contain uniquely precious evidence for the high art of
                                calligraphy, China’s finest visual art, still its most dearly and
                                commercially valued traditional art form.</p><p>Besides aspiring,
                                some day, to a significant connoisseurship of Chinese calligraphy,
                                John Cayley is also a poet and a translator of poetry and has been
                                small publisher of these complementary language arts. He has
                                published translations from Gu Cheng, Yang Lian, Bing Xin, and
                                others, and assembled a book-length study of the well-known
                                contemporary artist Xu Bing. Links to his experimental writing in
                                what he calls networked and programmable media are at <link
                                    url="http://programmatology.shadoof.net"
                                    >programmatology.shadoof.net</link>. Recent and ongoing projects
                                    include <title lang="eng">imposition</title>, <title lang="eng"
                                    >riverIsland</title>, <title lang="eng">what we will</title>,
                                    and <link url="http://thereadersproject.org"><title lang="eng"
                                        >The Readers Project</title></link>. His last printed book
                                of poems, adaptations and translations was <title lang="eng">Ink
                                    Bamboo</title> (Agenda &amp; Belew, 1996).</p><p>In 2001 Cayley
                                was the winner of the Electronic Literature Organization’s Award for
                                Poetry (<link url="http://eliterature.org">eliterature.org</link>).
                                Currently he is a Professor in the <link
                                    url="https://brown.edu/academics/literary-arts/">Department of
                                    Literary Arts at Brown University</link>, with a brief to teach
                                and develop writing in digital media. His most recent work explores
                                ambient poetics in programmable media, writing in immersive
                                artificial audiovisual environments, and aestheticized vectors of
                                reading. He also publishes theory about these new modes of writing,
                                essays on subjects such as the role of code in new writing, the
                                temporal properties of text, and something he calls ‘writing to be
                                found’ both with and against the ‘services’ that threaten us with
                                overwhelming statistical models of language.</p></note>
                        <note><p>John Cayley writes:</p><q><p><link
                                        url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=Or.8210/S.3753"
                                        >Or.8210/S.3753</link> is not a sutra, nor a scroll. It is a
                                    relative small fragment of distinctively tinted, ‘fancy’, paper
                                    with traces of cursive characters. These traces would be
                                    immediately recognisable to any student of Chinese calligraphy
                                    and likely also to anyone more generally educated in the Chinese
                                    cultural sphere, extending beyond the mainland, throughout East
                                    Asia and now, the globe. This vastly more numerous group would
                                    not only see that the calligraphy was good, they would be likely
                                    to know the name of the artist who wrote these characters and is
                                    responsible for their aesthetic form, Wang Xizhi (303–361),
                                    China’s most famous calligrapher. Strangely, in terms of a
                                    Eurocentric understanding of high art, nearly all of these
                                    amateurs of calligraphy would also know, without having to be
                                    told, that these traces of ink on the paper of <link
                                        url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=Or.8210/S.3753"
                                        >Or.8210/S.3753</link> were not actually put there by Wang
                                    Xizhi. The true students of calligraphy amongst them would be
                                    aware that the current state of scholarship suggests to us that
                                    there are no actual traces of Wang Xizhi’s brushwork extant. As
                                    the eminent art historian, Robert E. Harrist, puts it in the
                                    title of a highly relevant article, we have nothing but ‘copies,
                                    all the way down.’ How then do we understand the significance
                                    and value of this treasure? We say that <link
                                        url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=Or.8210/S.3753"
                                        >Or.8210/S.3753</link> is a fragment of a <term lang="chi-Latn"
                                        >fatie</term> or ‘model (of) calligraphy’. We can say further
                                    that the art of Chinese calligraphy is a complex practice that
                                    has embraced many forms of what, from a Eurocentric perspective,
                                    we would regard — and tend to denigrate — as ‘copying’.</p><p>In the
                                    Chinese cultural sphere, these practices of ‘copying’ are
                                    understood as authentic and generative, and many of them are
                                    able to preserve, more or less intact, the aesthetic and
                                    cultural value of fine artistic works. In all their
                                    instantiations and despite their variously mediated
                                    transmission, such works of aesthetic writing may be
                                    definitively associated with a first author, with a single,
                                    named and often famous calligrapher. <link
                                        url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=Or.8210/S.3753"
                                        >Or.8210/S.3753</link> is a freehand copy (Chinese: <term
                                        lang="chi-Latn">lin</term>) and is dated, by its inclusion in
                                    the Dunhuang collection, to the Tang dynasty. The personal notes
                                    and courtesy letters written by Wang Xizhi were preserved and
                                    copied due to the beauty of his writing. Once his calligraphy
                                    had achieved the status of fine art treasure — within his
                                    lifetime — rare originals and more widely disseminated copies
                                    immediately became models for all calligraphy students and
                                    remain so right down to the present day. <link
                                        url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=Or.8210/S.3753"
                                        >Or.8210/S.3753</link> is a remarkably early copy of one of
                                    these models. The most prized collected copies of Wang Xizhi’s
                                    writing (such as <title lang="chi-Latn">Xingrang
                                        tie</title> or <title lang="eng">Ritual to Pray for Good
                                        Harvest</title> in the John B. Elliott Collection) are
                                    tracing copies, although these tracing copies done, probably
                                    under imperial patronage, with a finesse that somehow preserves
                                    even the spontaneity of the first artist’s cursive
                                    gestures.</p><p>Successful copies of all kinds may capture the <term
                                        lang="chi-Latn">shenyun</term> or ‘spirit resonance’ of Wang’s
                                    writing. Whenever performed by a calligraphic master, a freehand
                                    copy—most often written with some earlier ‘model’ or <term
                                        lang="chi-Latn">fatie</term> at the calligrapher’s side — may
                                    capture the <term lang="chi-Latn">shenyun</term> of the first writer and
                                    become itself a model. For <link
                                        url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=Or.8210/S.3753"
                                        >Or.8210/S.3753</link>, we have no indication of its
                                    contemporary calligrapher’s name, but we can see for ourselves
                                    that the characters are good and the early date of this copy
                                    renders it all but uniquely precious. There is another fragment,
                                    in the Pelliot collection in Paris (<link
                                        url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=Pelliot%20chinois%204642"
                                        >Pelliot chinois 4642</link>), likely from the same set of
                                    model copies and based on the same series of Wang Xizhi models,
                                        the <title lang="chi-Latn">Shiqi tie</title> or ’<title lang="eng">17 model
                                    calligraphies</title>.’ The majority of <link
                                        url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=Or.8210/S.3753"
                                        >Or.8210/S.3753</link> comprises the lower remains of a brief
                                    eight-line note known to calligraphers and connoisseurs as
                                        the <title lang="chi-Latn">Zhanjin tie</title>.</p><p>For
                                    still wider dissemination, model calligraphy might be traced and
                                    transferred onto the surface of prepared tablets or monumental
                                    stones. The character forms, no matter how cursive and gestural,
                                    were then carefully carved in intaglio. Finally, models could be
                                    ‘published’ from these inscriptions by making ink rubbings on
                                    sheets of paper tamped into the carved incisions — a slow process,
                                    but one that allowed for multiple ‘prints’ to be reproduced from
                                    the same model. Rubbings from the earliest carved inscriptions —
                                    think of all the mediating steps in this complex tradition of
                                    reproduction! — might themselves come to be esteemed for their
                                    preservation of a calligrapher’s writing and its <term
                                        lang="chi-Latn">shenyun</term>. If the stones were later lost
                                    or destroyed, a rubbing might be all that was left. There are,
                                    in fact, a few treasured early rubbings in the Dunhuang
                                    collection, including <link
                                        url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=Or.8210/S.5791"
                                        >Or.8210/S.5791</link> with the calligraphy of Ouyang Xun
                                    (557-641). Some time ago, as an experiment, I took a digital
                                    image of the main part of <link
                                        url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=Or.8210/S.3753"
                                        >Or.8210/S.3753</link>, and overlaid it on a scan from the
                                    publication of a much later rubbing based on the ‘same’ work.
                                    The white character forms of the rubbing are still, in
                                    principle, traceable back to the initial brush strokes of Wang
                                    Xizhi, but there can have been no direct connection — other than
                                    through artistry and <term lang="chi-Latn">shenyun</term> — with <link
                                        url="http://idp.bl.uk/database/oo_loader.a4d?pm=Or.8210/S.3753"
                                        >Or.8210/S.3753</link>’s anonymous freehand traces of ink on
                                    Tang dynasty paper. The way in which the two images align is not
                                    perfect but it is extraordinarily close — perceptible evidence, in
                                    a sense, of the preservation of <term lang="chi-Latn"
                                    >shenyun</term> across centuries and despite many and various
                                    processes of transmission by generative reproduction.</p><p>How
                                    valuable to wealthy collectors over time? In his essay 'The Cost
                                    of Living and the Cost of Art in Late Ming China’, Craig Clunas
                                    quotes a Chinese source giving evidence that some version —
                                    necessarily a reproduction — of this very piece of calligraphy,
                                        the <title lang="chi-Latn">Zhanjin tie</title>, changed hands
                                    in the late Ming for almost twice what it would cost to buy the
                                    equivalent of a Park Avenue or Mayfair mansion. In 2010, four
                                    lines of Wang Xizhi’s calligraphy — probably Tang tracing copies
                                    — sold at auction for £29m. A fragment of silk with nine lines
                                    on it had been torn in half and the first four lines were
                                    disposed of for this fabulous sum.</p></q><p>Clunas, Craig. ‘The
                                Cost of Living and the Cost of Art in Late Ming China.’ <title
                                    lang="eng">Association of Art Historians</title>. Sheffield,
                                1988.</p><p>Giles, Lionel. <title lang="eng">Descriptive Catalogue of
                                    the Chinese Manuscripts from Tunhuang in the British
                                    Museum</title>. London: Trustees of the British Museum,
                                1957.</p><p>Harrist Jr., Robert E. ‘Copies, All the Way Down: Notes
                                on the Early Transmission of Calligraphy by Wang Xizhi.’ <title
                                    lang="eng">The East Asian Library Journal</title> X.1 (2002):
                                176-96.</p><p>‘Rare Chinese calligraphy scroll fetches $46m at
                                auction.’ BBC News Asia-Pacific, 22 Nov. 2010. <link
                                    url="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-pacific-11811868"
                                    >http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-pacific-11811868</link>.</p></note>
                        <note><p><link
                                    url="http://idpuk.blogspot.co.uk/2014/03/a-few-of-our-favourite-things-20-john.html"
                                    >Link to original post on IDP blog.</link></p></note>
                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
            </msDescription>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
