<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title lang="eng">Translation of The Lament of the Lady of Qin</title><author lang="eng">Giles, Lionel</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Brill</publisher><pubPlace>Leiden</pubPlace><date>1925-6</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>International Journal of Chinese Studies</p><bibl id="Giles_1925-6"><author>Giles, Lionel</author><title level="a" lang="eng">The Lament of the Lady of Ch'in</title><title level="j">T'oung
                        Pao</title><biblScope>24 (1925-6):
                        305-80</biblScope><date>1925-6</date><keywords>Rebellion</keywords><keywords>Huang
                        Chao</keywords><genBibl/></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc>Translation</projectDesc></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><head><p>This is a translation by Lionel Giles of a poem about the Huang Chao rebellion. In
                an introduction to the translation (pp.305-325), Giles describes how he collated the
                text from fragments in London and Paris, and sketches the historical background of
                Huang Chao's rebellion. He concludes with the following remarks about the
                translation, "The diction, as befits narrative, is simpler and more direct than in
                the standard poem, and is for the most part free from the allusiveness which is apt
                to make Chinese poetry so obscure. The law of parallelism, too, is not so strictly
                observed, though it is seldom ignored altogether. While trying to make my
                translation readable, I have aimed above all at literalness, so far as this is
                compatible with the fundamental differences of Chinese and English.The poem is a
                long one of its kind - almost exactly twice the length of 'The Everlasting
                Resentment' - and may be conveniently divided into some dozen or more episodes, as
                shown in the following synoptical analysis:</p><p>1-16. Introductory: the poet's
                meeting with the Lady.</p><p>17-32. The Lady's story: the coming of the
                rebels.</p><p>33-52. The sack of Chang'an.</p><p>53-84. The fate of the four
                girls.</p><p>85-108. The Lady in the rebel's camp.</p><p>109-126. A forlorn
                hope.</p><p>127-146. Desolation of the city after the storm.</p><p>147-158. The
                journey through the ruined countryside.</p><p>159-178. Episode of the Golden
                God.</p><p>179-188. On the road to Luoyang.</p><p>189-216. Episode of the old man
                reduced to beggary.</p><p>217-224. Reports from other provinces.</p><p>225-236. A
                visitor from Jiangnan.</p><p>237-238. Envoi.</p></head><body><msDescription n="1" type="LG"><msIdentifier><idno type="current">Or.8210/S.692</idno><idno type="current">Or.8210/S.5476</idno><idno type="current">Or.8210/S.5477</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="Whole text"><title lang="eng">The Lament of the Lady of Qin. By the Right Buque
                            Weizhuang.</title><q lang="eng"><lg><l>In the guimao year of Zhonghe, in the third month of spring,</l><l>Outside the city walls of Luoyang, the blossom was like snow.</l><l>East and west, north and south, wayfarers were at rest;</l><l>The green willows were still, their fragrant scent was
                                    departed.</l><l>Suddenly, by the wayside I saw a flower-like lady</l><l>Reclining in solitude beneath the shade of the green willows.</l><l>Her phoenix head-dress was awry, and a lock of hair lay athwart
                                    her temples.</l><l>Her face showed traces of care, and there was a pucker between
                                    her eyebrows.</l><l>I made bold to question her, saying: "O Lady, whence do you
                                    come?"</l><l>Looking distressed, she was about to speak, when a sob choked her
                                    utterance.</l><l>Then, turning her head and gathering up her sleeves, she
                                    apologized to the traveller:</l><l>"Tossed and engulfed in the waves of revolution, how can I find
                                    words to speak?</l><l>Three years back I fell into the hands of the rebels and was
                                    detained in the land of Qin,</l><l>And the things that happened in Qin seem engraved in my
                                    memory.</l><l>If you, Sir, can loosen your golden saddle to hear my story,</l><l>I for my part will stay my jade footsteps in your company....</l></lg><lg><l>The year before last, on the fifth day of the sacrificial moon in
                                    Gengzi,</l><l>I had just shut the golden bird-cage after giving a lesson to my
                                    parrot</l><l>And was looking sidelong in my phoenix mirror as I lazily combed
                                    my hair,</l><l>Idly leaning the while on the carved balustrade in silent
                                    thought,</l><l>When suddenly I beheld a cloud of red dust rising outside the
                                    gates,</l><l>And men appeared in the streets beating metal drums.</l><l>The citizens rush out of doors half-dazed with terror,</l><l>And the courtiers come flocking in, still suspecting a false
                                    rumour.</l><l>Meanwhile, Government troops are entering the city from the
                                    west,</l><l>And propose to meet the emergency by marching to the Tong
                                    Pass.</l><l>The general cry is that the Boye troops are holding the enemy in
                                    check,</l><l>And all agree that the rebel army, though on the way, has not yet
                                    arrived.</l><l>Yet a little while, and my husband gallops up on horseback;</l><l>Dismounting, he enters the gate; stupefied he stands, like a
                                    drunken man.</l><l>Even now he had met the Purple Canopy departing into exile,</l><l>And had seen the white banners advancing from all parts of the
                                    country....</l></lg><lg><l>Supporting the infirm and leading children by the hand, fugitives
                                    are calling to one another in the turmoil;</l><l>Some clamber on to roofs, others scale walls, and all is in
                                    disorder.</l><l>Neighbours in the south run into hiding with neighbours in the
                                    north,</l><l>And those in the east make for shelter with those in the
                                    west.</l><l>Our northern neighbour's womenfolk, trooping all together,</l><l>Dash wildly about in the open like stampeding cattle.</l><l>Boom, boom! — Heaven and earth shake with the rumbling of chariot
                                    wheels,</l><l>And the thunder of ten thousand horses' hoofs re-echoes from the
                                    ground.</l><l>Fires burst out, sending golden sparks high up into the
                                    firmament,</l><l>And the twelve official thoroughfares are soon seething with
                                    smoke and flame.</l><l>The sun's orb sinks in the west, giving place to the cold pale
                                    light of the moon.</l><l>God utters never a word, but His heart is surely bursting within
                                    him.</l><l>A dark halo of misty cloud seems to encircle the moon with many
                                    rings,</l><l>And the Eunuch Stars, gliding in their courses, assume the colour
                                    of blood;</l><l>The Purple Exhalation secretly follows the Emperor's Throne as it
                                    shifts from place to place,</l><l>And baleful rays are stealthily shooting at the Tai Stars for
                                    their destruction.</l><l>Every home now runs with bubbling fountains of blood,</l><l>Every place rings with a victim's shrieks — shrieks that cause
                                    the very earth to quake.</l><l>Dancers and singing-girls must all undergo secret outrage;</l><l>Infants and tender maidens are torn living from their parents'
                                    arms.</l></lg><lg><l>Our eastern neighbour had a daughter, whose eyebrows were but
                                    newly painted:</l><l>A beauty above all price, to overthrow a city or a state;</l><l>Between tall spears she is escorted into a warrior's chariot,</l><l>Turning to gaze back at her fragrant boudoir, while her
                                    handkerchief is soaked with tears.</l><l>So now she is pulling out golden thread and learning to sew
                                    banners,</l><l>Or she is raised upon a carved saddle and made to sit a galloping
                                    steed.</l><l>Now and again, from her horse, she catches sight of her
                                    goodman,</l><l>But dares not turn her eyes upon him, and has to shed tears in
                                    vain.</l></lg><lg><l>Our western neighbour had a daughter — verily, a fairy
                                    maiden!</l><l>Sidelong glances flashed from her large limpid eyes,</l><l>And when her toilet was done, she reflected the spring in her
                                    mirror;</l><l>Young in years, she knew naught of the world outside her
                                    door.</l><l>A ruffian comes leaping up the steps of her abode;</l><l>Pulling her robe from one bare shoulder, he attempts to do her
                                    violence,</l><l>But, though dragged by her clothes, she refuses to pass out of
                                    the vermilion portal,</l><l>And thus with her rouge and fragrant unguents she meets her death
                                    under the knife.</l></lg><lg><l>Our southern neighbour had a daughter — I cannot recall her
                                    name;</l><l>'Twas but the other day that a worthy go-between had brought her
                                    betrothal present</l><l>She had heard no footfalls on her steps of glazed tiles,</l><l>And saw but the shadows of men on her blind of kingfisher
                                    blue.</l><l>Suddenly the clash of sword-blades is heard in the courtyard
                                    below,</l><l>And in a moment's space heads and trunks are lying severed on the
                                    ground.</l><l>Raising their eyes to heaven, then covering their faces, and
                                    uttering one wail of horror,</l><l>She and her sister threw themselves together into a well.</l></lg><lg><l>At our northern neighbour's, the youthful matron was being urged
                                    to depart;</l><l>So she was shaking out her cloud-like tresses, and wiping the
                                    paint from her eyebrows,</l><l>When she heard the noise of men battering down the lofty
                                    gates,</l><l>And instinctively she climbed the stairs into the upper
                                    storey.</l><l>But soon on every side there appeared the blaze of fire,</l><l>And when she would have descended again, the staircase itself was
                                    destroyed.</l><l>Then came loud screams from amidst the smoke, still imploring for
                                    rescue,</l><l>But ere long her corpse, hanging over the cross-beams, was
                                    reduced to ashes.</l></lg><lg><l>By good hap, I was able to preserve myself intact from murderous
                                    weapons;</l><l>But daring not stand irresolute nor look back at the home I was
                                    leaving, I combed the hair over my brows to follow the army on
                                    their march,</l><l>And, forcing a cheerful expression,33) issued forth from the door
                                    of my dwelling.</l></lg><lg><l>No means, after this, of returning to my old village;</l><l>No place, henceforth, where I could seek my kith and kin;</l><l>For since I fell into the rebels' hands three years have run
                                    their course,</l><l>And always I have been a prey to anxious care, my heart quaking
                                    with fear.</l><l>At night I lie encircled by a thousandfold ring of swords and
                                    spears,</l><l>In the morning I have to make a meal off minced human livers.</l><l>Albeit I am taken to a nuptial couch, how can it give me joy?</l><l>Though I have jewels and riches in plenty, they are not my
                                    heart's desire.</l></lg><lg><l>Their hair is unkempt, their faces begrimed, their eyebrows
                                    shaggy and red:</l><l>Often when I turn my eyes upon them, I cannot endure the
                                    sight.</l><l>Their clothes are put on all awry, the language they speak is
                                    strange;</l><l>Overweening pride in their prowess is writ large in their
                                    faces.</l><l>Their officers of the Cypress Terrace are a lot of cunning
                                    foxes,</l><l>Their members of the Orchid Office are so many slinking rats.</l><l>In their close-cropped hair they would fain stick ornamental
                                    hairpins,</l><l>Without removing their Court robes they roll themselves in
                                    embroidered coverlets.</l><l>Clutching their ivory tablets upside down, they masquerade as
                                    Ministers of State;</l><l>With the golden fish at their girdles wrong way up, they play the
                                    part of Court officials.</l><l>In the morning I hear them entering the Audience Chamber to
                                    present their memorials,</l><l>But in the evening one sees them brawling as they make their way
                                    to the wine tavern.</l></lg><lg><l>One morning, in the fifth watch, everybody gets up in alarm,</l><l>With much shouting and excited clamour, as though discussing some
                                    secret news.</l><l>During the night, it seems, a mounted scout had ridden into the
                                    Imperial City</l><l>To say that the previous day the Government troops had occupied
                                    Chishui.</l><l>Now, Chishui is but a hundred li from the city,</l><l>And if they set out at dawn they ought to be here by
                                    nightfall.</l></lg><lg><l>The ruffianly crew sit in gloomy silence on their horses,</l><l>But the female attendants in my chamber give secret vent to their
                                    joy.</l><l>All say that our grievous wrongs will now be avenged,</l><l>And we confidently expect that the villainous horde will this day
                                    meet their doom.</l><l>Horsemen galloping hither and thither fill the air with exciting
                                    rumours:</l><l>'Tis said that our army is on the march to enter the capital in
                                    full strength!</l><l>Big Peng and little Peng look at each other in distress,</l><l>While What's-his-name and What-d'ye-call-him cling to their
                                    saddles and weep.</l></lg><lg><l>Thus things drift on for several days, and still there is no
                                    news,</l><l>So we must suppose that these advancing troops already have jade
                                    tablets in their mouths,</l><l>And that they came waving flags and brandishing swords only in
                                    order to submit;</l><l>Further it is reported that all the Government armies have been
                                    routed and put to flight.</l></lg><lg><l>After this, great misery and distress prevail on every side;</l><l>A bushel of gold is the price of a single peck of grain;</l><l>In Shang Rang's kitchen the bark of trees is used as food,</l><l>On Huang Chao's table human flesh is carved.</l><l>Communication is cut off from the south-east, and there is no
                                    road for supplies.</l><l>Gradually the ditches and streams are choked up, while the
                                    population dwindles.</l><l>Stiffening corpses lie in heaps outside the Liujun Gate,</l><l>And the Qijia Camp is strewn with those who have starved to
                                    death.</l></lg><lg><l>Chang'an lies in mournful stillness: what does it now
                                    contain?</l><l>— Ruined markets and desolate streets, in which ears of wheat are
                                    sprouting.</l><l>Fuel-gatherers have hacked down every flowering plant in the
                                    Apricot Gardens,</l><l>Builders of barricades have destroyed the willows along the
                                    Imperial Canal.</l><l>All the gaily-coloured chariots with their ornamented wheels are
                                    scattered and gone,</l><l>Of the stately mansions with their vermilion gates less than half
                                    remain.</l><l>The Hanyuan Hall is the haunt of foxes and hares,</l><l>The approach to the Flower-calyx Belvedere is a mass of brambles
                                    and thorns.</l><l>All the pomp and magnificence of the olden days are buried and
                                    passed away;</l><l>Only a dreary waste meets the eye: the old familiar objects are
                                    no more.</l><l>The Inner Treasury is burnt down, its tapestries and embroideries
                                    a heap of ashes;</l><l>All along the Street of Heaven one treads on the bones of State
                                    officials.</l></lg><lg><l>Day was breaking when we arrived at the highway east of the
                                    city,</l><l>And outside the walls wind-borne smoke tinged the landscape with
                                    the dismal hue of the frontier region.</l><l>Along the road we sometimes saw roving bands of soldiers;</l><l>At the foot of the Slope was heavy silence — no speeding nor
                                    welcoming of guests.</l><l>Looking eastward from Baling, we see no trace of human life, or
                                    habitation;</l><l>From Li Shan bosomed in trees, the wealth of blue and gold has
                                    utterly departed.</l><l>All the great roads are now become thickets of brambles,</l><l>And benighted travellers sleep in ruined shells, under the light
                                    of the moon.</l></lg><lg><l>Next morning, at dawn, we arrive at Sanfenglu,</l><l>Where of countless inhabitants not a single household
                                    remains;</l><l>The deserted fields and gardens show nothing but weeds;</l><l>The trees and bamboos are destroyed, and everything is
                                    ownerless....</l></lg><lg><l>I turn to interrogate a Golden God in his wayside shrine,</l><l>But the Golden God is silent: he is more melancholy than
                                    ourselves.</l><l>Of the aged cypresses before the temple only mangled stumps
                                    remain;</l><l>The bronze incense-burners in the sanctuary secrete nothing but
                                    dust.</l><l>Ever since the frenzied Eobber brought the Middle Kingdom under
                                    his yoke,</l><l>Heaven and earth have been shrouded in gloom and darkened with
                                    storms;</l><l>The holy water before the altar has failed in its magic
                                    power,</l><l>The warriors of the underworld, painted on the wall, have been
                                    unable to repel the invaders.</l></lg><lg><l>In days of ease (says the God) I was merely content to enjoy the
                                    food-offerings bounteously provided,</l><l>But in time of stress I can bring no aid, nor manifest my
                                    supernatural power.</l><l>Now I am ashamed of being such a helpless God:</l><l>Let me flee far into the mountains and there hide me as best I
                                    can.</l><l>Within these precincts I hear no sound of flutes and pipes,</l><l>In the place of offering I look in vain for a sacrificial
                                    victim.</l><l>Therefore let some hideous demon be installed in my place near
                                    the village,</l><l>Who shall torture and slay the unhappy people from morning to
                                    night.</l></lg><lg><l>— When I heard these words, my melancholy grew deeper still.</l><l>Heaven sends down calamities in their season which are not in our
                                    power to control.</l><l>If a God can flee thus from trouble into the mountains,</l><l>Why should we look with censure on the noblemen in the East?</l></lg><lg><l>The year before last, I was also taken over the Yangzhen
                                    Pass,</l><l>And, raising my head, saw Mount Jing towering into the
                                    clouds.</l><l>It was like passing out of hell into the company of living
                                    men</l><l>To be suddenly ware of a world untroubled and at peace.</l><l>The Governor of Shanzhou is loyal and upright:</l><l>He excites no clash of arms, but contents himself with guarding
                                    his city.</l><l>The Governor of Pujin is able to repress the spirit of war,</l><l>And all is tranquil for a thousand li: no sound of weapons is
                                    heard.</l><l>By day you may carry your valuables abroad, and no man will
                                    interfere with you;</l><l>By night you may travel all alone, with gold hairpins sticking in
                                    your coiffure.</l></lg><lg><l>Next morning, as we passed eastwards of Xin'an,</l><l>We fell in with an old man begging for rice-gruel by the
                                    wayside,</l><l>His hair sprinkled with white, his face of a livid hue,</l><l>Who was crouching for concealment amidst the undergrowth of
                                    weeds.</l><l>I asked him, saying: "To what village do you belong?</l><l>And why are you lying under the cold sky, exposed to frost and
                                    dew?"</l></lg><lg><l>The old man stood up for a moment and was about to tell his
                                    story,</l><l>But sank back with his head in his hands and wailed aloud to
                                    heaven.</l><l>— "My native homestead was on the register of Dongji Xian,</l><l>And every year I had land covered with crops and mulberry trees
                                    amounting to nearly a tian;</l><l>The fertile fields which I sowed each year were two hundred chan,
                                    in extent;</l><l>The household tax I paid annually came to thirty million
                                    cash.</l><l>My daughters were practised in weaving cloaks of serge and
                                    sarcenet,</l><l>My daughters-in-law were able to cook meals of red millet.</l><l>A thousand granaries were mine!</l><l>Ten thousand waggons too!</l><l>And after Huang Chao's passage, a moiety still was left.</l></lg><lg><l>But ever since the armed hosts have been encamped in Luoxia,</l><l>Day and night, patrolling bands have entered the village
                                    ramparts;</l><l>The glittering blade, like unto the Green Serpent, is plucked
                                    from its scabbard;</l><l>The wind above our heads blows out the flags and reveals the
                                    White Tiger.</l><l>Entering the gates, they dismount and swoop down like a
                                    whirlwind,</l><l>Ransack the buildings, empty the money-bags: everything is swept
                                    bare.</l><l>And when all my patrimony is gone, even my flesh and blood are
                                    torn from me,</l><l>So that now, in my declining years, I am left alone in my
                                    wretchedness.</l><l>Alone in my wretchedness, ah me! yet what call have I to
                                    lament?</l><l>— In the hills there are thousands on thousands like myself,</l><l>Who spend their days searching for wild berries to still their
                                    hunger,</l><l>And sleep by night under the frosty sky, couching upon the rank
                                    weeds".</l></lg><lg><l>On hearing this old fellow's heart-rending tale of woe,</l><l>Tears coursed down my cheeks all day like rain.</l><l>Stirring abroad, I heard but the hooting of the owl, that bird of
                                    revolution.</l><l>We intended to hasten still further east, to find some place of
                                    abode,</l><l>But now we hear that all traffic by boat or cart is stopped on
                                    the road to Pien.</l><l>They also say that there has been mutual slaughter at
                                    Peng-men,</l><l>Where the aspect of the countryside would cause even a warrior to
                                    swoon,</l><l>And where the rivers and streams are half composed of the blood
                                    of murdered men....</l></lg><lg><l>Now I happen to hear that a visitor has arrived from
                                    Jinling,</l><l>Who reports that in Jiangnan things are quite
                                    otherwise than here;</l><l>For ever since the Great Brigand
                                    invaded the Central Plain,</l><l>No war-horses have been bred on
                                    the frontiers of that land.</l><l>The Governor there regards the
                                    extirpation of thieves and robbers as a work of heavenly
                                    merit,</l><l>While he treats his people as tenderly as though
                                    they were newborn babes.</l><l>His walls and moats offer secure
                                    protection, as if made of metal and filled with boiling
                                    water,</l><l>And with the levies and taxes that pour in like
                                    rain he provides troops and ramparts.</l><l>While the whole
                                    Empire, alas! is in a state of fermeut,</l><l>This one district
                                    remains smoothly tranquil and undisturbed;</l><l>It is only the
                                    denizens of the capital that must flee to escape calamity,</l>So
                                that in our yearning for peace we must envy even the ghosts of
                                Jiangnan.</lg><p>— I pray, Sir, that when you have plied the oar once more and
                                journeyed back to the East, You will present to His Excellency this
                                lengthy ballad that I have sung.</p></q></msItem></msContents></msDescription></body></text></TEI.2>
