<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title lang="eng">Translation of The Tale of Master Yuan of Mount Lu</title><author id="TS">Tansen Sen</author><author id="VM">Victor H. Mair</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Hawai'i Press</publisher><pubPlace>Honolulu</pubPlace><date>2005</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Printed book</p><bibl><ref>"Steinhardt_Mair_Goldin_2005"</ref></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc>Translation</projectDesc><editorialDecl>Converted into TEI XML by Maude Croucher in 2007. Imported to 4D on
                13/06/07 by Sam van Schaik.</editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><head><p>"The Tale of Master Yuan of Mount Lu" (Lu shan Yuan gong hua) is one of numerous
                manuscripts Marc Aurel Stein (1862-1943) procured from Dunhuang in 1907. Numbered
                Stein 2073 the manuscript is written in two hands on coarse, whitish paper. A
                colophon notes that the text was copied by Zhang Changji in the fifth year of the
                Kaibao era (972). The manuscript is now housed in the British Library, London,
                United Kingdom.</p><p>The main character of this story is the eminent monk Huiyuan
                (334—416), known for his contacts with contemporary gentry, exchanges with the
                usurper Huan Xuan (369—404), correspondence with the renowned translator Kumarajiva
                (344—409/413), and his teaching of dhyāna(meditation) practices at Mount Lu in
                Jiangxi Province from 373. Huiyuan emphasized the importance of worshiping Amitabha
                Buddha, who presides over the Western Paradise, and is famous for his essay "A Monk
                Does Not Bow Down before a King" (Shamen bu jing wang zhe lun). In his youth,
                Huiyuan diligently studied the Confucian classics and was particularly fond of
                Taoism. Thus he was broadly learned, not only in Buddhist precepts, but in
                traditional Chinese thought as well.</p><p>Another eminent monk mentioned in the
                text is Daoan (312—385). Daoan was one of the most influential Buddhist
                personalities in China during the Eastern Jin period (317—420). He stressed the need
                for vinaya (monastic rules of discipline) and immersed himself deeply in the study
                of prajñā-pāramitā (intuitive wisdom) literature. And, whereas Huiyuan encouraged
                the worship of Amitabha, Daoan had organized a cult to Maitreya, the Buddha of the
                future.</p><p>It is curious that, in real life, Huiyuan was a disciple (in fact, the
                favorite pupil) of Daoan, and it was his encounter with the latter in the year 354
                that made him turn to Buddhism in the first place. In the present tale, however,
                Huiyuan is depicted as though he were the teacher of Daoan. Consequently, we can
                safely assume that "The Tale of Master Yuan of Mount Lu," which dates to more than
                half a millennium after the lifetimes of its protagonists, must have been composed
                for the sectarian purpose of elevating Huiyuan and his partisans over Daoan and his
                adherents. There are also many other aspects of the tale that are at odds with
                historical reality, such as the name of Huiyuan's teacher mentioned in the second
                paragraph, his capture by the bandit Bo Zhuang, his servitude to Prime Minister Cui,
                the displacement of a birthmark on Daoan's arm to Huiyuan's, his alleged authorship
                of an enormous commentary on the Mahāparinirvāna-sūtra, and so forth.</p><p>Without
                going into elaborate detail, the probable source of the massive distortions in "The
                Tale of Master Yuan of Mount Lu" is roughly determinable. First of all, in his
                Treatise on the Three Rewards (San bao lun), Huiyuan did write about nirvana, the
                central doctrine of this tale. Furthermore, he had a disciple named Daosheng who
                concentrated heavily on the Nirvāna-sūtra and was one of its strongest advocates.
                Now, when written quickly (in "grassy" style), the Chinese characters for Daoan and
                for Daosheng look rather similar. Thus it is quite likely that some early author had
                penned an attack on Daosheng (Huiyuan's student) for having appropriated Huiyuan's
                ideas on nirvana and that his sloppy calligraphy resulted in the transfer of his
                critique to Daoan (Huiyuan's teacher). To complicate matters further, there was
                another, later Huiyuan (523-592) who was—like Daosheng—also a staunch advocate and
                well-known exegete of the Nirvāna-sūtra. A contemporary of his, Tanyan (d. 588),
                indeed, wrote a huge commentary on this sutra in fifteen scrolls, and it was this
                commentary that was most influential as a guide to the text during the period when
                our tale was composed.</p><p>Regardless of their origin, the legends embodied in
                this tale were still being widely circulated as late as the fourteenth century, when
                Buddhist historians denounced them as false depictions of Huiyuan and Daoan. Despite
                all of the historical inaccuracies and legendary aspects of "The Tale of Master Yuan
                of Mount Lu," however, this fascinating narrative is valuable for its vivid
                description of medieval Buddhist lectures and debates. Finally, in terms of the
                development of narrative, this is the longest sustained tale to have appeared in
                China up to the time when it was written.</p><p>The following translation is based
                directly on a very close reading of the original Dunhuang manuscript. As such, it is
                occasionally different from all modern published versions of the text. The
                discrepancies result from factors such as the following: where to break sentences;
                where to insert punctuation; how to divide up words; how to interpret graphs that
                are sloppily written, erroneous, out of order, interpolated, omitted, or rubbed out;
                and so forth.—TS, VHM</p></head><body><msDescription n="1" type="VS,TM"><msIdentifier><idno type="current">Or.8210/S.2073</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="Whole text"><title lang="eng">The Tale of Master Yuan of Mount Lu</title><q lang="eng"><p>Now, we have heard that the Dharma
                                    King<note type="footnote" n="1">Dharma basically means "statute"
                                    or "law." When capitalized in this story, it signifies the body
                                    of teachings expounded by the Buddha. It is the duty of a
                                    Buddhist to be knowledgeable about the Dharma and to act in
                                    accordance with it so as to achieve enlightenment. When not
                                    capitalized, dharma refers to the basic, minute elements from
                                    which all things are made, to the principle or law that orders
                                    the universe, or to the teachings of other religions than
                                    Buddhism.</note>is magnificent and the teachings of the Buddha
                                are imposing. The laws of the king are devoid of selfishness, and
                                the actions of the Buddha are impartial.<note type="footnote" n="2">Chinese pingdeng = Sanskrit sama(tā). This is a key word in the
                                    story. It signifies equitableness, especially with regard to the
                                    impartiality and universality of the Buddha.</note>While the
                                king transmitted the Right Teachings, the Buddha has expounded the
                                True Tenets. All these are now part of the twelve canonical
                                    genres.<note type="footnote" n="3">Sanskrit
                                    dvādasānga-dharma-pravacana. These are: (1) sūtra (primarily
                                    prose discourses of the Buddha), (2) geya (verses which repeat
                                    the substance of the prose discourse found in the sutras), (3)
                                    gāthā (verses containing ideas not found in the sutras), (4)
                                    nidāna (historical narratives), (5) itivrttaka (past lives of
                                    the disciples of the Buddha), (6) jātaka (past lives of the
                                    Buddha), (7) adbhuta-dharma (tales of miracles performed by the
                                    Buddha), (8) avadāna (allegories), (9) upadeśa (discussions of
                                    doctrine, often in question-and-answer form), (10) udāna
                                    (statements of the Buddha not prompted by questions from his
                                    disciples), (11) vaipulya (sutras that deal with broad topics),
                                    (12) vyākarana (prophecies of the Buddha regarding the
                                    enlightenment of his disciples). It is obvious from this list
                                    that Buddhist literature is highly elaborated and that it values
                                    narrative and parables. The richness and sophistication of the
                                    Buddhist literary tradition was one of the most attractive
                                    features of this Indian religion when it came to
                                China.</note>They are all bridges to salvation built by Śākyamuni.
                                After the nirvana<note type="footnote" n="4">Since the Sanskrit word
                                    nirvāna (literally, "blowing out; extinguishing") is found in
                                    English dictionaries, it will not be written in italics and with
                                    diacriticals below, except in the Sanskrit titles of scriptures.
                                    A particularly important term in this story, nirvana in Hinduism
                                    refers to emancipation from ignorance and the elimination of all
                                    attachment or an ideal condition of stillness, stability, and
                                    harmony. In Buddhism, it signifies the ultimate state in which
                                    one attains disinterested wisdom and compassion. When used with
                                    reference to a Buddha, it indicates the sloughing off of his
                                    mortal body.</note>of the Tathāgata,<note type="footnote" n="5">Dharma King, Buddha, Śākyamuni (Sage of the Śākyas), and
                                    Tathāgata (The One Who Has Come/ Gone Thus) are all different
                                    manifestations of the same person. There are serious textual
                                    problems right at the very beginning of the tale, and it is
                                    possible that the author originally intended the first, third,
                                    and fifth clauses to refer to the secular king, his laws, and
                                    his doctrines. Such an interpretation, however, would require a
                                    certain amount of emendation.</note>the sages have all submerged
                                themselves in the doctrine of images.<note type="footnote" n="6">Sanskrit saddharma-pratirūpaka. The formal or imitative/image
                                    period of Buddhism, which is the second of three stages in the
                                    development of the religion: the real, the formal, and the
                                    final; or correct, semblance, and termination. These are also
                                    thought of as the three periods of a Buddha-kalpa (era or eon),
                                    the first lasting five hundred years, the second a thousand
                                    years, and the third also a thousand years.</note></p><p>There
                                was a monk called Zhantan<note type="footnote" n="7">Sanskrit
                                    candana (sandalwood). The author(s) of the story seem to be
                                    using a Sanskrit name for Hui-yuan's teacher in order to
                                    legitimate his training in Buddhist doctrine and to distance him
                                    from his actual teacher, Daoan, who is here transformed into his
                                    antagonist.</note>who had a disciple named Huiyuan. Speaking of
                                this Huiyuan, his family lived in Yanmen.<note type="footnote" n="8">In Shanxi Province.</note>There were only two brothers and no
                                other kinsmen. The older of the two, called Huiyuan, renounced lay
                                life and became a monk. The younger brother, called Huichi,
                                [remained behind] to look after their mother. When Huiyuan was with
                                monk Zhantan, he often recited the True Law and frequently read the
                                canonical texts. He delighted in his understanding of the Third
                                Stage of dhyāna<note type="footnote" n="9">This is the third dhyāna
                                    heaven of form, i.e., the highest paradise that is still
                                    conditioned by physical form.</note>and realized that the
                                [advent of the final] stage [in the development of Buddhism] was not
                                far. Then one day, with his palms pressed together, he said to the
                                monk, "Your disciple has humbly served you for many years already.
                                But, in the pursuit of learning, due to my own stupidity, I am still
                                uncultivated. Now, I would like to visit a famous mountain,<note type="footnote" n="10">Since famous Buddhist monasteries were
                                    often located in the mountains, saying "visit a mountain" was
                                    often tantamount to saying "visit a monastery."</note>follow
                                streams and cross rivers, visit priests and attend monks, and dwell
                                as a hermit beside a precipitous gorge so that I may live out my
                                life contentedly."</p><lg><l>His teacher asked, "If you leave now, to which mountain do you
                                    intend to go?"</l><l>Huiyuan said, "Your disciple can't distinguish between east and
                                    west, nor do I know of north, and south. I just have the desire
                                    to leave, but I don't know where I should go."</l><l>His teacher said, "If you leave now, just stay to the left of the
                                    river when you proceed on your pilgrimage. Stop when you reach
                                    Mt. Lu. That will be the place where you can cultivate
                                    yourself."</l></lg><p>Hearing these words, Huiyuan was so pleased that he was unable to
                                control himself. So, having received his teacher's instructions and
                                injunctions, how dared he disobey? Then, pressing his palms
                                together, he went forward and bowed. Twice formally bidding adieu to
                                the monk, he embarked on his long journey.</p><p>Wending his way and
                                taking with him a copy of the Nirvana Sutra,<note type="footnote" n="11">Nirvana Sutra, also called the Mahāparinirvāna-sūtra. The
                                    most influential translations of this scripture are by Faxian in
                                    418, Dharmaraksa in 421, and Xuanzang in 652. There are, as
                                    well, other earlier and later translations of the Nirvana Sutra
                                    into Chinese, several of them partial. One that may be of
                                    particular interest for the present tale is that done sometime
                                    between the years 424 and 452 by Huiyan and others. The
                                    confusing similarity of Huiyan's name to that of our hero,
                                    Huiyuan, perhaps help to account for the otherwise inexplicably
                                    close link between the latter and the Nirvana Sutra in this tale
                                    (see also the introduction to the tale). As with nirvana (see n.
                                    4), the Sanskrit word sūtra is now found in English
                                    dictionaries. Hence it will not be italicized and written in
                                    italics below except when it appears in the titles of Sanskrit
                                    scriptures or in philological analyses.</note>Master Yuan
                                traveled towards Mount Lu to cultivate the Way. It was the season
                                when rays of spring shone radiantly, the beautiful flowers emitted
                                fragrance, green willows waved supply in the breeze, and the tips of
                                bamboos bent gracefully. He gazed upon cloudy peaks in the distance
                                and watched winter geese hurrying homeward. Confident that his
                                determination to learn the Way was solid, he was intent upon early
                                attainment of the True Principles.</p><p>After walking for many
                                days, Master Yuan arrived at Jiangzhou.<note type="footnote" n="12">Jiang Prefecture, modern Jiujiang in Jiangxi Province.</note>He
                                walked through various byways and alleys, rested a couple of days,
                                and then started off again. After he had gone westward for more than
                                fifty tricents,<note type="footnote" n="13">A tricent (li) is three
                                    hundred paces or approximately one-third of a mile (Latin milia
                                    [passuum], "a thousand [paces]").</note>and just as he was
                                walking along the road, he came upon a mountain. He asked someone,
                                "What mountain is this?"</p><p>The villager answered, "This is Mount
                                Lu."</p><p>Master Yuan said [to himself], "On the day when I first
                                parted from my teacher, he instructed me to stop upon reaching Mount
                                Lu. This place is where I should cultivate the Way!"</p><p>The
                                mountain did not look like an ordinary one. What sort of unusual
                                realm was it?</p><lg><l>There were myriad soaring cliffs,</l><l>Thousands of interfolding plateaus;</l><l>High peaks reared upward,</l><l>Sharp crags loomed above.</l><l>Gibbons cried in dark valleys,</l><l>Tigers roared in deep ravines;</l><l>Withered pines were enwrapped by ancient wisteria,</l><l>Peach blossoms were touched by eternal freshness.</l></lg><p>Master Yuan was eager to enjoy himself on this mountain. As the sun
                                was about to complete its journey to the west, he entered into the
                                depths of the mountain looking for a place to stay. Then, on the
                                northern side of the top of Incense-Burner Peak, he built himself a
                                temporary grass hut. From his waist he took out his fire-stone and,
                                striking it, he lit some Priceless-Treasure incense. He sat down
                                with his legs crossed and began reading several chapters of the
                                Nirvana Sutra. The sounds of him reading the sutra were so clear and
                                distinct that they could be heard far and near. Dharmic rhymes
                                echoed and Sanskrit tones spread afar. Touched by [his recitation],
                                the great rocks swayed and the hundred grasses bowed. Auspicious
                                birds and numinous beasts all came to sing their praise.</p><p>At
                                this time, the Mountain Spirit in his temple suddenly realized that
                                this was an auspicious omen and was astonished like never before.
                                The Mountain Spirit inquired, "Who's on duty today?" The stout Tree
                                Spirit came in front of the hall and called out, "Yes, sir!" With a
                                voice like thunder, one head with three faces, eyes like suspended
                                mirrors, and carrying in his hands an iron staff as tall as himself,
                                the Tree Spirit said, "I so-and-so am on duty." The Mountain Spirit
                                responded, "So, it's you who is on duty! Just now as I was in my
                                temple, I suddenly noticed that the rocks of the mountain were
                                swaying and the birds and beasts were startled. Go and inspect the
                                mountain for me. Find out what omens there are. Perhaps a sage or
                                saint from some other place has come to my mountain. Or maybe some
                                strange creature or spirit has taken refuge among these mountains.
                                If it brings peace and happiness to my mountain, then admit it. If
                                it unsettles my mountain, then you should drive it away immediately
                                and make it leave this mountain."</p><p>The Tree Spirit called out,
                                "Yes, sir!" He covered everywhere over hill and dale, followed along
                                streams and crossed rivers. He even searched thoroughly under each
                                of the trees in the mountain forest, but could not find a single
                                person. However, when he reached the northern side of Incense-Burner
                                Peak, he saw a monk who had built a meditation hut and, sitting
                                cross-legged in it, was just at that moment reciting a
                                sutra.</p><p>Seeing this, the Tree Spirit hid his spectral form and
                                immediately changed into the body of an old man. He looked aged as a
                                dried water willow with white hair like mulberry leaves.<note type="footnote" n="14">The images of old age in this sentence
                                    are based on literary allusions dating to works of around the
                                    years 430 and 220 respectively.</note>Coming up to the hut, he
                                greeted the monk in a loud voice. Master Yuan said, "Myriad
                                blessings upon you!" The old man slowly came forward and started
                                speaking: "Your disciple does not know where you come from, how you
                                got here, and what you seek. I humbly beg you to be so kind as to
                                grant me an explanation."</p><p>Master Yuan answered, "This poor
                                monk has come from Yanmen to settle in this mountain for awhile and
                                engage in cultivation of the Way."</p><p>The old man asked again,
                                "Just now I heard your marvelous sounds. What were those
                                sounds?"</p><p>Master Yuan answered, "The sounds you heard just now
                                were of a poor monk reciting the sutras. When living beings hear
                                such sounds, they invariably wish to escape sorrow and seek
                                    deliverance."<note type="footnote" n="15">Sanskrit moksa, mukti,
                                    vimoksa, vimukti (liberation, emancipation, release,
                                    escape).</note></p><p>When the old man heard these words, he
                                exclaimed, "Good! Good!" Once again he inquired of the monk, "Having
                                already come here, monk, is there anything that you
                                need?"</p><p>Master Yuan replied, "If this poor monk can find a
                                monastery to dwell in, then I can avoid the wind and the frost. This
                                is the only wish that the poor monk has."</p><p>The old man said,
                                "If you wanted something else, then there might not be any, but if
                                it's a monastery that you desire, then this is a trivial matter.
                                Your disciple lives in the village to the west. Wait till I reach
                                the village and discuss the matter with various elders; then we will
                                come and build a monastery for you."</p><p>When he had finished
                                speaking, the old man bade farewell to the monk and
                                left.</p><p>After having taken leave of the monk, the old man was
                                only a hundred steps away from the front of the hut when he suddenly
                                disappeared. Instantly, he had changed back from the body of the old
                                man into his spectral form! When he arrived in front of the hall of
                                the Mountain Spirit, he bowed and called out, "Sir! I obeyed your
                                order and covered everywhere over hill and dale, searching for
                                goblins and fox-spirits, but failed to find anything. When I reached
                                the northern side of Incense-Burner Peak, I saw a monk who had built
                                himself a meditation hut. Sitting cross-legged, he was reciting a
                                sutra. He said that he had come from Yanmen and had temporarily
                                taken up residence in this mountain to engage in cultivation of the
                                Way."</p><p>After hearing this, the Mountain Spirit could only say
                                that he was greatly astonished. "I have guarded this mountain for
                                countless ka/pas"<note type="footnote" n="16">A kalpa is a thousand
                                    cycles of mahāyugas (periods of 12,000 years each), hence
                                    12,000,000 years, an unimaginably long time.</note>[thought the
                                Mountain Spirit,] "but never have I seen a monk take refuge in this
                                mountain. All of this will bring lasting fortune to my mountain and
                                ward off calamities." The Mountain Spirit asked again, "Does the
                                monk who has come here need anything?"</p><p>The Tree Spirit
                                memorialized, "I just asked him that. He doesn't really need
                                anything, but says that he would only want a monastery to live
                                in."</p><p>The Mountain Spirit said, "If he had wanted something
                                else, then it may have been difficult. But, if all he needs is a
                                monastery to dwell in, that is entirely a small matter. You don't
                                have to go anywhere far off. Just muster out the ghosts and the
                                spirits on this mountain on my behalf and ask them to build a
                                monastery for this monk."</p><p>After receiving the order, the Tree
                                Spirit, standing on the western slope, thrice knocked resoundingly
                                [with his staff]. All of a sudden, the clouds and mists darkened.
                                Right away, all the ghosts and spirits in the mountain arrived. That
                                night, as they wielded their magical implements, a hundred bolts of
                                lightning flashed and thunder pealed a thousand times. The
                                tumultuous noise went on till dawn as the ghosts and spirits built a
                                monastery. When dawn came, they had already completed an
                                extraordinary monastery. Here's what it was like:<note type="footnote" n="17">Literally," [all you could] see," a
                                    favorite phrase of storytellers to introduce a set piece of
                                    purple prose or verse.</note>the multistoried towers and
                                pavilions were no less [marvelous] than [the palaces of] the
                                Trāyastrimśa heaven;<note type="footnote" n="18">This is the heaven
                                    of the Brahmanical god Indra.</note>the jeweled halls and
                                terraces were equal to those of the Western Paradise;<note type="footnote" n="19">Of Amitabha Buddha.</note>there were
                                dense groves of trees and thickets of bushes; flowers bloomed
                                throughout the four seasons of the year; springs and streams flowed
                                beside it during both spring and winter, never drying up; all the
                                more, rare flowers and tender blossoms grew beside the cloisters of
                                enlightenment; and magical birds of good omen flew up toward the
                                roofs of the vihāra.<note type="footnote" n="20">A sanctuary for
                                    spiritual training.</note></p><p>Thereupon, when Master Yuan
                                came out of the hut and looked, he suddenly saw a completed
                                monastery. He gasped at how extraordinary it was. After
                                contemplating it for a long time, Master Yuan said, "This is not
                                something I could have done. This must be due to the mighty power of
                                the Mahānirvāna-sūtra" Observing its rarity, Master Yuan composed
                                the following gatha:<note type="footnote" n="21">Stanza of Buddhist
                                    verse.</note></p><lg><l>The tall, rustling bamboos turn the four seasons into spring,</l><l>The streamlets flowing in all directions clean the dust away;</l><l>Green is each branch of ivy that climbs on the walls,</l><l>Fresh is each patch of moss that covers the ground.</l><l>The distant wilderness is free from the hubbub of city
                                    markets,</l><l>The pure space has nothing vulgar as its neighbor;</l><l>The Mountain Spirit has built a vihāra at this place,</l><l>Monks must now be invited to turn the Dharma Wheel.</l></lg><p>And so Master Yuan himself entered the monastery; he went to
                                every room and walked through each courtyard. The monastery [seemed]
                                to have everything. However, they were short of water and there was
                                no place to fetch it. Master Yuan said, "This monastery is as
                                perfect as the Dharma. But if there is no drinking water, how can
                                one live here? Later, when the monks arrive, how will they get
                                water?" As he came down in front of the Buddha Hall, he saw that
                                there was a big rock [and thought that] there ought to be water
                                beneath it. Master Yuan pried the rock with his staff, whereupon he
                                found water that welled up out of the ground. To this day, it is
                                known as the "Monk's Staff Spring." There is also a monastery called
                                the "Monastery Built by Transformation."<note type="footnote" n="22">The original name of the monastery was "Monastery of the
                                    Illusory City."</note>The pool of running water beneath the
                                monastery is called the "White Lotus Pond."</p><p>Several months
                                after Master Yuan had moved into the monastery and settled down, an
                                audience hurried thither from the four directions. On this day
                                Master Yuan broadly explained the teachings of the Mahdnirvdna-sutra
                                to his assembled followers. Within a year, the audiences were as
                                thick as clouds, and their donations poured in like rain. All the
                                listeners at the meeting place noted that there was an old man in
                                the assembly who had been listening to the sutra for a year. They
                                said that this old man never gave his name when he came and never
                                mentioned his style when he left. He was always in his seat from the
                                beginning of the lecture and, as soon as the lecture ended, he would
                                go back. Master Yuan was very puzzled by this, so he asked those who
                                sat in the same row to direct the old man to him. When the old man
                                was called upon, he straightaway came in front of Master
                                Yuan.</p><p>Master Yuan asked, "Where do you live, old man? You have
                                been listening to the Dharma for a long time, yet we do not know
                                your name or surname. We would like to know some particulars about
                                you."</p><p>The old man answered, "Although the disciple has
                                listened for a year, I still have not understood the doctrines in
                                the Nirvana Sutra. Until I do, I cannot tell my name and
                                surname."</p><p>After he had finished speaking, the old man ran out
                                of the monastery gate. Master Yuan tried following the old man but
                                could not see any trace of him. Who was this person? It was the
                                Dragon [Spirit] of the thousand-feet-deep pool of Mt. Lu. He had
                                come to listen to Master Yuan preach the Dharma.</p><p>After he had
                                seen the old man depart, Master Yuan would feel regretful whenever
                                he thought of him. "This old man," thought Master Yuan, "has
                                listened to the Dharma for almost a year, but still does not
                                understand the meanings and the principles in the Nirvana Sutra. How
                                much less can I expeditiously help all living creatures to attain
                                enlightenment? How can I make the listeners understand? Surely, now,
                                I must produce a commentary on the Nirvana Sutra."</p><p>When he had
                                finished thinking these thoughts, he informed the Buddhas of the Ten
                                Directions, [saying,] "Now,for all sentient beings who are mired in
                                confusion and thus have not yet been enlightened to the teachings of
                                    Mahāyāna,<note type="footnote" n="23">The "Great Vehicle" of
                                    Buddhism, which is predominant in East Asia.</note>I, your
                                disciple, intend to make a commentary on the Nirvana Sutra and open
                                the hearts of all living beings to enlightenment. They will be able
                                to understand the Buddhist Dharma clearly and abandon falsehood to
                                follow truth. They will be free from all trace of doubts forever."
                                Then, in front of the Buddha Hall, he took a divine purple-cloud,
                                fine-haired writing-brush and, informing the Buddha-Tathāgatas of
                                the Ten Directions [of his intentions], while requesting that the
                                Earth God and all the local spirits bear witness, [announced,] "If
                                the saints and sages have objections, then may this brush fall down
                                immediately." When he had finished speaking and had burnt incense,
                                he declared his piety, then took the brush and threw it into the
                                air. At that moment, the brush remained motionless in midair. Master
                                Yuan knew that [his proposal] met with the approval of the
                                Buddha-Tathāgatas. He then requested that the brush descend from
                                midair. How do we know this? Until this day, there is still a
                                Throw-Brush Peak at Mount Lu in Jiangzhou.</p><p>Thus did Master
                                Yuan produce his commentary. From start to finish it took him three
                                years to complete, but still he was afraid that there were mistakes
                                in writing and that the purport of various passages might not be
                                comprehensible. So he wanted to take all the more than eight hundred
                                scrolls of the commentary outside the eastern gate of the monastery
                                and place them on a fire. He made a big bonfire with fragrant
                                firewood and repeatedly addressed the Buddhas of the Ten Directions,
                                the various bodhisattvas, and the saints and sages: "For all the
                                sentient beings who are mired in confusion and who have not yet been
                                enlightened to Mahāyāna, I, your disciple, wanted to eliminate their
                                doubts, so I composed this commentary. If the purport [of the
                                commentary] is in agreement with the sutra, then I hope that the
                                fire will not be able to burn it. If the commentary and the sutra
                                are in conformity, then water will not be able to submerge
                                it."</p><p>When he had finished speaking, he set the commentary
                                ablaze. Then the crimson flames reached up to the sky and the dark
                                smoke billowed thickly, but the sutra in the middle of all this
                                remained completely unscathed. Master Yuan knew that the commentary
                                had distantly met with the approval of the Buddhas. However, he was
                                still not satisfied! So next he took the commentary to the edge of
                                the White Lotus Pool and threw it toward the water. When the
                                commentary was still about ten feet above the water, it remained
                                motionless in midair. Master Yuan knew that the commentary had
                                distantly met with the approval of the Buddhas. Later, Master Yuan
                                took the commentary and carried it into the monastery, where he
                                placed it in the sutra library. Afterward, there was no lack of
                                disciples, and the people who came to listen to his lectures were
                                exceedingly numerous. Master Yuan's propagation of the teachings of
                                the Mahānirvāna-sūtra for the masses attracted listeners from all
                                directions. Like pouring rain and billowing clouds they eagerly came
                                to listen to the Dharma. From the beginning to the end, he delivered
                                his lectures for several years.</p><p>At this time, there suddenly
                                arose in the region of Shouzhou<note type="footnote" n="24">Shou
                                    Prefecture, approximately two hundred miles north of Mt. Lu in
                                    Anhui; modern Shou District.</note>a group of bandits led by a
                                man surnamed Bo and called Zhuang. Speaking of this man, when young
                                he loved doing daring things. Regardless of the danger to his life,
                                he frequently engaged in violence and robberies. By nature he was
                                fond of slaughter. By chance, Bo Zhuang heard someone say that at
                                Mt. Lu in Jiangzhou there was a monastery built by magical
                                transformation which was very wealthy. The donations the monastery
                                received were enormous, so its riches were not inconsiderable. From
                                far and near, he assembled a band of more than five hundred men.
                                Traveling double-time under the starlit skies, they reached inside
                                the borders of Jiangzhou. Quickly they encamped and settled down. Bo
                                Zhuang then said to his band, "Do not say [anything] to anyone, lest
                                people come to know about us. Tomorrow, when the monks have their
                                vegetarian meal, we will go rob the monastery." Everyone voiced
                                their agreement. Thus, there is a proverb which says, "When a person
                                has good intentions, Heaven will support him; if he has evil
                                aspirations, Heaven will halt him." No sooner had Bo Zhuang declared
                                his intent at that very spot than it was already known to the local
                                earth god. Secretly, with his magical powers, the earth god came and
                                informed the monks at the monastery on Mt. Lu [about Bo's plans].
                                The word spread from room to room and was passed from courtyard to
                                courtyard. The earth spirit, speaking from the sky, said to the
                                monks, "Tomorrow, during the vegetarian meal, a gang of bandits will
                                come to rob this monastery. I urge that all monks be sure to run
                                away." The monks were frightened out of their wits when they heard
                                this. They all ran away in different directions, fleeing as best
                                they could.</p><p>While all the other monks were trying to escape,
                                only monk Yunqing, the chief disciple of Master Yuan, dared not
                                scramble off because of his devotion to and concern for his teacher.
                                Instead, he came straight to the monk's meditation-hut and informed
                                him, saying, "A moment ago a spirit came and reported that bandits
                                are coming to rob this monastery. I humbly request that you kindly
                                withdraw somewhere." Master Yuan replied, "Even though you may not
                                have known it, I was already aware of this matter a long time ago.
                                If [we follow] the teachings of the Nirvana Sutra, then there is
                                nothing to fear. If there is fear, how can there be nirvana? You,
                                along with the other monks, should all swiftly run away. Now that I
                                am here in this place, I can never leave it." Yunqing, seeing that
                                the monk would not heed his repeated request to withdraw, rained
                                tears of sorrow. Alone, he came out of the monastery gate and
                                followed the others in their flight.</p><p>After watching the monks
                                leave, Master Yuan sat in the meditation-hut by himself without any
                                fear. Soon Bo Zhuang, leading his band, approached the monastery. He
                                arranged his army in battle formation across the ridge and had other
                                soldiers spread out along the valley. Their war cries made the hills
                                crumble and rocks crack. To east and west they scurried, to north
                                and south they charged. Breaking into the monastery en masse, they
                                shouted, "Catch them alive!" Bo Zhuang entered the monastery with
                                his army. Hoping to find great stores of treasure, he searched each
                                and every courtyard, but there was not a single thing in the
                                monastery. Bo Zhuang exclaimed, "Amazing! When we were discussing
                                our plans yesterday, no one else knew of them. Who could have
                                informed the people in the monastery and prompted them to run away
                                someplace?"</p><p>Bo Zhuang ordered his assistants, "Go search
                                everywhere inside and outside of the monastery for me. If you catch
                                any monks, bring them to me immediately!" The assistants shouted,
                                "Yes, sir!" and searched everywhere but could not find anyone. When
                                they reached outside the eastern gate of the monastery, they saw a
                                monk sitting quietly in a meditation-hut. The assistants dared not
                                disturb him, so they left stealthily and went back into the
                                monastery, where they came straight before Bo Zhuang. They reported,
                                "In accordance with the General's orders just now, we searched
                                everywhere inside and outside of the monastery looking for monks,
                                but couldn't find anyone. When we reached outside the gate of the
                                monastery, we saw a monk and dared not let this situation go
                                unreported." Bo Zhuang asked, "Where is the monk?" The assistants
                                reported to the General, "We saw him sitting in the meditation-hut
                                outside the eastern gate of the monastery." Thereupon, grasping the
                                reins of his horse and climbing up on the saddle, Bo Zhuang rushed
                                straight outside the eastern gate where he indeed saw a monk sitting
                                cross-legged inside a hut. Bo Zhuang shouted at top of his voice and
                                ordered the assistants to fetch the monk in front of his
                                horse.</p><p>Bo Zhuang asked Master Yuan, "What riches or textiles
                                are in this monastery of yours? Bring them out to me immediately!"
                                Master Yuan walked towards Bo Zhuang and reported, "This monastery
                                has always been very poor; there's nothing at all here. Although
                                there have been a few donations, they were used entirely for daily
                                expenses and meals. General, I dare not deceive you; there really
                                are no riches." Bo Zhuang then closely examined Master Yuan and
                                began to feel admiration toward him. This was because Master Yuan
                                had the likeness of a bodhisattva and his body had a
                                    distinctive<note type="footnote" n="25">The text refers to the
                                    silvery glow as a xiang (Skt. laksana [distinctive mark,
                                    characteristic, or sign]). This is in keeping with the statement
                                    in the previous clause that Huiyuan had the appearance of a
                                    bod-hisattva, since Buddhist iconography holds that such
                                    enlightened beings possess a certain number (often thirty-two)
                                    of laksanas.</note>silver glow, he stood seven feet<note type="footnote" n="26">Equal to about 5'8" by U.S. Customary
                                    standards (1.74 meters). This would have been considerably above
                                    average for a man of the Eastern Jin period.</note>tall, his
                                hair was as though daubed with lacquer, and his lips were as though
                                dotted with vermilion.</p><p>As soon as Bo Zhuang saw this, he said
                                to his assistants, "This monk is fit to be a servant for me." He
                                then said to Master Yuan, "I want you to be my aide. Are you willing
                                or not?" Master Yuan stepped forward. He was willing to devote
                                himself to become the General's slave; he consented to serve in
                                front of Bo Zhuang's horse. Master Yuan said, "There's one other
                                small matter that I wish you would kindly hear. Do you, General,
                                want this poor monk's body, or do you want,my karma?"<note type="footnote" n="27">The sum total of a person's
                                    actions.</note>Bo Zhuang asked, "What do you mean by 'body,' and
                                what do you mean by 'karma'?" Master Yuan replied, "My karma is to
                                recite sutras. If you just want me to serve you, then here is my
                                body. If you want this poor monk's [entire karma], then I request
                                that you not prevent me from reciting sutras." Bo Zhuang replied,
                                "So long as I receive your services, who would prevent you from
                                reciting sutras?" Master Yuan agreed and followed behind the
                                General.</p><p>When they were about a hundred paces from the
                                monastery, Master Yuan once again addressed the General: "Please
                                allow me to go back into the monastery and take off these monk's
                                robes while I am there. I will return here right away to follow your
                                banners." Bo Zhuang said, "Return quickly and do not make me angry.
                                If you are late in coming, I will send my assistants to seize you
                                and cut you into three parts right in front of my horse. Don't say I
                                didn't warn you!" Master Yuan agreed, then entered the monastery and
                                stood in front of the hall. At that time, his chief disciple
                                Yunqing, from the top of a high peak, saw his teacher inside the
                                monastery. He came rushing down the mountain and went straight
                                before him. He reported to the monk, "Just now, as the wild outlaws
                                were charging forward, I was extremely frightened. Now I am happy to
                                see the army of bandits retreat and will share in your joy." Master
                                Yuan said, "The Nirvana Sutra teaches that there is no fear; if
                                there is fear, how can there be nirvana? From now on, you must try
                                to improve yourself and maintain [the Dharma] well. Today, I am
                                going to bid farewell to you forever." Yunqing asked the monk, "What
                                could make you say such a thing?" Master Yuan replied, "Just now,
                                outside the gate of the monastery, I gave my word to become a slave
                                of the General. I cannot stay here for too long. You must strive to
                                do your best later on." Hearing this, Yunqing beat himself all over
                                until fresh blood flowed from the seven apertures [of his
                                    head].<note type="footnote" n="28">Eyes, ears, nostrils, and
                                    mouth.</note>After a long time, he revived and got up from the
                                ground, then composed the following gāthā:</p><lg><l>We were like birds in flight,</l><l>You, master, were like a great tree;</l><l>Now that the great tree is moving,</l><l>Where shall you send us for shelter?</l><l>Where will your transformed body dwell?</l><l>Leaving only a sentence of nirvana;</l><l>We vow to grasp the lamp of wisdom,<note type="footnote" n="29">This line appears to mean "May you bestow upon us the lamp
                                        of wisdom," but chuí (bestow) is most likely an orthographic
                                        error for bǐng (grasp), which has a similar appearance when
                                        handwritten.</note></l><l>So that we do not recklessly lose our way.</l></lg><p>After he had finished speaking, Yunqing began to cry all the more
                                grievously. Master Yuan said, "I am afraid that the General will
                                blame me for being late." Master Yuan went out through the monastery
                                gate and, catching up with the banners [of Bo Zhuang's army],
                                followed along behind them. As the days came and the months went by,
                                he followed them for several years.</p><p>After Yunqing saw the
                                master leave, he once again gathered the community of monks and
                                started giving lectures based upon the Commentary on the Nirvana
                                Sutra. Invariably, the audience would shed tears like rain, just as
                                though they were seeing the great teacher. As Yunqing had received
                                no news of the master for several years, he gave the Commentary on
                                the Nirvana Sutra to a monk named Daoan. Soon after receiving the
                                Commentary on the Nirvana Sutra, Daoan took it to the Fuguang
                                Monastery in the Eastern Capital<note type="footnote" n="30">Normally, "Eastern Capital" would refer to Luoyang. However,
                                    since the Jin dynasty had already abandoned the north at the
                                    time in question, that would be impossible here. Thus it is
                                    likely that the capital thought of here is that of the Eastern
                                    Jin, Jiankang, i.e., modern Nanjing (Nanking).</note>and began
                                lecturing with it. Not knowing what sort of person Daoan really was
                                like, the listeners were, nonetheless, touched by his lectures; they
                                flocked to him like clouds, and donations poured in like
                                rain.</p><p>This was the time when the Eastern Capital was under
                                Emperor Wen<note type="footnote" n="31">There was an Emperor Jianwen
                                    who ruled from 371 to 372 during the Eastern Jin dynasty, which
                                    would be roughly the right time for the main events and
                                    characters depicted in this story. Since the present account is
                                    largely fictional, however, it is impossible (and pointless) to
                                    determine whether he is the emperor referred to here.</note>of
                                the Jin dynasty. When Daoan lectured, it caused heavenly flowers to
                                flutter down, suffusing a pleasant fragrance as they fell, and
                                caused five-colored<note type="footnote" n="32">Sanskrit
                                    pañcarūpa-megha orpañcavarna-megha, "five-colored" indicating
                                    auspiciousness.</note>clouds to appear. The crowds of people
                                increased until the audiences were incalculable. They would trample
                                the lecture mats to pieces, making it impossible to open the
                                sessions. As a result, Daoan wrote a memorial, which he presented to
                                Emperor Wen of the Jin: "In compliance with your orders, I have been
                                lecturing on the Nirvana Sutra at the Fuguang Monastery. The
                                audiences have increased so much that there have been scuffles on
                                the dharma mats, making it impossible to open the sessions. I humbly
                                beg that you issue orders bestowing special instructions." At that
                                time, an order was issued: "Those wanting to hear Daoan's lectures
                                must pay one bolt of silk. This will allow them to listen for one
                                day." Since it was then a period that witnessed peace and
                                tranquility, prices of commodities were low. Those who could pay one
                                bolt of silk each day numbered about twenty to thirty thousand.
                                However, as the temple courtyard was small and narrow, there was not
                                enough space to accommodate everyone [who paid]. Once again, a
                                memorial was sent to inform Emperor Wen: "In compliance with your
                                orders, I inaugurated the lecture sessions at Fuguang Monastery, and
                                as per your previous decree charged one bolt of silk. However, the
                                audience has continued to increase, and it is difficult to control
                                them. I humbly beg that you once again bestow special instructions."
                                At that time an order was issued: "Those who want to listen to
                                Daoan's lectures must pay one hundred strings of cash<note type="footnote" n="33">A cash (Portuguese caixa, Tamil kācu
                                    [copper coin], Sanskrit karsa [a weight {of precious metal}]) is
                                    a Chinese copper coin (wen), one thousand of which make up a
                                    string (chuan or guan). One hundred strings of cash would be a
                                    hundred thousand copper coins, a considerable
                                amount.</note>each. This will allow them to listen for one day." Due
                                to this interdiction, the people who came to listen to Daoan's
                                sessions at the Eastern Capital did not exceed three to five
                                thousand a day.</p><p>And where was Master Yuan? Master Yuan was all
                                the while following Bo Zhuang, who attacked any prefectures and
                                counties he came upon. In the morning he wandered through streams
                                and fields, and in the evening he settled down in mountain forests.
                                His hair cut level with his eyebrows<note type="footnote" n="34">Such a hairstyle was the sign of a servant.</note>and a short,
                                coarse cloth on his body, Master Yuan constantly followed behind Bo
                                Zhuang. After several years, he began thinking about the Gates of
                                    Emptiness,<note type="footnote" n="35">Buddhism.</note>but there
                                was no way he could reenter those gates. Moreover, Bo Zhuang had
                                left a trail of crimes. He consorted with vicious rogues who loved
                                killing and hated life. Pillage was their modus
                                operandi.</p><p>Perchance, one day when Bo Zhuang was in the
                                mountains, he set up camp on the eastern ridge, and Master Yuan
                                halted for the night on the western slope. At that time, an autumn
                                breeze suddenly stirred, the falling leaves drifted down, the hills
                                were silent and the woods sparse, and frost nipped the grass. The
                                wind passed into the woods and blew through the bamboos as though
                                they were silken [strings]. The moon shone in the dark blue sky, and
                                the scarlet mist looked like a tapestry. Beside the flowing stream,
                                Master Yuan's heart was full of sadness. He fell into a dazed sleep
                                and dreamed of the Buddhas of the Ten Directions,<note type="footnote" n="36">North, south, east, west, northeast,
                                    southeast, southwest, northwest, up, and down.</note>all of whom
                                appeared among the clouds with innumerable sages and wisemen. They
                                came down to him and called out, "Bodhi-sattva, arise! Don't be
                                yearning for benighted slumber. You have borne witness to the
                                significance of nirvana; how come you are not reciting the Nirvana
                                Sutra for all sentient beings?" In his dream, Master Yuan bowed
                                reverently over and over. As he was a completely ordinary
                                    mortal,<note type="footnote" n="37">Since elsewhere throughout
                                    the text Master Yuan is described as an individual of
                                    extraordinary qualities, it does not make sense to say here that
                                    he is "completely ordinary," nor would this be likely to inspire
                                    Aksobhya Buddha to grant him such an amazing prophecy. Hence, it
                                    is likely that the rhetorical interrogative particle qĭ has
                                    inadvertently been omitted by the scribe before "was." With it
                                    restored, the revised translation would be something like "As he
                                    was by no means a completely ordinary mortal.. ."</note>it moved
                                    Aksobhya<note type="footnote" n="38">"Immovable"; the name of a
                                    Buddha in the east.</note>Tathāgata to grant him a prophecy. He
                                asked Master Yuan to come closer and said, "Do not let your heart be
                                troubled. You have a debt from the past which has not yet been
                                repaid. Since you were once a guarantor for someone in a previous
                                life, you have to settle the account in your present incarnation.
                                Your creditor is not far off—he is the current Prime Minister. Bring
                                yourself close to the Prime Minister and then sell yourself to him.
                                Hand over the five hundred strings of cash that you get to Bo
                                Zhuang. You can then return to Mount Lu, where I shall rendezvous
                                with you."</p><p>Master Yuan awoke with a start from his dream and
                                was terribly frightened. Thereupon he sat up and read a number of
                                chapters from the Nirvana Sutra. This startled Bo Zhuang awake on
                                the eastern ridge, so he asked his assistants, "What is that sound
                                in the west?" His assistants responded, "We inform you, General,
                                that it is the sound of the lowly slave you captured reciting sutras
                                in the west." When Bo Zhuang heard this he got extremely angry, so
                                he called Master Yuan to come directly before him. Rebuking him
                                loudly, Bo Zhuang said, "If you were in a monastery, it would be all
                                right for you to recite like this. But how could you recite a sutra
                                when you are in attendance upon me?"<note type="footnote" n="39">There are a number of difficult problems with these two
                                    sentences. Literally, they seem to mean, "Even if you were in a
                                    monastery and wanted to recite, it would not be permitted. All
                                    the more, now that you are in attendance upon me, how could you
                                    recite a sutra?"</note></p><p>Master Yuan said, "That day when
                                you took me as a lowly slave, General, you gave me permission to
                                recite sutras."</p><p>Bo Zhuang said, "When did I gave you
                                permission to recite sutras?"</p><p>Master Yuan did not say anything
                                right away, but the assistants explained, "Actually, General, you
                                did give him permission to recite sutras."</p><p>Bo Zhuang said,
                                "Reciting sutras is a waste of time. We've all done our share of
                                killing, so we don't want to have to hear the sound of
                                sutra-recitation."</p><p>Master Yuan said, "Since you won't allow me
                                to recite sutras in a loud voice, how would it be if I recited them
                                silently?"</p><p>Bo Zhuang said, "That will not do. The reason I
                                captured you in the first place was because we didn't get any loot,
                                and in the second place was because I didn't have enough slaves. So
                                we were angry and took you prisoner. Now the amount of our money is
                                not little and our manpower is actually quite great, so I'll let you
                                return to your mountain and you can cultivate yourself as you
                                wish."</p><p>Master Yuan said, "I devoted myself as your slave and
                                agreed to serve you my entire life. If I abandon you halfway, how
                                can this be called devotion? If the master still needs my services,
                                then there's nothing more to talk about. However, if you do not want
                                this lowly slave anymore, then sell me somewhere else and you'll get
                                a bit of money to buy liquor and meat. Can't this be
                                done?"</p><p>Hearing this Bo Zhuang laughed out loud [and said],
                                "You are totally wrong. Only if I had bought you somewhere and
                                possessed an old contract could I sell you. But since I took you a
                                prisoner, how could I sell you?"</p><p>Master Yuan said, "If you do
                                not want to sell me, then there is nothing more to talk about. But
                                if you do want to sell me, pretend that I was born into your house
                                as the son of a slave and then you can sell me without a
                                contract."</p><p>Bo Zhuang said, "If I do as you say, where could I
                                sell you?"</p><p>Master Yuan said, "If and when you want to sell
                                your lowly slave, just take me to the Eastern Capital and you will
                                be able to sell me off."</p><p>When Bo Zhuang heard this, he became
                                alarmed and very angry. "You low-class scoundrel!" said Bo Zhuang.
                                "You still haven't given up your scheming tricks. You're intending
                                to go to the Eastern Capital and make the rounds of the offices high
                                and low, handing in accounts of my transgressions and saying that I
                                am a bandit so that orders will be issued to capture
                                me."</p><p>Master Yuan said, "If your lowly slave has such an
                                intention to plot against my master, then in all future incarnations
                                may I die and fall into hell without any hope of escaping. I only
                                beseech you, master, not to harbor any worries. I'm definitely not
                                [planning] such a thing."</p><p>When Bo Zhuang heard this, he
                                trusted Master Yuan. He then scattered the band under his command,
                                keeping only three or four men. He disguised himself as a merchant
                                and, taking three or four pack animals which he loaded with
                                merchandise, went directly to the Eastern Capital to sell Master
                                Yuan. He headed for the slave and horse section of the market to
                                sell him.</p><p>Upon reaching the marketplace, Master Yuan held a
                                sign to sell himself. Among the throngs of people, there were none
                                who did not sigh at the sight. This was the appearance of<note type="footnote" n="40">See note 17.</note>Master Yuan with his
                                sign:</p><lg><l>He was seven feet tall,</l><l>His body had a distinctive silver glow;</l><l>His forehead was broad and eyebrows high,</l><l>His face was like the full moon;</l><l>His hair was as though daubed with lacquer,</l><l>And his lips were as though dotted with vermilion;</l><l>He marched as if a king of bulls,</l><l>His hands hung down past his knees.<note type="footnote" n="41">Each line of this description consists of a conventional
                                        characteristic of heroes and handsome men in the medieval
                                        Chinese literary tradition.</note></l></lg><p>As he paced back and forth, without exception the spectators gasped
                                in admiration. The onlookers clustered together in groups of three
                                or four, [making such comments as,] "In my lifetime, I've
                                encountered thousands of detained lower-class people, but truly I
                                have never seen one like this." The more they sighed the more
                                onlookers were attracted.</p><p>At this time, Master Yuan was filled
                                with remorse and hated himself, knowing that his debt from a
                                previous life had not yet been paid back. He waited eagerly to sell
                                himself in order to compensate Bo Zhuang. In a short while, his
                                situation moved Sovereign Śakra,<note type="footnote" n="42">Indra,
                                    the tutelary god of the Indo-Aryans.</note>who transformed
                                himself and came down in the form of a messenger of Prime Minister
                                Cui. He went directly to the slave and horse section of the market
                                and called out to the slave and horse broker in a loud voice, "This
                                fine chattel must not be sold to anyone else! [His services] may be
                                enjoyed only in the residence of the current Prime Minister,
                                    Cui.<note type="footnote" n="43">The author seems to have
                                    dragged a mid-eighth-century Prime Minister, Cui Hao, into the
                                    story.</note>He may not be purchased by anyone else!" The
                                broker, hearing this, fully believed that there were indeed such
                                orders and so brought Master Yuan to Prime Minister Cui's residence.
                                At this time, Bo Zhuang followed behind, but Master Yuan said to
                                him, "There is no reason for you to come along. No matter what lies
                                ahead, I will take the responsibility. If the Minister is pleased,
                                then you can take all the money to the last penny."</p><p>Bo Zhuang
                                said, "In the business that lies ahead, be sure to respond correctly
                                and not make any mistakes."</p><p>Master Yuan exclaimed, "Yes, sir!"
                                Then, accompanying the broker, he went directly in front of the
                                Minister's gate.</p><p>The gatekeeper asked the broker, "Who is this
                                man that you've brought?" [The broker answered,] "I was called here
                                by a personal messenger of the Minister because of this caitiff. I
                                dare not sell him to anyone else, so I have especially brought him
                                for the needs of the Minister's residence." The gatekeeper said,
                                "Wait here while I go inside and report to the Minister." The
                                gatekeeper then went in front of the hall and announced to the
                                Minister, "There is a slave-broker at the gate. He has brought a
                                lowly person to show to the Minister today. I dare not let it go
                                unreported!" The Minister said, "Have them brought in." Thereupon,
                                in accord with the Minister's instructions, the gatekeeper had the
                                broker lead Master Yuan directly in front of the hall. Seeing the
                                Minister, Master Yuan bowed and paid his respects, then stood off to
                                one side. When the Minister took a look, he exclaimed, "Amazing!
                                Last night I dreamed that a spirit entered my dwelling, and now I
                                see this slave—does this not correspond with my dream?" The Minister
                                asked the broker, "Was he born of a slave in the Bo Zhuang
                                household, or was he bought from somewhere else?" The broker
                                responded to the Minister, "He was born of a slave in the Bo Zhuang
                                household." The Minister said, "Since he was born of a slave in the
                                Bo Zhuang household, of course there won't be a contract." He asked
                                the broker, "How much money do you want for this slave?" Before the
                                broker could say anything, Master Yuan stepped forward and said to
                                the Minister, "If you want to buy this lowly slave, all we ask is
                                five hundred strings of cash." The Minister inquired, "What kind of
                                skills do you possess to cost five hundred strings of cash? You
                                don't have to go into great detail. Let's just hear a general
                                description of your talents."</p><p>Master Yuan responded, "I can
                                tell how rich a family was three hundred years ago. I also know how
                                poor a family will be two hundred years from now. I know how to fold
                                clothes, decoct medicine for the four seasons, and send messages.
                                There are no questions that I cannot answer. As to various schools
                                of calligraphy, I have a rough knowledge of a number of them. In all
                                of these, I am ready to compete against anyone unaided. As for
                                hoeing rice and harvesting wheat, I understand quite a bit. When it
                                comes to business and trade, I know all the places to go. If you
                                have some errand to send me on, I'll come like the wind and I won't
                                be stubborn or slow. If the Minister does not believe me, I will
                                myself write out a contract to sell myself, and then you will know
                                that all this is true."</p><p>The Minister instructed his assistants
                                to fetch paper and brush and give them to Master Yuan. Master Yuan
                                took the paper and brush, then asked for an incense burner, and one
                                was given to him immediately. After he had bowed to the Minister, he
                                went to the front of the hall and wrote out a contract to sell
                                himself. It was not like most contracts. Master Yuan wrote, "In such
                                and such a year and month, I sell myself to the Minister to be his
                                slave, to serve him with utter faithfulness till the end of his
                                life. If I desert him halfway, in all future incarnations may I die
                                and fall into hell. And when my punishments there are finished, may
                                I be reborn as a beast of burden. A saddle will be placed on my
                                back, stirrups will hang by my sides, and a bit will be inserted in
                                my mouth as punishment for my previous transgressions. But if I
                                serve you for the rest of your life, then in my future incarnations
                                may I perfect the ten stages<note type="footnote" n="44">Sanskrit
                                    daśabhūmi.</note>of developing the Buddha-wisdom and achieve
                                rebirth among the congregation of the buddhas." When he had finished
                                the contract, he handed it over to the Minister. Having received it,
                                the Minister exclaimed, "Amazing! Is this not a bodhisattva or
                                mahasattva who has come to my house?" And so he ordered that five
                                hundred strings of cash be given to the broker and passed on to Bo
                                Zhuang at once. When Bo Zhuang received the money, he dared not stay
                                longer, so he went back and crossed the borders into
                                Shouzhou.</p><p>Having bought the lowly slave, the Minister ordered
                                his domestics in the western courtyard to settle Master Yuan in a
                                room there. Aware that he had to pay off his debt, Master Yuan dared
                                not bear a grudge against anyone else. Whether coming or going, he
                                would invariably be at the Minister's side and run errands for him.
                                Suddenly, one day when Master Yuan was sitting alone in his room
                                deep into the night and had repeatedly poked the wick of the
                                guttering lamp, he could see that the Milky Way was calm and the
                                moon filled the sky. He sat for a long time until his eyes became
                                blurry and he fell asleep. Once again in his dream he saw the
                                Buddhas of the Ten Directions—all of them appeared in the void.
                                Along with innumerable sages and wise men, they gathered like clouds
                                and called out, "Bodhisattva, arise! Do not yearn for benighted
                                slumber. You have borne witness to the significance of nirvana; how
                                come you are not reciting the sutra for all sentient
                                beings?"</p><p>Master Yuan awoke with a start. He sat up and recited
                                the Nirvana Sutra until the skies brightened. The Minister was in
                                his hall when all of a sudden he heard the sound of someone reciting
                                a sutra. He got up and, walking slowly by himself, came in front of
                                the gate of the western courtyard and listened to the sounds of the
                                sutra recital. He then ordered his assistants to summon his wife.
                                Having been summoned, the wife came in front of the western gate.
                                Then the Minister, accompanied by his wife, listened to the reciting
                                of the sutra until the skies brightened.</p><p>The next morning,
                                after returning from court, the Minister ascended his hall and took
                                a seat. Then he ordered his assistants to call the domestics of the
                                western courtyard to him. Soon, thirty people huddled in front of
                                the hall. The Minister inquired, "Last night in the western
                                courtyard, which of you domestics was reciting a sutra?" At that
                                time, the head domestic informed the Minister, "The person reciting
                                a sutra last night was none other than the newly bought slave. The
                                voice [you heard] reciting a sutra [was his]." Hearing that it was
                                the new slave who was reciting the sutra, the Minister asked Master
                                Yuan, "Were you the one who was reciting a sutra last night?" Master
                                Yuan replied, "Yes, it was the sound of this lowly slave reciting a
                                sutra." The Minister inquired, "What was the title of the sutra?"
                                Master Yuan replied, "The one that I was reciting last night was the
                                Mahānirvāna-sūtra." The Minister asked, "How many chapters of the
                                sutra are you able to recite?" Master Yuan replied, "Your poor slave
                                can recite the whole text in twelve scrolls, and last night I
                                recited them all." The Minister asked, "You are not lying, are you?"
                                Master Yuan said, "How dare I deceive you, Minister?" The Minister
                                then ordered Master Yuan to sit down and recite the Nirvana Sutra
                                again. Thereupon, Master Yuan once again opened with the sutra tide,
                                and for a second time raised the sounds of the sutra. During the
                                entire recitation there was not a single mistake. Seeing this, the
                                Minister frequently exclaimed, "Splendid!" Then he called the people
                                in the residence, young and old, distinguished and lowly, all
                                together more than three hundred persons, to come in front of the
                                hall. The Minister ordered that from then on no one was to look down
                                upon the new slave. At the same time he gave Master Yuan a nickname,
                                calling him Shanqing.<note type="footnote" n="45">Meaning literally
                                    "Good-Congratulations."</note></p><p>Every day, after retiring
                                from the court, the Minister regularly visited the Fuguang Monastery
                                and paid the fee of one hundred strings of cash to listen to Daoan's
                                sutra-lectures. And on this next day, he brought Shanqing along with
                                him to the monastery. However, as Shanqing was just beginning his
                                service with the Minister, he was not allowed to enter the monastery
                                to hear the sutra-lecture, but could only guard the Minister's horse
                                outside the gate. After a short while, he saw the audience going
                                into the monastery resembling the scudding clouds and driving rain.
                                And then suddenly the bells stopped ringing; the tide of the sutra
                                was taken up; and the Sanskrit words that sounded at a distance
                                gradually penetrated into his ears. When Shanqing heard this, his
                                heart was filled with sadness. Master Yuan said to himself, "I just
                                don't know how this Daoan is able to lecture and sing the hymns so
                                capably. I wish one day I could once again mount the raised
                                platform, bear witness to the fruits of the ten stages of developing
                                Buddha-wisdom, and save all living beings from disaster. Whether
                                with form or without, having an appearance or not, all beings are
                                emancipated by nirvana."</p><p>After a short while, the sermon
                                ended, and the men and women dispersed. The Minister returned to his
                                residence. He rested for a while in the center of the hall and,
                                after he had composed himself, went to the upper part of the hall
                                and took his seat there. Covering her face with her sleeve, his wife
                                came directly in front of the Minister and said, "For several years
                                you have listening to the Reverend Daoan lecture on the Nirvana
                                Sutra at the Fuguang Monastery. What doctrines have you heard him
                                discuss? It is said that the Nirvana Sutra is infinite and
                                illimitable. How much of the sutra do you remember? Why do you
                                remain silent and say nothing? Why don't you explain a line or half
                                a line of the stanzas to me?" The Minister replied, "Have you ever
                                read the Lotus Sutra?" "Yes, I have read the Lotus Sutra" answered
                                the wife. The Minister said, "In that sutra, it is said, 'Speak
                                without request and no one will listen.'"<note type="footnote" n="46">This sentence actually cannot be found in the Lotus
                                    Sutra.</note>The wife said, "I wish that you would say a few
                                words [about the Nirvana Sutra] to the distinguished and lowly
                                members of the residence to enlighten our minds." The Minister said,
                                "I will explain the inner meanings of the Nirvana Sutra to you." The
                                wife then ordered the domestics to sweep and clean the audience hall
                                and erect a high wooden podium. She then called the people in the
                                residence, the young and the old, the distinguished and the lowly,
                                all together more than three hundred persons, to gather in front of
                                the hall. She requested the Minister to explain the inner meaning of
                                the Nirvana Sutra, and everyone was to listen in complete
                                silence.</p><p>That night, the Minister first explained to his wife
                                the interrelated woes of the eight kinds of suffering. The first of
                                these is the suffering of birth. The suffering of birth: to be born,
                                the body must depend on the shelter of the mother inside her womb.
                                In about a month the fetus is like cheese. Then, within ninety days,
                                it can start taking form. The males are attached on the mother's
                                left side, the females on the right. Close to her heart and liver,
                                the fetus is endowed with material energy and begins to take form.
                                Thereupon, it endures various types of sufferings. It is same with
                                the wise and the foolish, the rich and the poor. The favor of a kind
                                mother does not vary according to her station. When the mother eats
                                hot food, it feels no different from boiling the body in a cauldron
                                of scalding liquid. When the mother eats cold things, it is just
                                like being in a frigid hell. If the mother overeats, it is like
                                being crushed between stones. And, when the mother is hungry, then
                                one endures the suffering of being hung upside down. After a full
                                term of ten months,<note type="footnote" n="47">Chinese
                                    traditionally believed that the full period of human gestation,
                                    from conception to birth, required ten months.</note>the time of
                                birth approaches. The hundred bones and joints are spread out as if
                                they were being severed by a saw. It is simply as though the four
                                limbs were being rent from the body and the five organs were
                                subjected to excruciating pain. There is no difference between this
                                and being wounded by a knife or cut by a sword. One feels as though
                                one is undergoing a thousand births and ten thousand deaths, until
                                at last one faints and becomes insensate. One's life hangs by a
                                thread and one has no desire to live any longer. Before long, the
                                mother and child are separated, and there is as much blood as if a
                                sheep had been slaughtered. The mother, in a semiconscious state,
                                asks if it is a boy or girl. If the answer is that it's a girl, then
                                the separation of the mother and child is considered to have been
                                safely completed. But if the reply is that it's a boy, then the
                                excruciating pain felt by the hundred bones and joints is forgotten,
                                and, in her semiconscious state, she smiles faintly. This is what is
                                called a filial son.</p><p>Now, if it is a disobedient child, how is
                                the parturition? Inside his mother's belly, he makes her
                                uncomfortable. He kicks the mother and does not let her rest for
                                even a moment. Suddenly jumping onto her heart, then over to her
                                waist, and then among the five organs, there is nowhere this child
                                does not go. The child is born only after a full term of ten months.
                                At that time, the child grabs hold of the mother's heart and liver,
                                kicks her groin bones, and for days and nights cannot be contented.
                                From here on, the mother's life is in jeopardy. The mother,
                                believing that she is on the verge of death, shakes the earth with
                                her cries. It is as though her heart were being carved out by a
                                sword. Her brothers and mother have no idea what to do. Perhaps the
                                child is someone with a grievance or to whom a debt is owed from a
                                previous incarnation and will stop only after taking a life. Thus
                                the mother is first forced to endure [the birth of] the child, after
                                which she may die. This, then, is called [the suffering of]
                                birth.</p><p>On that night, the Minister also explained to his wife
                                the suffering of old age. The suffering of old age: the hundred
                                years that people are granted for a lifetime are as trifling as a
                                spark. Quickly they turn seventy or eighty and their strength begins
                                to fade. In the beginning, one's voice is youthful and one's
                                appearance is like a spring flower. Now, when old age comes, it is
                                no different from the autumn grass. The skin is like that of a
                                chicken and the hair like the feathers of a crane. The normal
                                desires wither, vision dims, the ears become deaf, and one cannot
                                distinguish between green and yellow. The four limbs become heavy
                                and the hundred bones are wracked with pain. The body gradually
                                droops farther from the sky and comes closer to the earth. At night,
                                when sleeping on a pillowed bed, the aged person tosses and turns a
                                thousand times. At this time, the person cannot perform any worldly
                                affairs, just as if one were in a dream. Haven't you seen the
                                peaches and plums alongside the roads that blossom year after year?
                                But where are yesterday's ruddy complexions now? Once invaded by old
                                age and sickness, the white hair can never turn black again. The
                                youthful vigor of earlier times fades with the eight festivals;<note type="footnote" n="48">The beginnings of the four seasons, the
                                    equinoxes, and the solstices.</note>the ruddy complexion of
                                yesterday now changes with the four seasons. Everyone ages; it is
                                the same for the rich or the poor, nor is there a distinction
                                between the wise and the foolish. They all share in the suffering of
                                old age. It is better, therefore, to create fields of good fortune
                                as early as one can. Human life is over in a second, and the world
                                passes us by right while we're watching. One must pay heed and
                                cultivate morality. Once the human body is lost there is no way to
                                revive it. This, then, is called the suffering of old age.</p><p>On
                                that night the Minister also explained to his wife the suffering of
                                illness. The wife asked, "What is the suffering of illness?" The
                                suffering of illness: how could it be that there is solidity at the
                                loci of the four elements?<note type="footnote" n="49">Sanskrit
                                    mahābhūta: earth, water, fire, and wind (or air), i.e., the four
                                    elements.</note>Everything is due to their agglomeration: earth,
                                water, fire, wind. An offbeat pulse is the beginning of illness.
                                Suddenly one is so tired that one remains stuck in bed, the souls
                                are unsettled, the spirits of the five organs are lost, the lips dry
                                up, the tongue contracts, the brain hurts, the head aches, and the
                                hundred bones and joints feel as if they were being severed by a
                                saw. The pain persists throughout the night without any relief.
                                Begging for life is of no use, begging for death is to no avail. The
                                marvelous techniques of the world only cure people who are fated to
                                live. How can those who are destined to die be saved? One can try
                                curing with medicine, but [those who are destined to die] cannot be
                                healed. For days and nights one endures all sorts of intense
                                suffering. Some use the strong drugs of Jīvaka<note type="footnote" n="50">A famous Indian physician from the time of the Buddha.
                                    His name means "able to revive."</note>or the needle of Bian
                                    Que,<note type="footnote" n="51">A legendary physician of the
                                    Warring States period in China. See selection 28.</note>but when
                                death due to illness approaches these are of no use. The people of
                                the world vainly accept depraved counsel and, even before they are
                                in bed with sickness, blame the spirits and ghosts.<note type="footnote" n="52">Making several emendations to the latter
                                    part of the sentence, it may alternatively be interpreted as
                                    "when they are constantly confined to bed with sickness, beseech
                                    the spirits and ghosts."</note>They burn money, disregard
                                prohibitions, and vainly slaughter living creatures. This type of
                                person falls straight into hell. The upper limit [of human life] is
                                no more than a hundred years, and very few survive till seventy. [In
                                general,] three people together are granted one hundred years,<note type="footnote" n="53">In other words, most people only get to
                                    live for a little over thirty years.</note>but how much time can
                                they [really] get? If people living in this world have access to
                                marvelous techniques, then there ought to be those who can live a
                                total of a thousand years. Why don't people think things through
                                thoroughly? They vainly believe in the physicians' horrifying lies.
                                This, then, is called the suffering of illness.</p><p>On that night,
                                the Minister also explained to his wife the suffering of death. The
                                suffering of death: the great desires<note type="footnote" n="54">The four passions are sexual love, sexual beauty, food, and
                                    lust.</note>diminish, and the souls are blown away by the wind.
                                Brothers bid long farewells, fathers and mothers are forever apart,
                                and wives and husbands, sons and daughters can never meet again.
                                After visitors, friends, and guests bid adieu, they can never meet
                                again. Gold, silver, money, and other objects when spent are gone
                                forever. Residences, shops, manors, and courtyards cannot be taken
                                along when one goes. Due to craving and the suffering of death, when
                                the four elements separate, the souls fly away to an unknown place.
                                With the departure of the last mouthful of breath comes the advent
                                of the next rebirth. But, after one dies, when can rebirth be
                                achieved? While birth is debated as heroic, death is argued as
                                religious merit. Rebirth is acquired according to karma, and one is
                                assigned a new existence based on it. It is either a stay in hell,
                                in the heavenly palace, rebirth as an animal, or as a hungry
                                ghost—circling in the six paths of transmigration<note type="footnote" n="55">The six ways (Skt. sad-gati) of
                                    reincarnation or conditions of sentient existence: those of
                                    hells (naraka-gati), hungry ghosts (preta-gati), animals
                                    (tiryagyoni-gati), malevolent nature spirits (asura-gati), human
                                    beings (manusya-gati), and heavenly beings
                                (deva-gati).</note>without a period of rest. There's just one slight
                                chance in ten thousand of achieving human form once again. This,
                                then, is called the suffering of death.</p><p>On this night, the
                                Minister also explained to his wife the suffering that comes from
                                the five aggregates.<note type="footnote" n="56">The five skandhas,
                                    which are the components of an intelligent being: form,
                                    perception, consciousness, thought, cognition. The first skandha
                                    is physical; the other four are mental. Attachment to the
                                    skandhas is a cause of suffering.</note>The suffering that comes
                                from the five aggregates: the lives of the people in the world are
                                like night and day. Pus, blood, and skin enwrap the body like fine
                                silk. Among the five aggregates, effluvia constantly flow from the
                                seven orifices. Within is harbored the foul smell of ordure and
                                filth which oozes from the bones with the blood. And see how the
                                sack of pus and dripping mucus flow day and night. It is utterly
                                unbearable, yet completely without reality. All desires are born
                                from a mouthful of material energy,<note type="footnote" n="57">I.e., one's life.</note>and they are the germs of the three
                                    poisons,<note type="footnote" n="58">Avarice, anger, and
                                    stupidity.</note>while the five viscera are the source of the
                                five desires.<note type="footnote" n="59">The desires which arise
                                    from the objects of the five senses.</note>For this the Great
                                    Teacher<note type="footnote" n="60">The Buddha.</note>has the
                                following gāthā:</p><lg><l>The pus and blood inside the thin skin,</l><l>Stinking bones enwrapped by muscles;</l><l>What we see from head to toe,</l><l>Is the whole body dripping with pus.</l><l>Many sufferings of this kind assail the body.</l><l>This, then, is called the suffering that comes from the five
                                    aggregates.</l></lg><p>On that night, the Minister also explained to his wife the suffering
                                of not getting what one seeks. Each person in the world seeks
                                something. There are those who wish for good fortune and those who
                                seek supreme bodhi (enlightenment). Within the three ages,<note type="footnote" n="61">Past, present, and future.</note>some
                                seek the good fortune of birth in heaven. How many can enjoy the
                                luxuries of the world or gain the wealth they seek in the realm of
                                humans? Midway, they meet a premature demise. If one seeks gold,
                                silver, cloth, and silk with the intention of having luxury for
                                kalpa after kalpa, one may not even get enough food and clothing to
                                suffice for oneself. Father, mother, and younger and older brother
                                are each concerned with relieving their own distress. The son borne
                                and the daughter raised, they have their own separate pursuits. If
                                [good deeds] were not sown in the previous life, then one cannot
                                cultivate them in a succession of kalpas. If one wants worldly
                                luxury, then one must cultivate fields of blessing in the present
                                life. Today,<note type="footnote" n="62">The Minister actually says
                                    "this morning."</note>I earnestly exhort everyone in the
                                audience to understand that your food and clothing were determined
                                in a previous life. Thus, the Great Master has the following
                                gāthā:</p><lg><l>What one does in the present determines what happens to one in
                                    the future;</l><l>Why not sow grains of good fortune for the future?</l><l>[The quality of] one's present life determines [the quality of
                                    one's] future life;</l><l>Why not cultivate blessings for your future life?</l><l>Many are [the sufferings of] this sort.</l><l>This, then, is called the suffering of not getting what one
                                    seeks.</l></lg><p>On that night, the Minister also explained to his wife the suffering
                                that comes from having to meet with what is hateful. The suffering
                                that comes from having to meet with what is hateful: the people of
                                the world have hearts that are full of desires. When they see that
                                someone else has a wife, they too want a wife. Within two to three
                                years of taking a wife, they give birth to a son and plant seeds for
                                a daughter. What may this be compared with? Like a butterfly
                                gathering nectar from flowers, [at first] it just circles around in
                                the air, but suddenly it sees a bunch of peonies and alights among
                                the fragrant stamens to do its gathering. However, it does not
                                realize that a spider has made a web on the flower and so gets tied
                                up within it. Hundreds of twists and thousands of turns bind the
                                butterfly in [the web], and myriad strategies to escape fail. This
                                illustrates the suffering. Anyone who loves sexual beauty ends up
                                like this. We see that even the young have hearts full of love and
                                affection. Then, as the months and years pass, they have sons and
                                daughters. When the children grow up and become adults, they are not
                                filial to their parents. Their fivefold rebellious acts<note type="footnote" n="63">Sanskrit pañcānantarya: parricide,
                                    matricide, killing an arhat (saint), shedding the blood of a
                                    Buddha, and destroying the harmony of the samgha (Buddhist
                                    community).</note>fill the skies. They do not befriend wise
                                people, but rather associate with vicious thugs. They talk without
                                thinking and destroy the six relationships,<note type="footnote" n="64">Those with one's father, mother, older brother, younger
                                    brother, wife, and children.</note>including even those with
                                their honorable elders. If they are at home, they are a drain on
                                one's mental vigor. If they are away from home, they are a constant
                                source of worry. This, then, is how one often gives birth to one's
                                enemies, and, thus, for generation after generation there is no
                                rest. I earnestly exhort you in the audience [to accumulate] good
                                    causes,<note type="footnote" n="65">So as to reap good results
                                    in the future.</note>thus you are aware [of what needs to be
                                done]. If you wish to have no enemies in later generations, it would
                                be better to cultivate the pure path in this lifetime. You will
                                always be separated from your enemies, and your deepest emotions
                                will not be troubled by them. How numerous are the concatenations of
                                cause and effect<note type="footnote" n="66">Sanskrit
                                    hetupratyaya.</note>between men and women! Thus, the Great
                                Master has the following gāthā:</p><lg><l>Since distant kalpas, one endures drifting in the depths,</l><l>Each and every place is visited during rebirth in the six
                                    paths;</l><l>If [bonds] are not decisively broken off in this lifetime,</l><l>When will there ever be an end to the mutual retribution of
                                    enemies?<note type="footnote" n="67">It is a common trope in
                                        Chinese literature to refer to one's lover as one's "enemy."
                                        The reasoning behind this notion is that two people are
                                        thought to be brought together in the closest possible
                                        relationship in this life to work out a grievance that one
                                        of them had against the other in a previous life. Indeed,
                                        the word translated here as "enemy" (yuanjia) quite
                                        literally means "person with a grievance."</note></l><l>This, then, is called the suffering that comes from having to
                                    meet with what is hateful.</l></lg><p>On this night the Minister also explained to his wife the suffering
                                that comes from being apart from those whom one loves. If a family
                                brings up a son, the parents look upon him as a pearl or jade. When
                                he grows up and can distinguish east from west, then he leaves his
                                native village. Night after night his parents long for him, and day
                                after day they wait by the door till they weep with grief. They
                                become ill from such yearning, but when can they receive care and
                                    medicine?<note type="footnote" n="68">Because the son is not
                                    there to look after them.</note>Then, all of a sudden, it is
                                    winter<note type="footnote" n="69">The text appears to be
                                    defective at this point. It is possible that this refers to the
                                    "winter" of the parents' life.</note>or some festival, and the
                                members of the family are all present. But the thoughts of the
                                parents suddenly turn to the son far away, whereupon their breath
                                catches in their throats and fills their breasts. This, then, is
                                called the suffering that comes from being apart from those whom one
                                loves.</p><p>On that night the Minister finished explaining the
                                interrelated woes of the eight kinds of suffering. All three hundred
                                and some members of the residence, young and old, distinguished and
                                lowly, politely thanked the Minister. Only Shanqing was found
                                weeping profusely and did not have anything to say. He was thinking:
                                "I remember those days at Mt. Lu when I first lectured on the title
                                of this sutra. It made the great rocks sway and the grasses bow.
                                Auspicious birds and beasts came flying and filled the monastery.
                                Clouds of good fortune lingered, all the while wreathing the sides
                                of the Purple Hall. Auspicious breezes circled close to the edges of
                                the Vermilion Towers. Various gods listened to the Dharma, and the
                                ten types [of beings] heard the sutra. Those with shape and without
                                shape, those with form and without form, all cultivated emancipation
                                in order to achieve nirvana." Shanqing's eyes were full of tears
                                when he finished thinking these thoughts.</p><p>The Minister felt
                                that Shanqing's behavior was strange and asked him, "I have
                                explained the sutra to you, so what is your reason for weeping so
                                incessantly? Is it because you have a grievance against someone? If
                                you have any sense, tell me the reason immediately or else look out
                                for a flogging."</p><p>Shanqing stepped forward and addressed the
                                Minister: "Your lowly servant doesn't really have a grievance
                                against anyone else. It is only because Honorable Daoan's lecturing
                                can never be impartial."</p><p>The Minister said, "Ever since the
                                Honorable Daoan came to the capital and started lecturing, kings,
                                nobles, generals, and ministers listen to his preaching every day.
                                But you have never seen him preach; how could you know that his
                                lecturing cannot be impartial?"</p><p>Shanqing stepped forward and
                                addressed the Minister: "Last night, I followed you to the
                                monastery. However, I was left outside the gate and could not listen
                                to the sutra-lecture. This is how I know that Honorable Daoan's
                                preaching cannot be impartial. Although my station in life is that
                                of a lowly slave, I understand a bit of the Buddha's teachings. My
                                clothes may be different from a monk's robes, but there should be no
                                distinction in the Dharma. From this, it is clear that Daoan's
                                preaching cannot be impartial. He doesn't know how to convey the
                                teachings to the ears of the three classes of people, to those of
                                four kinds of birth, nor to the ten types [of beings]."</p><p>The
                                Minister asked, "What do you mean by 'the four kinds of birth' and
                                'the ten types [of beings],' and what are the 'ears of the three
                                classes of people'? Please explain them to me in detail. Make my
                                heart enlightened so that I clearly apprehend the Buddhist
                                teachings."</p><p>Shanqing said, "The three classes of people: the
                                first is the sick person on his bed; the second is the imprisoned
                                convict; the third is people without freedom. The dharma master
                                sitting on his raised platform does not understand how to convey his
                                explanations everywhere to the ears of the three classes of people
                                through skillful means.<note type="footnote" n="70">Also translated
                                    as "skill-in-means," this is the Buddhist concept of teaching
                                    known as upāya.</note>When such a mistake occurs, it is an
                                instance of not understanding how to share one's preaching
                                impartially."</p><p>The Minister asked, "What are the four kinds of
                                birth and the ten types [of beings]?"</p><p>Shanqing addressed the
                                Minister: "The four kinds of birth are viviparous, oviparous,
                                aqueous, and metamorphous.<note type="footnote" n="71">Sanskrit
                                    catur-yoni, as with (1) mammals; (2) birds, snakes; (3) worms,
                                    fishes; (4) moths (from the chrysalis), devas (heavenly beings),
                                    beings in hells or in newly evolved worlds.</note>These are the
                                four kinds of birth. The ten types [of beings] are: having shape,
                                having no shape, having form, having no form, not having form, not
                                having no form, with four capacities, two capacities, many
                                capacities, and no capacities. These are called the ten types [of
                                beings]."</p><p>The Minister spoke to Shanqing: "Because I do not
                                comprehend these things, please explain them to me in detail so that
                                I can abandon error and seek refuge in truth."<note type="footnote" n="72">The opposite qualities translated here as "error" and
                                    "truth" are often rendered as "heterodoxy" and
                                    "orthodoxy."</note></p><p>Shanqing said, "Viviparous birth: this
                                is a person who hears the Dharma. For example, two people go to a
                                monastery to listen to a sutra. One of them is not cupidinous and
                                goes into the monastery to listen to the sutra. The other one is
                                cupidinous and turns around to leave right away. The one who entered
                                the monastery sits in meditation by himself in the Good Dharma Hall
                                and listens to one sentence<note type="footnote" n="73">The
                                    character for "sentence" (ju) has been misread as the
                                    graphically somewhat similar zi (self).</note>of the marvelous
                                teachings that enter into his body and soul. Thereupon his heart is
                                filled with joy. But suddenly he remembers the one who did not enter
                                the monastery, whereupon his heart is filled with distraction.
                                Although there are words that he can hear, he is thoroughly
                                depressed. Like a child in a mother's womb whose view of the sun is
                                blocked by drifting clouds, he imperceptibly sinks into viviparous
                                birth.</p><p>"Oviparous birth: again, this is a person who [has the
                                opportunity to] hear the Dharma. Therefore, he goes to the monastery
                                to listen to a sutra. Sitting in front of the Good Dharma Hall, he
                                wants to entrust himself to the Dharma Master. However, the Dharma
                                Master does not expound [the sutra], but instead talks about
                                extraneous matters. Consequently, he talks of any old dharma,
                                causing people to be confused and making it hard for them to
                                understand. Thoroughly depressed, they soon sink into oviparous
                                birth.</p><p>"Aqueous birth: this kind of person often receives
                                clandestine teachings. They learn a sentence or a gāthā but do not
                                tell it to others. They crave to enrich themselves but do not know
                                how to disseminate [their learning] to the people. For this reason,
                                they sink into aqueous birth.</p><p>"Metamorphous birth: for
                                example, if someone goes to a monastery to listen to the Dharma and
                                receives one sentence of marvelous teaching, they separately obtain
                                an infinite and unlimited amount of meaning. The text draws out the
                                transformative powers of the doctrine that are countless as the
                                sands of Ganges. It is like lighting one lamp, and from that ten
                                lamps and a hundred lamps, then a thousand lamps and from that
                                hundreds, thousands, tens of thousands, and hundreds of thousands of
                                lamps. From lamp to lamp, the flame is never extinguished. This is
                                called metamorphous birth."</p><p>Then the Minister asked, "What are
                                the ten types [of beings]?"</p><p>Shanqing said, "First, having
                                shape: seeing the statue of a deity inside its clay niche, one
                                worships it devoutly. Such a person even says that the Buddha is
                                like Mount Sumeru.<note type="footnote" n="74">The axial mountain of
                                    the universe.</note>When the mind is activated only if a shape
                                is seen, this is called 'having shape.' Second, having no shape:
                                where there is no nature, no nature can be seen—like the moon in the
                                water and the wind in the air. The ten thousand dharmas are all
                                nonexistent; there is nothing whatsoever. This is called 'having no
                                shape.' Third, having form: supposing that one sees a handsome
                                person on the street and says to oneself that the person is handsome
                                because he had previously cultivated the Way. So one goes to a
                                monastery to listen to the Dharma and sees a master who is plump and
                                fair. Soon one takes a fancy to him and is completely captivated.
                                Having been completely captivated, vain thoughts arise. Vain
                                thoughts having arisen, they lead to ignorance. Having fallen prey
                                to ignorance, there is vexation. Having been overcome with vexation,
                                one begins to founder. Having foundered, one descends to hell. Such
                                transgressions continue for many kalpas, so that one's body and soul
                                are both unsettled, and consequently one endures suffering. This is
                                called 'having form.' Fourth, having no form: since the ten thousand
                                dharmas are all empty, how could there be reality? East and west
                                there are no traces; north and south there are no tracks. Things
                                have nothing to do with the body and soul, which altogether far
                                transcend the three worlds.<note type="footnote" n="75">Sanskrit
                                    triloka or trailokya, the three realms of desire, form, and pure
                                    spirit.</note>This is called 'having no form.' Fifth, not having
                                form: when spoken of, it exists, but, when one has finished
                                speaking, it returns to nothing. When posited, it exists, but, when
                                no longer posited, it returns to nothing. When believed in, it
                                exists, but, when no longer believed in, it returns to nothing. The
                                ten thousand dharmas have nothing to do with the body and mind. This
                                is called 'not having form.' Sixth, not having no form: without
                                language, without speech; without going, without coming; without
                                movement; without thought; without birth, without death—this is true
                                    reality.<note type="footnote" n="76">Sanskrit bhūtatathatā
                                    (substantial-thusness).</note>Without going, without coming;
                                this is the Buddha nature. This is called 'not having no form.'
                                Seventh, two capacities:<note type="footnote" n="77">Since the "two
                                    capacities" are generally understood to be "blessedness" (fa)
                                    and "intelligence" or "wisdom" (zhi), it may be argued that
                                    everywhere in this passage "person[hood]" (shen) is an
                                    orthographical error for fa (blessedness).</note>people living
                                in the world possess personhood and intelligence, which are
                                provisionally referred to as the two capacities. There may be
                                personhood but no intelligence, or there may be intelligence but no
                                personhood. If personhood and intelligence do not happen to
                                converge, then the individual will founder on an evil path. When
                                personhood and intelligence do converge, then one can achieve birth
                                on the path to Buddhahood. Therefore, the Great Master has the
                                following gāthā:</p><lg><l>Personhood may be born, but intelligence not,</l><l>Or intelligence may be born when the person is already old;</l><l>The person loathes the late birth of intelligence,</l><l>And intelligence loathes the premature birth of the person.</l><l>If personhood and intelligence do not converge,</l><l>One may repeatedly pass through old age;</l><l>But if personhood and intelligence converge,</l><l>One may achieve the path to Buddhahood.<note type="footnote" n="78">These verses are by a Korean Zen monk named Chingak
                                        (Modern Standard Mandarin pronunciation Zhenjue [True
                                        Awareness; 870-947]) and may also be found on Dunhuang
                                        manuscript S2165.</note></l></lg><p>When one possesses both personhood and intelligence, then it is
                                referred to as having 'two capacities.' Eighth, four capacities: the
                                four elements of human existence belong to earth, water, fire, and
                                wind, the four directions, and the four seas. These are called the
                                'four capacities.' Ninth, with many capacities: one is conversant
                                with the ten thousand dharmas and there is nothing with which one is
                                unfamiliar. One is knowledgeable about all the affairs of the world.
                                When asked about sutras and books, there is nothing one cannot
                                answer. All twelve divisions of sacred scripture have been
                                memorized. This is referred to as having 'many capacities.' Tenth,
                                no capacities: although one is a human, one is encumbered by
                                    everything.<note type="footnote" n="79">The last clause is
                                    impossible to understand without emendation, but if bù (not) is
                                    changed to the graphically similar yì (also; likewise;
                                    whatever), it makes good sense.</note>Unable to distinguish
                                between east and west, one is no different from an animal. This is
                                referred to as having 'no capacities.' The above ten types [of
                                beings] are each distinct. If you have any further doubts, please
                                feel free to ask."</p><p>When the Minister heard these words, it was
                                as though sweet dew<note type="footnote" n="80">Sanskrit amrta
                                    (ambrosia; the nectar of immortality).</note>was entering his
                                mind. The wife, who had also been listening to them, was filled with
                                the perfect Buddha-truth.<note type="footnote" n="81">More
                                    literally, "[felt] as though ghee were being poured on the top
                                    of her head," i.e., as though she were being annointed with the
                                    essential truth of Buddhism.</note>The Minister called Shanqing
                                to come forward [and said], "It seems from your sermon just now that
                                you are not inferior to Daoan. Tell me some more so that my mind
                                will be enlightened and I can have a clear understanding of the
                                Buddhist Dharma."</p><p>Thereupon Shanqing explained to the Minister
                                the twelve links in the chain of dependent origination,<note type="footnote" n="82">Sanskrit dvādaśānga pratītyasamutpāda;
                                    the twelve nidānas.</note>which are as follows:<note type="footnote" n="83">The following passage is severely garbled
                                    and abbreviated on the manuscript; it can only be restored by
                                    reference to its source in the chapter of the Lotus Sutra
                                    entitled "The Parable of the Metamorphic City."</note>ignorance
                                is the cause of activity, activity is the cause of consciousness,
                                consciousness is the cause of name and form, name and form are the
                                cause of the six senses, the six senses are the cause of contact,
                                contact is the cause of sensation, sensation is the cause of desire,
                                desire is the cause of grasping, grasping is the cause of existence,
                                existence is the cause of birth, and birth is the cause of old age,
                                sickness, death, anxiety, sorrow, suffering, and distress. Old age,
                                sickness, death, anxiety, sorrow, suffering, and distress are the
                                cause of ignorance. When ignorance is eliminated, then activity is
                                eliminated. When activity is eliminated, then consciousness is
                                eliminated. When consciousness is eliminated, then name and form are
                                eliminated. When name and form are eliminated, then the six senses
                                are eliminated. When the six senses are eliminated, then contact is
                                eliminated. When contact is eliminated, then sensation is
                                eliminated. When sensation is eliminated, then desire is eliminated.
                                When desire is eliminated, then grasping is eliminated. When
                                grasping is eliminated, then existence is eliminated. When existence
                                is eliminated, then birth is eliminated. When birth is eliminated,
                                then old age, sickness, death, anxiety, sorrow, suffering, and
                                distress are eliminated. These are the twelve links in the chain of
                                dependent origination.</p><p>Hearing this, the Minister exclaimed,
                                "Excellent! Excellent!" And, at that moment, the wife sighed and
                                obtained immeasurable fields of happiness. Shanqing then descended
                                from the seat on the raised platform and addressed the Minister:
                                "What Dharma Master Daoan says is like building a palace in thin
                                air. In the end, he can never succeed! When it seems success is
                                close, it will certainly still come crashing down. Although this
                                slave is from a lowly class, the Buddhist Dharma is the same for
                                all. Our clothing may be different, but our bodies are not
                                dissimilar. Now, this lowly slave would like to go with the Minister
                                to the monastery and have a debate with Dharma Master
                                Daoan."</p><p>The Minister said, "If you have made up your mind, I
                                won't stop you." And so the Minister and his wife led Shanqing into
                                the western courtyard where he bathed with warm, scented water and
                                changed his clothes. Then they let Shanqing return to his room to
                                rest and wait until early next morning, when there were to be
                                further orders.</p><p>Having returned to his room, Shanqing cleared
                                his mind and purified his thoughts. He kept this up till dawn, not
                                sleeping at all. Soon it was time to go to court, and Shanqing
                                followed the Minister to the palace. After the Minister came out of
                                court, he returned home to rest. Then he summoned Shanqing. The
                                Minister said, "This Daoan is one of the most eminent monks in the
                                country. You must carefully reconsider your plans."</p><p>Shanqing
                                addressed the Minister: "There is a proverb which says, 'Entering
                                the mountains without avoiding wolves and tigers is the bravery of
                                the woodcutters. Entering a lake without avoiding snakes and dragons
                                is the bravery of the fishermen.' If I can get the opportunity to
                                debate Daoan, it will be like a thirsty person getting water or like
                                someone who is cold having a fire. Sir, I request you to be at ease
                                and not worry." They waited for the time of preaching to begin, and
                                then they set off.</p><p>They soon reached [the monastery]. First,
                                the Minister paid two hundred strings of cash and then led Shanqing
                                into the monastery. At that time, the crowds of people who came to
                                listen were like clouds, and donations poured in like rain. As soon
                                as the bell rang, the lecture began. The main lecturer announced the
                                title of the sutra, the deacon<note type="footnote" n="84">Sanskrit
                                    karmadāna (duty-distributor), second only to the abbot of a
                                    monastery.</note>recited a Sanskrit hymn, and the members of the
                                four orders<note type="footnote" n="85">The four varga, namely
                                    bhiksu, bhiksunī, upāsaka, and upāsikā (monks, nuns, male and
                                    female devotees).</note>looked up in reverence as if scaling
                                Mount Grdhrakūta.<note type="footnote" n="86">"Vulture Peak," the
                                    mountain in Magadha, India, near Rajagrha, where the Buddha
                                    expounded many sutras.</note>Daoan expected that everything
                                would proceed happily, as though he were sitting in a meeting at the
                                Āmravana Garden.<note type="footnote" n="87">A garden of mango trees
                                    that was supposedly donated to the Buddha by a female
                                    devotee.</note>Thereupon, with his scepter in hand and sitting
                                on a jeweled platform, Daoan lit a large amount of priceless incense
                                and started to proclaim the marvelous significance of the sutra. He
                                emitted a [sacred] sound, then sang, enouncing the tide of the
                                sutra: The Great Nirvana Sutra, chapter "The Longevity of the
                                Tathāgatha," section one.</p><p>Having begun the sutra lecture,
                                Daoan praised the Buddha's majesty. First, he paid homage to the
                                sages and the wise men, and then he extolled the virtues of the
                                emperor. "I humbly wish that the way of the reigning emperor will be
                                favored with the appearance of a dragon chart,<note type="footnote" n="88">A mythological map that was carried out of the Yellow
                                    River by dragons and horses as an auspicious omen of the
                                    legendary Yellow Emperor's reign.</note>that his virtues may
                                shine like a golden garden, that he may hold a golden mirror to
                                illuminate the nine heavens,<note type="footnote" n="89">The highest
                                    heavens (an expression frequently employed by
                                Taoists).</note>and that he may follow the divine rays to visit all
                                directions. I wish that the various kings and princes may be forever
                                strong as golden branches, and that their jade leaves may be
                                eternally vernal. May the princesses and the imperial consorts be
                                forever radiant as chaste flowers. May the ministers and officials
                                of the court be completely filial and loyal. May the provincial and
                                county officials be pure and upright. As for the good men and good
                                women beneath this seat in the audience, may the thousand calamities
                                roll back with the mists and may pestilences disperse with the
                                clouds. May disasters not invade [the realm], and may merits be
                                copious. May sufferings end and sorrows cease on the three
                                    roads<note type="footnote" n="90">The paths leading to the hell
                                    of fire, the hell of blood, and the hell of sharp-edged
                                    swords.</note>of hell. May all the people in the Dharma world
                                achieve this prosperity together." When he had finished with his
                                invocation, Daoan intended to enter upon [a discussion of] the title
                                of the sutra.</p><p>At that moment Shanqing stood up in the hall,
                                and in loud voice shouted to stop the reading of the sutra title.
                                Everyone in the four orders who saw him was shocked. Shanqing slowly
                                came forward and, pointing at Daoan, said, "Honorable Daoan, you are
                                very capable in preaching the Dharma. As an eminent teacher,<note type="footnote" n="91">Sanskrit ācārya.</note>you open the sutra
                                to lecture and sing hymns, propagating the True Tenets of the
                                Buddha. Far and wide, you have saved those who are ignorant and
                                those who have gone astray by propagating the sacred doctrine. Your
                                language is brilliant and peerless within the realm. The number of
                                living beings you have benefited is incalculable. Long have you
                                served as a Dharma-boat<note type="footnote" n="92">To ferry them to
                                    nirvana.</note>for those in the sea of suffering. You have borne
                                great fruit in helping others to escape from the cycle of
                                transmigration. But I haven't been able to determine which sutra
                                text it is that you are lecturing on and which dharma you are
                                propagating for all living beings. Whose commentary elaborates the
                                True Tenets? I would like to get to the root, so I beg you to
                                explain. Dharma Master, you are famous for your lectures throughout
                                the land, and our ruler has proclaimed you as the best in the
                                country. The Minister's presence here indicates his approbation, and
                                this congenial place of worship<note type="footnote" n="93">Sanskrit
                                    bodhimandala (circle of enlightenment).</note>betokens dharmic
                                joy. If Your Honor bestows a great beneficence by doing what is
                                right and not ignoring me for being a rustic, I would be much
                                obliged."</p><p>When Daoan heard these words, he changed color and
                                became angry. He shouted at Shanqing, "Who are you to point in the
                                air and scold?! The principles in the marvelous canon of our
                                Buddha-Tathāgata are deeply profound. The Buddhist Dharma is
                                difficult to grasp; it is not something you can comprehend. Even if
                                I do not decline to explain [the teachings] to you, it would be like
                                a block of rock placed in water. Although the water, by nature, is
                                moist, it cannot penetrate into the rock. I see that your present
                                status is that of a lowly menial. How can you just do as you please?
                                If I commend the Buddhist Dharma to kings and high officials, only
                                the wise among them can comprehend such teachings. Haven't you heard
                                what the heretical books say? 'If someone is worthy of being spoken
                                to, then speak to them. If they are not worthy of being spoken to,
                                it would be a waste of words to do so.'<note type="footnote" n="94">Based on a passage (1; .8) in the Analects (Lunyu) of
                                    Confucius: "The Master said, 'If you can speak to someone but
                                    fail to do so, that is to waste a person. If you cannot speak
                                    with someone but go ahead and do it anyway, that is a waste of
                                    words. The wise person wastes neither people nor
                                words.'"</note>Even the teachings handed down by the Sage<note type="footnote" n="95">Confucius.</note>recommend rejection in
                                such cases. I will not make any explanations for an inferior,
                                ignorant person like you. Let the deacon examine the situation and
                                not allow anyone to cause a ruckus. The time for listening to the
                                sutra is to be used sparingly. If you do not understand, you must
                                lower your head, keep quiet, and pay attention to what you are
                                hearing. The lecture mat on the dais is for proclaiming to the
                                audience, all of whom listen to the Dharma. It's not your business
                                to be a person who asks questions about the Dharma."<note type="footnote" n="96">The syntax of this sentence is badly
                                    jumbled. What the author probably originally intended to say was
                                    roughly the following: "When the presiding elder is on his lotus
                                    mat, the audience should all listen to the Dharma. If they cause
                                    a ruckus and ask a lot of questions, they are not behaving as a
                                    person [who has come] to listen to the Dharma
                                [should]."</note></p><p>Indeed, no one among the people sitting at
                                the sermon disagreed with his opinions. Although everyone else was
                                afraid of your Daoan, when it came to this Shanqing, his attitude
                                was, "Who's afraid of you?" So, when Shanqing heard these words, he
                                raised his voice all the more and, pointing at Daoan, angrily
                                rebuked him: "Ācārya,<note type="footnote" n="97">See note
                                    91.</note>your behavior shows that you are a common monk who has
                                lost the Way.<note type="footnote" n="98">This sentence has a couple
                                    of rare (yōng [commonplace, mediocre]) and miswritten (zhi
                                    [ambition] — wang [lose; lack]) graphs that require explanation
                                    and emendation to make sense.</note>What you say and ask is not
                                in accord with the sacred purport. The teachings bequeathed by our
                                Tathāgata are explicit in the sutras. Dumb animals and intelligent
                                beings are all imbued with the Buddha-nature. Have you read the
                                Vajracchedikā-sūtra? Viviparous, oviparous, aqueous, metamorphous,
                                the ten types [of beings] and the four kinds of births; having
                                shape, having no shape, having form, having no form—everyone can
                                achieve nirvana and this is called emancipation. Surely, I am a
                                human. How can I be unfit to hear<note type="footnote" n="99">Wén
                                    (hear) should probably be emended to wèn (ask about).</note>the
                                Dharma? I may be an inferior menial, but the Buddha-nature is
                                unbiased. My clothes may be different from a monk's robes, but there
                                should be no distinctions in the Dharma. Haven't you heard about
                                Confucius who, although he was a sage, was for a long time puzzled
                                by an argument about the sun?<note type="footnote" n="100">This is
                                    an allusion to a famous passage in the "Questions of Tang"
                                    chapter of the Taoist text entitled Master Lie (Lie Zi): When
                                    Confucius went on an excursion to the east, he saw two boys
                                    having an argument. He asked them what it was about. One of the
                                    boys said, "I think that the sun is closest to us when it first
                                    comes up and is farthest at noon." The other boy thought that
                                    the sun was farthest when it first came up and closest at noon.
                                    The first boy said, "When the sun first comes up, it is big as a
                                    chariot canopy, but at noon it is only the size of a plate or
                                    bowl. Isn't this because things that are distant seem small and
                                    things that are close seem big?" The second boy said, "When the
                                    sun first comes up, the air is chilly, but at noon it's as hot
                                    as though one had immersed one's hand in boiling water. Isn't
                                    this because things that are close seem hot and those that are
                                    distant seem cool?" Confucius couldn't make up his mind which of
                                    the boys was right. The two little boys laughed and said, "Who
                                    says you're so smart?"</note>The World-Honored One of Great
                                Enlightenment himself had difficulty with a metal-tipped spear.<note type="footnote" n="101">In several Buddhist texts, it is
                                    mentioned that the Buddha was jabbed in the foot by a spear or
                                    sharp piece of wood because, in a previous existence, he had
                                    stabbed someone in the foot.</note>The layman Vimalakīrti<note type="footnote" n="102">Vimalakīrti was the lay paragon of
                                    Buddhist learning who, nonetheless, was upbraided by an
                                    attendant of Mañjuśrī, the Bodhisattva who is the idealization
                                    of Wisdom.</note>was rebuked by Prabhāvyūha. And Ksāntivādi rsi
                                was dismembered by Kalingarāja.<note type="footnote" n="103">The
                                    name of the ascetic literally means "Bear Insult." He was
                                    Śākyamuni Buddha in a former life and suffered mutilation in
                                    order to convert the evil King Kalingarāja. His story is told,
                                    among other places, in the jātakas (tales of the Buddha's
                                    previous incarnations) and is depicted on the wall-paintings at
                                    Qizil in Eastern Central Asia.</note>An honorable man doesn't
                                cheat in a dark room'—this is a popular saying of the common
                                    literati.<note type="footnote" n="104">This must have been a
                                    widely used expression among Confucian-minded persons in the
                                    early Tang since it is included both in "Rhapsody on a Firefly"
                                    by the poet Luo Binwang (b. 640) and in the Family Instructions
                                    of the Grand Duke (Taigong jiajiao), which is a collection of
                                    popular wisdom well represented among the Dunhuang
                                    manuscripts.</note>This lowly slave is determined to ask about
                                the text of the sutra, but it is you up there on your platform who
                                are 'pointing in the air and scolding.' Potent medical herbs grow
                                even on steep mountains, and lotuses bloom precisely in the
                                    mud.<note type="footnote" n="105">A favorite Buddhist parable
                                    found in the Vimalakīrti-sūtra and other texts.</note>There may
                                be bright pearls inside of a cotton bag, while an embroidered pouch
                                may contain useless chaff. Master of the dais, when you go into the
                                mountains to gather timber, do not select the trees solely on the
                                basis of their external appearance. If you do things this way, you
                                would miss the likes of Ziyu.<note type="footnote" n="106">A
                                    disciple of Confucius who had an ugly appearance but was of high
                                    moral character.</note>Now, the Buddha's teachings are, in
                                substance, equitable. They are like the sweet moisture which rains
                                down and dampens everything all over. It cannot just keep falling
                                and nourishing the flat fields and low grasses while withholding its
                                benevolent moisture from hollows and hillocks. The rain is from the
                                first impartial and natural, not giving rise to a consciousness of
                                self and other; everything is without differentiation. Haven't you
                                seen how the Medicine King Bod-hisattva<note type="footnote" n="107">Bhaisajyarāja Bodhisattva, the healing savior.</note>demarcates
                                the four seasons so that the five fruits, peaches, and plums follow
                                the eight festivals<note type="footnote" n="108">See note
                                48.</note>and are produced from the earth. In the 'Parable of
                                Medicinal Herbs'<note type="footnote" n="109">A chapter of the Lotus
                                    Sutra.</note>it is clearly explained that the big roots, big
                                trees, big branches, and big leaves all depend on their original
                                capacities and are produced from the earth. One cannot say that
                                because some fruit is sweet the rain is sweet, or that because other
                                fruit is sour the rain is sour. Rain, after all, has a single taste;
                                and each of the plants that receives the rain has its own distinct
                                nature. Only when we cultivate an impartial mind will the
                                    dharma-world<note type="footnote" n="110">Sanskrit dharmadhātu,
                                    which refers either to things in general, whether noumenal or
                                    phenomenal, or the unifying spiritual reality that serves as the
                                    basis of all things.</note>naturally be peaceful. The Minister
                                is here, sir, so you should not deceive the people. Just be nice and
                                do what is right. I hope that you will be so good as to engage in a
                                debate with me."</p><p>Having been scolded, Daoan was deeply
                                chagrined. He was too embarrassed to glance at the Minister, and
                                blushed when he looked at the four orders. Then he grabbed his
                                    ruler<note type="footnote" n="111">The dianchi (standard-ruler)
                                    of the text is an error for the graphically similar jiechi
                                    (boundary-ruler). The latter is a sort of paperweight kept on
                                    the table or lecture stand. Buddhist masters considered jiechi
                                    to be homophonous with another sinographic form meaning
                                    "precept-ruler." Aside from using the ruler as a paperweight,
                                    they would strike the table or lectern with it to draw the
                                    attention of their auditors. A totally different interpretation
                                    of the problematic phrase would read it as suì chì diănlăn
                                    (thereupon threw aside his lecture notes).</note>and, throwing
                                it aside, slowly came forward. In an angry voice, he rebuked,
                                "Shanqing, haven't you heard that it's not worth fighting an
                                unworthy opponent even if he dies?<note type="footnote" n="112">It
                                    has been necessary to emend dĭ (bottom) to dí (opponent) in
                                    order to make sense of this sentence.</note>Why go to the
                                trouble of shooting a crossbow with a draw of a thousand pounds
                                because of the peccadilloes of a mouse? If [I start to beat] my drum
                                at you,<note type="footnote" n="113">This clause may perhaps better
                                    be interpreted as "If you hear my instructions," substituting
                                    jiào (teaching, doctrine) for the seemingly out of place but
                                    graphically somewhat similar qǔ (drum).</note>you'd better not
                                decline to respond. But it would be like a wren flying along with a
                                roc. I'd be wasting my energy on you. If you have any sense, you'll
                                lower your head, keep silent, and listen carefully. If you still
                                fail to follow my instructions, I'll have no choice but to ask the
                                Minister to have you caned. You will be driven out of the monastery
                                and not be allowed to listen to the sutra. If you keep on ranting
                                and raving, you will come to regret it!"</p><p>Hearing this,
                                Shanqing raised his voice still higher and, pointing at Daoan across
                                the room, said, "Such brazen, arrogant recklessness! Sir, you wear a
                                monk's robes and often proclaim the True Sutras. Therefore, you
                                should have an immeasurable heart, possess the conduct of the six
                                    pāramitās,<note type="footnote" n="114">The six things that
                                    ferry one across the sea of mortality to nirvana: charity,
                                    obeying the commandments, patience, zeal to progress, meditation
                                    (Zen), wisdom.</note>express the bodhi-mind, and benefit all
                                living beings so that they may transcend the three worlds.<note type="footnote" n="115">See note 75.</note>How can your heart be
                                without compassion or sympathy? Instead, you harm others grievously,
                                cheat ordinary people, and request the Minister to have someone
                                caned. This type of behavior does not accord with the True Tenets.
                                How are the words that you utter different from those of the
                                heretics? Ācārya, you think of yourself as the roc which presumes to
                                raise its wings and touch the sky, and you dismiss others as wrens
                                that spend most of their time roosting in the low grasses, unable to
                                see the heart of the Way. Those who are rude cheat others, and those
                                who are degenerate forget justice. Needless to say, this morning you
                                should be cautious<note type="footnote" n="116">With appropriate
                                    emendations, the first part of this sentence more likely was
                                    intended to mean "this morning you [should] respond (mò [don't]
                                    - yīng [outstanding - respond]) to my questions (yŭ [speak] –
                                    jié [interrogate])."</note>and not speak insultingly or
                                heedlessly. If there are any errors in my words, then I will serve
                                as your disciple. You should hold fast to your prize and not let it
                                slip out of your hands. But, if there is a mistake with a single
                                word of your response, then it will be up to me to request that the
                                Minister have you caned. You will be dragged down from your raised
                                platform and driven out of the monastery. You will not be permitted
                                to propagate the teachings to the public. Don't say that you weren't
                                told!"</p><p>Having been reprimanded, Daoan kept silent without a
                                word to utter. He was too embarrassed to glance at the Minister, and
                                blushed when he looked at the four orders. After a long while he
                                called Shanqing to come forward [and said], "The words that I said
                                before were all to jest with you. You don't need to criticize me,
                                and I won't find fault with you. When I first heard what you were
                                saying, I was really suspicious. I thought that you actually wanted
                                to create disorder in the lecture hall and upset the audience. Now I
                                know that you are truly a capable person. If you ask the title of
                                the sutra I shall respectfully answer."</p><p>Shanqing said,
                                "Ācārya, you yourself said 'You don't need to criticize me.' The
                                Tathāgata left behind his doctrines, and they were preserved in the
                                sutras because of King Ajatasatru's<note type="footnote" n="117">A
                                    famous king of Magadha who was at first opposed to Buddhism but
                                    later became a generous supporter. The text is corrupt at this
                                    point and further garbled by its modern editors, but it is
                                    possible to discern the drift of Shanqing's
                                words.</note>[sponsorship. Thus the World-] Honored's discussions
                                are known to everyone. I dare not go beyond the questions that you
                                have allowed me to ask today. I would just like to inquire about the
                                title of the sutra, and then I will definitely have some follow-up
                                questions for you."</p><lg>"Just now you asked this poor monk about
                                the sutra that I lecture on," said Daoan. "It is the
                                Mahānirvāna-sūtra. Now that you have heard the title, Shanqing,
                                remember it clearly."<note type="footnote" n="118">The text appears
                                    to be corrupt here and for the next several paragraphs. However,
                                    if one realizes that the commentary which Daoan is citing to
                                    Huiyuan (i.e., Shanqing) was actually written years earlier by
                                    Huiyuan himself, the ironies, prompts, and awkward transitions
                                    of this passage are much easier to
                                follow.</note></lg><lg>Shanqing asked, "What is the meaning of mahā?
                                What is the meaning of nir? And what is the meaning of
                                vāna?"</lg><lg>Daoan answered, " Mahā stands for 'broad': to broadly
                                benefit all sentient beings and help them escape from the sea of
                                suffering. Nir means 'no-more-birth,' neither birth nor extinction;
                                this is in conformity with True Thusness.<note type="footnote" n="119">See note 76.</note>Neither going nor coming; this is the
                                Buddha-nature. The word vāna: transport all sentient beings out of
                                the three worlds and lead them to the opposite bank."<note type="footnote" n="120">The actual etymology of "nirvana" is
                                    nir- (out, away) + vāna (blowing), hence "blowing out;
                                    extinction."</note></lg><lg>Shanqing said, "The three
                                word-segments just mentioned illustrate seven things."</lg><p>"Now,
                                Shanqing, you will hear them, so you must remember them. The first
                                thing that they illustrate is comparable to how, when the spring
                                sunlight becomes active, the ten thousand grasses all begin to grow.
                                Flowers blossom everywhere no matter whether it is a shallow valley
                                or a deep ravine. Similarly, once the name of this sutra of the
                                marvelous Dharma was established and it was propagated and
                                transmitted by the Tathāgata, then all sentient beings who hear the
                                sutra, without distinguishing high or low, invariably become better.
                                The second thing they illustrate is like tying a rope around the
                                crooked branches of a tree [to straighten them. Similarly, hearing
                                them] can disperse depravity and restore rectitude. The third thing
                                they illustrate is like a bubbling spring which never dries up.
                                Similarly, the sutra text has been in the world for a long time and
                                has continued to spread without a respite. The fourth thing they
                                illustrate is like the rivers and seas which enable boats with a
                                capacity of ten thousand bushels to sail on them. Similarly,
                                sentient beings who want to cross rivers and lakes must first rely
                                on a long oar. The sutra text transmitted to the world can boost
                                those aiming to escape from the mundane world.<note type="footnote" n="121">I.e., those who wish to achieve nirvana.</note>Those who
                                want to get close to and cultivate the Way must first rely on the
                                power of the sutra. The fifth thing they illustrate is like heaven
                                and earth which cover and support all sentient beings. If heaven and
                                earth were completely nonexistent, upon what would the myriad
                                    images<note type="footnote" n="122">Sanskrit pratirūpa(ka),
                                    which collectively constitute the reality of
                                phenomena.</note>stand? Since the text of the Nirvana Sutra exists,
                                sentient beings can depend on it to cultivate themselves. But if the
                                Dharma of the sutra were completely nonexistent, what could they
                                rely on to escape from the world? The sixth thing they illustrate is
                                like the warp and the woof which can be made into a colorful brocade
                                or fine, white silk. Whether a long piece of thin silk or a damask,
                                they are all because of the warp and the woof. Once the name of the
                                marvelous sutra is established, cultivation of the Way is achieved
                                based on this. And, totally relying on the power of the sutra, one
                                can even attain unsurpassed wisdom.<note type="footnote" n="123">Sanskrit anuttara bodhi, the enlightenment of a
                                Buddha.</note>The seventh thing they illustrate is like the roads
                                and tracks which provide passage to people coming and going. People
                                who desire to travel a thousand tricents have to start off from a
                                road. Sentient beings who are determined to cultivate the Way must
                                first read and recite the text of the sutra. Therefore, the ways of
                                the later sages are taken from this. "Although the seven meanings
                                above are each distinct, together they explain the one word 'sutra.'
                                Now that you have heard them, Shanqing, you must remember
                                them."</p><p>Shanqing then asked, "The word 'sutra' by itself has so
                                many meanings. Is there anything further regarding the name of the
                                sutra?" Daoan replied, "The meaning of 'nirvana' is 'immeasurable
                                and limitless.' How could one completely finish explaining the title
                                of the sutra? We may compare it to the thousands and tens of
                                thousands of families and households belonging to the hundred
                                    surnames.<note type="footnote" n="124">The "hundred surnames"
                                    signifies the common people or the totality of all the Chinese
                                    surnames.</note>How can they be organized? It is for this reason
                                that prefectures and counties were established, and the territories
                                of each were divided up and boundaries were drawn. The single word
                                'sutra' separately proclaims tens of thousands of dharmas.
                                Consequently, each one is different. The prefectures and counties
                                must depend upon officials to keep records; the marvelous Dharma
                                requires the establishment of sutra titles. If prefectures and
                                counties do not have officials, how could the hundred surnames be
                                ordered? The writing of commentaries on the texts of the sutras is,
                                in a sense, to 'comb'<note type="footnote" n="125">The Sinitic words
                                    for "comb" (shu) and "(sub)commentary" (shu) are etymologically
                                    closely linked, both deriving from a root signifying "separate;
                                    keep apart."</note>them. We may compare it to tangled hair that
                                gets combed. When a sutra title is established for the ten thousand
                                dharmas, the sages can thereby attain the Way. The answers that I
                                have provided above are all based on the sutras. If you have further
                                doubts, please feel free to ask again."</p><p>"Ācārya, I'll let you
                                off on the seven meanings of 'sutra,'" said Shanqing. "But I have a
                                few more questions. Would you allow me to ask them?"</p><p>Daoan
                                replied, "This poor monk regards heavenly beings and humans as his
                                teachers. The meanings are like bubbling springs, and the dharmas
                                are flowing water. If you want to ask something, please do ask, and
                                I will respond as quickly as I did when explaining your previous
                                    doubts."<note type="footnote" n="126">The last clause is
                                    obviously garbled. With suitable rearrangement, it may perhaps
                                    be better understood to mean "and I will now respond as I did
                                    before, [so] if you have any doubts continue speaking (i.e.,
                                    asking)."</note></p><p>Shanqing said, "As for the Buddhist
                                Dharma, all may take refuge in it. Light dust accumulates to form a
                                mountain; falling dew adds up to flowing water. When one ladles out
                                the latter, one cannot gauge its origin; when one journeys toward
                                the former, one seldom can reach its limits. Yet this lowly slave
                                [wishes] to ask the Dharma Master, like a firefly competing with the
                                sun, or a cicada trying to hold back a chariot. Thinking himself to
                                be a huge bird, he dares to climb onto the phoenix terrace. Under
                                the crash of thunder, it is difficult to hear the beating of muffled
                                drums; in front of green jade, how can a tiny dagger be
                                presumptuous? Only the Buddha-nature is omnipresent in sentient
                                    beings.<note type="footnote" n="127">Sanskrit
                                sattva.</note>Again, I ask what the essence of the Buddha-Tathāgata
                                is."</p><p>Daoan replied, "Come closer, Shanqing. You need not be so
                                humble. The essence of our Buddha is compassion."</p><p>Again,
                                Shanqing asked, "Since you have said that the essence of our Buddha
                                is compassion, why do you not save the unbelieving<note type="footnote" n="128">Sanskrit icchantika (full of
                                    desire[s]).</note>sentient beings?"</p><p>Daoan replied, "You do
                                not understand the real reasons. Listen while I explain. The
                                unbelieving sentient beings are like this because they themselves
                                have created bad karma. For example, if a family raises a boy who
                                grows up to be a man that steals and robs in the village, when this
                                matter is revealed he is arrested by the local authorities and is
                                sent to jail. He is beaten, and the documents of the case are
                                prepared. He confesses his crimes and is led to court, where it
                                appears that his death is imminent. Although the boy's parents are
                                kind and compassionate, how can the boy be rescued from the laws of
                                the state? Although our Buddha is compassionate, unfortunately the
                                power of the Buddha is not the same as the power of the boy's karma.
                                In instances of this sort, then it will be difficult to save the
                                person."</p><p>Shanqing asked, saying, "Although the unbelieving
                                sentient beings have created bad karma, our Buddha is compassionate
                                and would save even them. All that you have said just now relates to
                                    external<note type="footnote" n="129">Sanskrit bahirdhā, i.e.,
                                    peripheral or indirect causation.</note>causation. What does our
                                Buddha-Tathāgata consider to be nature?"</p><p>Daoan replied, "He
                                takes impartiality to be nature."</p><p>Shanqing asked, "Since you
                                have stated that nature is impartiality, why do sentient beings sink
                                into the cycle of birth-and-death,<note type="footnote" n="130">Sanskrit samsāra (birth and rebirth; life and
                                death).</note>while the Buddha can testify to nirvana without
                                    residue?"<note type="footnote" n="131">Sanskrit aśesa (without
                                    anything left over).</note></p><p>Daoan replied, "Sentient
                                beings sink into the path of evil due to ignorance and false
                                thoughts. The Buddha can testify to nirvana without residue because
                                everything has been extinguished."</p><p>Shanqing asked once again,
                                "If sentient beings are ignorant and distressed<note type="footnote" n="132">Sanskrit kleśa.</note>by delusion, what is their
                                relationship to the Buddha nature?"</p><p>Daoan replied, "Sentient
                                beings are characterized by ignorance and distress; the Buddha
                                nature is characterized by everything being cut off.<note type="footnote" n="133">Sanskrit
                                sarva-nigraha-sthāna.</note>This is why sentient beings are not
                                separated from the Buddha and the Buddha is not separated from
                                sentient beings. The words that I have said above are all careful
                                answers of this sort."</p><p>Shanqing said, "Ācārya, the words that
                                you have just spoken are greatly in error. Your lecturing, hymns,
                                and sutra text are greatly inaccurate. It's all a bunch of
                                thoughtless nonsense meant to please the disciples, who listen to
                                whatever sounds good. For example, the rivers, lakes, and great seas
                                have numerous sentient beings within them. They are either turtles
                                and lizards, or they may be shrimp, crabs, dragons, and fish. There
                                are many different kinds of creatures like these that belong in the
                                water. Although fish and water have affinities, there are
                                differences between them. If a fish does not have any water, it will
                                die. However, if water does not have any fish, it is placid as
                                always. Sentient beings founder when they are separated from the
                                Buddha. The Buddha, however, remains in a quiet state when separated
                                from sentient beings. We have heard that the Buddha is the most
                                uniquely honored being to have appeared in the world. In his
                                    unity,<note type="footnote" n="134">Sanskrit ekatva, which may
                                    stand for bhūtatathatā (see n. 76).</note>he far transcends the
                                three worlds. Yet, due to his compassion, he saves the sentient
                                beings. As for the Buddha and the common people being identical, the
                                examples that have been given are all incorrect. In the sutra on
                                nirvana, there are profound similes everywhere. Now, I would like to
                                request that Your Honor briefly explain them a bit to the
                                audience."</p><p>Daoan answered, "The similes in the Nirvana Sutra
                                are quite numerous. There are three thousand major similes and eight
                                hundred minor ones."</p><p>Shanqing interrupted and asked, "What is
                                the meaning of 'Black Wind'?"</p><p>Daoan replied, "The Black Wind
                                is the wind of sentient beings' ignorance. For countless kalpas,
                                sentient beings have been buffeted and shaken by this wind. This
                                wind can be divided into eight types. To introduce their meanings
                                individually and discuss them completely is impossible."</p><p>At
                                this point, Shanqing knew that Daoan did not understand and could
                                not explain the similes. Shanqing asked, saying, "Ācārya, you are
                                acclaimed as one of the country's most virtuous<note type="footnote" n="135">Sanskrit bbadanta (great virtue), originally a tide of
                                    the Buddha, but applied also to monks.</note>monks. You ought to
                                be able to give ten answers for every question. Although you have a
                                skull, it is without eyes. For someone to cross water, he must first
                                know how to float. If he does not know how, it will be a waste of
                                effort to enter the water. As for the meaning of Black Wind, who has
                                lectured on it, and who has written the commentary on the sutra
                                text?"</p><p>Thereupon, in his mind Daoan wanted to answer, but his
                                mouth could not reply. And when his mouth was ready to answer, his
                                mind could not reply. Fidgeting with his hands and feet, all he
                                could do was exclaim, "Mea culpa! I hope that you will be
                                compassionate and explain for me."</p><p>Shanqing said, "There's
                                nothing whatsoever to get frightened about over the meaning of the
                                Nirvana Sutra. Please relax and do not worry. I won't ask you
                                anything else, but would simply ask your honor where you obtained
                                the commentary on the Nirvana Sutra."</p><p>Daoan replied, "It was
                                brought from the place of the Great Master Yuan at Mount
                                Lu."</p><p>Shanqing asked, "If you were to see Master Yuan today,
                                would you still be able to recognize him?"</p><p>Daoan replied, "If
                                I were to see Master Yuan today, I honestly wouldn't be able to
                                recognize him."</p><p>Shanqing asked, "Since you say you wouldn't be
                                able to recognize him, where did you get the commentary
                                from?"</p><p>Daoan replied, "I got it from the monk Yunqing, the
                                chief disciple of Master Yuan."</p><p>Shanqing said, "If you are
                                looking for someone else, then I truly am not he. But if you are
                                looking for Master Yuan, then this lowly slave is the
                                one."</p><p>Hearing this, Daoan became very suspicious, "I have
                                heard," he said, "that the Great Master has a distinct mark—a fleshy
                                protuberance around his wrist.<note type="footnote" n="136">Popular
                                    legends about the historical Huiyuan recount that he was born
                                    with an inch-wide "bracelet" of flesh around his left wrist and
                                    that this was taken as a sign of his bodhisattvahood. See, for
                                    example, Imperially Reviewed Encyclopedia of the Reign of Great
                                    Peace (Taiping yulan) comp. 984), vol. 369. It is indicative of
                                    the strangely intertwined strands of legend and history, fantasy
                                    and reality, in this tale that, according to his biography in
                                    Biographies of Eminent Monks (Gaoseng zhuan), it was Daoan who
                                    actually had a birthmark on his hand.</note>If you are indeed
                                the Great Master, then show it to me."</p><p>Thereupon, in order to
                                put Daoan's suspicion to rest, Master Yuan rolled up his left sleeve
                                and, sure enough, there was a fleshy protuberance around his wrist.
                                It emitted a bright light, which was seen by everyone in the
                                audience. Then Daoan got up and came down from the raised platform.
                                He beat himself all over the body until fresh blood flowed from the
                                seven apertures.<note type="footnote" n="137">The eyes, ears,
                                    nostrils, and mouth. This sentence is a typical expression of
                                    extreme remorse that is found in many Dunhuang popular
                                    narratives.</note>Overcome with repentance, he went forward a
                                step at a time and, out of self-hatred for not recognizing the
                                superior person, was about to use a sharp dagger to gouge out his
                                eyes. Tears falling like rain and wailing sorrowfully, he prostrated
                                himself and begged the superior person to show compassion for his
                                penitent grief.</p><p>Master Yuan said, "Do not harbor doubt or
                                worry. There is no need for you to suffer and wail with grief. You
                                are fully<note type="footnote" n="138">To use "full[y]" in this way
                                    is awkward both in English and in Chinese, but its frequent and
                                    natural usage in Sanskrit shows to what extent Buddhist hybrid
                                    styles of "translatese" had permeated even popular narratives
                                    that were composed by individuals who almost certainly were not
                                    schooled in Indian languages. The present text is replete with
                                    such usages, but we have chosen to mention this instance only
                                    because of its obviousness and representativeness. This
                                    phenomenon of Sino-Indian linguistic and stylistic hybridity in
                                    medieval Buddhist texts is comparable to the Germanic and Slavic
                                    syntax and flavor of typical Chinese Communist writing
                                    (including that of Mao, who knew no Russian or German, but who
                                    was steeped in the translated works of Marx, Engels, and Lenin).
                                    Similarly, through the massive amounts of translation of
                                    scientific, technical, legal, administrative, and literary
                                    texts, English has had an enormous impact on the lexicon and
                                    even the grammar of Sinitic languages during the past two
                                    centuries.</note>a common person. How could you have recognized
                                in me the one who expounded the meaning of nirvana?<note type="footnote" n="139">This sentence is somewhat garbled and
                                    may also be interpreted as meaning "How could you have
                                    understood the meaning of nirvana explained by me?" But this is
                                    directly contrary to Huiyuan's own critique of Daoan in which he
                                    repeatedly stressed that it was essential for a capable teacher
                                    of Buddhist doctrine to be able to explain things in such a way
                                    that common mortals could understand them. Suffice it to say
                                    that, like most Dunhuang popular narratives, the present text is
                                    replete with such problematic constructions, a fair indication
                                    of their social status and literary nature.</note>I shall soon
                                occupy my seat as teacher, but let me first apologize to the
                                Minister. I shall then come back and preach the True Dharma to
                                you."</p><p>And so Master Yuan went straight in front of the
                                Minister and addressed him saying, "The days this lowly slave has
                                served you, Minister, are few in number, and I have not performed
                                any 'sweating-horse merits.' Abruptly entering the monastery, I
                                disrupted the sermon. Yet I have been the recipient of Your Honor's
                                generosity in not being blamed for this crime. Today, in front of
                                the audience, I request that you mete out to me a painful
                                caning."</p><p>Hearing these words, the Minister beat himself all
                                over. On hands and knees, and with his face to the ground, he would
                                not get up. After a long time, he revived and walked towards the
                                superior person whom he addressed, saying, "Although I am the Chief
                                Minister, I am inept in dealing with affairs. I have benefited from
                                the three vows<note type="footnote" n="140">Perhaps referring to the
                                    three vows to take refuge in the Buddha, the Dharma, and the
                                    Samgha (community of monks). Apart from the fact that the word
                                    translated as "vows" is written with a very strange character,
                                    there are numerous other difficulties in understanding this
                                    refractory sentence. With major restructuring and emendation, it
                                    may be rendered as "... I have been inept in dealing with
                                    affairs. It has already been six years (literally, 'winters')
                                    that I have used [you as my servant] morning and
                                night."</note>and been rewarded by the court. However,how could I,
                                an ordinary mortal with carnal eyes, distinguish a sage?<note type="footnote" n="141">This amounts to a proverb widely used in
                                    varying forms in China since at least the Tang period. Because
                                    the notion of carnal (or fleshy, physical) eyes (Skt.
                                    māmsacaksus) is clearly derived from Buddhist sources, this is
                                    another indication of the depth to which Indian concepts and
                                    linguistic usages had penetrated Chinese culture.</note>The
                                guilt that I bear is so great that it fills the entire universe, yet
                                you spare me of blame. For six years you were my slave, and you
                                often labored in my house. Sometimes I used harsh language to scold
                                Your Honor. How should I repent for such sins?"</p><p>Master Yuan
                                said, "This is due to my acting as a guarantor during a previous
                                life in which debts were not settled. If one does not want to have
                                any grievances in this life, then all accounts should be settled
                                here. Once all debts are completely cleared, there won't be anything
                                to be afraid of. And, from now on, when you look forward, there
                                won't be any need for worrying."</p><p>Hearing these words, the
                                Minister started to wail with grief all over again. He begged the
                                honorable person for compassion, and asked him to explain the karma
                                of his previous life.</p><p>Master Yuan said, "The Minister was a
                                merchant in his previous life and that fellow Bo Zhuang was also a
                                merchant. The Minister borrowed five hundred strings of cash from Bo
                                Zhuang. In that transaction, I was the guarantor. Later, when the
                                Minister died [before returning the money], I wanted to pay back the
                                debt. Unfortunately, I too died [before returning the money]. After
                                several samsaric circles, we have unexpectedly met. Because of these
                                karmic causes, the debt that was guaranteed has been
                                repaid."</p><p>Upon hearing this, the Minister walked forward and,
                                wailing with grief, began to shed tears like rain. Blaming himself
                                for his transgressions, he confessed, "Since it was I, your
                                disciple, who contracted a debt to another person, I should have
                                paid it back myself. How stupid I was for having given Your Honor so
                                much trouble! I will certainly fall into hell after this
                                lifetime."</p><p>Master Yuan said, "The debt has now been
                                compensated, so you do not have to be apprehensive. From now on,
                                avoid contracting further [debts]. Earnestly encourage your family
                                members and disciples, if they have debts, to be sure to pay them
                                back. To fulfill my duty as a guarantor, this poor monk even had to
                                serve as a slave for six years or the matter would not have been
                                concluded. The common person of shallow knowledge is not afraid of
                                committing sins. But if one commits a host of sins, how can one
                                repent?"</p><p>At this time, the audience wailed with grief and shed
                                tears like rain. Feeling sorry for Master Yuan, they were completely
                                filled with sadness. A thousand people gazed upon him reverently,
                                and ten thousand sighed with admiration. On this day, everyone in
                                the audience ceased their grudging and greed. Then, before Master
                                Yuan had finished, he was repeatedly requested by all those present
                                at the sermon, including the Minister, to once again mount the
                                raised platform.</p><p>On that day, Master Yuan was like a withered
                                tree at the edge of a cliff that had once again found spring, or
                                like a fish that had been hooked or netted, which, when released,
                                goes back into the rivers and seas. His heaven-endowed spirit was
                                not like that of any ordinary person; the divine appearance of his
                                body was rarely seen in the world. After the bells had been rung
                                repeatedly, starting once again with the title of the sutra, he
                                propagated [the Dharma] for the assembly. At that moment, Daoan was
                                also sitting in the audience.</p><p>At that time, no sooner had
                                Master Yuan begun [the lecture] with the title of the sutra than the
                                earth responded with six types of trembling,<note type="footnote" n="142">The six different types of rumblings and shakings of the
                                    earth are usually closely associated with important events in
                                    the Buddha's life. To link them with Huiyuan is to elevate him
                                    to an extremely high position.</note>and five-colored auspicious
                                clouds spread across the vast skies. Hundreds and thousands of
                                heavenly beings played music together. Innumerable sages and saints
                                made Sanskrit sounds. Crystal-clear were the sounds of the sutra,
                                jingling were the rhymes of the Dharma. All those assembled observed
                                these rarities, and everyone in the audience said that they were
                                exceptional.</p><p>At that time, the Minister was once more<note type="footnote" n="143">Since zài (at) is actually a miswriting
                                    of zuò (do), this clause more accurately may be rendered as "the
                                    Minister sponsored the sermon in the Lotus Palace."</note>at the
                                sermon in the Lotus Palace.<note type="footnote" n="144">Sanskrit
                                    Padmavimāna, the Pure Land of the sambhogakāya (the reward-body
                                    of a Buddha).</note>Once again, he unrolled the mats of
                                    Incense-Land.<note type="footnote" n="145">This land, where the
                                    inhabitants survive on the fragrance of their superlative
                                    incense, is described in the Vimalakīrti-sūtra.</note>He brought
                                together a great assemblage of monks and nuns from the monasteries
                                on the two main streets of the city and held a tonsure
                                    ceremony.<note type="footnote" n="146">Tonsure and ordination
                                    ceremonies were sponsored by the government upon occasions of
                                    celebration.</note>On that day, right there in the Fuguang
                                Monastery, the Minister wrote a memorial concerning these events and
                                presented it to Emperor Wen of the Jin dynasty.</p><p>When the
                                emperor read the memorial, the imperial countenance was greatly
                                delighted. "Excellent! Excellent!" he repeated. "Exceptional!" he
                                exclaimed. He immediately issued an edict which ordered the
                                Secretariat-Chancellery to gather representatives of the Three
                                Doctrines—Buddhism, Daoism, and Confucianism—to go together to
                                Fuguang Monastery and invite Master Yuan to the imperial precincts
                                for veneration. At that time, there was another edict, which ordered
                                the presentation of a scepter, a string of pearls,<note type="footnote" n="147">For use as a rosary.</note>a six-ringed
                                    staff,<note type="footnote" n="148">Sanskrit khakkara.</note>and
                                several sets of monk's robes to Master Yuan. Moreover, a royal
                                carriage was sent to bring Master Yuan to the imperial precincts.
                                When the edict was passed down, it was known by everyone inside and
                                outside the imperial precincts. How stirring it was with all the
                                officials, ministers, and Chief Ministers lined up! [The bearers of]
                                the imperial regalia entered directly into the monastery to request
                                the Great Master to board the carriage.</p><p>At that time, Master
                                Yuan repeatedly declined to board the carriage. "I am an
                                insignificant, common monk," said Master Yuan. "Although I am always
                                grateful for My Lord's request, your subject-monk wishes to return
                                to the mountains. This is what this poor monk wishes."<p>Minister
                                    Cui walked forward and addressed the monk: "I beg for
                                    compassion. Please do not turn down the invitation. The emperor
                                    is eagerly waiting in the imperial precincts especially to see
                                    you. I look up to the honorable person with reverence, first for
                                    the sentient beings of the dharma-world and, secondly, I wish
                                    that you would not turn down the emperor's request."</p>Only
                                after receiving several invitations, Master Yuan began walking. All
                                sorts of entertainers and imperial musicians were in front welcoming
                                him. Clusters of high officials offered congratulations and wished
                                long life to the reigning monarch.</p><p>Master Yuan, after coming
                                out from the gate of the monastery, had walked about a hundred yards
                                or so when he suddenly leaped up into the sky. No one knew where he
                                was. The Minister was fearful and paid his respects. Looking toward
                                the sky, he made the following sincere announcement: "The Great
                                Master has limitless abilities. I wish to beg for compassion and
                                [ask you to] accede to the king's request." He kept going as he made
                                the announcement, winding along the way.</p><p>On that day, Master
                                Yuan had already arrived at the gate of the council chamber before
                                the others and respectfully received the imperial edict. Thereupon,
                                knowing that Master Yuan had arrived, the emperor came out of the
                                palace gate. He paid a thousand regards in reverence and expressed
                                his devotion ten thousand times. As soon as he saw Master Yuan, the
                                imperial countenance showed signs of great pleasure and his
                                happiness was endless.</p><p>And so the emperor said, "It is a great
                                joy to experience the advent of the honorable person in our small
                                kingdom. That the people of the country are at peace and prosperous
                                is all due to the monk."</p><p>The emperor venerated Master Yuan in
                                the imperial precincts for a number of years. He was welcomed with
                                admiration into the six palaces and revered with devotion in the
                                five courtyards. From the monk, the emperor received the Threefold
                                    Refuge<note type="footnote" n="149">In the Buddha, the Dharma,
                                    and the Samgha.</note>and the Five Precepts,<note type="footnote" n="150">Sanskrit pañca veramanī or pañca śīla,
                                    the five prohibitions, precepts, or commandments against
                                    killing, stealing, adultery, lying, and intoxicating
                                    drinks.</note>of which there were none that he did not
                                follow.</p><p>Ever since Master Yuan had been in the imperial
                                precincts, he had observed that in various halls paper with
                                characters on it was often used for unclean purposes in the privy.
                                He scolded the people [who did so] and composed the following
                                gāthā:</p><lg><l>The Confucian child recites the Five Classics;<note type="footnote" n="151">This line is usually considered to
                                        be corrupt and is emended to mean "Confucian doctrine
                                        emphasizes the Five Classics." In fact, it reflects a little
                                        known but very interesting body of Chinese Buddhist lore in
                                        which Confucius is referred to as "the Confucian child," his
                                        favorite disciple Yan Hui is called Guangjing (Pure Light)
                                        Bodhisattva, and Lao Zi is an avatar of Mahākāśypa, the most
                                        senior monk among the Buddha's disciples. The Five Classics
                                        are the Book of Odes, Book of Documents, Book of Rites, Book
                                        of Changes, and Spring and Autumn Annals.</note></l><l>Buddhist doctrine has established the Three Schools;<note type="footnote" n="152">These schools represent the ideas of
                                        emptiness or unreality (the absolute), falseness or
                                        temporary reality (the relative), and neither of the
                                        preceding.</note></l><l>Observe ritual to exercise loyalty and filial piety,</l><l>Employ flogging and banishment to carry out the nine types of
                                        agriculture.<note type="footnote" n="153">This line is
                                        obviously corrupt. An alternative reading of the first part
                                        of the line might be something like "Employ irrigation and
                                        dispersal (?) . . ."</note></l><l>"Tall Willows"<note type="footnote" n="154">This is the
                                        "Changyang fu" (Rhapsody on Changyang Park) by the great Han
                                        writer Yang Xiong (53 b.c.e.—18 c.e.). It is clearly being
                                        cited here to stand for belles lettres in general.</note>and
                                    the fivefold examination essays—</l><l>The characters used to write them are the same as those in the
                                    canonical sutras</l><l>Those who do not understand how to show respect</l><l>Use paper with writing on it for filthy purposes in the
                                    toilet.</l><l>To attain enlightenment, they will have to eliminate sins as
                                    numerous as the sands of the Ganges,</l><l>For which several lifetimes of repentance would not suffice;</l><l>Their bodies will be reduced to a lowly state for five hundred
                                    kalpas,</l><l>And they will often be born as worms in the privy.<note type="footnote" n="155">These verses are also by the Korean
                                        Zen monk Chingak (see note 78).</note></l></lg><p>At that time, because Master Yuan had spoken the gāthā, everyone in
                                the imperial precincts cultivated blessings. Suddenly one day,
                                Master Yuan, recalling the words of Aksobhya-Tathāgata,<note type="footnote" n="156">This is the Buddha of the Eastern
                                    Paradise (Abirata [Delightful]).</note>resigned from the
                                emperor's services and said, "Your subject-monk has received His
                                Majesty's veneration in the imperial precincts for a number of
                                years. Now, I would like to return to Mt. Lu. I beg Your Majesty to
                                issue a decree."<note type="footnote" n="157">The words "issue a
                                    decree" are written at the beginning of the last of the sheets
                                    of paper that are glued together to make up the scroll. The
                                    handwriting before this point, which is in columns of
                                    approximately twenty characters, has grown increasingly hurried,
                                    as though the copyist were rushing to finish the text. With
                                    "issue a decree," however, it is slower and neater, as though
                                    the copyist realized that whatever he was going to write simply
                                    had to be made to fit on this last sheet of paper. Now the
                                    handwriting becomes more deliberate and is in columns of
                                    approximately twenty-four characters. The different appearance
                                    of the handwriting before and after the break, the fact that the
                                    sheets of paper join in such a fashion as to make the columns
                                    line up poorly on either side of the seam, plus the
                                    conspicuously shorter length of the last sheet of paper in
                                    comparison with the previous sheet all led some editors in the
                                    first half of the twentieth century' to mistake the last sheet
                                    as a separate text. It would appear that the copyist was simply
                                    running out of the right size paper (at thirty-four-and-a-half
                                    feet, it is already a very long scroll), grabbed a slightly
                                    longer sheet of paper as a makeshift extender in the penultimate
                                    position, then used the last sheet of paper of the proper length
                                    to complete the scroll—but not the text (see note
                                169).</note></p><p>Upon hearing these words, the emperor's eyes
                                filled with tears. After a long time had passed, he said to the
                                monk, "Our small kingdom has failed to venerate you. When you were
                                in our imperial precincts for several years, we have unintentionally
                                treated you with disrespect. Although we serve as the leader of the
                                people, we are ill qualified for our role as ruler of Heaven and
                                Earth. We appreciate very much that the honorable person has come to
                                this small kingdom. We wish for compassion from the monk, and would
                                request him to stay for three or four more days. Can this be
                                done?"</p><p>Master Yuan said, "According to the teachings of
                                nirvana, there are fundamentally no causes for us to lay hold
                                    of.<note type="footnote" n="158">Sanskrit ārambhana; these are
                                    essentially the presumed bases of sense perceptions.</note>If
                                one supposes that there are causes that we may lay hold of, that is
                                all in the realm of vain thoughts. I request that Your Majesty not
                                feel disappointed that this poor monk has made a vow to return to
                                the mountain."</p><p>The emperor, seeing that Master Yuan's words
                                were firm and knowing that it would be hard to make him stay since
                                his mind was made up, issued an edict promptly to inform [the
                                residents of] the six palaces to line up privately<note type="footnote" n="159">Presumably this was done in secret only
                                    by the top officials and without letting the populace know
                                    because they would most likely have been distraught at the
                                    prospect of Huiyuan's impending departure, and their efforts to
                                    retain him in the capital might have led to
                                disturbances.</note>for a farewell ceremony.<note type="footnote" n="160">This particular ceremony features a sacrifice to the
                                    Spirit of the Roads before someone embarks on a
                                journey.</note>At that time, the emperor was filled with longing,
                                and the Chief Minister was disconsolate. Together with the top
                                officials of the whole kingdom, they bade farewell to Master
                                Yuan.</p><p>Master Yuan started out on his journey, departing
                                through the watchtowers outside the palace gate and taking leave of
                                the imperial dwelling. Heading for Mount Lu, his way was long;
                                gazing at the rivers and lakes, his road was distant. On that day,
                                Master Yuan embarked on his long journey by foot, but he soon
                                secretly manifested his supernatural powers. Once Master Yuan left
                                    Chang'an,<note type="footnote" n="161">The reference here to
                                    Chang'an (capital of the Tang dynasty) shows that we are purely
                                    in the realm of fiction.</note>clouds formed under his feet.
                                Like a strong man flexing his muscles,<note type="footnote" n="162">A cliché for a swift action found in many Buddhist
                                    texts.</note>he arrived at Mt. Lu in a twinkling.</p><p>Master
                                Yuan did not return to the old monastery, but temporarily made
                                himself a thatched hut on a steep ridge about ten tricents<note type="footnote" n="163">Ten tricents would be roughly three and
                                    a third miles (see n. 13).</note>away. In it he sat cross-legged
                                in lotus posture and once more he sought the old scrolls. Again he
                                raised the sounds of the sutra.</p><p>Time slipped by and several
                                more months passed. Suddenly, Master Yuan gazed upon a high plateau
                                and climbed to the top of it. It was a realm of steep peaks where
                                cranes cried and deep ravines where dragons roared. Hundreds of
                                valleys and thousands of peaks were all abloom with flowers. Over
                                the land flowed streams that were always full; in the gardens
                                blossomed flowers that never wither. This was a place where the
                                Tathāgata had cultivated the Way. So Master Yuan sat upright and
                                entered into samādhi.<note type="footnote" n="164">The highest stage
                                    of meditation.</note>Then he purified his thoughts and cleansed
                                his heart, contemplating only the Way of the Buddha. He thought that
                                this ephemeral life could not go on for too long and reflected that
                                the mundane world would not endure. With his self-nature and
                                sovereign-mind, he wanted to make a Dharma-boat in order to return
                                to the upper world. To make the boat, Master Yuan did not use
                                materials of the common world, nor did he need anything else. He
                                only took passionless<note type="footnote" n="165">Sanskrit anāsrava
                                    ("undefiled," literally, "no leak/drip").</note>Mahāyāna for the
                                hawser, bodhi<note type="footnote" n="166">Intelligence.</note>and
                                    prajñā<note type="footnote" n="167">Intuitive wisdom.</note>he
                                used for railings, the esoteric thunderbolt-handed divinities<note type="footnote" n="168">Sanskrit Vajrapāni, protectors of
                                    Buddhism.</note>for. . . ,<note type="footnote" n="169">The text
                                    breaks off in midsentence, even though the paper is not torn.
                                    The copyist merely stopped writing about one-third of the way
                                    from the end of the last sheet that makes up the scroll,
                                    allowing him room for a colophon and extra paper to wrap around
                                    the stick that serves as the end roller. As a matter of fact,
                                    the copyist had actually come very close to the end of the
                                    story, since all that remained to be told (judging from other
                                    medieval renditions) was Huiyuan's getting into the Dharma-boat
                                    and sailing up to Tusita Heaven.</note></p><p>Record of copying
                                by Zhang Changji in the fifth year (972) of the Opened Treasure
                                reign period.<note type="footnote" n="170">The usual interpretation
                                    of the colophon is as given in the translation. Considering all
                                    of the problems with the manner in which the manuscript is
                                    brought to a close (see nn. 157 and 169), it is possible that
                                    the colophon may amount to no more than a statement of
                                    acquisition by Zhang Changji in the year 972.</note></p></q></msItem></msContents></msDescription></body></text></TEI.2>
