<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Tibetan Literary Texts and Documents concerning Chinese Turkestan. Part II:
                    Documents. The Śa-cu Region (pp. 39-113) [JRAS., 1927, pp. 807-844, 1928, pp.
                    63-98]</title><author id="FWT">Thomas, F.W.</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Published for the Royal Asiatic Society By Luzac and Company, LTD.</publisher><pubPlace>46 Great Russell Street, London, W.C.1</pubPlace><date>1951</date></publicationStmt><editionStmt><edition>First edition</edition></editionStmt><sourceDesc><p>Printed book</p><bibl><ref>Thomas_1951</ref></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc>Catalogue</projectDesc></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><head><p>These catalogue entries are taken from F.W. Thomas's Tibetan Literary Texts and Documents, Part II: Documents. They are all from Chapter 2: The Sha-cu region (pp.389-118). The texts are all secular Tibetan documents relating to Shazhou / Dunhuang.</p></head><body><msDescription n="1"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">IOL Tib J 1383</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><note><p>Ch.83.vi.5 (vol. 70, fol. 32: 27 x 7 cm.: ll. 3 of clear, rather small<term lang="tib">dbu can</term>script).</p><p><q lang="tib">[1]...Sha cu Rgya /Stong sar
                  dang/Rgod sar stong sde gnyis kyi //glang gi lo dang/stagi lo'i/Drug chun gy[i]
                  thag//-s [2]...Kwa cur 'dren bar chad nas//blon G.yu bzhre<note type="footnote" n="1">Compendious for<term lang="tib">bzher</term>, as often.</note>gyi stsang
                  /Kwa cu gzhi na mchis pa dang/Sha cu [3]....las//lnga bcu rkang//Khong Sban tse'i
                  tshan/Wang Bun tsong la nas khal gcig/Cang...</q></p><p><q lang="eng">"...Chinese<name lang="tib" type="place">Sha cu</name>, Thousand
                  districts of<name lang="tib" type="place">Stong sar</name>and<name lang="tib" type="place">Rgod sar</name>, Ox year and Tiger year, having been ordered to be
                  conveyed to<name lang="tib" type="place">Kwa cu</name>after being ground by the
                  (?) mills of the<name lang="tib" type="place">Drug chun</name>, from the corn of
                  Councillor<name lang="tib" type="person">G.yu bzher</name>, wich was on the<name lang="tib" type="place">Kwa cu</name>estate, and from...<name lang="tib" type="place">Sha cu</name>, fifty bundles (<term lang="tib">rkang</term>).
                  Account (<term lang="tib">tshan</term>) of<name lang="tib" type="person">Khong
                    Sban tse</name>; to<name lang="tib" type="person">Wang Bun</name>tsong one
                  load of barely; [to]<name lang="tib" type="person">Cang...</name>"</q></p><p>l. 1:<q lang="tib">Rgya</q>, perhaps an error for<term lang="tib">rkya</term>,<q lang="eng">"crop</q>."</p><p>l. 1: on<q lang="tib">stong sde</q><q lang="eng">"district of 1000 (estates ?)"</q>see above, p. 25 sqq. (ITJ 1253)
                and infra, pp. 315 sqq., vol. i,<ref target="Thomas_1935">pp. 282-3</ref>.</p><p><name lang="tib" type="place">Drug chun(g)</name>=<q lang="eng">"Little Dru
                gu"</q>(see pp. 30: M.I.xxviii.001, IOL Tib N 875, pp. 274-6: M.I.iv.57,
                Or.15000/312-316, M.I.iv.81, IOL Tib N 227, M.Tagh.a.vi.0031, IOL Tib N 1782).</p><p>l. 2:<q lang="tib">stsang</q>: see. pp. 17 (Fragment.66, IOL Tib J 897), 19
                (Fragment.67, IOL Tib J 1126), and Index.</p><p>l. 3:<q lang="tib">rkang</q>,<q lang="eng">"bundle"</q>, as in p. 240
                (M.Tagh.a.iii.0063, Or.15000/91); 92.A2 and elsewhere.</p><p><q lang="tib">tshan</q><q lang="eng">"account"</q>: see p. 91 (Ch.73.viii.5, IOL Tib J 1357) below.</p><p>From this fragment it appears likely that the<name lang="tib" type="place">Sha
                cu</name>division consisted mainly of two thousand-districts (<term lang="tib">stong sde</term>),<name lang="tib" type="place">Stong sar</name>and<name lang="tib" type="place">Rgod sar</name>, those, in fact, of which we mostly hear
                elsewhere. But below (p. 45: Ch.79.xvi.7, IOL Tib J 914, p. 58: Ch.82, IOL Tib J
                1018) we have<name lang="tib" type="place">Snying tsoms</name>,<name lang="tib" type="place">Spyi tshogs</name>and<name lang="tib" type="place">Tshas
                stobs</name>.</p><p>The personal names will appear in the consolidated list (infra, pp. 113 sqq.).</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="2"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">IOL Tib J 844</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><note><p>Ch.80.v.1 (734, vol. 53, fol. 39: paper document: 28.5 x 22 cm.: ll. 9 of ordinary
                epistolary<term lang="tib">dbu can</term>script, the last line inverted; complete.
                Five seals, illegible, between end of l. 8 and beginning of l. 9).</p><p><q lang="tib">[1]@/://Rgod sar gyi sde/Cang Ka dzo'i tshan/Cang Kun tses//stsang
                  mngan rnying lo Byi Btsan gyi gnyer [2]rnying gi stsang las gro khal phye dang
                  gnyis dang bre bzhi chags pa las//phagi lo'i stong 'bul [3]bar rtse rjes gnang
                  ste//dkar chag spospa las//phagi lo'i dpyid sla 'bring po'i ngo la'[4]mkhan po
                  Thub brtan la dmag dpon gis stsang zhig gnang ba'i phyag rgya mchis shes
                  mchiste/[5]gnyer pa Dar Rgyal ma dang Tre Mye slebs lastsogs pas bda'ste//gro khal
                  phyed dang gnyis dang[6]bre bzhi lan 'di 'i dpyid sla 'bring po tshes bcu gcig la
                  mngan rnying lo Byi brtsan la phul [7]te/ /Byi brtsan gyi 'bul rgyas btab pa'i
                  dban la//Bam Stag slebs dang/Dze'u Gog tsheng dang/[8]Cang klu legs lastsogs pa'i
                  dpang rgyas btab pa'//</q>(several seals, illegible). Inverted<q lang="tib">[9]bkye gnyer khums ste chags rgya shad kyis gnan</q></p><p>(ll. 1-3):<q lang="eng">"<name lang="tib" type="place">Rgod sar</name>division.
                  Account of<name lang="tib" type="person">Cang Ka dzo</name>.<name lang="tib" type="person">Cang Kun tse</name>, agent to<name lang="tib" type="person">Byi
                    btsan</name>, the corn official of the old year at wheat two less a half loads
                  and four<term lang="tib">bre</term>, the orders of the chief (<term lang="tib">rtse rje</term>) were that it should be delivered in the autumn of the Hog
                  year. (ll. 3-5) There was a change in the lists, and in the middle spring month of
                  the Hog year there came a letter stating that some corn had been granted by the
                  General to the<name lang="tib" type="person">Thub brtan</name>abbot. Thereupon
                  the superintendents (<term lang="tib">gnyer pa</term>'the persons in charge'),<name lang="tib" type="person">Dar Rgyal ma</name>and<name lang="tib" type="person">Tre Mye slebs</name>and the others, made the levy. (ll. 5-7) Two
                  less a half loads and four<term lang="tib">bre</term>of wheat were delivered to<name lang="tib" type="person">Byi brtsan</name>, the corn official for the old
                  year, on the eleventh day of the middle spring month of the present year. (ll.
                  7-8) In witness of<name lang="tib" type="person">Byi brtsan</name>'s receipt seal
                  having been given the attestation seals of<name lang="tib" type="person">Bam Stag
                    slebs</name>,<name lang="tib" type="person">Dze'u Gog tsheng</name>,<name lang="tib" type="person">Cang Klu legs</name>and so forth are (here)
                given."</q>(Several seal impressions illegible)</p><p>(Endorsement, inverted):<q lang="eng">"The despatch has been carried out. The
                  amount is impressed by marks (<term lang="tib">shad kyis gnan</term>)."</q></p><p>l.1:<q lang="tib">tshan</q>: see p. 91 (Ch.73.viii.5, IOL Tib J 1357) below.</p><p>Concerning<q lang="tib">stsang</q>=<q lang="eng">"corn"</q>,<q lang="tib">mngan</q>=<q lang="eng">"government"</q>,<q lang="eng">"authority"</q>, see pp.
                19 (Fragment.67, IOL Tib J 1126), 341 (Ch.86.ii, IOL Tib J 848).</p><p><q lang="tib">gnyer</q><q lang="eng">"to be in charge of"</q>,<q lang="eng">"to be placed in charge
                of"</q>, and<q lang="tib">gnyer 'gum</q>(<term lang="tib">bkum</term>,<term lang="tib">khums</term>)<q lang="eng">"to carry out a charge"</q>are among the
                most common expressions in these Tibetan documents, whether on paper or on wood. For
                examples see the next documents and pp. 19 (Fragment.67, IOL Tib J 1126), 79 (IOL
                Tib J 1254), 358: 40 (M.I.xiv.0016, IOL Tib N 552). etc.</p><p>l. 2:<q lang="tib">khal</q><q lang="eng">"load"</q>is no doubt technical = Sanskrit<term lang="san">vāha</term>.</p><p>l. 4: We understand<q lang="eng">"the<name lang="tib" type="person">Thub
                  brtan</name>abbot"</q>to be connected with the previously mentioned<name lang="tib" type="person">Byi brtsan</name>.</p><p>As regards the intervention of "the General" (<q lang="tib">dmag dpon</q>), cf. the
                document given above (pp. 19-20).</p><p>l. 6:<q lang="tib">lan</q>=<q lang="eng">"year"</q>, as often (e.g. p. 75.B 7:
                IOL Tib J 1254, p. 137. 1: M.I.xiv.109.b, Or.15000/426 ?).</p><p>l. 9: In (conjecturally) interpreting<q lang="tib">chags</q>as<q lang="eng">"measure"</q>or<q lang="eng">"weight"</q>and<q lang="tib">chags rgya</q>(in
                the addendum) as<q lang="eng">"record of measure or weight"</q>we may appeal to
                the expression<term lang="tib">chag khongs</term><q lang="eng">"basket for measuring grain"</q>,<term lang="tib">chag tshad</term><q lang="eng">"correct measure"</q>,<term lang="tib">tshags</term><q lang="eng">"a sieve"</q>,<term lang="tib">tshags bu</term><q lang="eng">"a bag attached to a sieve"</q>,<term lang="tib">tshags dam po</term><q lang="eng">"strict care"</q>,<term lang="tib">tshags tshad</term><q lang="eng">"to test properly"</q>. The word<q lang="tib">shad</q>usually
                denotes the vertical line used in punctuation: and, in fact, some of the documents
                seem to show lines of such a kind appended to signify numbers. In this connexion the
                word<q lang="tib">gnan</q>, which should mean<q lang="eng">"pressed"</q>, may
                possibly denote<q lang="eng">"confirmed"</q>or<q lang="eng">"reinforced"</q>: or
                were the signs actually<q lang="eng">"impressed"</q>upon the measures or bundles
                or parcels? As regards the persons, see the consolidated list (pp. 113 sqq.).</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="3"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">IOL Tib J 1379</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><note><p>Ch.77.xv.10 (733, vol. 70, fol. 27: 26.5 x 11 cm.; fragmentary at top left; ll. 7
                of ordinary epistolary<term lang="tib">dbu can</term>script + ll. 2 inverted + l.
                1 on verso; four or more red impressions of seals, illegible).</p><p><q lang="tib">[1]...stsang //mngan rnying lo Byis brtsan gyi sug pa na /[2]...dkar
                  chag spos pa las //slad kyis dmag pno<note type="footnote" n="1">Compendious for<term lang="tib">pon</term>.</note>[3]thub brtan gyi nod du kha bstan no zhes
                  mchi' nas //[4]...u...Kh[o]ng M[a]ng tse la gro khal phyed dang gnyis dang<note type="footnote" n="2">This syllable is erased.</note>lo 'di'i dpyid[5]sla
                    ngo<note type="footnote" n="3">This syllable is erased.</note>'bring po'i ngo
                  la mngan lo Byis brtsan la phul te /bul rgya dang/Tre Mye slebs dang/Bam [6]Log
                  log/Cang Tshe shing //lastsogs pa'i dpang rgyas btab pa'//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[8]bkye gnyer khums nas chags rgya dang gthugste shad kyis gnan</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[9]bkye gnyer bkum nas chags rgya shad kyis gnan</q></p><p>Rev.:<q lang="tib">Khong Man tse'i bul</q></p><p><q lang="eng">"[ll.1-3]...being in the hand (at the disposal?) of<name lang="tib" type="person">Byis brtsan</name>, corn official for the old year, subsequently,
                  the list having been changed, word came that the General had promised its delivery
                  to<name lang="tib" type="person">Thub brtan</name>[ll. 4-6] ...to<name lang="tib" type="person">Khong Man tse</name>two less a half loads of wheat,
                  and on the first of the middle spring month of this year it has been delivered to
                  the year official,<name lang="tib" type="person">Byis brtsan</name>. A receipt
                  and the witness-seals of<name lang="tib" type="person">Tre Mye slebs</name>and<name lang="tib" type="person">Bam Log log</name>and<name lang="tib" type="person">Cang Tshe shing</name>and others are attached. [ll. 6-7] An
                  additional six<term lang="tib">bre</term>of wheat having been delivered, seals
                  are attached."</q></p><p>Endorsements</p><p><q lang="eng">"[l.8] Despatch carried out; amount, compared with signature,
                  impressed with marks.</q></p><p><q lang="eng">[l. 9] Despatch carried out, amount impressed with marks.</q></p><p>Rev.:<q lang="eng">Receipt of<name lang="tib" type="person">Khong Man
                  tse</name>."</q></p><p>The subject being similar to that of No. 2, and the persons partly the same, little
                comment is needed.</p><p>l. 4: The completion of the proper name is obvious from the receipt (verso).</p><p>l. 8:<q lang="tib">gthugs</q>seems to belong to<term lang="tib">gtug pa</term>,<term lang="tib">thug pa</term>,<q lang="eng">"reach"</q>,<q lang="eng">"agree"</q>, and to mean<q lang="eng">"having compared"</q>; cf.<term lang="tib">thug chad</term>,<q lang="eng">"agreement"</q>, and<term lang="tib">de dang
                  gtugs ching</term>, p. 74.16 (IOL Tib J 1254).</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="4"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">IOL Tib J 914</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><note><p>Ch.79.xvi.7 (732, vol. 54, fol. 42; 27.5 x 13.5 cm.; paper document, complete; ll.
                7 of scrawled epistolary hand, the last line inverted; one red seal impression).</p><p><q lang="tib">[1]@/:/Spyi tshogs gyi stsang mngan rnying lo Byis brtsan gyi sug pa
                  na mcis pa las//Li [2]Kang tses gro khal phye dang gnyis dang bre bzhi zhig snga
                  g.yar du mnos pa//phag gi lo'i dpyid [3]zla 'bring po tshes bcu gsum la/ban de
                  Thub brtan gyi nod du kha bstan pa'i tshe/Byis [4]brtsan la phul te//bul rgya dang
                  gnyer pa/Tre Mye slebs dang/Khyung po Stag [5]legs las stsogs pa'i dpang rgyas
                  btab pA//dkar chag pyi mo bla na mchis pa ni slad gyis shad gyis gnan [6]par
                  bgyis//</q></p><p>(After end of l. 6, read seal) l. 1:<q lang="tib">'Byis brtsan</q>l. 2
                (illegible).</p><p><q lang="tib">[7]bkye gnyer khum ste chags rgya shad kyis gnan</q></p><p><q lang="eng">"[ll.1-4] Being in the hand (at the disposal) of<name lang="tib" type="person">Byis brtsan</name>, the corn official of<name lang="tib">Spyi
                    tshogs</name>for the old year, two less a half loads and some four<term lang="tib">bre</term>of wheat having been previously (<term lang="tib">snga</term>?) received on loan (<term lang="tib">g.yar du</term>) by<name lang="tib" type="person">Li Kang tse</name>, on the thirteenth day of the middle
                  spring month of the Hog year, at the time when its receipt was promised to the<term lang="tib">ban de</term><name lang="tib" type="person">Thub brtan</name>, it was delivered to<name lang="tib" type="person">Byis brtsan</name>. [ll. 4-6] Receipt and seals of
                  superintendents<name lang="tib" type="person">Tre Mye slebs</name>and<name lang="tib" type="person">Khyung po Stag legs</name>and the others attached. A
                  later list having come already (<term lang="tib">bla na</term>?), afterwards an
                  impression with marks was made."</q></p><p>(Seal (?) and signature of)<name lang="tib" type="person">'Byis brtsan</name>.</p><p>(Endorsement)<q lang="eng">"[l. 7] Despatch carried out, amount impressed with
                  marks."</q></p><p>Subject and persons for the most part as in Nos. 2 and 3.</p><p><name lang="tib">Spyi tshogs</name>is not known, unless it is the<name lang="tib">Spyil cog</name>of a Bstan 'gyur colophon (<ref target="Cordier_1909_1915">I, p.
                  33</ref>), which is not very unlikely, as the person there mentioned is a<term lang="tib">Thod gar</term>.</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="5"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">IOL Tib J 850</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><note><p>Back of Ch.86.ii (vol. 53, fol. 50; 27.5 x 18.5 cm.; ll. 12 of ordinary epistolary<term lang="tib">dbu can</term>script, for the most part legible).</p><p><q lang="tib">[1]@//:/bya gagi lo'i dpyid//Rgod gyi [L]eng h[o] Ling lugi mchis
                  brang Song Sam nyan gyis//Leng ho Shib [2]tigi bran mo/Be'u zhan la brel te/rjes
                  phor pa bzhi dang deb tse gs[u]m dang /ras kyi rgyu bkal lags[3]pha rkya ma
                    phyid<note type="footnote" n="1">For<term lang="tib">phyed</term>.<q lang="tib">d</q>erased</note>de rnams/Shib bir la<note type="footnote" n="2">Below line.</note>chags te//slad 'phul ba'i [d]us ni//khyi'i lo'i dphyid sla
                  tha chungs [4]tshes lnga tshun cu<note type="footnote" n="3">Erased. Read<term lang="tib">cad</term>.</note>la//Le[ng ho] Shib bir gyi sgor 'bul bra<note type="footnote" n="4">Compendious for<term lang="tib">bar</term>.</note>bgy[i]s//dus dir ma 'p[h]ul:gchig [5]las g[nyi]su bsgyur de //khong ta'i sgor nas
                  saM zang spyad 'aM phor pa yang rngung(rung) ste/dphrogs kyang [6][zhal] chu ma
                  mchis par bgyis//yang ras chag phyed dang bzhi dang /nas rgya bre bzhi ni/sgo
                  lcags [7]lde myig dang [bca]s pa gta' g.gs nas//khyi'i lo'i dpyid sla 'bring po
                  tshes bcu tshun [8]cad slad blus par bgyis dusu ma blus na/sgo lcags g.[khyogi]
                  rgyu(?) yang yal bar bgyis[9]pa'i dpang la//Cang Gu gu dang/La Legs lod dang/Khe'u
                  Bzang gong dang/[10]...lastsogs pa'i dpang rgya dang //Song -i -ng dang//mo'i khyo
                  Ling lug kyi su[g] yig tshad dang/Sam nyang gyi mdzub tshad btabpa'</q></p><p>(Inverted)</p><p><q lang="tib">[1]khyo L[e]ng [ho] Ling lugi sug[2][yig] tshad/</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[1]Khe'u Bzang gong gyi sug [2]yig tshad//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[1]Song SaM/nyang /gi mdzub [2]mo tshad</q></p><p><q lang="eng">"[ll.1-4] Spring of the Bird year: the wife of<name lang="tib" type="person">Leng ho Ling lug</name>of<name lang="tib" type="place">Rgod</name>,<name lang="tib" type="person">Song Sam nyang</name>, in employment
                  with<name lang="tib" type="person">Be'u zhan</name>, female servant of<name lang="tib" type="person">Leng ho Shib tig</name>, having exchanged four cups,
                  three register baskets (<term lang="tib">deb tse</term>?) and woven (<term lang="tib">spun</term>) cotton material, half a<term lang="tib">rkya ma</term>,
                  these belonging to<name lang="tib" type="person">Shib bir</name>, are to be given
                  back by the fifth day of the last spring month of the Dog-year [ll.4-6] at the
                  door of<name lang="tib" type="person">Leng ho Shib bir</name>. If not delivered
                  at the time, one is to become two. Also whatever barely or copper-utensils or cups
                  are in her possession are to be taken without protest. [ll.6-10] As furthermore
                  four less a half weights of cotton and four<term lang="tib">bre</term>of Chinese
                  barely, together with the key of the door-bolt, were obtained in pledge, to be
                  redeemed by the tenth day of the middle spring month of the Dog-year, if these are
                  not redeemed in time, the iron (<term lang="tib">rgyu</term>?) of the door-bolt
                  also is to be exacted; in attestation whereof the witness seals of<name lang="tib" type="person">Cang Gu gu</name>,<name lang="tib" type="person">La
                    Legs lod</name>,<name lang="tib" type="person">Khe'u Bzang gong</name>, and ...
                  and the rest, and the written signature of the women's husband,<name lang="tib" type="person">(Leng ho) Ling lug</name>, and the finger size-mark of<name lang="tib" type="person">Sam nyang</name>are attached."</q></p><p>(Endorsement)</p><p><q lang="eng">"[1] Hand of the husband,<name lang="tib" type="person">Leng ho Ling
                    lug</name>. Hand of<name lang="tib" type="person">Khe'u Bzang gong</name>[2]
                  in writing. Finger-size-mark of<name lang="tib" type="person">Song Sam
                  nyang</name>."</q></p><p>It will be seen that<name lang="tib" type="person">Leng ho Ling lug</name>, whose
                surname, recurrent at<name lang="tib" type="place">Sha cu</name>(see p. 115), is
                possibly identical with<name lang="tib" type="person">Ling hu</name>known from
                Chinese sources (<ref target="Chavannes_1913">Index</ref>), is described as<q lang="eng">"of<name lang="tib" type="place">Rgod</name>"</q>. This is, however,
                hardly sufficient to prove that the<name lang="tib" type="place">Sha cu</name>itself was in the<name lang="tib" type="place">Rgod division</name>.</p><p>Concerning the names (e.g.<name lang="tib" type="person">Shib tig</name>=<q lang="eng">"Ten beauty"</q>,<term lang="san">daśa-śrī</term>), see pp. 71-3
                (Ch.75.iii.3, IOL Tib J 1240) and the list, infra, pp. 113 sqq.</p><p><q lang="tib">Deb tse</q>(l. 2) seems to occur in a Bstan 'gyur colophon (<ref target="Cordier_1909_1915">II, p. 328</ref>);<q lang="tib">sug yig tshad</q>in
                p. 143 (M.I.xiv.109.a, Or.15000/426), etc.</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="6"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">IOL Tib J 1459</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><note><p>Fr. 80 (730, vol. lxxiii, fol. 37, imperfect at the right; 15.5 x 16 cm.; ll.11 of
                clear, rather small, regular<term lang="tib">dbu can</term>script).</p><p><q lang="tib">[1]@/:/Pho brang 'On cang<note type="footnote" n="1">Inverted below
                    line.</note>do nas bkye'i phyag rgya phog ste//zha sngar snyan du/...[2]pos
                  (mos, sos, los?) /Sha cu'i skun kar 'bangs dang bchas su phyag du bzhes
                  te//...[3]chab srid la bsdos te/ /Bod 'bangs kyi mchog bkum gyis shing
                  //thugs....[4]pag[mag?] To dog rtse rjer bskos the dgung lo bdun lags na yang
                  //Sha [cu?]...[5]bkum nas//slad gyis khrom gyis mdab non pas lhog pa'i
                  [rno?]...[6]bdag spus bthus te rtse rjer stsald nas//dgung lo bchu...[7]nang krug
                  dang pan pun du ma gyurd pha lags//rje blas [kyang stsang]...[8]pa yang myi chad
                  phar 'bul zhing blar yang sman yon thogs pa bdag [glo]...[9]snas myi dbul bra
                  phyag rgya 'ga' zhig chi gnang zhes gsol...[10]dbul bar gnang zhes//Bka'/blon
                  Btshan bzher dang blon [ny]...[11]phyag rgya 'chang du stsald pha://</q></p><p><q lang="eng">"[l. 1] From the palace<name lang="tib" type="place">'On cang
                  do</name>sent, seal attached, for hearing in the presence.</q></p><p><q lang="eng">'The<term lang="tib">Btsan (?) po</term>having taken possession of
                  the fort of<name lang="tib" type="place">Sha cu</name>along with the subjects,
                  the Chinese(?), in rivalry for domination, having killed the best of the Tibetan
                  subjects, appointed...as<term lang="tib">To dog</term>chief ruler. [ll. 4-6]
                  Seven years having passed...killed. Afterwards the city, according merit to
                  me...when I had been able to recover it by great efforts(?), sent me as chief
                  ruler. [ll. 6-8] Ten years...there has been no internal strife and disagreement.
                  To His Excellency also corn...has been delivered without intermission (or order),
                  a highly beneficial gift. [ll. 8-11] Please send signature that...is not to be
                  delivered' – upon this petition...to be delivered is sanctioned, - to this effect<term lang="tib">Bka'</term>Councillor<name lang="tib" type="person">Btshan
                    bzher</name>and Councillor...sent, bearing a signature."</q></p><p>This document refers apparently to a capture of<name lang="tib" type="place">Sha
                  cu</name>by the Tibetans, a subsequent revolt, instigated, no doubt, by the
                Chinese, and the recovery of the palace and its retention during a peaceful period
                of ten years. The event may be that related from Chinese sources by Bushell in<ref target="Bushell_1880">p. 514</ref>. The writers reside in the palace<name lang="tib" type="place">'On cang do</name>, which therefore must have been
                situated not too far from<name lang="tib" type="place">Sha cu</name>. From a
                colophon in the Bstan 'gyur (<ref target="Cordier_1909_1915">II, p. 478</ref>),
                again, we know that<name lang="tib" type="place">'On cang do</name>was in<name lang="tib" type="place">Skyi</name>, a district several times mentioned in the
                Chronicle, ll. 81, 88, 110, 115, to which further we may assign the following places
                (the authority is added in brackets): -</p><p><name lang="tib" type="place">Bra ma thang</name>(Chronicle, ll. 4 and 56).</p><p><name lang="tib" type="place">Byar lings tshal</name>(ibid., ll. 96, 197, 251).</p><p><name lang="tib" type="place">Dra tshal</name>(ibid., 133, and therefore also<name lang="tib" type="place">Dra'i Gro pur</name>, of<name lang="tib" type="place">Dra</name>, ibid., ll. 66, 154,<name lang="tib" type="place">Dra 'i
                  Zar phur</name>, l. 157).</p><p><name lang="tib" type="place">Gling rings tshal</name>(ibid., ll. 59, 101, and
                M.I.viii.46 (IOL Tib N 420), M.Tāgh.iii.0016).<name lang="tib" type="place">Phyi
                  tshal</name>(Brit. Mus. MS. Or. 8212/187, l. 19).</p><p><name lang="tib" type="place">Lhas gang tshal</name>(ibid., ll. 110, 115, 119,
                125, 182, 193, 210).</p><p><name lang="tib" type="place">Rtse gro</name>in<name lang="tib" type="place">Dra</name>(Brit. Mus. MS., l. 10).</p><p><name lang="tib" type="place">Sho ma ra</name>(ibid., ll. 201, 207, 245).</p><p><name lang="tib" type="place">Zar phur</name>(ibid., l. 157,<name lang="tib" type="place">Dra 'i Zar phur</name>).</p><p>It seems possible that<name lang="tib" type="place">'On cang do</name>, which
                itself is mentioned in the Chronicle (ll. 81, 88, 111, 115, 120), may mean<q lang="eng">"'On city-land"</q>, the<q lang="tib">'On</q>being a people known
                from Buddhist literature and from the Chronicle (ll. 12, 52, 73).</p><p>l. 3.<q lang="tib">chab srid la bsdos te</q>: For the phrase see Index.</p><p>l. 4.<q lang="tib">To dog</q>= Chin.<term lang="chi">tu tu</term>, Turk.<term lang="tur">tu tuq</term>, recurs p. 81.</p><p>l. 5.<q lang="tib">mdab non pas</q><q lang="eng">"by a great effort (or strong rally)"</q>(?).</p><p><q lang="tib">spus bthus</q>: The phrase has been found above, p. 23.31.</p><p>l. 7.<q lang="tib">nang krug ('khrug)</q><q lang="eng">"internal strife"</q>.</p><p><q lang="tib">pan pun</q><q lang="eng">"dissension"</q>=<term lang="tib">phan phun</term>; cf.
                M.Tāgh.a.vi.0065 (Or.15000/163),<term lang="tib">phan phun zhig du gyur na</term>.</p><p>l. 8.<q lang="tib">blar</q><q lang="eng">"highly"</q>: cf. p. 23, l. 16 (IOL Tib J 1253) and Index.</p><p><q lang="tib">sman yon</q><q lang="eng">"beneficial gift"</q>occurs also Vol. I,<ref target="Thomas_1935">p.
                  29, n. 1</ref>.</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="7"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">IOL Tib J 134</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><note><p>Ch.73.iv.14 (125, vol. 68, fol. 29, paper; c. 25 x 8.5 cm.; now attached to a
                literary MS., wherewith it has no connexion; ll. 5 of ordinary<term lang="tib">dbu
                  can</term>script).</p><p><q lang="tib">[1]/Bog yas//khrom ched po'i 'dun tsa//Leng cu nas//rta'i lo'i dbyar
                  sla 'bring po'i...[2]-gs kyi phyag rgya phogste//Sha cu dang //Kwa cu'i tshi shi
                  la mchid stsal pa//Phag Stag l...[3]gsol na//na ning khrom chen pos//chab sr[i]d
                  Dang to kun du mdzad nas//slar gshegs...[4]shul du//dor po pe'u gcig//Gir kis gyis
                  btabste//sgyes pa pho gza' ni bkum/...[5]pa nangs su 'tshal pa 'i nang nas//S[u]g
                  cur Gnyo za Dge ldem zhes mchi' ba /</q></p><p><q lang="eng">"[ll. 1-2] From<name lang="tib" type="place">Leng cu</name>(<name lang="chi" type="place">Liang-chou</name>), assemblage of the great city of<name lang="tib" type="place">Bog yas</name>, letter sent, with seal
                  of...attached, on the...of the mid-summer month of the Horse-year, to the<term lang="tib">tshi-shi</term>of<name lang="tib" type="place">Sha cu</name>and<name lang="tib" type="place">Kwa cu</name>. Petition of<name lang="tib" type="person">Phag Stag l...</name></q></p><p><q lang="eng">[ll. 3-4] The city chief(?) having last year been carrying on the
                  government in<name lang="tib" type="place">Dang to kun</name>, on the way back a<term lang="tib">pe'u</term>of teamsmen was attacked by Kirghiz.</q></p><p><q lang="eng">[ll. 4-5] The<term lang="tib">sgyes pa</term>s, men and wives, were
                  killed. From among those who sought to escape one<name lang="tib" type="person">Dge ldem</name>, a<name lang="tib">Gnyo za</name>, is going to<name lang="tib" type="place">S-g cur</name>..."</q></p><p>l. 1: Since the document seems to begin here,<name lang="tib" type="place">Bog
                yas</name>must be the name of the great city (or is<name lang="tib" type="place">Leng cu</name>the city of<name lang="tib" type="place">Bog yas</name>?); and
                since<term lang="tib">Bog</term>is a tribal designation, and we have elsewhere (p.
                294: M.Tagh.0291, IOL Tib N 1240, p. 407: M.I.i.25.a, Or.15000/269) a reference to a<name lang="tib" type="place">Bog yul</name><q lang="eng">"Bog</q>district" (or read<term lang="tib">Bod</term>?), it seems
                that we must recognize a district of this name somewhere in the region of<name lang="tib" type="place">Leng cu</name>.</p><p><q lang="tib">khrom ched po</q>should mean<q lang="eng">"great city"</q>; but
                below (l. 3)<q lang="tib">khrom chen po</q>, the alternative spelling, seems to
                mean either<q lang="eng">"the [chief of] the great city"</q>or<q lang="eng">"the
                  great man (chief) of the city"</q>. Cf. p. 145: 41.1 (M.I.xliv.0013,
                Or.15000/536).</p><p>l. 2:<q lang="tib">tshi shi</q>. Is this the<term lang="tib">ts'e che</term><q lang="eng">"prefect"</q>of<ref target="Chavannes_1913">pp. 60, 72</ref>, =
                Uigur<term lang="uig">cigsi</term>(Pelliot).</p><p>l. 3:<name lang="tib" type="place">Dang to kun</name>is certainly a place; see
                the next document and p. 316.</p><p>l. 4:<q lang="tib">dor po pe'u</q>: A<term lang="tib">dor po</term>is, no doubt,
                a person in charge of a<term lang="tib">dor</term><q lang="eng">"yoke of oxen (or yaks)"</q>.<q lang="tib">Pe'u</q>is unknown so
                far, except as = Chinese<term lang="chi">pao</term><q lang="eng">"a gem"</q>and in names,<name lang="tib" type="person">Pe'u tse</name>, etc.</p><p><q lang="tib">Gir kis</q>: a mention of Kirghiz has been previously cited (<ref target="Thomas_1927a">p. 282</ref>).</p><p><q lang="tib">Sgyes pa</q>, perhaps =<term lang="tib">sgye'u ga</term><q lang="eng">"bagman"</q>.<q lang="tib">Nangs</q>occurs M.I.viii.3 (IOL Tib N
                377),<q lang="tib">thabs ma nongs par zind</q>, p. 158 (M.I.viii.43, IOL Tib N
                417), q.v.</p><p><name lang="tib" type="place">S-g cur</name>may be the<name lang="tib" type="place">Sug</name><q lang="eng">"province"</q>(if<q lang="tib">cur</q>=<term lang="tib">cor</term>,<term lang="tib">chor</term>, Turkī<term lang="tur">cur</term>, noted
                supra, pp. 8 and<ref target="Thomas_1927a">p. 283</ref>).</p><p><name lang="tib">Gnyo za</name>is a man of the<name lang="tib">Gnyo</name>tribe
                or clan (see consolidated list, infra, and cf.<q lang="tib">Gnyos Ho se</q>in
                M.I.xliv.7 (Or.15000/530)).</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="8"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">IOL Tib J 896</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><note><p>Ch.fr.61 (747, vol. 54, fol. 17, paper; c. 26.5 x 17.5 cm.; ll. 12 of a rather
                peculiar, clumsy<term lang="tib">dbu can</term>script, with short lines (<term lang="tib">shad</term>), more often than, but sometimes hardly distinguishable
                from, points, separating the syllables).</p><p><q lang="tib">[1]@//Dang to/ kun/du/Khri/sgra'/dang Khyung kong dang Bzang kong
                  gsum/gyis/bran/bgos/[2]te/bran/so/sor/thob/pa'i/mying rus/spi las dang khrald
                  ji/lta[3]r/bya ba'i:spyi yi/ger/bris
                  pa........................................................</q></p><p><q lang="eng">"[ll. 1-3] In<name lang="tib" type="place">Dang to kun</name>the
                  three [persons],<name lang="tib" type="person">Khri sgra'</name>,<name lang="tib" type="person">Khyung kong</name>and<name lang="tib" type="person">Bzang kong</name>, having apportioned servants, the names and families of the
                  servants acquired by them severally [are set down] in common (<term lang="tib">spyi las</term>), and how they are to be taxed (or punished or forced to
                  labour,<term lang="tib">khrald</term>?) is inscribed in a common
                  document.............................................."</q></p><p>This document being cited only in order to verify the place-name<name lang="tib" type="place">Dang to kun</name>, elicited supra (p. 49: Ch.73.iv.14, IOL Tib J
                134), and presenting difficulties owing to uncertainty regarding the numerous proper
                names, the reminder may be reserved for a subsequent treatment. In l. 9 there is
                mention of a<name lang="tib">'A zha</name>named<name lang="tib" type="person">Zhag ldom</name>.</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="9"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">Or.15000/496</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><note><p>M.I.xxviii.0036 (fol. 75; paper, c. 25 x 8 cm., with a horseman seal impression at
                top left; ll. 8 of clear, regular<term lang="tib">dbu can</term>script).</p><p><q lang="tib">[1]@//blon Mtsho bzher dang blon Lha bzher lastsogs pas//dgun sla tha
                  cungs tshes...[2]phyag rgya phog ste//pho nya Ring lugs ltang sogs 'Dong phreng
                  'Dor dgu dang ngo mkhan[3]spyugs myi sde Tsog stod gyi sde Mog Kyem po(?) dang
                  Nyan rmai'i sde Bong La ku gnyis/Tshal byi'i Nob chungu...[4]gar slebs slebs su
                  snyegs shing/Kwa cu Khar tsan yang chad du mchiste/'tshal ba g.yar...[5]tshal ma
                  thang mnyam ste/'Brog Slungs la bya na gson lod spel ma'i bka' rims phye
                  phul...[6]rims phye khor bzhi'i thang /rad pa srang [b]rgyad brgya ni skyel ma'i
                  ste len du 'gel to/pho nya gzhan dang 'grogs m--e...[7]rings pa zla la khrid du
                  myi gang//myi bros ste snye[g] zhing mchi ba la://Slungs dang so pa ma mchis
                  te/bab no...[8]so pa gang nas gya ba nas/lam tshor ldangs...[g]chi[g] dang...</q></p><p><q lang="eng">"[ll. 1-2] By Councillor<name lang="tib" type="person">Mtso
                  bzher</name>and Councillor<name lang="tib" type="person">Lha bzher</name>, on
                  the ... day of the last winter month,...seal attached. [ll. 2-4] Messenger<name lang="tib" type="person">Ring lugs</name>(courier), porter<name lang="tib" type="person">'Dong phreng</name>and<name lang="tib" type="person">'Dor
                  dgu</name>(or is<term lang="tib">'dor dgu</term>=<term lang="tib">dor dgu</term><q lang="eng">"nine yoke of oxen or yaks"</q>?), and guide...must follow a company
                  of banished men,<name lang="tib" type="person">Mog Kyem po</name>of the Upper<name lang="tib" type="place">Tsog</name>district and<name lang="tib" type="person">Bong La ku</name>of the<name lang="tib" type="place">Nyan
                  rna</name>district, these two, wherever from Little<name lang="tib" type="place">Nob</name>in<name lang="tib" type="place">Tshal byi</name>they go and go.
                  [ll. 4-6] Proceeding as far as<name lang="tib" type="place">Khar tsan</name>of<name lang="tib" type="place">Kwa cu</name>, their food, while in the upper
                  country (<term lang="tib">g.yar</term>)...rations at a level rate. If the business
                  takes them to<name lang="tib" type="place">'Brog Slungs</name>(the nomad<name lang="tib" type="place">Slungs</name>), increase of maintenance
                  circular-order-flour allowance(?), handfuls...circular-order-flour at the rate of
                  four<term lang="tib">khor</term>. [ll. 6-7] The company being for conveyance of
                  800<term lang="tib">srang</term>weight, to obtain that [they have] orders.
                  Consorting with other messengers...and taking<term lang="tib">rings pa</term>into friendship is not allowed. [l. 7] If the men run away and, while they are
                  going in pursuit,<name lang="tib" type="place">Slungs</name>and soldiers have
                  not come, stage...having signalled (? read<term lang="tib">g.yab</term>?)
                  soldiers from anywhere, sufficient for a road company(?)..."</q></p><p>It will be seen that the translation of this interesting, but unfortunately
                imperfect, document becomes in the latter part very doubtful and in fact
                conjectural. But the general sense is clear, and the geographical information is
                valuable. The route laid down is from Little<name lang="tib" type="place">Nob</name>(Mīrān) to<name lang="tib" type="place">Kwa cu</name>(An-hsi); and it
                is evidently contemplated that it should be the direct mountain route and not follow
                the desert edge via<name lang="chi" type="place">Shan-shan</name>. The document
                supplies two important facts, namely the first that, as has been intimated above (p.
                31), and will be more abundantly shown later, the<name lang="tib" type="place">Tsal
                  byi</name>command included Mīrān, and secondly, that the town of<name lang="tib" type="place">Khar tsan</name>(for this is clearly the name to be completed in the
                lacuna) was attached to An-hsi. As regards the other places mentioned, the Upper<name lang="tib" type="place">Tsog</name>district (<term lang="tib">sde</term>)
                mentioned, the<name lang="tib" type="place">Nyan rna</name>district and<name lang="tib" type="place">'Brog Slungs</name>(the Nomad<name lang="tib" type="place">Slungs</name>),<name lang="tib" type="place">Tsog</name>has been
                mentioned above (p. 11), and with<name lang="tib" type="place">'Brog Slungs</name>we may compare the<name lang="tib" type="place">Rgya Slungs</name>, Chinese<name lang="tib" type="place">Slungs</name>, of M.Tagh.c.iii.0043 (IOL Tib N 2285) (pp.
                  276-7)<note type="footnote" n="1">Other references for<name lang="tib" type="place">Slungs</name>are p. 296:23 (M.Tagh.a.iv.0092, IOL Tib N 1708) (a
                  person's 'card' of wood<q lang="tib">Rgya Slungs 'Bog lang</q>), p. 296:24
                  (M.Tagh.a.vi.003, IOL Tib N 1755), p. 431:1 (M.Tagh.c.iii.0022, IOL Tib N 2088)
                    (<q lang="tib">byang Slungs</q>), p. 64:11J (IOL Tib N 692) (<name lang="tib" type="place">Slungs</name>in connection with<name lang="tib" type="place">Snying tsoms</name>), M.I.xliii.002 (IOL Tib N 1048) (<name lang="tib" type="place">Slungs</name>), Chronicle, l. 169 (<q lang="tib">Slungs stod
                  smad</q>): see pp. 296-7 (M.I.xv.0020, IOL Tib N 749).</note>: perhaps the word is
                connected with Tibetan<term lang="tib">lung</term><q lang="eng">"a valley"</q>and means<q lang="eng">"the people of the Valley"</q>.<name lang="tib" type="place">Nyang rna</name>has not yet been found: since the
                word is used in the sense of a<q lang="eng">"messenger"</q>we might translate<q lang="eng">"<name lang="tib" type="person">Bong La ku</name>of the messenger
                  division (<term lang="tib">sde</term>)"</q>.</p><p>Concerning the names<name lang="tib" type="person">Mog Kyem po</name>and<name lang="tib" type="person">Bong La ku</name>see the classified list.<q lang="tib">Rings pa</q>(l. 7) =<q lang="eng">"runner"</q>(cf. p. 136.3: M.I.ii.40,
                Or.15000/293).</p><p>The expression<q lang="tib">rad pa</q>(l. 6) occurs not very infrequently in the
                documents: that it means a travelling party (<term lang="tib">bgrod</term>?) appears
                from several documents, e.g. p. 141. 3-4 (M.I.xiv.109.a, Or.15000/426),<q lang="tib">rad pa gsum mjald te</q><q lang="eng">"three parties (caravans
                met)"</q>, pp. 61 (M.I.xiv.113, Or.15000/430), 205 (M.Tagh.a.iv.007, IOL Tib N
                1631), 371 (M.Tagh.b.i.002, IOL Tib N 2270), 378 (M.I.viii.3, IOL Tib N 377).
                M.Tagh.i.0027 (Or.15000/42), M.I.iii.21 (Or.15000/301).<q lang="tib">Khor</q>is
                perhaps for<term lang="tib">khyor</term><q lang="eng">"handful"</q>: see pp. 112 (Ch.75.xii.5, IOL Tib J 455), etc.</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="10"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">IOL Tib J 1375</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><note><p>Ch.xvii.2 (716, vol. 70, fol. 15, a little torn; c. 26 x 7.5 cm.; ll. 6 obv. and 6
                rev. of ordinary, rather small<term lang="tib">dbu can</term>script).</p><p><q lang="tib">[A. 1]@'ung g[i] 'og tu Btsan po Khri Srong rtsan gyi ring la//Khyung
                  po spu[n] sad Zu tse lta zhig rgalte(ste) nyi ma 'der gnang ngo//'ung nas [l.
                  2]Btsan po'i zha sngar /Zu tse gsol pa //spun yab Gnam ri'i ring la//bdag gis
                  'bangsu bkug pa lta zhig//ya[b] [l. 3] kyis kyang ma gzigs/zhabs kyis kyang ma
                  bcags na //Btsan po sras kyis/spyan kyis gzigs shing /zhabs kyis [l.
                  4]bcagste//bdag rgan po'i spum// pa Khri bomsu dgyes skyems ston mo gsol bar ji
                  gnang zhes gsol nas /[l. 5]Btsan po Khri srong rtsan gyis Zu tse gsol ba bzhin du
                  gnang ngo/'Ung gi rjes la //Mgar yul zung pho brang Ma '[dri][l.6]bar bka' stsal
                  te//Zu tse ga[n] tu mkhar Khri bomsu mchis nas //Mgar...gol[?] bltas na /Mgar [B.
                  1]d[e]'i bka' gros la gtogste Zu tse glo ba nye'o //'ung gi 'og du //Bstan
                  po...Sr[o]ng rtsan gyi ring la/[l. 2]Myang Zhang snang glo ba rings pa Zu tses dku
                  'phel te //Btsan po'i snyang du gsol te /Zhang snang bkum nas Zu tse[l. 3]glo ba
                  nye'o //To yo chas la'i rjo bo Bor Yon tse Brlag ste //To yo chas la lastsogs te
                  byang gi Zhang zhung thams[l. 4]cad//Khri srong rtsan gyi phyag du phul te //Zu
                  tse glo ba nye'o //Btsan po'i blon po nang na //spun sad Zu tse las glo [B l.
                  5]nye ba sngon chad kyang ma byung ngo//Zu tse 'dzangs so zhes so//sgu che zhing
                  mkhas so//dpa' shes pa'o /chu gang [B l. 6]che'o//yang ba ring ngo //myi chig la
                  tshogs dgu tshogs na/s[pun sa]d Zu tse la stsogs dgu tshogs so//</q></p><p><q lang="eng">"[ll. 1-2] After that, in the life time of the<term lang="tib">Btsan
                    po</term><name lang="tib" type="person">Khri Srong rtsan</name>, the<name lang="tib">Khyung po</name>family was destroyed, only a certain<name lang="tib" type="person">Zu tse</name>being allowed on that day to escape (?). Afterwards<name lang="tib" type="person">Zu tse</name>petitioned in the presence of the<term lang="tib">Btsan po</term>, [ll. 2-4] 'In the lifetime of<name lang="tib" type="person">Gnam ri</name>, the father of the family, called up, I was treated
                  by himself as a subject, forsooth. By the father even I was not even looked at,
                  nor even trampled under his feet (disciplined). By the son<term lang="tib">Btsan
                    po</term>I was regarded with the eye and disciplined. I petitioned. 'Be pleased
                  to invite your aged relative to pleasure, drinking, and feasting in<name lang="tib" type="place">Khri boms</name>.' [l. 5-B l. 1] The<term lang="tib">Btsan po</term><name lang="tib" type="person">Khri Srong rtsan</name>assented to<name lang="tib" type="person">Zu tse</name>'s petition. Following upon that, he sent
                  orders to the palace<name lang="tib" type="place">Ma 'dri ba</name>, holding
                    (<term lang="tib">zung</term>?) the<name lang="tib">Mgar</name>district.
                  Coming to<name lang="tib" type="person">Zu tse</name>at the city of<name lang="tib" type="place">Khri boms</name>, the<name lang="tib">Mgar...</name>saw him.<name lang="tib" type="person">Zu tse</name>was attached to the council
                  of that<name lang="tib">Mgar</name>and was in favour. [B. ll. 1-3] After that,
                  in the lifetime of the<term lang="tib">Btsan po</term><name lang="tib" type="person">[Khri] Srong rtsan</name>,<name lang="tib" type="person">Myang Zhang snang</name>, a clever man, being outwitted (<term lang="tib">dku 'pel</term>?) by<name lang="tib" type="person">Zu tse</name>,
                  petitioned in the hearing of the<term lang="tib">Btsan po</term>.<name lang="tib" type="person">Zu tse</name>killed<name lang="tib" type="person">Zhang snang</name>and [remained] in favour.<note type="footnote" n="1">Or we
                    might translate<q lang="eng">"<name lang="tib" type="person">Myang Zhang
                      snang</name>being reported for treachery by<name lang="tib" type="person">Zu
                        tse</name>in the hearing of the<term lang="tib">Btsan po</term>,<name lang="tib" type="person">Zhang snang</name>was killed...."</q></note>[B
                  ll. 3-4] The chief of<name lang="tib">To yo chas la</name>,<name lang="tib" type="person">Bor Yong tse</name>, having revolted,<name lang="tib" type="person">Zu tse brought</name><name lang="tib">To yo chas la</name>and all the rest of northern<name lang="tib" type="place">Zhang zhung</name>under the hand of<name lang="tib" type="person">Khri Srong rtsan</name>and [remained] in favour. [B ll. 4-6]
                  Among the councillors of the<term lang="tib">Btsan po no</term>one before even
                  had ever been more in favour than<term lang="tib">spun sad</term><name lang="tib" type="person">Zu tse</name>.<name lang="tib" type="person">Zu
                    tse</name>, it was said, is a wise man; he is very cunning and expert; he has a
                  heroic soul; he has much sap (?<term lang="tib">chu gang</term>'water full' or =<term lang="tib">cu gang</term>); he has a wide outlook (<term lang="tib">yang
                    ba</term>'expanse' ?); if any single man combines all that is to be combined,
                  it is so with<term lang="tib">spun sad</term><name lang="tib" type="person">Zu tse</name></q>."</p><p>l. 1.<name lang="tib">Khyung po</name>is a clan name; see above, pp. 44
                (Ch.79.xvi.7, IOL Tib J 914), 225 (M.Tagh.b.ii.0033, IOL Tib N 1927), 249
                (M.Tagh.c.ii.0065, Or.15000/243), and Vol. I,<ref target="Thomas_1935">p. 277, n.
                  14</ref>.<q lang="tib">spun sad</q>we have translated as if it were<term lang="tib">˚gsad</term>or<term lang="tib">˚bsad</term>: if that is right, the
                subsequent recurrence of the phrase as an epithet of<name lang="tib" type="person">Zu tse</name>has the sense of<q lang="eng">"last of his family"</q>, or is for<term lang="tib">spun spad</term>=<q lang="eng">"kinsman"</q>?<q lang="tib">Rgal</q><q lang="eng">"escape"</q>(usually<q lang="eng">"surmount"</q>) is also a
                conjecture. Is<q lang="tib">nyi ma 'der</q>for<term lang="tib">nyi ma
                lder</term>?</p><p>l. 2. We have taken<q lang="tib">bdag</q>as<q lang="eng">"self"</q>, not as<q lang="eng">"I"</q>.</p><p>l. 3.<q lang="tib">Btsan po sras</q>is evidently in contrast to<term lang="tib">(Btsan po) yab</term>.</p><p>l. 4 and 6.<name lang="tib" type="place">Khri boms</name>is mentioned also in the
                Chronicle (l. 35); also in M.Tagh.a.iv.00136 (Or.15000/125), M.Tagh.c.iii.0063 (IOL
                Tib N 2127), and p. 461 (M.Tagh.c.iv.0033, IOL Tib N 2168).<term lang="tib">˚bom(s)</term>(=<term lang="tib">bams</term>) occurs further in<name lang="tib" type="place">'Go bom</name>below (p. 87: Ch.0021, IOL Tib J 689).</p><p>ll. 5-6.<name lang="tib" type="place">Mgar yul</name>and the palace<name lang="tib" type="place">Ma 'dri ba(?)</name>are not known to me. But in the
                Tibetan<title lang="tib">Me long</title>the famous minister of<name lang="tib" type="person">Srong btsan Sgam po</name>,<name lang="tib" type="person">Gar gdong
                  btsan</name>, is called (fol. 21a.4 30a.5)<name lang="tib">Mgar</name>, which is,
                no doubt, his tribal name. In the Chronicle we have<name lang="tib" type="person">Mgar Gung ston</name>, etc. (ll. 4, 66, 67, 75), and in the Bstan 'gyur colophons<name lang="tib">'Gar</name>(<ref target="Cordier_1909_1915">I, p. 198</ref>,
                etc.).</p><p>B l. 1.<q lang="tib">glo ba ne</q><q lang="eng">"intimate"</q>,<q lang="eng">"in favour"</q>, occurs in the<name lang="tib" type="place">Lha sa</name>inscriptions. (<ref target="Waddell_1910">p. 1277, l. 22, p.
                1279, ll. 73-4</ref>); so also<q lang="tib">glo ba rings</q>(p. 1276, l. 7, p. 1282, ll.
                59 and 62) and p. 121 (M.I.xix.001, IOL Tib N 785), and pp. 23-4 (IOL Tib J 1253)
                supra and Chronicle, l. 67.</p><p>B l. 2.<name lang="tib">Myang</name>is a tribal name of frequent occurrence in
                the documents; see p. 305 (M.I.xiv.131.b, IOL Tib N 717 ?; M.Tagh.a.ii.0016, IOL Tib
                N 1494) and the Chronicle, l. 250.</p><p>B l. 3.<name lang="tib">To yo chas la</name>is not otherwise known to us.<name lang="tib" type="place">Zhang zhung</name>occurs elsewhere as name of<name lang="tib" type="place">Gu ge</name>; and since in<name lang="tib" type="place">Pu 'rangs</name>, which is adjacent to modern<name lang="tib" type="place">Gu
                ge</name>, a place<name lang="tib" type="place">Do yo</name>, or<name lang="tib" type="place">To yo</name>, is actually named (<ref target="Francke_1914_1926">II,
                  Index</ref>), it is very possible that that locality is here meant.</p><p>B l. 6.<q lang="tib">tshogs dgu</q>contains<q lang="tib">dgu</q>in the known
                sense of a plural or a collection.</p><p>Since<name lang="tib" type="person">Gnam ri</name>is the name of the father of<name lang="tib" type="person">Srong btsan Sgam po</name>and also because of the
                ready admission of<name lang="tib" type="person">Zu tse</name>to favour with<name lang="tib" type="person">Khri Srong btsan</name>, it seems probable that<name lang="tib" type="person">Zu tse</name>himself was related to the royal house (cf.
                l. 5). The<q lang="tib">yab</q>is perhaps the father of<name lang="tib" type="person">Khri Srong btsan</name>, not of<name lang="tib" type="person">Zu
                  tse</name>. The latter is remembered in (<term lang="tib">Bon po</term>)
                literature.<name lang="tib" type="person">Khri Srong rtsan</name>is<name lang="tib" type="person">Srong btsan Sgam po</name>, who in the<name lang="tib" type="place">Lha sa</name>treaty (in<ref target="Waddell_1909">p. 950, l.
                26</ref>) is called<name lang="tib" type="person">Khri Lde srong btsan</name>.</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="11"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">IOL Tib J 999</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><note><p>(Vol. 55, fol. 20: c. 31 x 10 cm., ll. 12 of ordinary epistolary<term lang="tib">dbu can</term>script, rather close together; much dicoloured, injured by
                folding, and hardly legible.)</p><p><q lang="tib">[1]@/:/nang rje blon G.yu(?) bzher la//Khris legs mchid gsol
                  ba'//'Phrul dang mtshungs pa'i zha ngas nas /snyun rnying slar ma ['bre]d
                  [ches][2]thoste glo ba dga' zhing mchis//snyun gsol gi mchi[d yi]g sngar/rnam du
                  ma zhig gso[l] na/[slad] lan ma mchis pa dang /sbyar na/'A zha ngan bdagis gya ga
                  [3]du ma phul ba lta zhig [na']/nang rje po Kwa chu pa'i /Ser sbyong gi spun du
                  bsgos pa/Hi ma ter gdan gshegste/sgrol(sgol? skrol?) bka' 'grosu mdzad na dmag
                  [pu...pyad lnga'(lta'?)][4]las kyang/dog sa [thagstu] rab tu che zhabs thugs myi
                  bde bas/gdan gshegs gyi(bgyi?) kyang 'phrin las mdzad la sman pa myi 'dra bar/ring
                  lugs kyi 'phrin [by]ang [5][d]ang/chad pa'i gzhi /Bde gamsu mchis nas/bdagis/bla
                  'og dug gsol zhes...pyung shig ches 'byung ba/ring lugs kyi 'phrin byang khamsu
                  mchis m-(mchiste?)[6]...la chad pas<note type="footnote" n="1"><q lang="tib">s</q>below line</note>chod shig ches/kha mar stsal nas/rtsi sar gthad dang /khri
                  [m(?)...s] dang sbyar na/sa bar snyad(mkhar chud?) lo chig gi sna
                  stsal.....i..[-ba rdzug][7].......pas gchad pa'i gzhi byung zhing mchis na/de las
                  thugs myi<note type="footnote" n="2"><q lang="tib">myi</q>crossed out</note>chud
                  ba tsam dug gsold//slan chad bla nas thugs re ste/'phrin lasu b[sdos
                  st..][8]..........'phrin las gzung bzhin du mdzad pa'i rigs par bdag ngan pa bka'
                  grosu gso[l] zhing mchis//gchen gcu po m[gon] zhi[n(?)/ste][9]...........gs bzher
                  gyi g.yar du stsalpa ni/sman yon ji yang ma bgyiste/'dun sa snar(?) spyi yang myi
                  gda' zhing mchis te//bdag ngan[10]..............rtag tu snyan snyungs pa gsol zhes
                  bka' bab bam myi bab/Mdo gams nas/mjal stsongs/d[ru]l pho che dag gchig s[nga
                  slad] [du]go [mtshams?][11]......rdzas dang/sga g.yer phal mo che zhig mchis shes
                  gda'ba/mched gyi chab sgor phal cher 'phus shes bka' mchid ltos(?)
                  na[12].......snyungs gsol zhing mchis na/phyag rgya stsald te/bang chen 'di
                  las/brdzang na tsam du thugs dphag jir mdzad//</q></p><p><q lang="eng">"[ll. 1-2] To the Minister of the Interior, Councillor<name lang="tib" type="person">G.yu bzher</name>, letter-petition of<name lang="tib" type="person">Khris legs</name>. I am very glad to hear that on the part of you,
                  equal to a theophany, there is no recurrence of your old illness. [ll. 2-4] As
                  regards the fact that, though I sent various letters before this inquiring as to
                  your health, no answer has come, and whereas I, a humble<name lang="tib">'A
                  zha</name>, have sent various presents: Minister of the Interior, styled of the<name lang="tib">Ser sbyon</name>family of<name lang="tib" type="place">Kwa
                    chu</name>, residing in your seat at<name lang="tib" type="place">Hi ma
                  te</name>, engaged in saving(?) counsels, from the army also...five...very great
                  distance...your servant is ill at ease. [ll. 4-5] There being unequalled advantage
                  in carrying on the business even while you are in your residence, when the
                  courier's missive and the substance of the orders came to<name lang="tib" type="person">Bde gams</name>, it was opportune for me to submit matter to my
                  superiors(?). [ll. 5-6] Having sent down a verbal order that 'a courier's missive
                  having come into the country, carry out the orders (or punish)...,' I sent to the
                  palace of the census (<term lang="tib">rtsi sar</term>). [ll. 6-7] As regards the
                  law, the decision to punish having...one year..., accordingly begged to be not
                  weak. [ll. 7-10] Afterwards, being more hopeful than before, and relying upon the
                  business (instructions), your humble servant submitted in council that it was
                  right to act in accordance with the business undertaken (instructions received?).
                  The ten brothers being the leaders(?)...as to sending up to...<term lang="tib">bzher</term>, no advantage whatever was effected, and in the meeting nothing at
                  all being possible, it was ordered more or less that your humble servant should
                  constantly write inquires as to health. 'From<name lang="tib" type="place">Mdo
                    gams</name>, some market merchandize, very rotten, early and later...things and
                  general indifference (<term lang="tib">sga g.yer</term>?)', so it was said. Having
                  regard to the saying, 'at a brother's door usually...'we have sent a signed letter
                  of inquires as to health. If you send a letter, please trouble to send by this
                  courier."</q></p><p>Possibly the translation of this difficult document may be improved later.</p><p>l. 2. On<q lang="tib">dang sbyar na</q>=<q lang="eng">"as regards"</q>: see p.
                29 (IOL Tib 1253).</p><p>l. 4.<q lang="tib">'phrin byang</q>or<q lang="tib">byang</q>alone seems to be
                in these documents one of the expressions denoting a letter. Some wooden documents
                (pp. 203-4: M.Tagh.a.iii.0016, IOL Tib N 1577; M.Tagh.a.iv.007, IOL Tib N 1631)
                refer to themselves as<q lang="tib">byang 'di</q><q lang="eng">"this communication"</q>.<term lang="tib">byang bu</term>is<q lang="eng">"label"</q>or (wooden)<q lang="eng">"postcard"</q>. The Chronicle
                also has<q lang="tib">byang</q>. See pp. 331-2 and Index.</p><p>l. 5.<name lang="tib" type="person">Bde gams</name>has occurred already. (pp. 22,
                25: back of Ch.87.xiii, IOL Tib J 856).</p><p><q lang="tib">'byung ba</q>: see p. 29 (IOL Tib 1253).</p><p>l. 9.<q lang="tib">sman yon</q>: see above, p. 48 (Fragment.80, IOL Tib J 1459).</p><p>l. 10.<q lang="tib">snyan snyungs</q><q lang="eng">"a letter of inquires after health"</q>seems to mean merely a formal
                letter of that nature (cf. p. 22: back of Ch.87.xiii, IOL Tib J 856). We have
                several among the documents.</p><p><name lang="tib" type="place">Mdo gams</name>: see below, pp. 61, 106.</p><p>l. 11.<q lang="tib">chab sgor</q><q lang="eng">"by the door of"</q>or<q lang="eng">"an opportunity of"</q>(?).<q lang="tib">sga g.yer</q><q lang="eng">"indifferent"</q>(?); cf. pp. 21, 22 (back of Ch.87.xiii, IOL Tib J
                856).</p><p>l. 12.<term lang="tib">thugs dpag</term>(or<term lang="tib">pags</term>) and<term lang="tib">thugs dpag jir(cir) mdzad</term>, asking or stating attention,
                are common in the documents.</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="11A"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">IOL Tib J 1018</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="11A"><note><p>Verso of Ch.fragm.82 (paper, vol. 55, fol. 27, c. 28 x 19 cm.; ll. 12 of clear,
                ordinary, cursive<term lang="tib">dbu can</term>writing).</p><p><q lang="tib">[1]@/:/byi ba lo'i dbyar sla ra ba'i ngo la/Tshas stobs gyi
                  sde/[2]@/:/byi balo'i dbyar sla ra ba'i ngo la//Snying tsoms gyi sde/-e Lha skyes
                  gyi gro [3]nas khal gsum zhig/Rgod sar gyi sde/Sag Dge legs gis snga g.yar du
                  'tshalde[4]slar 'bulba'i dus nil an 'di 'i ston lsa 'bring po ma gum tshun tshad
                  bre byed bzang[s?]u[5]bgyis/dus gcig<note type="footnote" n="1">These two
                    syllables crossed out.</note>bre phul myi chad par dus gcig du Lha skyes gyi
                  sgor 'bul bar[6]bgyis/su<note type="footnote" n="2"><q lang="tib">su</q>crossed
                    out.</note>dus der ma phul lam gya gyu zhig 'tshal na/gnyicig<note type="footnote" n="3"><q lang="tib">nyi</q>crossed out.</note>la gnyis
                  su...[7]bsgyur te/dngos sgyur dang bcas par kho na'i sgor phyi phyig dang nang
                  rdzas sug spyad rgyab 'go[s][8]ci la bab kyang rungste/ring lugs su phrog na yang
                  zhal cu tshig kyang myi mchis bgyi[s][9]brgya la Dge legs bye ha<note type="footnote" n="4">These two syllables crossed out.</note>gzhi la ma
                  mchissam/rje blas bkur te gung chad du gyur[10]na mjal gnya kha len kho na'i pho
                    bra......ni<note type="footnote" n="5"><q lang="tib">ni</q>crossed out.</note>dam gong nas byung bzhin du[11]mchid gyis 'tshal zhing 'bul bra'<note type="footnote" n="6">Compendious for<term lang="tib">bar</term>.</note>bgyis
                  pa'i dpang-----[12]----lastsogspa'i dpang rgyadang sug yig tshad gyisbtabpa.</q></p><p><q lang="eng">"[1] At the beginning of the first summer month of the Mouse year:
                  district of<name lang="tib" type="place">Tshas stobs</name>. [2-3] At the
                  beginning of the first summer month of the Mouse year: district of<name lang="tib" type="place">Snying tsoms</name>. Belonging to<name lang="tib" type="person">Lha skyes</name>some three loads of wheat and barely having
                  previously been required (<term lang="tib">g.yar du</term>?) 'on loan' by<name lang="tib" type="person">Sag Dge legs</name>of district<name lang="tib" type="place">Rgod sar</name>, as regards the time of rendering it back, it is
                  the middle autumn month of the present year. [4-5] Until death (or until this is
                  effected?<term lang="tib">gum</term>=<term lang="tib">khums</term>), half a<term lang="tib">bre</term>is agreed (?<term lang="tib">bzangsu</term>? as
                  interest): the delivery of the<term lang="tib">bre</term>is to take place
                  without interruption at one time at the door of<name lang="tib" type="person">Lha
                    skyes</name>. [6-9] If it is not then delivered, or if trickery is attempted,
                  the amount becomes doubled. Present goods at his house with their increase,
                  outside cattle and things indoors, tools, clothes on his back, wherever put, may
                  be seized according to the old usage without a word of protest. [9-11]
                  Alternatively, if<name lang="tib" type="person">Dge legs</name>is not at home or
                  if through consideration of the part of His Excellency a division is made, then
                  the witnesses to the agreement and a guarantor upon a demand [at their residences]
                  by letter in accordance with the outcome of the above indenture are required to
                  deliver: [11-12] in attestation whereof of the attestation marks and written
                  signatures of....and the others are attached."</q></p><p>The agreement is a draft, as appears from the fact that in l. 1 a different
                document was commenced, and also from the gaps left in ll. 11-12 for insertion of
                the names of witnesses, etc. Concerning the phrases<q lang="tib">zhal cu</q>,<q lang="tib">dam gong nas byung</q>,<q lang="tib">brgya la</q>, we may refer to the
                notes on the similar document discussed infra, p. 145 (M.I.xliv.7, Or.15000/530).
                This instrument comes from the Tun-huang library (it is written on the back of a
                MS.) and relates to the<name lang="tib" type="place">Sha cu</name>region.</p><p>l. 1.<name lang="tib" type="place">Tshas stobs</name>: This district has not
                hitherto been found.</p><p>ll. 2-3.<name lang="tib" type="place">Snying tsoms</name>and<name lang="tib" type="place">Rgod sar</name>: On these districts see the references in pp. 40
                (Ch.83.vi.5, IOL Tib J 1383), 83 (Ch.73.xv.5, IOL Tib J 1359).</p><p>l. 3.<name lang="tib">Sag</name>: On this clan name see pp. 50 (Ch.73.iv.14, IOL
                Tib J 134), 115.</p><p>l. 4.<q lang="tib">bzangsu</q>: Reading and sense uncertain.</p><p>l. 5.<q lang="tib">myi chad par</q>: This seems clearly to mean<q lang="eng">"without interruption"</q>; one would have preferred<q lang="eng">"if the
                  delivery of the<term lang="tib">bre</term>is not carried out"</q>.</p><p>ll. 6-7.<q lang="tib">gcig la gnyisu..bsgyur</q>: Cf. p. 45. 4-5 (back of
                Ch.86.ii, IOL Tib J 850) and Index.</p><p>l. 7.<q lang="tib">phyi phyi(a)g...rgyab 'gos</q>: The rendering is somewhat
                uncertain.</p><p>l. 9.<q lang="tib">bkur te gung chad du</q>: the rendering is uncertain.</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="11B"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">Or.15000/430</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="11B"><note><p>M.I.xiv.113 (paper fragment, fol. no. 49 in vol.; c. 18 x 14 cm.; ll. 8 of ordinary
                cursive<term lang="tib">dbu can</term>script).</p><p><q lang="tib">[1]...gste rgyas btan/...[2]...lnga chags [rgy]as btan[3]...l nas bre
                  gsum chagste rgyas btan...[4]...rgyas [b]tan//'di rnams la chagste 'bul ba'i rgyas
                  btan...[5]...tshun chad 'bul bar bgyis/dus der ma phulna tsha gnyis su bsgyur
                  te[6]...dpang rgya 'di sus 'tshal te mchis pas khon ta'i rad gos dang nas zan
                  tsha[7]...par bgyis pa'i dpang la/'Greng ro Khyi brug /rtsig Lha rtsa
                  skyes/...[8]...dpang [rgy]as btabs/</q></p><p><q lang="eng">"[ll. 1-5]...attested as measuring...attested as measuring
                  five...attested as measuring three<term lang="tib">bre</term>of
                  barely...attested as received with the measures stated in these attestations...are
                  agreed to be paid not later than...[5-7] If not paid at that time, the amount is
                  to be doubled...whoever [in possession of] this witnessed document presents a
                  demand [may seize] the party's travelling clothes and barely, food provision...;
                  [7-8] In witness of which agreement the signatures of<name lang="tib">'Greng ro</name><name lang="tib" type="person">Khyi brug</name>and<term lang="tib">rtsig</term><name lang="tib" type="person">Lha rtsa skyes</name>...are attached."</q></p><p>For similar legal documents, see pp. 45, 62, etc. The designation<name lang="tib">'Greng ro</name>denotes, as we shall see below (pp. 99, 100: Ch.9.i.37, IOL Tib
                J 751), the country of the<name lang="tib">'Greng</name>people of<name lang="tib" type="place">Mdo gams</name>. Professor Pelliot has pointed out that<name lang="tib" type="place">Mdo gams</name>, which is identical with, or a part of,<name lang="tib" type="place">Mdo khams</name>, north-eastern Tibet, was known to
                the Chinese of Mongol and Ming times as<name lang="chi" type="place">Tokan</name>(i.e.<name lang="tib" type="place">Do gam</name>): see<ref target="Bretschneider_1888">ii, pp. 203, 224</ref>.<name lang="tib">'Gren</name>,
                he thinks, may be the native name represented by the term<term lang="chi">K'iang</term>, applied by the Chinese to the Tibetans of<name lang="tib" type="place">Kan su</name>,<name lang="chi" type="place">Ssu-ch'uan</name>, and<name type="place">Koko-Nor</name>.</p><p>ll. 1-4,<q lang="tib">chags</q>: See supra, p. 42 (Ch.80.v.1, IOL Tib J 844).</p><p>l. 6,<q lang="tib">rad gos</q>:<q lang="eng">"Travel clothes"</q>: see p. 205
                (M.Tagh.a.iv.007, IOL Tib N 1631) and Index.</p><p>l. 7,<q lang="tib">rtsig</q><name lang="tib" type="person">Lha rtsa skyes</name>: On this designation and person
                see infra, p. 143 (M.I.xiv.109.a, Or.15000/426) and Index.</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="11C"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">IOL Tib N 390</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><note><p>M.I.viii.13 (wood, c. 11 x 1.5 cm., complete; hole for string at r.; l. 1 of
                cursive<term lang="tib">dbu can</term>script).</p><p><q lang="tib">@//Greng ro Zla gtsug</q></p><p><q lang="eng">"<name lang="tib" type="person">Zla gtsug</name>, of<name lang="tib">[']Greng ro</name>."</q></p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="11D"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">IOL Tib N 422</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="11D"><note><p>M.I.viii.48 (wood, c. 11.5 x 2 cm., complete; hole for string at r.; l. 1 of
                cursive<term lang="tib">dbu can</term>script.)</p><p><q lang="tib">@//'Greng ro Klu brtan/</q></p><p><q lang="eng">"<name lang="tib" type="person">Klu brtan</name>, of<name lang="tib">'Greng ro</name>."</q></p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="11E"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">Or.15000/31</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="11E"><note><p>M.Tagh.0509.+0510. (two paper fragments which can be fitted together, left (1509)
                and right (1510), the whole being still fragmentary at the commencement: 1509, c. 16
                x 11 cm.; 1510, c. 14 x 8.5 cm., ll. 7 (1509) + 5 (1510) of regular<term lang="tib">dbu can</term>writing: red stain).</p><p><q lang="tib">[1]gyis tha ma la bd-[l]..u......</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[2]las dmar srang gcig du b[s]gyurd th[e]//bya [1510] gag lo'i [dbg-g
                  gl]...</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[3]cad du dmar srang gcig '[bu]l bar bgyis//[1510]dus der ma gcald na
                  srang cig</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[4]las srang nyis/su bsgyurd [l]i:Rme'u Bying la [1510][g]sas gyi sko
                  nas progs/gyang<note type="footnote" n="1"><q lang="tib">i</q>crossed out.</note>rtsigs[u]</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[5]cig gyang myi mci bar bgyis pha 'i dpang po [1510]la<note type="footnote" n="2"><q lang="tib">ng</q>crossed out here.</note>Phyug tshams
                  Rhul po dang [D]ar/</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[6]Dbyi rma dang/Tsi bra Lha gong dpang po 'di [rnams][1510]'A:nang
                  Bying la g.....sug</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[7]rgyas bthab [bo]</q></p><p><q lang="eng">"[ll. 1-3]...having on the last occasion become one<term lang="tib">srang</term>of copper, it was arranged that not later than...of the Bird-year
                  one<term lang="tib">srang</term>of copper should be delivered. [ll. 3-5] If at
                  that time payment should not have been made, from one<term lang="tib">srang</term>it should become two; and even if it should be seized from the door
                  of<name lang="tib" type="person">Li Rme'u Bying la gsas</name>, it was agreed
                  that there should be no word [of protest]. [5-7] Witnesses are the following:<name lang="tib" type="person">Rhul po</name>of<name lang="tib" type="place">Phyug [m]tshams</name>and<name lang="tib" type="person">Dar Byi rma</name>and<name lang="tib" type="person">Tsi bra Lha gong</name>. These witnesses have
                  deposited their attestation with<name lang="tib" type="person">Rma 'A nang Bying
                    la g[sas?]</name>."</q></p><p>On<name lang="tib" type="place">Phyug mtshams</name>as a Thousand-district of<name lang="tib" type="place">Mdo gams</name>see p. 106 (Ch.9.i.37, IOL Tib J
                751), vol, 1<ref target="Thomas_1935">p. 279</ref>. The surnames<name lang="tib" type="person">Li</name>and<name lang="tib" type="person">Dar</name>are
                instanced in the consolidated list infra (p. 113 sqq.);<name lang="tib">Rma</name>has occured supra (p. 20: Fragment.67, IOL Tib J 1126);<name lang="tib" type="person">Rhul po</name>occurs p. 215 (M.Tagh.0050);<name lang="tib">Tsi
                bra</name>(for<name lang="tib">Tsib ra</name>?) is not known, but is, no doubt,
                name of some district.</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="11F"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">IOL Tib N 2250</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="11F"><note><p>M.Tagh.0614 (wood, c. 24 x 2-2.5 cm., broken away at l., r., and bottom; ll. 2 of
                squarish<term lang="tib">dbu can</term>script).</p><p><q lang="tib">[1]@/:/Bzag/'Or/gyi:ste:Zir:rgu:Cag:cung/gyis:'Brong/tsams/gyi/ste:Ba:Snang/rma:...</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[2]las/rta:cig:mtshjald<note type="footnote" n="1"><q lang="tib">ch</q>here crossed out.</note>:de [d]a'i:-o:[r]is/dang/s-a:r[t?]ags:la/...</q></p><p><q lang="eng">"<name lang="tib" type="person">Zir Rgu cag cung</name>of the
                    Good-<name lang="tib">'Or</name>regiment having borrowed(?) from<name lang="tib" type="person">Ba Snang rma</name>of the<name lang="tib" type="place">'Brong</name>-border regiment one horse, its [marks are as
                  follows]..."</q></p><p><name lang="tib" type="place">'Brong tsams</name>(<term lang="tib">mtshams</term>),<name lang="tib" type="place">'Brong</name>-border, the name of
                which is parallel to that of<name lang="tib" type="place">Phyug tshams</name>(p.
                62: Or.15000/31), etc. belongs doubtless, along with<name lang="tib" type="place">'Brong stong</name>, to the<name lang="tib" type="place">'Brong</name>district
                of<name lang="tib" type="place">Mdo gams</name>, concerning which see infra (p.
                459: M.Tagh.a.vi.0019, IOL Tib N 2284; M.Tagh.c.ii.0046, IOL Tib N 2052). The script
                also, though the document comes from the Khotan region, is probably one
                characterstic of that area. It may be remarked that<name lang="tib" type="place">'Brong</name>is probably<q lang="eng">"the Yak country"</q>, just as<name lang="tib" type="place">Cog (Tsog) ro</name>may be<q lang="eng">"the Donkey
                  country"</q>.</p><p>l. 1,<name lang="tib" type="person">Zir Rgu cag c[h]ung</name>:<q lang="eng">"<name lang="tib" type="person">Rug cag</name>minor of<name lang="tib">Zir</name>"</q>; but it may be<q lang="eng">"<name lang="tib" type="person">Cag
                    cung</name>of<name lang="tib">Zir rgu</name>"</q>.</p><p><q lang="tib">Bzang 'Or gyi ste</q>: On this regiment see vol. I (<ref target="Thomas_1935">p. 299</ref>) and infra (pp. 292-3: M.Tagh.0345, IOL Tib N
                1293); p. 456).</p><p>l. 2,<q lang="tib">mtshjald</q>: Is this from<term lang="tib">'tshal</term><q lang="eng">"request"</q>, or from<term lang="tib">'tshol</term>, or from what?</p><p><q lang="tib">-o [r]is dang s-a rtags</q>: =<term lang="tib">ngo ris dang sna
                  rtags</term>?</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="11G"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">IOL Tib N 2284</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="11G"><note><p>M.Tagh.a.vi.0019 (wood, c. 12-12.5 x 2 cm., complete; hole for string at r.; ll. 1
                recto and 2 verso of cursive<term lang="tib">dbu can</term>script).</p><p><q lang="tib">[A]@//'Brong tsams khyi sde Po yong 'Dus rma/</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[B1] dngos 'Uten na mchis na dmag skyin nas g[la]</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[B2] thud 'bul lam myi 'bul rma/</q></p><p><q lang="eng">"<name lang="tib" type="person">Po yong 'Dus rma</name>, of the<name lang="tib" type="place">'Brong</name>-border regiment, being at present in
                  Khotan, inquires whether the additional wages in barely(?) owing to the army is to
                  be paid or not."</q></p><p>l. B1,<q lang="tib">nas</q>:<q lang="eng">"Barely"</q>: or should we translate<q lang="eng">"from (<term lang="tib">nas</term>) what is owing"</q>?</p><p>B2,<q lang="tib">thud</q>: =<term lang="tib">mthud ma</term>; cf. p. 415
                (M.I.xliv.6, )r.15000/529), Chronicle, l. 253 (<term lang="tib">khral˚</term>).</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="11H"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">IOL Tib N 1565</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="11H"><note><p>M.Tagh.a.iii.004 (wood, c. 16 x 1.5-2 cm., broken away at the bottom; hole for
                string at r.; l. 1 of cursive<term lang="tib">dbu can</term>script).</p><p><q lang="tib">@/:/Br[ong] tsham gyi sde/se Nyab tsen /</q></p><p><q lang="eng">"<name lang="tib" type="person">Se Nyab tsen</name>of the<name lang="tib">'Brong</name>-border regiment."</q></p><p>On<name lang="tib" type="person">Se</name>, as a surname, see pp. 427, 456
                (M.Tagh.0332, IOL Tib N 1280) 468 (M.Tagh.c.ii.0016, IOL Tib N 2023).</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="11I"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">IOL Tib N 692</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="11I"><note><p>M.I.xiv.96 (wood, c. 11.5 x 2 cm., complete; hole for string at r.; l. 1 of cursive<term lang="tib">dbu can</term>script).</p><p><q lang="tib">@/:/'Brong stong Cung gong gi mchid gsol ba/</q></p><p><q lang="eng">"Letter-petition of<name lang="tib" type="person">Cung gong</name>of<name lang="tib">'Brong stong</name>."</q></p><p>Possibly<q lang="tib">'Brong stong</q>,<q lang="eng">"'Brong</q>-Thousand", is
                intended for<name lang="tib" type="place">'Brong stod</name>,<q lang="eng">"Upper<name lang="tib" type="place">'Brong</name>"</q>.</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="11J"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">IOL Tib N 309</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="11J"><note><p>M.I.vii.32 (wood, c. 19 x 2.5 cm., complete, but one small piece detached; hole for
                string at r.; ll. 2 recto + 3 verso of<term lang="tib">dbu can</term>writing,
                faint).</p><p><q lang="tib">[1]@/:/blon Ldong bzang /glo ba myi bde nas//Spa zhar rings su
                  brdzang[2]btang//Slungs 'O ma Bu lud(ng?) dang/Snying tsoms kyi 'bangs/Zing[B1]Rin
                  cen dang/Bag(bgu?) bre Dpa[l] ('du/)dang/'Dza('Je? 'Dzi?)lda 'A lum gsum[B2]Nob
                  ched por brdzang bar//snga slad lan du ma zhig phed(?) [B3]ba las//phrin byang kyi
                  lan tsam yang ma mchi[s]</q></p><p><q lang="eng">"By Councillor<name lang="tib" type="person">Ldong bzang</name>, who
                  is anxious, ordered to be despatched in haste to<name lang="tib" type="place">Spa
                    zha</name>. Whereas the<name lang="tib">Slungs</name><name lang="tib" type="person">'O ma Bu lud(ng?)</name>and<name lang="tib" type="place">Snying tsoms</name>people,<name lang="tib" type="person">Zing Rin
                    cen</name>and<name lang="tib" type="person">Bag bre Dpal 'ngud</name>and<name lang="tib" type="person">'Dza lda 'A-lum</name>, these three, have been
                  sent to<name lang="tib" type="place">Nob ched po</name>, first and last several
                  times even a reply by message tablet has not come."</q></p><p>On<name lang="tib">Slungs</name>see supra p. 52 (M.I.xxviii.0036, Or.15000/496),
                and infra, pp. 296-7 (M.Tagh.a.iv.0092, IOL Tib N 1708; M.Tagh.a.vi.003, IOL Tib N
                1755; M.I.xv.0020, IOL Tib N 749). The district<name lang="tib" type="place">Snying
                  tsoms</name>has already been mentioned. For the surnames<name lang="tib" type="person">Zing</name>,<name lang="tib" type="person">Bag(Bgla?) bre</name>,<name lang="tib" type="person">'Dze('Je? 'Dzi?) lda no</name>citations seem
                available.<name lang="tib" type="place">Spa zha</name>also, as place-name (?), is
                apparently unknown. On<name lang="tib" type="place">Nob ched po</name>see infra,
                pp. 115 sqq., and on<q lang="tib">phrin byang</q>supra, p. 58 (IOL Tib J 999).</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="11K"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">Or.15000/399</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="11K"><note><p>M.I.xiv.59 (fol. No. 42; paper, c. 21x 7 cm., fragmentary at right; discoloured;
                ll. 6 of smallish, cursive<term lang="tib">dbu can</term>script.)</p><p><q lang="tib">[1]@//jo co Klu sman gyi zha sngar/ /Rtsang Lde ya gyi mchid gsol<note type="footnote" n="1"><q lang="tib">l</q>below line.</note>...[2]bar smond te
                  //mchid yig las snyun gsol zhing mchisna//bka' stsald pa tsam ji gnang/[3]pa
                  las//Po gams Kwa cur chad de //zhal ma mthong ba //khol mo gum ba dang 'dra
                  zhi...[4]bal pho re gang zhig mchisna bzhes par ji gnang//chab mar dag chig db[u]l
                  [ba]r b...[5]gyis 'bul bar 'tshal zhing mchis//'bangs 'ga' zhig 'bro
                  myi...g...[6]yang 'bangs dang bsgrogs te gthang bar 'tshal na/bk(g?)a...</q></p><p><q lang="eng">"[ll. 1-2] To the presence of Lord<name lang="tib" type="person">Klu
                    sman</name>: letter-petition of<name lang="tib" type="person">Rtsang Lde
                  ya</name>. Prayers for...Thanks for having, with a letter inquiring after health,
                  sent instructions. [3-4] Not to have seen your face when departing for<name lang="tib" type="place">Po gams</name>[in]<name lang="tib" type="place">Kwa
                  cu</name>was to your maidservant like death. [4-6] Favour me by accepting the
                  wool, one whole<term lang="tib">pho re</term>, if it has come. I desire to
                  present...the water and oil which were to be presented. Some servants having
                  [absconded? being ill?], when I meet my servants again, I will send..."</q></p><p>The letter seems to have been written by a lady who had left Mīrān (<name lang="tib" type="place">Nob ched po</name>) for<name lang="tib" type="place">Po
                  gams</name>in<name lang="tib" type="place">Kwa cu</name>.<name lang="tib" type="place">Po gams</name>is unknown, unless it is the<name lang="chi" type="place">Pou-kouang</name>of<ref target="Chavannes_1913">p. 130</ref>; as
                regards the element<q lang="tib">gams</q>in the name cf.<name lang="tib">Bde
                gams</name>, etc. From the tenor of the letter the lady would appear to be a
                landowner of Miran who could make presents of water and oil to the Tibetan chief.</p><p>l. 4,<q lang="tib">bal pho re gang</q>: With this phrase cf. pp. 152: 46.3
                (M.I.xiii.12, Or.15000/380), 377: 63.3 (M.I.xxi.1A, Or.15000/462).<q lang="tib">Pho
                  re</q>would seem to be =<term lang="tib">phor</term>.</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="11L"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">IOL Tib J 1274</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="11L"><note><p>Ch. – (paper, fol. no. 220 of vol. 57: ll. 7 of good cursive<term lang="tib">dbu
                  can</term>script, complete, covering, with other notes, part of a leaf at the end
                of a Buddhist MS. on large folios).</p><p><q lang="tib">@/:/Ser Dzin kheng gi bu lon Rgya thag gcig dang shog shog yug thung
                  bcu Li'u Klu rton la chags te /[2]'bul ba'i dus ni /'Brugi lo'i dgun sla tha
                  chungs tshes nyi shu la /Dzin kheng gang na mchis par 'bul /[3]bar bgyis /dus der
                  ma phul na/shog shog dang Rgya thag gnyis ka bsgyur te /dam rgya gsum myi /[4]dgos
                  par dam rgya phyi mo gcig bgyis pa des ring lugs bgyiste /Klu rton gyi dam phyis
                  dang Shi'u /[5]kin ji la bab kyang rung ste phrogs kyang zhal mchu tshig gcig
                  kyang myi mchi bar bgyis pai'i /[6]dpang la /Sag Stag slebs /'Im 'Bye le'u /Khang
                  Mang zigs /Song Legs b<note type="footnote" n="1"><q lang="tib">Legs b</q>crossed
                    out.</note>Lug lug las /[7]stsogs pa'i dpang rgya dang /Klu rton gyi sug pa gyi
                  mdzub tshad gyis btab pa /</q></p><p>(Inverted)<q lang="tib">Klu rton sug rgya ma mchis the</q></p><p><q lang="eng">mdzug tshad btab pa //</q></p><p><q lang="eng">"[ll. 1-3] Loan [on the part] of<name lang="tib" type="person">Ser
                    Dzin kheng</name>: one Chinese cord and ten short pieces of paper being in the
                  hands of<name lang="tib" type="person">Li'i Klu rton</name>, as regards the time
                  of payment, it was arranged that payment should be made to<name lang="tib" type="person">Dzin kheng</name>, wherever he should be, on the twentieth day of
                  the last winter month of the Dragon year. [3-5] If at that time payment should not
                  have been made, the paper and the Chinese cord should both become double: three
                  bonds not being required, procedure according to custom should be taken upon the
                  last bond singly, and<name lang="tib" type="person">Klu rton</name>'s (by the
                  last bond 'and<name lang="tib" type="person">Shi'u kin</name>'s') [property],
                  wherever found, may be seized without a single word of complaint. [5-7] In
                  attestation of which agreement the attestation seals of<name lang="tib" type="person">Sag Stag slebs</name>,<name lang="tib" type="person">'Im 'Bye
                    le'u</name>,<name lang="tib" type="person">Khang Mang zigs</name>,<name lang="tib" type="person">Song Lug lug</name>and the rest, and the
                  finger-measure of the hand of<name lang="tib" type="person">Klu rton</name>are
                  impressed. [Inverted]<name lang="tib" type="person">Klu rton</name>not having a
                  hand-signature his finger-measure is impressed."</q></p><p>This legal document is on the same lines as No. 5. For the clan names<name lang="tib">Ser</name>,<name lang="tib">Li'u</name>,<name lang="tib">Sag</name>,<name lang="tib">'Im</name>,<name lang="tib">Khang</name>,<name lang="tib">Song</name>, see the consolidated list.</p><p>l. 1,<q lang="tib">Rgya thag gcig</q>: This might mean<q lang="eng">"one
                  seal-cord"</q>; but, since<name lang="tib" type="person">Dzin kheng</name>has a
                Chinese name, the given rendering is more probable.</p><p><q lang="tib">shog shog</q>: The usual reduplicated form, as p. 84. B1.</p><p><q lang="tib">chags</q>: See pp. 258.10 (M.Tagh.b.i.00104, Or.15000/192), 323.</p><p>l. 4,<q lang="tib">dam phyis...</q>: The syntax is here obscure: we gather that<name lang="tib" type="person">Shi'u kin</name>is to be included, as a guarantor,
                in the last agreement.</p><p><q lang="eng">"According to custom"</q>: On<q lang="tib">ring lugs</q>see p. 16
                (IOL Tib J 1368).</p><p>l. 5,<q lang="tib">zhal mchu</q>: See pp. 59.8 (Ch.82, IOL Tib j 1018), 180
                (M.Tagh.0050), and Index.</p><p>l. 7,<q lang="tib">mdzub tshad</q>: See p. 46.1-2 (Ch.86.ii, IOL Tib J 850).</p><p><q lang="tib">mdzub</q>: The alternative, less usual, form,<q lang="tib">mdzug</q>, which here follows, recurs also in p. 75. B9 (IOL Tib J 1254): in p.
                74.11<q lang="tib">mdzub</q>reappears. Cf. the -b/-g in<term lang="tib">Nob</term>/<term lang="tib">Nag</term>.</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="12"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">IOL Tib J 1360(A)</idno><idno type="current">IOL Tib J 1360(B)</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><note><p>Ch.73.xv.10.fr.12 (vol. 69, foll. 62-3, originally a single roll; c. 76 x 15 cm.;
                fragmentary at the beginning; ll. 53 recto of ordinary<term lang="tib">dbu
                can</term>script, l. 2 verso in another hand).</p><p><q lang="tib">[1].................................................Pho kwang s[i]'i
                  [l]ha 'bangs J 'u/Zhi nyang 'phongs/</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/Song Shing dgon/</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Pho kwang si'i lha 'bangs Yang G.yu tshe 'phongs/</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[5]Rgod sar kyi sde/Bam Kun tse/dgon g.yon/ru 'bring Shud pu Legs zigs
                  kyi dar tshan 'An Dze hing dang sbyor //</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[8]<note type="footnote" n="1">ll. 8-9 in red ink.</note>@/:/Rgod sar
                  kyi sde/ru 'bring/Shud pu Legs gzigs [9]pon g.yog bzhi bcu tshar gcigi yul yig la/
                  /</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[10]Rgod sar kyi sde/'An Dze hing 'phongs/g.yasu ru cung //Cang Ka
                  dzo'i dar tshan/Bam Kun tse dang sbyor//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/ban de Tong Thong thong dgon//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/Cang Hwa hwa 'phongs/</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[15]Rgod sar kyi sde/ban de Tsong Tsheng tshen dgon//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/Cang Kun tse 'phongs/</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/Cang Se'u se'u dgon/</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/Cang 'Bye tig 'phongs/</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/ban de Dwan Ke'u zhi dgon/</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[20] Rgod sar kyi sde/Ba' Kun kun 'phongs/</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/ban de Tong Phug man dgon/</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/Zhim Li the'u 'phongs//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/ban de Cang Le'u cin dgon//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/Zhim Kwon 'ing 'phongs//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[25]Rgod sar kyi sde/ban de Cang Pe'u pe'u dgon//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[26]Pho kwang si'i lha 'bangs/Je'u Tshe tshe 'phongs//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/Dwan Hing dar dgon//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/Zhim Ju ju 'phongs//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/Ser Kun dgon//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[30]Rgod sar kyi sde/Ser Kheng kheng<note type="footnote" n="2">Corrected from<q lang="tib">Tshen tshe</q></note>'phongs 'dzin pa/</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/Shud pu Legs dgon//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/Cang Tsheng tsheng 'phongs/drod pa/</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/Wang Kog ne dgon//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/Cang Zhang tse 'phongs//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[35]Rgod sar kyi sde/ban de Cang La tshir dgon//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/Zhim Hing tse 'phongs//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/ban de Dze'u Kwe kwe dgon//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Cang Tshe'u cung 'phongs//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Pho kwang si'i lha 'bangs Hag Dze'u shun dgon//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[40]Rgod sar kyi sde/Wang Tsheng tsheng 'phongs/</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Leng ho si'i lha 'bangs/Wang Kun tse 'phongs//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/Wang dzin shen dgon//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/Tong Wang 'do 'phongs//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/ban de Li Jing 'an dgon//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[45]Rgod sar kyi sde/Ser Dzin 'in 'phongs//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/Cang Dze tse dgon//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/Cang Gen tse 'phongs//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/ban de Kun tse dgon//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">Rgod sar kyi sde/Tsong Dze tsheng 'phongs//</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[50]Rgod sar kyi sde/Tsong Dze shing dgon g.yon</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[51]tu dbuu ru'i ru 'bring yang Stag legs kyi dar tshan//Dze'u Shib
                  tig dang sbyor//</q></p><p>Verso (in another hand)</p><p><q lang="tib">[1]zhus lags/nga ba(u)s spud/</q></p><p><q lang="tib">[2]Pho tshon bris//</q></p><p><q lang="eng">"[1] The god's servant of<name lang="tib">Pho kwang si</name>,<name lang="tib" type="person">Je'u Zhi nyang</name>,<term lang="tib">'phongs</term>.<name lang="tib" type="place">Rgod sar</name>division,<name lang="tib" type="person">Song Shing</name>,<term lang="tib">dgon</term>. The god's servant
                  of<name lang="tib">Pho kwang si</name>,<name lang="tib" type="person">Yang G.yu
                    tshe</name>,<term lang="tib">'phongs</term>.<name lang="tib" type="place">Rgod
                    sar</name>division,<name lang="tib" type="person">Bam Kun tse</name>,<term lang="tib">dgon</term>, along with<name lang="tib" type="person">'An Dze
                  hing</name>,<term lang="tib">dar tshan</term>of<name lang="tib">Shud pu Legs
                    gzigs</name>, middle left horn.</q></p><p><q lang="eng">. . . . . . .</q></p><p><q lang="eng">[ll.8-9 Red ink]<name lang="tib" type="place">Rgod sar</name>division, middle horn:<name lang="tib">Shud pu Legs gzigs</name>, master and
                  servants, forty, one<term lang="tib">tshar</term>, district list.</q></p><p><q lang="eng">[10]<name lang="tib" type="place">Rgod sar</name>division,<name lang="tib" type="person">'An Dze hing</name>,<term lang="tib">'phongs</term>,
                  along with<name lang="tib" type="person">Bam Kun tse</name>,<term lang="tib">dar
                    tshan</term>of<name lang="tib" type="person">Cang Ka dzo</name>, little right
                  horn.</q></p><p><q lang="eng">. . . . . . .</q></p><p><q lang="eng">[41] The god's servant of<name lang="tib">Leng ho si</name>,<name lang="tib" type="person">Wang Kun tse</name>,<term lang="tib">'phongs</term></q></p><p><q lang="eng">...................................</q></p><p><q lang="eng">[50]<name lang="tib" type="place">Rgod sar</name>division,<name lang="tib" type="person">Tsong Dze shing</name>,<term lang="tib">dgon</term>,
                  along with<name lang="tib" type="person">Dze'u Shib tig</name>,<term lang="tib">dar tshan</term>of<name lang="tib">Stag legs</name>, middle horn of the
                  centre left horn.</q></p><p>(Rev.)<q lang="eng">Submitted. I, son-brother,<name lang="tib" type="person">Pho
                    tshon</name>wrote this."</q></p><p>There would be no purpose in a fuller translation of this document, which has been
                selected as showing clearly the system of the nomenclature. It is, as will be seen,
                simply a list of persons, who are alternately designated<q lang="tib">dgon</q>and<q lang="tib">'phongs</q>. Most of the persons belong to the<q lang="eng">"<name lang="tib" type="place">Rgod sar</name>division (<term lang="tib">sde</term>)"</q>; but four are<q lang="eng">"god's servant"</q>of<name lang="tib">Pho kwang si</name>and<name lang="tib">Leng ho si</name>respectively, these being, no doubt, the<q lang="tib">si</q>(probably Chinese<term lang="chi">ssŭ</term><q lang="eng">"temple"</q>of<name lang="tib">Pho kwang</name>and<name lang="tib">Leng ho</name>respectively (since we already know<name lang="tib">Leng
                ho</name>, p. 46 (IOL Tib J 850).</p><p>The red-ink heading in ll. 8-9 shows that what follows is a district list (<q lang="tib">yul yig</q>) of one<q lang="tib">tshar</q>, forty persons, belonging
                to the<name lang="tib" type="place">Rgod sar</name>division. But the expressions<q lang="eng">"right"</q>and<q lang="eng">"left horn"</q>suggest that it has a
                military significance. There are many indications that the Tibetan military system
                was territorial; and, in fact, we have mention of many regiments bearing the name of
                  districts<note type="footnote" n="3">A list of the regiments will be given later
                  (pp. 455 sqq.). On<name lang="tib">Shud pu</name>see p. 66. Note that not one of
                  the 10<term lang="tib">ban de</term>s is a<term lang="tib">'phongs</term>.</note>; in consequence the word<q lang="tib">sde</q>,<q lang="eng">"district"</q>or<q lang="eng">"division"</q>, has most often to be
                rendered<q lang="eng">"regiment"</q>, and that is, no doubt, the meaning here.
                There are further indications: for besides the<q lang="eng">"horn"</q>(<q lang="tib">ru</q>) and its commander (<term lang="tib">ru dpon</term>), which
                occur several times – on the term<q lang="tib">tshar</q>,<q lang="eng">"parish"</q>, elsewhere evidenced (along with its<term lang="tib">tshar
                dpon</term>), see pp. 169 (M.Tagh.a.iv.0074), 338 (M.I.xii.3, IOL Tib N 520), the<q lang="tib">dar tshan</q><q lang="eng">"silk badge"</q>(<term lang="tib">mtshan</term>) will very likely be
                the banner-bearer: cf.<q lang="tib">dar</q>,<q lang="eng">"banner"</q>, Vol. I,<ref target="Thomas_1935">pp. 277 sqq</ref>. Of the two alternating terms attached
