<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>A Definition of Mahayoga (IOL Tib J 436)</title><author>Sam van Schaik</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Tantric Studies 1</publisher><pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace><date>2008</date></publicationStmt><editionStmt><edition>First electronic edition</edition><date>2012</date><respStmt>Created by Sam van Schaik</respStmt></editionStmt><sourceDesc><p>Published in Sam van Schaik,"A Definition of Mahayoga: Sources from the Dunhuang
                    Manuscripts",<title>Tantric Studies</title>1: 45-88.</p><bibl><ref>vanSchaik_2008</ref></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc>Translation</projectDesc><editorialDecl></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><head><p>"A Summary of the View of Mahāyoga According to Scripture" is substantially the
                longest and most detailed definition of Mahāyoga provided in any of the Dunhuang
                manuscripts. Thus it is one of the most important texts for our understanding of the
                tantric system of Mahāyoga, as it was practised in the 9th and 10th centuries. It is
                found in a single Tibetan manuscript, IOL Tib J 436, which is poorly written and
                physically damaged, and the text is probably missing its opening lines. The Summary
                treats Mahāyoga under four headings: (i) view, (ii) samaya, (iii) union and
                liberation, and (iv) meditation.</p><p>This text comes from a time when Mahāyoga was considered the pinnacle of tantric
                ritual practice, while it was simulataneously in the process of being displaced from
                that position by the developing rubrics of Anuyoga and Atiyoga. At this point the
                latter (Anuyoga and Atiyoga) seem to have been primarily view or theory-based
                approaches, with little or no ritual presence in the manuscripts. Toward the end of
                this period we see a movement towards the stratification of the tantric categories
                of Mahāyoga, Anuyoga and Atiyoga. That trend is best represented in doxographical
                texts and – for Mahāyoga – the central text of this survey, The Summary of the View
                of Mahāyoga According to Scripture.</p><p>Based on the Summary we may offer the following brief definition of Mahāyoga in 10th
                century Tibet:</p><p>1. The theoretical content or view is defined as the ‘single mode’ (tshul gcig) in
                which the buddhas of the five families are embodied in a single deity, usually
                Vajrasattva.</p><p>2. Meditation is defined by the gradual visualization practice of of the three
                concentrations (ting nge 'dzin). These are the concentrations on (i) suchness, (ii)
                total illumination, and (iii) the cause.</p><p>3. Ritual practice is subsumed by the two categories of union and liberation (sbyor
                sgrol), that is, sexual practice with a consort and ritual murder. The Summary
                leaves some room for interpreting these practices metaphorically.</p><p>4. The samaya vows (dam tshig) that bind a practitioner who has received a Mahāyoga
                empowerment comprise three root and twenty-five branch vows.</p><p>5. The result of Mahāyoga practice is defined in a succession of four levels of
                accomplishment known as the four kinds of vidyādhara (rigs 'dzin).</p><p>6. The scriptural group associated with Mahāyoga is the ‘eighteen tantras’, although
                the content of this group is uncertain.</p><p>In the transcription, that follows the translation, I have attempted to provide a
                clear reading of the manuscript without over-correcting the archaic orthography. In
                most cases the divergences from classical orthography (eg.<term>rin cen</term>,<term>dam tsig</term>) are self-explanatory. I have made a very few insertions
                (marked by square brackets) where these seemed necessary to make the reading more
                clear.</p><p>Conventions:</p><p>- - deleted in original manuscript</p><p>+ + inserted in original manuscript</p><p>... lost due to manuscript damage</p><p>{ } unclear reading</p><p>[ ] inserted by the present editor</p></head><body><msDescription n="1"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">IOL Tib J 436</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title>A Summary of the View of Mahāyoga According to Scripture</title><q lang="eng"><p><lb n="1r"></lb>Now, the view of Mahāyoga. What is the view of the
                                five families as a single mode? When the great elements are subsumed
                                into one, they exist in utter perfection. This is the female deity.
                                The forms that come into being from them are the male deity: he who
                                is called Totally Illuminating (Vairocana). As he cannot be carried
                                off by external forces, he is known as The Immoveable (Akṣobya). As
                                he fulfills all wishes, he is known as The Jewel-Born
                                (Ratnasambhava). As he goes to the realms of light he is known as
                                Limitless Light (Amitābha).<lb n="1v"></lb>As ... he is known as
                                Meaningful Accomplishment (Amoghasiddhi). The five families are, in
                                this way, a single mode.</p><p>What are the relevant samaya? One should gather the samaya in order
                                to embrace that which is concordant, in order to restrain that which
                                is discordant, and in order to obtain and accomplish. The 28 samaya
                                are the transmitted precepts. According to the esoteric instructions
                                these are grouped into three. This one should know. What are they?
                                They are:</p><p>(i) The samaya of view.</p><p>(ii) The samaya of practice.</p><p>(iii) The samaya of accomplishment.</p><p>Now to distinguish these. The samaya of mind (not disseminating the
                                secret instruction to others) and the five aspects to be known, are
                                the samaya of the view. The samaya of the body (not developing
                                ill-will or scorn towards the vajra master and brothers and sisters)
                                and the five samaya to be practised, and the five samaya not to be
                                renounced, are the samaya of practice. The samaya of speech (not
                                ceasing in the mantras and mudrās) and the five samaya to be
                                accomplished, are the samaya of accomplishment.<lb n="2r"></lb>The
                                unsurpassable fruit of these three is the nature of
                                accomplishment.</p><p>The union of Mahāyoga is called "the union of the vajra and the
                                lotus." It is also threefold:</p><p>(i) The union in the single ornament.</p><p>(ii) The union of the five families in a single mode.</p><p>(iii) Indiscriminate union.</p><p>One should know that each of these has four parts:</p><p>(i) Union.</p><p>(ii) Subsequent union.</p><p>(iii) Total union.</p><p>(iv) Universal union.</p><p>Of these, meditating on oneself as the deity is union. Subsequent
                                union is developing the wisdom being at one's heart. Total union is
                                the unshakeable great bliss of the descent of the bodhicitta of the
                                union of vajra and lotus. Universal union is projection and
                                absorption, conferring empowerment upon limitless sentient beings,
                                each in their particular deity family.<lb n="2v"></lb></p><p>When [practising] union in Mahāyoga, the qualities of greatness are
                                said to be:</p><p>(i) Subduing the four Māras</p>.<p>(ii) Playing with the five space
                                mistresses.</p><p>(iii) Possessing the four secret consorts.</p><p>The four Māras are:</p><p>(i) Māra the aggregates.</p><p>(ii) Māra the afflications.</p><p>(iii) Māra the god.</p><p>(iv) Māra the lord of death.</p><p>Of these, the phase of meditation on the mahāmudrā of the deity's
                                body is called conquering Māra the aggregates. The phase of the
                                unshakeable great bliss of bodhicitta is called conquering Māra the
                                afflictions because the mind of the three times does not arise. The
                                phase of acting for the benefit of sentient beings is called
                                conquering Māra the god. The phase of experiencing the savour of
                                bodhicitta, which transcends birth and death, is called conquering
                                Māra the lord of death.</p><p><lb n="3r"></lb>The five space mistresses are:</p><p>(i) The vajra space mistress.</p><p>(ii) The lotus space mistress.</p><p>(iii) The jewel space mistress.</p><p>(iv) The karma space mistress.</p><p>(v) The airborne space mistress.</p><p>Of these, the male is called the vajra space mistress and the female
                                is called the lotus space mistress. The phase of unshakeable great
                                bliss which is the descent of bodhicitta endowed with the vajra and
                                the lotus is called the jewel space mistress. The phase of activity
                                for the benefit of sentient beings [by] projecting and absorbing the
                                bodhicitta is called the karma space mistress. And thus making all
                                bodhicitta of one taste without it bursting out is called the
                                airborne space mistress.</p><p>The four secret consorts are:</p><p>(i) The Lady of Mudrā.</p><p>(ii) The Lady of Intoxication.</p>(<p>iii) The Lady of Eating.</p><p>(iv) The Lady who Prolongs Life.</p><p>Of these, the body of the consort is known as the Lady of Mudrā. The
                                unshakeable great bliss of bodhicitta is known as the Lady of
                                Intoxication<lb n="3v"></lb>. Experiencing the savour as
                                bodhicitta, or alternatively accepting and eating, is known as the
                                Lady of Eating. The phase of obtaining the praiseworthy qualities of
                                bodhicitta is known as the Lady who Prolongs Life because it
                                transcends birth and death.</p><p>The liberation of Mahāyoga is said to comprise:</p><p>(i) Liberation of oneself.</p><p>(ii) Liberation of others.</p><p>Of these, liberation of oneself comprises:</p><p>(i) Approaching the deity.</p><p>(ii) Clarifying the tantras.</p><p>Of these, in approaching the deity the measure of accomplishment is
                                the ability to levitate up to four finger-widths. And clarifying the
                                tantras means becoming learned in the eighteen tantras, or
                                alternatively it indicates the sages who possess the transmitted
                                precepts and esoteric instructions. The liberation of others means
                                that having assembled many such great lords, those in the category
                                of the ten fields are placed into the maṇḍala of the heroes. Within
                                the circle they are liberated to bring them into accord with
                                others.</p><p>Meditation, via the gradual development of the three aspects of
                                Mahāyoga, is as follows:<lb n="4r"></lb></p><p>(i) One begins with meditation on the dharmatā.</p><p>(ii) One then meditates on the unassailable total illumination.</p><p>(iii) One then meditates on the causal concentration.</p><p>Here ends<title>A Summary of the View of Mahāyoga According to
                                Scripture</title>.</p></q><p></p><q lang="tib"><lb n="1r"></lb>bsgom pa/ 'di//de la ma ha yo ga'i lta/rIg-s- lnga
                            tshul gcIg tu lta -b-gang zhe na//'byung ba ched po la gcig gi nang na
                            //kun rdzogs par yod pa nI//yum yin la/de las gzugs su red pa nI/yab ste
                            rnam par snang mdzad//ces bya//de nyid gzhan gyis myI 'phrogs pa ni myI
                            bskyod pa zhes bya//de thams cad re ba yid bzhin du skong ba ni//rin
                            -ce- cen 'byung ldan zhes [b]ya {snang zhing song bas ni snang} [ba
                            mtha' yas] zhes bya// ... thams cad ... nI {gyis}// ...<lb n="1v"></lb>... nI// {don yod grub pa zhes} bya //rig[s] lnga de ltar tshul gcig
                            go//de la {rtse}'i phyo[gs] dam tsig ce na//'dra bar dkra' ba'i phyIr
                            dang/ myi 'dra bar sdom ba'i phyIr dang//thob -par- cing grub pa'I phyir
                            dam tsig tseg bya/'o//de la dam tsig nyi shu rtsa brgyad nI//lung yin la
                            man ngag gIs ni gsu du 'dus pa shes gpar bya ste//dpe yang gang zhe
                            na//lta ba'i dam tsig dang/spyod pa'i dam tshig dang//bsgrub pa'i dam
                            tsig go//de la dbyen thugs kyi dam tsig gsang ba'i man ngag//gzhan la
                            myi spel ba dang//shes par bya ba'I dam tsig la ni/lta ba'i dam tsig go
                            sku'i dam tsig -ni- rdo rje slobs dpon dang/mched lcam dral la ngan sems
                            dang spyad sems myi bskyed pa dang//spyad par bya {du} dang/myi spang ba
                            lnga ste/spyad pa'i dam tsig go//gsung gi dam tsig sngags phyag rgya
                            rgyun myi gcad pa dang/ grub par bya ba<lb n="2r"></lb>dam tsig lnga
                            nI bsgrub pa'i dam tsig go//'di gsum ya char ma gyur pa'i 'bras bu nI
                            grub pa'I rang bzhin no// de la maha yo ga'i/sbyor ba nI//rdo rje dang
                            pad mor sbyor ba zhes bya//de la yang gsum ste//rgyan cig par sbyor ba
                            dang/rIgs lnga tshul gcig par sbyor ba dang//phyal bar sbyor ba'o//de
                            yang re re la bzhi bzhir shes par ba ste//sbyor ba dang/rjes su sbyor ba
                            dang/rab tu sbyor ba dang/kun tu sbyor ba'o//de la bdag lhar sgom pa
                            ni/sbyor ba'o//rjes su sbyor ba nI//ye shes sems pa thugs kar bskyed
                            pa'o//rab tu sbyor ba ni rdo rje dang pad mor sbyor ba'i byang chub
                            sems/babs pa'i bde ba chen po myi g.yo ba'o//kun tu sbyor ba nI 'phro
                            'dus/sems can -gi don- rgya mtsho rigs su [r]es par dbang bskur
                            ba'o//[de] la maha yo ga'i sbyor ba'i<lb n="2v"></lb>[d]u[s]//ch[e]
                            ba'i yon tan n[i] bdud bzhi bcom ba dang//dbyings phyug ma lnga la rol
                            pa dang/gsang ba'i yum bzhi dang ldan no zhes byung ste//de la bdud bzhI
                            ni/pung po'i bdud dang/nyon mongs pa'i bdud dang/shi bdag gi bdugd dang/
                            lha'I bdud do//de la lha'I +sku+ phyag rgya chen por sgom pa'I dus
                            na//pung po'i bdud bcom zhes bya//byang chub kyi sems bde ba ched po myi
                            g.yo ba'i dus na//dus suṃ gi sems myi 'byng bas//nyon mongs pa'i bdud
                            bcom zhes bya//byang chub kyi sems kyi 'phro 'dus/sems can gi don byas
                            pa'i dus na//lha'i bdud bcom zhes bya//byang chub kyi sems kyi ro tsor
                            pa'i dus na//skye shi las 'das pa'i shI bdag gi bdud bcom zhes bya//de
                            la dbyings phyug<lb n="3r"></lb>ma lnga la//rdo rje dang pad mo'i
                            dbyIngs phyug ma dang//rin chen dbyIngs phyug ma dang/las kyi dbyIngs
                            phyug ma dang/mkha' dbyings phyug ma zhes bya'o//de la yab ni rdo rje
                            dbyings phyug ma zhes bya//yuṃ ni pad mo dbyings phyug ma zhes bya/ rdo
                            rje dang pad mor ldan pa'i byang chub kyi sems babs pa'i bde ba ched po
                            myi g.yo ba'i dus na//rin cen dbyings phyug ma zhes bya'o//byang chub
                            kyi sems kyi 'phro 'dus sems can gyi don byas pa'i dus na//las kyi
                            dbyings phyug ma zhes bya//de lta bas na//byang chub kyi sems kun ro
                            gcig par byas pa ni/ma brdos pa yin bas mkha' la dbyings phyug ma zhe
                            bya/ de la gsang ba'i yuṃ bzhi ni/phyag rgya mo dag rmongs byed mo
                            dang/za ba mo dang/rmongs byed tshe 'phel mo zhes bya//de la yuṃ kyi
                            {sku} nI phyag rgya ma zhes bya// byang chub kyi sems bde ba ched po myi
                            g.yo ba nI [rm]o[ng]s [byed mo//byang] chub kyi se[ms]<lb n="3v"></lb>su ro tshor ba 'am/yang na blangs te za ba ni/za ba mo zhes bya ba/byang
                            chub kyi sems ky[i] y[o]n tan bsngags po thob pa'[i] dus na//skye shi
                            las 'das pas tshe 'phel ma zhes bya//de la maha yo ga'i sgom pa ni//bdag
                            bsgral ba dang/ gzhan bsgral ba -'o-//zhes bya'o//de la bdag bsgral ba
                            ni/lha nye ba dang/rgyud gsal ba 'o/de la lha nye ba ni grub [4] pa'i
                            tshad de//sor bzhi yan cad nam ka la 'pag nus pa dang//rgyud gsal pa ni
                            rgyud bco brgyad la mkhas par gyur pa 'am//yang na lung dang man ngag
                            dang ldan pa'i skyes bu rnams la bya//gzhan pa sgral ba ni//de lta bu'i
                            dbang phyug ched po du -me- zhig 'tshogs nas//zhing bcu rim pa dang ldan
                            pa'i rnams dpa' bo'i dkyil 'khor du sbyar ba'o//bskor na mthun 'jug
                            'tsha-l-m pa'i sgrol ba'o//mā ha yo ga'i rnam sum rims kyis<lb n="4r"></lb>bskyed nas/bsgoms/pa ni//dang po chos nyid sgom pa ste gcig//de
                            nas kun tu snang ba'i myI brdos par bsgom ba dang gnyis/de nas rgyu'i ti
                            nge 'dzin sgom pa dang gsuṃ mo//maha yo ga'i lta ba lung du bsdus pa
                            rdzogs so//</q></msItem></msContents></msDescription></body></text></TEI.2>
