<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>A Chinese Pilgrim's Letters of Passage</title><author>Sam van Schaik</author><author>Imre Galambos</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>IDP</publisher><pubPlace>http://idp.bl.uk</pubPlace><date>2012</date></publicationStmt><editionStmt><edition>First electronic edition</edition><date>2005</date><respStmt>Created by Sam van Schaik</respStmt></editionStmt><sourceDesc><p>Published in Sam van Schaik and Imre Galambos,<title>Manuscripts and Travellers:
                        The Sino-Tibetan Documents of a Tenth-Century Buddhist Pilgrim</title>,
                    Berlin, de Gruyter, 2012.</p><bibl><ref>vanSchaik_Galambos_2012</ref></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc>Translation</projectDesc><editorialDecl></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><head><p>This is a translation and transcription of five letters of passage, written for a
                Chinese monk in the late tenth century, for his journey through Tibetan regions of
                what are now the Chinese provinces of Qinghai and Gansu. The letters are found on
                the first part of the manuscript, IOL Tib J 754(A). This scroll was found glued
                together with two other manuscripts that the pilgrim acquired on his travels. The
                longest part is IOL Tib J 754(B), with a Chinese sūtra on the recto and Tibetan
                tantric texts on the verso. Finally, the smallest part is IOL Tib J 754(C), which
                has a Chinese text commemorating the building of a monastery near Liangzhou, which
                turns out to be a copy of an inscription from the early seventh century. Crucially,
                the colophon to this manuscript states that the copy was made in 968 by the monk
                Daozhao, thus providing us with a date and a name.</p><p>The letters are written to a conventional pattern, with the exception of Letter 2,
                which has no addressee and is therefore an open rather than personal letter. The
                personal letters begin with the name or title of the addressee, followed by a phrase
                literally meaning “from the presence of ...” (<term lang="tib">zha snga nas</term>)
                but effectively meaning “addressed to ....” Then we have the name of the author of
                the letter, followed by the phrase “a letter submitted by ...” (<term lang="tib">mchid gsol ba</term>). This is followed by a polite enquiry regarding whether
                the addressee is fatigued or not. It is interesting that in our letters the enquiry
                about fatigue specifically addresses fatigue caused by meditation. This may be a
                variation on the formula, used when the addressee is a monk. Another apparently
                formulaic feature of the letters is the phrase “consider your commitments” (<term lang="tib">thugs dam la dgongs pa</term>), which appears toward the end of
                Letters 1, 3 and 5. This may have been a standard conclusion to a request directed
                at a monk</p><p>The letters of passage are undoubtedly an important historical
                source. They contain information about the Tibetan-ruled areas of Qinghai and Gansu
                not found anywhere else. Their date, from the late 960s, falls at the end of a
                historical ‘dark period’ for this region, when both Tibet and China were politically
                fragmented. The document offers no narrative as such, but is a primary source of
                information on regional towns, rulers, monasteries and monks. Earlier, in chapter 3,
                we followed the pilgrim’s route as outlined in the second letter – beginning in
                Wutaishan, and then travelling to Hezhou, Dantig Shan, Tsongka, Liangzhou, Ganzhou
                and Shazhou, with the ultimate destination being Nālandā in India. The places in
                which these letters were written surely overlap to some extent with this itinerary,
                although clear indications of the location of their authors are unfortunately
                lacking.</p><p>Note on transcriptions:</p><p>{} = uncertain reading</p><p>[] = transcribed by Thomas but now illegible</p><p>++ = addition</p></head><body><msDescription n="1"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein</collection><idno type="current">IOL Tib J 754(A)</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title>First Letter</title><q lang="eng"><p>This is addressed to the residence of the great master Yönten Chog:
                                Toleu Tagsum inquires regarding your health. According to what you
                                said in the letter brought by your servant, your body is not
                                fatigued by your meditation, and your authority is undiminished. In
                                this letter I enquire devotedly about your health, and ask how I may
                                fulfil your commands.</p><p>May I ask a favour regarding a Chinese monk who has been in my
                                presence? The monk wishes to go to India to see the relics of
                                Śākyamuni. If the abbot were to travel across to Liangzhou [with the
                                monk] it would not be such a great burden. If [the abbot] cannot
                                travel there, then a servant could accompany the monk. I beg you to
                                consider your commitments. The monk will give you more detailed
                                information.</p><p>Furthermore, this is addressed to the residence of the abbot: if
                                this letter comes to you, and you do comply with this request
                                immediately, it would be improper not to send back a letter of
                                confirmation. If you have complied with this request, please do so
                                by summer this year.</p></q><p></p><q lang="tib"><p><lb n="1"></lb>@// slobs dpon chen po yon tan mchog bzhugs pi zha snga
                                nas / /to le’u stag gsum gis snying gsol ba/ /zha ‘bring<lb n="2"></lb>[‘dab na]s ‘drul ba la mchid gis rmas na/ /dgongs pas sku
                                mnyel ma lags pa/ mnga’ tang la ‘grib pa myi mnga’<lb n="3"></lb>[bar khums/ /] mchid yi ge las gus pas snyun gsol zhing mchis/ bkas
                                rma bar ci gnang/<lb n="4"></lb>@// [na] gsol ba’/ rgya hwa shang
                                de spya ngar [deletion: brmangs] pa’i don ni/ hwa shang de rgya gar<lb n="5"></lb>yul du [shag kya] thub pa’i gdung len du mchi
                                lags na/ phar leng cur mkhan po gshegs pa lags<lb n="6"></lb>na
                                thugs khral cher myi mdzad kha ma mchis/ nyid myi gshegs na zha
                                ‘bring gcig gis hwa shang de leng chur<lb n="7"></lb>phyin bar myi
                                skye[l] kha ma mchis/ thugs dam la dgongs par gsol/ zhib tu hwa
                                shang kho bdag la spring//<lb n="8"></lb>@//slad na mkhen po
                                bzhugs pi zha snga nas/ mchid phrin de dang mjal ba lags na/ [?] /
                                do cig bzo<lb n="9"></lb>de bgyid pa’ lags na/ ‘drul ba la bka’
                                spring nges pa cig myi brdzang du myi rung/<lb n="10"></lb>bzo
                                bgyid par gyur na dbyar lo la ‘grub par bgyi//</p></q></msItem><msItem n="2"><title>Second Letter</title><q lang="eng"><p>This is a petition from the patron Ngog Luzhi Namka. A
                                Chinese monk from China who is unequalled as a great ascetic, a
                                great scholar and a great upholder of virtue is going to India to
                                see the sites of Śākyamuni. His route is as follows. Proceeding from
                                Wutaishan he arrived at the gold and turquoise halls of Hezhou;
                                after that he arrived at the mountain of Dantig Shan; after that he
                                arrived at the gold and turquoise halls of Tsongka; after that he
                                will arrive at the palace of Liangzhou; after that he will arrive at
                                the castle of Ganzhou; after that he will arrive at Shazhou. After
                                that he will certainly go to see the great teachers of Śrī Nālandā
                                and the relics of Śākyamuni at the Vulture’s Peak in India.</p><p>Up to this point [in the monk’s journey] both Chinese and Tibetans
                                have [treated him] honourably... and conducted him stage by stage.
                                From this point onward, ... [he should be treated] honourably. Treat
                                him as an object of veneration and conduct him stage by stage. [If]
                                anyone harms him or obstructs his virtuous activities, be they
                                Chinese or Tibetan, ... the news will carried away on the winds to
                                the ten directions. This is Namka’s message: let nobody hurt [the
                                monk]!</p></q><p></p><q lang="tib"><p><lb n="1"></lb>@//://yon dag ngogs lu zhi nam kas gsol ba rgya yul nas rgya ‘i hwa
                                shang rka thub chen po<lb n="2"></lb>mkhas pa ched po btsun chen
                                gong na myed pa gcig rgya gar yul na dpal shag kya<lb n="3"></lb>thub pa’i yul na thong du mchi ba lags so /lam ni ‘go de shan nas
                                mchis nas /<lb n="4"></lb>ga cu gser khang g.yu gang lam byung de
                                nas ri dan tig shan du byung de nes[=nas] tsong ka<lb n="5"></lb>gser kang g.yu khang du byung de nas le{ng} cu khab du ’byung de nas
                                kam cu mkhar<lb n="6"></lb>du ’byung ngo /de nas sha cu {rtsags
                                ’byung ngo} /de nas rgya gar yul na /dpal shi lin na len tra<lb n="7"></lb>{slob pa ched po} dang bya rgod {phags ri} la bcom
                                ldan ‘das shag kya thub pa’i {zha} ...<lb n="8"></lb>mthong du
                                {mchi bar} nges so /’di man chad rgya bod byin gyis kyang gar ...
                                {chad} ...<lb n="9"></lb>... {s..ching..g} dang /su skyal rim par
                                ba gyi+s pa lags so /de yan chad du yod ...<lb n="10"></lb>byin
                                gyi [brlabs] {kyang} /’di gar bab par mchod nas su bgyi ba dang
                                {bsu} skyel [rim par] ...<lb n="11"></lb>mdzo{ng} ... la gnod pa
                                byed pa ‘am dge ‘i bar cad byed pa gcig bod {pa} rgya [na]g<lb n="12"></lb>gnyis kyang ...[thams] cad kyi phyogs bcu nas sngag
                                kyi thun phab la rlung bskur<lb n="13"></lb>la gtang ngo// ...
                                //de ltar ni nam kas spring ngo /su yang ma gtse cig // .... //</p></q></msItem><msItem n="3"><title>Third Letter</title><q lang="eng"><p>This is addressed to the great teacher: a petitioning letter from
                                Markham Rinchen Dorje. Please write a letter to say whether your
                                body has been weakened by your profound meditation and whether, even
                                though there are no obstacles to your meditation on the nature of
                                reality (dharmatā), your precious self may have fallen ill.</p><p>On to other matters. A Chinese monk who is learned and an upholder of
                                virtue is travelling from China to India to pay homage to the relics
                                of Śākyamuni. It would be improper not to escort him to the Dayun
                                monastery. Consider your commitments.</p></q><p></p><q lang="tib"><p><lb n="1"></lb>st[o]n chen po’i zha sngar// //<lb n="2"></lb>smar kham
                                rin chen rdo rjes mchid gsol ba/<lb n="3"></lb>dgongs pa zab mo’i
                                sku ma nye{l} n... dang/ chos {nyid} kyi dgongs {la} {myi} la bar
                                myi mnga’<lb n="4"></lb>rin po che sku la snyun bzhes sam ma
                                bzhes// {yi ge las snyun gsol zhing mchis}<lb n="5"></lb>slad na
                                rgya yul nas hwa shang btsun ba {mkhas pa} la bul du gyis ... // ...
                                {rgya gar} nas<lb n="6"></lb>rgya gar gi yul du /bcom {ldan ‘das}
                                shag kya thub pa {gdung la phyag} tshal du mchi<lb n="7"></lb>ba
                                ‘di /’sprin chen gtsug lag khang du myi bskyal du myi rung // thugs
                                dam la dgongs//</p></q></msItem><msItem n="4"><title>Fourth Letter</title><q lang="eng"><p>This is addressed to the great elders and the great monks of the
                                Longxing temple: a petitioning letter from Mog Bumdag. According to
                                previous letters that have gone back and forth [between us], I hear
                                that you have no injuries or disease and your bodies as valuable as
                                gemstones are free from infirmity. Please send a letter about your
                                health.</p><p>On to other matters. A monk from the empire of China, a great
                                upholder of virtue, is going to the land of India in order to see
                                the face of Śākyamuni. Up to this point we lowly ones, the spiritual
                                guides of Serpa, have escorted him stage by stage. Therefore the
                                spiritual guides who consider their vows of benevolence, the ... [of
                                the] kingdom, the uncle-ministers and the rest should consider their
                                vows and the kingdom. Escorting [the monk] by stages, take him to
                                the Dayun monastery. It would be improper not to do so. I ask those
                                in the religious and the secular spheres to consider this.</p></q><p></p><q lang="tib"><p><lb n="1"></lb>{lung} song lha gang gi gnas brtan ched po ban de ched po’i zha
                                sngar//<lb n="2"></lb>dmog ‘bum bdag gis mchid gsol pa’<lb n="3"></lb>snga slad ‘drul ba’i ... mchid kyis rmas {nad} ... {ma nges
                                pas} lags pa na dbyigsu gces pa’i sku la<lb n="4"></lb>sku snyung
                                myi mnga’ bar khums / mchid gi yi ge la ... snyung gsol zhing [...ci
                                gnang / slad na] rgya’i rgyal<lb n="5"></lb>‘khams nas hwa shang
                                btsun pa ched {po} zhig {pu} rgya gar gi yul du shag kya thub pa’i
                                zhal mthong {du} mchi ba lags /<lb n="6"></lb>‘di tshun chad du
                                yang bdag cag {ngan} pa {gser} pa’i dge ba’i bshes gnyen {rnams kyis
                                kyang} bskyal rim par<lb n="7"></lb>[bgyis pa lags/ de yang de
                                phan chad du yang thugs dam la dgongs pa ‘i] dge ba’i bshes nyen
                                dang<lb n="8"></lb>[chab srid] ...gs {rin} zhang lon rga las
                                stsogs pa rnams kyis kyang / de bzhin du thugs dam dang chab srid la<lb n="9"></lb>[dgongs] ste bsu bskyal rim pa ra[=par]
                                [deleted: myi mdzad du myi rung] +mdzad nas sprin chen gtsug lag
                                khang du myi bskyal du myi rung+ // //lha myi phyogs kyang de bzhin
                                du dgongs par gsol</p></q></msItem><msItem n="5"><title>Fifth Letter</title><q lang="eng"><p>This is addressed to the lords of the teachings and the monastic
                                community, they who unite the sun and the moon, the sublime
                                ornaments of Jambudvīpa, the assembly of teachers who [venerate]
                                their precious enlightened masters and who single-mindedly carry out
                                their commitments: a petitioning letter from Dmog ‘bum bdag.
                                According to what has been said in the previous letters that have
                                gone back and forth [between us], your meditative activities of
                                maintaining all the vehicles, ... becoming accomplished,
                                single-mindedly [carrying out] your vows have not fatigued your
                                bodies. I hear that your precious bodies, as valuable as gemstones,
                                are free from infirmity. I request with devotion a letter from the
                                thirty great emanations.</p><p>On to other matters. A monk coming from the presence of the Chinese
                                emperor Tong kun, a great ascetic and a particularly fine scholar,
                                is going to India to see the face of Śākyamuni. Up to this point we
                                the monks of the Serpa thousand district have escorted him stage by
                                stage. Accordingly, from this point onward, [avoiding] unhappiness,
                                not to consider your commitments and conduct him to the monastic
                                estate of Longxing would be improper. It would be improper for any
                                in the religious and secular spheres not to consider
                            likewise.</p></q><p></p><q lang="tib"><p><lb n="1"></lb>@ bstan pa {dang dge’ ‘dun} gi mnga’ bdag /gnyi zla ‘od sbyor gi
                                rkyen /’dzam bu gling [rgya]n dam pa’ /slob ched po byang chub<lb n="2"></lb>rin po ches ...r du mdzad pa /thugs dam rtse gcig du
                                mdzad pa’i dg[e ba’i bshes gny]en sde tsogs kyi zha sngar// //<lb n="3"></lb>dmog ‘bum bdag gis mchid gsol bas/ /snga slad ‘drul
                                ba las mchid kyis {rmas} pa/ /spyi’i theg pa bskyang<lb n="4"></lb>ba dang [‘grub mang po] {chen po} {rkyen} du ‘gyur ba dang /thugs
                                dam rtse gcig du mdzad pa’i dgongs pas sku mnyel ba ma lags<lb n="5"></lb>pa / {sku ri}n po che dbyigs gces pa ma snyun [myi
                                mnga’ ba] khums /’sprul chen sum cu las gus par snying gsol<lb n="6"></lb>{bar} mchis / / [sla]d nas tong kun rgya rje’i spya
                                nga nas / hwa shang dka thub ched po mkhas pa’i phul du phyin pa cig<lb n="7"></lb>{rgya gar gi} yul du shag kya thub pa’i {zhal}
                                mthong du mchi ba lags /’di tshun chad du bdag cag gser ba stong
                                sde’i<lb n="8"></lb>{dge slong} rnams kyis kyang /bsu [deletion:
                                bskyal rim pas bgyis /] de phan chad du yang de bzhin thugs khral<lb n="9"></lb>... nas /thugs dam la dgongs pa ste /lung song
                                gi lha sde’i stsam du myi bskyal du myi rung// //<lb n="10"></lb>lha myi phyogs kyang de bzhin du myi dgongs su myi rung//</p></q></msItem></msContents></msDescription></body></text></TEI.2>
