<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>A narrative of the first teaching of the Bhadracaryā-praṇidhānarāja
                    (Pelliot tibétain 149)</title><author>Sam van Schaik</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Journal of the International Association of Buddhist Studies
                    30/1-2</publisher><pubPlace>Leiden</pubPlace><date>2007</date></publicationStmt><editionStmt><edition>First electronic edition</edition><date>2012</date><respStmt>Created by Sam van Schaik</respStmt></editionStmt><sourceDesc><p>Published in Sam van Schaik and Lewis Doney,"The Prayer, the Priest and the
                    Tsenpo: An Early Buddhist Narrative from Dunhuang",<title>Journal of the
                        International Association of Buddhist Studies</title>30/1-2: 177–217.</p><bibl><ref>vanSchaik_Doney_2007</ref></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc>Translation</projectDesc><editorialDecl></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><head><p>The manuscript presented in translation here, Pelliot tibétain 149, contains a brief
                historical narrative that illustrates the change from imperial to religious history
                in Tibet. The text probably dates from sometime
                between the late ninth and late tenth centuries, within Tibet’s ‘time of
                fragmentation.’ This period is often depicted in traditional and modern scholarship
                as a ‘dark age;’ indeed, owing to the paucity of historical literature from the
                period, it has been difficult to identify the sources for the early chos ’byung
                accounts. Thus the narrative in Pelliot tibétain 149 might be helpful in this
                regard; though it cannot be identified as a direct source for any of the extant
                Buddhist histories, it may be considered the kind of source that historians of the
                eleventh century onward would have utilized.</p><p>Pelliot tibétain 149 is actually the narrative setting for a single Buddhist text, a
                prayer known as the<title lang="san">Bhadracaryā-praṇidhāna</title>. This
                narrative, like the later Tibetan Buddhist histories, begins in India, and continues
                through to the imperial period in Tibet, specifically the period of the reign of
                Tsenpo Khri Srong lde brtsan (r. c.754–797?). Also in line with most of the later
                histories, but unlike the Old Tibetan Annals or Old Tibetan Chronicle, Pelliot
                tibétain 149’s narrative focuses on religious lineage rather than royal
                succession.</p><p>The manuscript contains the story of Sudhana’s quest for the<title lang="san">Bhadracaryā-praṇidhāna</title>, which leads him to the bodhisattvas Mañjuśrī
                and Samantabhadra. Obtaining the prayer from the lat- ter, he is able to reach the
                spiritual level (bhūmi) of ‘utter joy.’ The scene of the narrative then shifts to
                Tibet, where the prayer is trans- lated into Tibetan as part of the great
                translation project undertak- en during the reign of Tsenpo Khri Srong lde brtsan.
                The tsenpo’s priest, Dba’ Dpal byams, has a dream, which the Indian abbot
                Bodhisattva (known in other historical sources as Śāntarakṣita) inter- prets. The
                dream indicates that Dba’ Dpal byams must recite the<title lang="san">Bhadracaryā-praṇidhāna</title>for three days and nights. Dba’ Dpal byams fails
                to uphold this commitment, and so asks Khri Srong lde brtsan if he can go to a more
                spiritually conducive place. With the tsenpo’s blessing he travels towards the caves
                of ’Ching pu, where he meets two Tibetan monks who have experienced omens indicating
                that they should meet up with Dba’ Dpal byams. The three travel together and,
                reciting the prayer, ascend to the pure land of Sukhāvati.</p></head><body><msDescription n="1"><msIdentifier><settlement>Paris</settlement><repository>Bibliothèque nationale de France</repository><collection>Pelliot</collection><idno type="current">Pelliot tibétain 149</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title>The narrative of the first teaching of the
                            Āryabhadracaryāpraṇidhānarāja</title><q lang="eng"><p>There was the son of a śreṣṭhin called Sudhana. Because his intellect became supremely sharp, he learned by heart an inconceivable amount of the concise and extensive [teachings of] the sublime
                                dharma. After that, his faith became supremely great. Since he had
                                not yet received the<text>Āryabhadracaryāpraṇidhāna</text>, he went to see 101
                                spiritual friends. All of them said, “I don’t know [it], and since I
                                don’t, you are not destined to be my disciple.” The distance between
                                [each of] these spiritual friends was a half-day’s journey for a
                                horseman, a whole day’s journey on foot.</p><p>[Sudhana] met 100
                                teachers, and [then] saw the face of Mañjuśrī. He requested [the
                                prayer] from Mañjuśrī, who said: “I don’t know [it], and since I
                                don’t, you are not destined to be my disciple. In India, in
                                Mahābodhidvīpa, lives Samantabhadra. Make a request to Ārya
                                Samantabhadra.” This was his prophecy.</p><p>Then the son of a
                                śreṣṭhin called Sudhana [went and] made the request to Ārya
                                Samantabhadra in Mahabodhidvīpa. Ārya Samantabhadra said: “It is
                                contained in the<text>Ārya Gaṇḍavyūha</text>, also known as the<text>Buddhāvataṃsaka</text>,
                                the<text>Mang po ’dus pa</text>, the<text>Rdza plags pa</text>, the<text>Snyan gi gong rgyan</text>and
                                the<text>Rma ga chad</text>.” And he taught it. Afterwards the son of a śreṣṭhin
                                called Sudhana received [the prayer] as a commitment and practised
                                it ardently. As a result he saw the first bhūmi, ‘utter joy.’ In the
                                same way, others in India took the<text>Āryabhadracaryāpraṇidhāna</text>as a
                                commitment and consequently achieved the siddhi of
                                Samantabhadra.</p><p>Subsequent to that, [the<text>Āryabhadracaryāpraṇidhāna</text>] was translated by Ska ba’ Dpal rtsags,
                                Cog ro Klu’i rgyal mtshan and Rma Rad na ya kra, among others. In
                                the lifetime of tsenpo Khri Srong lde brtsan, the tsenpo’s
                                commitment-holder, a certain Dba’ Dpal byams, received [the<text>Āryabhadracaryāpraṇidhāna</text>] as a commitment, and afterwards, one
                                night in a dream, saw crowds of people in a series of seven golden
                                courtyards. When [Dba’ Dpal byams] petitioned the tsenpo, the tsenpo
                                could not interpret [the dream]. Not far away there was an Indian
                                abbot called Bodhisattva, and the tsenpo asked him, “If someone
                                dreams a dream like this, what does it mean?”</p><p>The Indian
                                abbot asked the tsenpo, “Who was it [that had the dream]?”</p><p>“He is a student of mine, a monk.” replied [the tsenpo].</p><p>[The
                                abbot] then commanded “He should recite<text>Āryabhadracaryāpraṇidhāna</text>and thereby gain the siddhi of Ārya Samantabhadra.” Then the
                                tsenpo repeated this to Master Dpal byams, and the abbot explained
                                extensively that [Dba’ Dpal byams] should chant for more than three
                                days and three nights.</p><p>Not long afterwards, [Dba’ Dpal byams]
                                made a request to the tsenpo: “Since I am emaciated and my
                                aggregates have deteriorated, I have not been properly upholding my
                                commitment to the tsenpo. Therefore may I have permission to travel
                                to a holy place?” Straight away [the tsenpo and Dba’ Dpal byams]
                                left Lha sa [and] Bsam yas [respectively] and travelled a half-day’s
                                journey for a horseman, a whole day’s journey on foot. At Spa dro
                                temple [Dba’ Dpal byams] was encouraged by the tsenpo again. They
                                each placed a hand on the other’s heart and recited the prayer. Then
                                [the tsenpo] left.</p><p>Not much later, at a nearby place called
                                ’Ching pu brag rgye’u, lived Ngan lam Rgyal mchog, the younger
                                brother of Ngan lam Stag sgra klu gong. At Sho ma la lived the
                                Master Sgro snya ye shes byang chub. [One day] these two had certain
                                omens that they couldn’t understand, such as a rainbows appearing in
                                the sky. Then they heard the words “Go and meet Master Dpal byams!”
                                So they left.</p><p>When these two met [Dba’ Dpal byams] on the
                                path, they paid their respects and exchanged news, and then they
                                asked each other “Where are you going?” [Dba’ Dpal byams] said,
                                “Three nights ago, I had a dream prophecy like this...” Since this
                                was concordant with the omens [experienced by] the two masters, they
                                went as es- corts. Master Dpal byams recited his commitments:</p><p>"When the time of my death comes..."</p><p>When he recited this, [they all] spoke in one voice.</p><p>"Then by purifying all my defilements..."</p><p>As they recited this, they ascended [into the sky].</p><p>"When I directly perceive Amitābha..."</p><p>As they recited this, accomplishments such as rainbows arose, just
                                like the signs that had [previously] arisen for the two masters, and
                                they cast off the shackles of the body.</p><p>"May I go to the land of Sukhāvati..."</p><p>Having arrived there, they recited these prayers and departed.</p><p>The above is the narrative setting.</p></q><p></p><q lang="tib"><lb n="1r"></lb>’phags pa bzang po spyod pa’i smon lam gyi rgyal po ’di
                            dang por bshad pa’i gleng gzhi ni / tshong dpon gi bu nor bzangs zhes
                            bya bas / shes rab rno ba’i mchog du phyin pa ’s ni dam pa’i chos mdo
                            dang rgyas pa’ bsam gis myi khyab pa zhig thugs su chud nas / dad pa che
                            ba’i mchog du phyin pas ni / ’phags pa bzang po spyod pa’i smon lam ’di
                            ma gsan pa’i slad bzhin du / dge ba’i bshes gnyen brgya rtsa gcig zhal
                            mthong ba’ las / kun gi zhal nas ngas myi shes pa ni ma yin na / nga ’i
                            ’dul skal du khyod ma gyur ro // gsungs pas ma gsan nas / dge ba’i bshes
                            gnyen de rnams kyi bar thag ni rta pa’i gdugs tsam / rkang thang gi zhag
                            lam tsam zhig mchis so // dge ba’i bshes gnyen brgya tham ba’ la thug pa
                            dang / ’phags pa ’jam dpal gi zhal mthong nas / ’phags pa’ ’jam dpal la
                            zhus pa las / ngas myi shes pa ni ma yin na nga’i ’dul skal du ma bab
                            pas / rgya gar gi yul byang chub chen po ma ha bo de’i gling na ’phags
                            pa’ kun tu bzang po bzhugs pas / ’phags pa kun tu bzang po la zhu zhig
                            par lung bstan to // de nas tshong dpon gi bu nor bzangs gyis ma ha bo
                            de byang chub chen po’i gling du ’phags pa kun tu bzang po la zhus pas /
                            ’phags pa kun tu bzang pos / ’phags pa stug po bkod pa zhes kyang bya /
                            sangs rgyas phal po che zhes kyang bya / mang po ’dus pa zhes kyang bya
                            / rdza slags pa zhes kyang bya / snyan gi go rgyan zhes kyang bya / rma
                            ga chad zhes kyang bya ba de’i nang nas bsus te bshad nas / tshong dpon
                            gi bu nor bzangs kyi thugs dam du bzhes pas / mos par spyod pa las sa
                            dang po rab du dga’ ba’i bden ba’ mthong / de dang mtshungs par rgya gar
                            gi yul du yang ’phags pa bzang po spyod pa’i smon lam thugs dam du bzhes
                            pas / mang pos ’phags pa kun tu bzang po ’i dngos grub brnyes so // de’i
                            ’og tu ska ba’ dpal rtsags dang cog ro klu’i rgyal mtshan dang / rma rad
                            na ya kra las bsogs pas bsgyur nas / btsan po khri srong lde brtsan gi
                            sku ring la / btsan po thugs dam ba’ dba’ dpal byams zhes bya ba zhig
                            gis thugs dam du bzhes nas / nub gcig gi myi lam na / gser gi sko ra
                            bdun dbu la breng ’dug par rmangs pa las / btsan po ’i snyan du gsol nas
                            / btsan pos dpyod ma mkhyen nas / khad myi ring ba’ zhig na rgya gar gi
                            mkhan po bo de sat tva zhes bya ba bzhugs pa de la btsan pos g.yar lam
                            ’di lta bu zhig rmyis na / ’di ci lags zhes zhus pa dang / rgya gar gi
                            mkhan pos de su lags zhes btsan po la zhus pa dang / bdag gi slob ma dge
                            sbyong zhig lags so zhes gsol pa dang / ’di ni ’phags pa’ bzang po spyod
                            pa’i smon lam ’don pas / ’phags pa kun tu bzang po ’i dngos grub thob pa
                            zhig ces bka’ rtsal pa dang / btsan pos slobs dpon dpal byams la bzlas
                            pa dang / mkhan pos lhag par yang spro ba bskyed nas /<lb n="1v"></lb>nyin lan gsum mtshan lan gsum bas kyang lhag par zhal [s]ton du mdzad do
                            // de nas ring ma lon ba dang / btsan po la zhus pa’ / bdag ni rad pa
                            phung po yang dgud pas / btsan po ’i thugs dam dngo myi thog pas / bdag
                            ni dgon gnas gcig du mchi bar ci gnang zhes zhus pa dang / de tsam na ni
                            lha sa bsam yas na bzhugs pa’ las / de nas rta pa’i gdugs lam rkang
                            thang gi zhag lam tsam na / spa dro dgon pa na zhes bya ba der btsan pos
                            kyang bskul nas / gcig gi thugs kar gcig gi phyag bzhag nas / sa sar
                            smon lam btab nas gshegs so // de nas ring zhig ma lon ba tsam na / khad
                            kyis myi ring ba zhig na / ’ching pu brag rgye’u zhes bya ba de na /
                            ngan lam stag sgra klu gong gi gcung po / ngan lam rgyal mchog skyong
                            bzhugs / sho ma la la ni slob dpon sgro snya ye shes byang chub bzhugs
                            pa las / gnyis gi sku ltas sam rtogs pa la nam ka’ las gzha’ tshon las
                            bsogs pa byung nas / slob dpon dpal byams bsur ’gro ’o zhes thos pa las
                            / gnyis ka slob dpon la zlor gshegs pa las lam du gnyis ka mjal nas /
                            zhe sa bgyis nas bka’ mchid bgyis nas / gar gshegs so sor zhus pa dang /
                            mdang gsum g.yar ltas ’di lta bu zhig byung ngo zhes gsol ba las / slob
                            dpon gnyis ka sku ltas mthun nas / zlor gshegs pa dang / slob dpon dpal
                            byams thugs dam ’don pa las / bdag ni chi ba’i dus byed gyur pa na /
                            gsung tsam na gsung lan gcig chad / de nas sgrib pa thams cad ni phyir
                            bsal te / gsung tsam na / gcung tsam yang ’phags / mngon gsum snang ba’
                            mtha’ yas de mthong na gsung tsam na / slob dpon gnyis kyi sku ltas la
                            byung ba bzhin du gzha’ tshon la bsogs pa’ dngos grub byung nas / lus
                            gdos pa’ can bor nas / bde ba can gyi zhing der rab du ’gro / der song
                            nas ni smon lam ’di dag kyang / zhes zlos shing gshegs so / de yan cad
                            ni son gi gleng gzhi ’o // ∵ //</q></msItem></msContents></msDescription></body></text></TEI.2>
