<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Aurel Stein Medal</title><author id="SW">Whitfield, Susan</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First electronic edition</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>British Library</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>2006</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Printed book</p><bibl><ref>Gallop_2006</ref></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc>Catalogue</projectDesc></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><head><p>This catalogue is a single entry by Susan Whitfield that was originally written for the book "A cabinet of Oriental curiosities: an album for Graham Shaw from his colleagues", edited by Annabel Gallop, and published by The British Library in 2006.</p></head><body><msDescription n="1" type="SW"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Prints and Drawings</collection><idno type="current">F580</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san">Aurel Stein Medal, 1929</title><note><p>Aurel Stein received numerous awards and honours during his
                                lifetime, including several medals. The Royal Geographical Society
                                in London has the main collection (discovered by Helen Wang) but, as
                                is the way, another recently came to light among the India Office
                                Realia, a random collection of objects transferred to Prints and
                                Drawings in 2005.</p><p>The medal commemorates Stein’s visit to
                                Budapest, his home town, to give a lecture entitled ‘On Alexander’s
                                Track to the Indus’ on 12 October 1929. It was apparently
                                commissioned by ‘a group of admirers,’ although who these were is
                                not known. They approached the leading Hungarian sculptor and
                                medallist of his day, Odon Fülöp Beck (1873-1945).</p><p>The
                                finished medal shows Aurel Stein on the obverse, with Beck’s
                                monogram and the Latin inscription AURELIO STEIN HOSPITI CLARISSIMO
                                IN URBEM NATALEM REVERSO BUDAPESTINUM MCMXXIX. As Helen Wang points
                                out, the portrait resembles Bassano’s photograph of Stein taken in
                                1924. The reverse shows Minerva with a scroll open on her lap
                                supported by her right arm. Her left arm is raised with forefinger
                                pointing to a map to her side marked ‘Eastern Turkestan.’ Around her
                                are key sites visited and the dates of Stein’s expeditions: Khotan
                                1900, Taklamakan 1906-8, Lop 1907, Tun-Huang 1914, Sistan 1915, Swat
                                1926 and Gedrosia 1927-8. Beck’s name appears in full below. The
                                medal was cast in bronze and probably presented to Stein during his
                                visit. Its history thereafter is not clear, but at least one other
                                copy of this medal exists in the Fruchter collection in
                                Hungary.</p><p>After Stein’s lecture, not to be outdone, the
                                Hungarian Academy of Sciences (HAS) commissioned a silver version of
                                the medal and it was planned that this would be presented to Stein
                                during his next visit to Budapest. However, for some reason the
                                medal was instead posted to Stein, care of P. S. Allen in Oxford, on
                                26 May 1930. In Stein’s absence Allen acknowledged receipt of the
                                parcel. Stein sent a letter of thanks dated 9 July from Mohand Marg,
                                his Kashmiri summer camp (Dept. of MSS. and Rare Books of the
                                Library of the HAS, RAL 444/1930). The medallist was paid 70 pengo
                                for this work and the National Mint sent another copy to the
                                National Museum of Hungary (Dept. of Coins and Medals) where it
                                remains today. Stein’s copy is probably that now in the Royal
                                Geographical Society, London.</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription></body></text></TEI.2>
