<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The art of Central Asia: the Stein collection in the British Museum (Volume 1)</title><author id="RW">Roderick Whitfield</author><editor>Roderick Whitfield</editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First edition</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Kodansha International in co-operation with the Trustees of the British Museum</publisher><pubPlace>Tokyo</pubPlace><date>1982</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Printed book</p><bibl><ref>Whitfield_1982-1985</ref></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc>Catalogue</projectDesc></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><head><p>Introduction to be added shortly.</p></head><body><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 1"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">Or.8210/S.4367</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="R.1"><title lang="san-Latn">Prajñāpāramitā-sūtra (detail: actual size)</title><title lang="chi-Hant">大般涅槃經</title><note lang="eng"><p>Early 5th century A.D.</p><p>Ink on paper</p><p>H.24.7cm, L. of each sheet 42.5cm</p><p>British Library, Stein 4367</p><p>See also Fig. 7</p><p>According to Stein himself, the paintings that he found in the small memorial chapel at Dunhuang, now Cave 17, were in irregularly shaped bundles, some of which, used to level the ground, were at the very bottom and others on the top of the “solid rampart” of manuscript bundles. Because of their compact nature, and because they were almost all sewn up tightly in coarse covers of linen, these bundles of manuscripts by and large suffered less damage than the paintings crushed beneath them. It also seems that some of them date back considerably earlier than the earliest of the paintings.</p><p>As their interest was literary rather than artistic they were placed in the Department of Oriental Manuscripts and Printed Books and now form part of the British Library. Nevertheless, in order to present a fair account of the nature of the deposit in Cave 17, and because of their intrinsic interest, it has seemed right to present a small selection here. They have been chosen both to illustrate the development of calligraphic styles and to show the appearance of the scrolls themselves, since these must have been one of the most familiar sights not only at Dunhuang but throughout Buddhist China, as the work of translating sutras and propagating the Buddhist faith was carried on. Many of the finest scrolls were in fact executed not at Dunhuang but at the capital, and the paper on which they were written also came from distant parts of China and is of the highest quality.</p><p>Although not dated, the manuscript shown in this plate is a fine example of the earliest documents found in the sealed library at Dunhuang. Written on a substantial, pale buff paper, the characters are written within ruled columns but exhibit considerable variation in size: often insufficient space has been left for the last character in a column, and the number of characters per column, though usually seventeen, varies between sixteen and nineteen. Features of the script are the very upright verticals, and slender horizontal strokes weighted at the right. Hairline connecting strokes show a basically circular movement of the brush that is also reflected in the curved ends of the oblique strokes and the prevailing gentle upward curve of the horizontal.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>5世紀初</p><p>紙本墨寫.</p><p>5世紀初</p><p>英國圖書館,S.4367</p><p>參見Figs.7</p><p>據斯坦因本人的記錄，他在一個小的紀念窟，現在的第17窟裏發現繪畫類作品的時候，它們都很不規則的捆紮在一起，有的鋪在地上，在最下層，有的則堆积在由一捆捆寫卷筑起的“堅固的堡壘”上。因為寫卷是緊緊地卷起來的，而且所有的寫卷都用粗麻布包裹着，所以和被擠壓在下邊的繪畫相比，損壞的程度要低得多。在年代上，最早的寫卷要比最早的繪畫早得多。</p><p>這批寫卷以及美術品作爲文獻要比美術品更引起大家的興趣，所以當時收入大英博物館的東方稿本和刻本部，現在成為大英圖書館的一部分。不過，為了展示敦煌第17窟藏品的性質以及所蘊含的價值，有必要從中選出幾件在此作一介紹。圖版的選擇，既考慮書法形式的發展變化，也考慮寫卷的外觀。因爲這些寫卷不但反映敦煌地區，也能反映全中國廣大地區進行的譯經、寫經及其傳播情況。事實上，許多精品寫卷不是在敦煌而是在首都製作的，書寫的紙張也是取自於中國遙遠的地方，紙質精良。</p><p>本圖所反映的寫本雖然沒有紀年，但是在敦煌藏經洞發現的屬於最早期的優秀寫卷之一。質地優良的淡黃色紙上畫烏絲欄，字書寫在烏絲欄內，字的大小不一，經常是每行最後一字所留空間不足。絕大多數情況下每行字數十七字，但也有十六字至十九字的。字體特徵是，“豎”劃筆直，“橫”的右端筆重。筆畫之間有細微的連筆，筆勢基本呈圓形。從“斜”劃的尖端彎曲挑起，“橫”的中間稍呈隆起等現象上也能看出其特徵。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 2"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">Or.8210/S.81</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="R.1"><title lang="san-Latn">Mahāparinirvāṇa sūtra</title><title lang="chi-Hant">大般涅槃經</title><note lang="eng"><p>Lang dynasty, dated 5th year of Tianjian (天監五年) (A.D.506)</p><p>Ink on paper</p><p>H.26.6cm, L. of each sheet 49.0cm</p><p>British Library, Stein 81</p><p>See also Fig. 7</p><p>This, the earliest dated manuscript from south China from the Stein collection, already exhibits the principal features of the more numerous supra manuscripts from imperial chancelleries of the Tang dynasty. It is written on very thin paper treated with a yellow preservative (probably the bark of the Amur cork tree, known in Japan as jihads, which protects the paper from insect attack); the characters are of even size and always number seventeen to a column; finally, a neatly set-out colophon at the end (Fig.7), beneath the title and number, gives the date, the donor’s name, that of the temple (in Hubei province) and those of the monks who actually copied out the text. The supra was written out on behalf of the donor’s deceased father. The end of the scroll is cut to form a tab, like the end of a photographic film, for attaching to the wooden stick on which it was rolled; the yellow preservative may have been brushed on as the paper keeps its original pale buff colour in a narrow strip at this point. The writing is noticeably more angular than that of the preceding manuscript, lacking the long horizontal and keeping well clear of the ruled lines of the columns. Nevertheless, some traces of Lishe style are still visible in the weighting of oblique strokes and horizontal to the right. Further advances towards the developed Aisha of the early Tang dynasty can be seen in another version of the same supra, dated to A.D. 561 in the Northern Chou dynasty (Figs. 2, 9). There, although the horizontal strokes still tend to be weighted to the right, the beginning of the stroke may also be accented, with the tip of the brush entering at right angles rather than in line with the stroke as a whole. Eventually in the regular script of the Tang, the brush tip is wholly concealed.</p><p>Although the text is well known from numerous other sources, such a manuscript as this is of great interest for the information it can give us of the movements of Buddhist monks and the centres of translation and sutra-copying, and eventually perhaps also of paper manufacture. The paper is of the finest quality, thin and strong, and must have been made in south China. That made at Dunhuang itself after it was cut off from Chinese supplies is thick and coarse and came in relatively small sheets. It would not have been at all suitable for making into long rolls. This southern origin is confirmed by the colophon, from which we learn that the scroll was copied in Hubei province in south central China. It must thus have survived not only the centuries in the sealed store at Dunhuang, but the long journey there in the first place, probably on the back of a travelling monk.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>梁代天監五年（506）</p><p>紙本墨寫.</p><p>高26.6cm，每紙長49.0cm</p><p>英國圖書館,S.81</p><p>參見Figs.7</p><p>斯坦因收集品的寫卷中，作爲有南朝紀年的，它是最早的，卻已经具備了衆多唐代宮廷寫經中所見的主要特徵。經文書寫在經黃色防蟲劑（日本稱之為黃蘗，可以防止紙張被虫蛀）處理過的薄紙上，字體大小一致，每行十七字。卷尾（參見Figs.7）在題名及卷數的左下方有一整齊的題跋，記錄了紀年、供養人名、所在寺院（在今湖北省）以及兩位抄經比丘的名字。本卷是供養者為超度亡父而供奉的經文。卷尾被剪成像膠片尾端一樣的燕尾，以便粘上用來捲卷子的木軸。由於這一窄條沒有染黃，保持了原來紙的淡黃色。與上一寫卷相比，字體明顯失去圓味，也沒有了長長的“橫”劃，文字整齊地寫在界欄內。既便那樣，“斜”或“橫”的右端筆重，這一點多少有隸書的韻味。與初唐時期楷書非常接近的大般涅槃經的另一抄本，年代為北周561年（參見Figs.2，9圖）。 其“橫”的右端仍有筆重的傾向，筆劃的起筆重，有按壓筆尖的痕迹。到了唐代，字體工整，這種筆尖的痕迹則完全消失。</p><p>盡管通過其他種種資料可以知道經文本身，然而從這個寫本我們可以獲得有關佛教僧侶的活動，譯經、寫經的中心地，甚至紙張的製作等非常有趣的信息。本卷所用紙張質地精良，既薄且韌，無疑是出產於中國南方。中原地區中斷供給後，敦煌本地所生産的紙既厚且粗，紙幅也小，不適於製作長卷子。由題跋中所記的書寫於中國南部湖北省看，可以確信此寫本來自南方。因此，該寫本在被封入敦煌藏經洞的數世紀之前，恐怕已經歷了由雲游僧背負著，從最初的製作地到達敦煌這一漫長的旅程。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 3"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">Or.8210/S.1427</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="R.1"><title lang="san-Latn">Satyasiddhi-śāstra, xiv (detail: actual size)</title><title lang="chi-Hant">成實論卷第十四（局部 原大）</title><note lang="eng"><p>Northern Wei dynasty, dated 4th year of Yongping (A.D.511)</p><p>Ink on paper</p><p>H.25.4cm, L. of each sheet 38.3cm</p><p>British Library, Stein 1427</p><p>This scroll is preserved complete with its original wooden stave, which projects about two centimeters beyond the roll. These projecting ends are lacquered dark brown. The end of the scroll, cut with deep even curves at top and bottom to make a tab, is pasted to the stave. The paper itself is more robust than that of the preceding manuscript, and is in smaller sheets, with a somewhat uneven application of the yellow preservative. Like the preceding manuscript, it is completed by a colophon (shown in the plate) giving the date and place of writing, in this case Dunhuang itself. Comparison of the styles of writing of these two manuscripts of similar date, first made by Professor Akita Frieda,(1) highlights the differences between that of the southern style, already indicative of the Sui and Tang styles to come, and that of the northern courts, as in this manuscript, strongly reminiscent of the writing on Han wooden slips. As in the manuscript shown in Pl. 1, there is a strong contrast between slender horizontal and stout verticals, and an emphasis on curved strokes, visible in many characters where there or more strokes are drawn concentrically. The number of characters per column, however, is a consistent seventeen.</p><p>(1)Akita Frieda, “A Study of Buddhist MS under the Northern Dynasties”, Bobbi, no.119 (1962) , p.3, Pals. 8 (S.81) and 9 (S.1427). See also the same author’s discussion of other dated manuscripts from Dunhuang (Bobbi, no. 156,pp.8-10); and his revised list in Sin bun, no.10 (1969),p.26.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>北魏永平四年 (511)</p><p>紙本墨寫.</p><p>高25.4厘米，每紙長38.3厘米</p><p>英國圖書館,S.1427</p><p>參見Figs.7</p><p>這一寫卷完整地保留了原來的木軸，木軸兩端各露出2cm左右，塗有暗褐色漆。卷尾兩端斜著剪成燕尾狀，粘在木軸上。紙張比上一個寫卷粗糙，紙幅稍小，染黃不均勻。和上一寫卷一樣，完整的題跋記錄了抄寫年代和地點，它是在敦煌本地抄寫的。時代大致相同的這南北兩種寫本，比較其字體，它們的差別正像藤枝晃教授所指出1的那樣，上一寫卷的南朝字體已經很接近隋唐風格，而這一寫卷的字體則深受漢簡字體影響。這一寫卷的文字與第1圖的文字一樣，細線的“橫”劃和粗筆道的“豎”劃成鮮明的對比，筆的使用更帶圓味，有很多字看似像用三根或更多的線描出的同心圓。每行字數按慣例爲十七個字。</p><p>1参照藤枝晃「北朝写经の字すがた」（『墨美』119号3页 图版8((S.81))，图版9((S.1427))），「ベリォ蒐集の北魏敦煌写本－『成实论』卷第八残卷解题」（『墨美』156号，8～10页，『Sin bun』10号26页のリスト。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 4"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">Or.8210/S.2154</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="R.1"><title lang="eng">Fuo Shou Shen Da Hui Xiang Jing, (detail: actual size)</title><title lang="chi-Hant">佛說甚深大迴向經（局部 原大）</title><note lang="eng'"><p>Sui dynasty, dated 9th year of Kai hang (A.D.589)</p><p>Ink on paper</p><p>H.28.3cm, L. of each sheet 52.0cm</p><p>British Library, Stein 2154</p><p>See also Fig.10</p><p>This fine manuscript was executed for the Empress, according to the colophon at the end. The sophistication of the Sui court can be seen in the elegant script. Most noticeable is the orderly spacing of strokes within each character: successive horizontal parallel to each other are no longer closely spaced, so that every stroke is distinct and clearly visible. This regularity extends naturally to the spacing of the whole composition. The scroll is made up of sheets of thin paper, each approximately 52cm in length.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>隋開皇九年（589）</p><p>紙本墨寫.</p><p>高28.3厘米，每紙長52.0厘米</p><p>英國圖書館,S.2154</p><p>參見Figs.10</p><p>根據卷尾題記，這卷精美的寫卷是皇后發願所抄寫的經卷。從優美的書法可以感覺到隋朝宮廷寫經的精致。格外引人注目的是，文字的筆劃和筆劃的間隔非常勻整。特別是“橫”劃之間非常直平，無狹窄之處，均清晰明瞭。這種工整的整體結構也影響到的文字與文字的間隔上。該卷是許多薄紙連接而成，每紙長約52厘米。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 5"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">Or.8210/S.2295</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="R.1"><title lang="eng">Laozi bianhua king (Sutra of the Incarnations of Laozi)</title><title lang="chi-Hant">老子變化經</title><note lang="eng"><p>Sui dynasty, dated 8th year of Daye(A.D.612)</p><p>Ink on paper</p><p>H.25.6cm, L. of each sheet 50.0cm</p><p>British Library, Stein 2295</p><p>The original narrow wooden roller and method of trimming the end of the scroll can clearly be seen here. The end is pasted onto the roller. The Daoist text is also set out in exactly the same way as Buddhist sutras, from the standard number of seventeen characters to a column, down to the title and colophon at the end. The latter gives, in addition to the date and scribe’s name, the number of sheets used (four) and the editor of the text, followed by an unfilled space for the person who dyed the paper yellow (Zhuang huang ren 裝潢人), and by the title of the bureau in which it was copied. The dye used was probably that obtained from the bark of the Amur cork tree (Japanese: jihads), which acts as an insect repellent. We may presume that the “paper-dyer” was responsible not only for the dyeing of the paper but also for the joining of the separate sheets and their attachment to the roller. The projecting ends of the roller are lacquered dark brown.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>隋大業八年（612）</p><p>紙本墨寫.</p><p>高25.6厘米 每紙長50.0厘米</p><p>英國圖書館,S.2295</p><p>通過圖版可以看到保留下來的原裝細木軸，以及卷尾兩端剪裁方法，卷尾粘貼在卷軸上。從每行十七字、題名以及題跋等書寫方式，可以看出道經寫本與佛經寫本的特徵基本相同。題跋記錄了寫卷的年代、寫經生的名字、用紙數（4）、覆校者姓名，後面有將紙染黃的“裝潢人”，未記錄名字。末行是組織寫經的官署名。染料可能是採用了具有防蟲作用的黃蘗的皮（日文：jihads）。我們可以推測裝潢人不僅負責染紙，而且還負責紙張的粘連以及木軸的安裝。木軸的兩端塗有暗褐色的漆。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 6"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Library</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">Or.8210/S.4209</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="R.1"><title lang="san-Latn">Saddharma-pundarīka sūtra (Lotus Sutra ),iii</title><title lang="chi-Hant">妙法蓮華經卷第三</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, dated 3rd year of Xianheng (A.D.672)</p><p>Ink on paper</p><p>H.26.0cm, L. of each sheet 45.7cm</p><p>British Library, Stein 4209</p><p>This scroll of the Lotus Sutra, one of several hundred examples of this text collected by Stein, is also one of a score of sutras written in the imperial chancelleries and dated in the 670s. The paper is of very fine quality, crisp to the touch and of even, opaque yellow-brown colour, besides being still in excellent condition. The ivory knobs at the ends of the roller are stained green and are elegantly turned. They are 3.8 cm long and project 1.5 cm above and below the scroll. This manuscript has lost its original cover and fastening tape; indeed, virtually none of the thousands in the collection have survived intact with their original outer covers. Numbers of covers have, however, been preserved separately; they may be made of a stouter paper or of a doubled sheet of the same quality as used in the manuscript itself and attached by paste to the first sheet of the manuscript, with a narrow bamboo splint pasted in at the beginning. The fastening tape (one example is a narrow strip of silk cut across the weave and folded lengthwise three times) is ingeniously attached by piercing the paper just behind the splint. The tape passes once around the splint and back through the same pierced hole, and through a slit in the tape itself. About 2 cm of the tape is left inside and may be pasted down. The result is a very simple but secure fastening, which remains quite flat and cannot come away from the cover. Once fastened, several scrolls could be kept together in a neat bundle by means of a wrapper. Examples of wrappers have also survived and are found in both the Stein and the Elliot collections (Vol.3, Pls.6, 7; Tissues, Pls.1, 3, 39).</p><p>Wall paintings at Dunhuang show monks reading from sutra scrolls identical to this, while several paintings in London and Paris show a pilgrim with backpack loaded with scores of neatly bundled scrolls (Vol.2, Pl.59). The presence in the sealed library at Dunhuang of great numbers of scrolls written in distant parts of China is clear evidence of the ease with which sutras were transported and propagated from one Buddhist centre to another throughout the empire and beyond. Further study of range of papers found at Dunhuang in their original condition, still strong and serviceable, is needed and should yield much information about such movements and about the paper industry that supplied the very considerable demands of Buddhist and imperial scriptures as well as everyday needs.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐咸亨三年（672年）</p><p>紙本墨寫.</p><p>高26.0厘米 每紙長45.7厘米</p><p>英國圖書館,S.4209</p><p>斯坦因收集品中法華經寫本達數百件，其中一些是670年代唐代宮廷寫經，這個寫卷就是其中之一。紙張極爲精致，手感平滑，呈淡黃色，至今保存狀態仍完好。木軸兩端軸頭嵌象牙，着綠色，極為考究。軸頭長3.8厘米，卷子上下各露出1.5厘米。</p><p>該卷護首和絲帶已失，其實數千件收集品中，沒有一件完整無損地保留著原來的護首，然而卻保留了許多從寫卷上脫落的護首。護首或是用更爲厚實的紙製作的，或是用兩張與寫卷一樣的紙粘合在一起製作的，護首粘在第一張紙上。卷首粘有細竹籤。絲帶（舉一例子，絲帶穿過自身，縱向折三次）巧妙地穿過竹籤後面的紙張。絲帶繞過竹籤後，再從同一紙孔穿出，再穿過絲帶本身的孔。約有2厘米的絲帶被粘在封皮裡面。這種方法非常簡單，但包紮得卻非常緊，相對平整，也不會從封皮脫出。一旦捆好，若干卷可以包成一帙。斯坦因和伯希和收集品中可以見到遺留下來的經帙的樣例（參見第3卷彩色圖版第6，7圖，伯希和圖錄《敦煌絲織品》篇圖版1，3，39）。</p><p>敦煌壁畫中，有描繪僧人誦讀經卷的圖像。斯坦因和伯希和的收集品中,也有若干件是雲遊僧背負裝著經卷的繪畫（參見卷2，圖59）。敦煌藏經洞出土很多抄寫于遙遠中原的經卷，說明佛經很容易從一個佛教中心傳播到另外一個中心，並遍及國內外。進一步研究敦煌出土的現在仍然結實耐用的紙張的原始狀況，不但是必要的，而且還可以提供有關紙的流通以及供應寺院、政府和日常生活所需的造紙工業等更多信息。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 7"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.6</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="R.1"><title lang="eng">Buddha Preaching the Law</title><title lang="chi-Hant">樹下說法圖</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, early 8th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.139.0cm, W.101.7cm</p><p>British Museum, Stein painting6. Ch.liii.001</p><p>See also Figs.15-17</p><p>This, one of the earliest among the paintings found in Cave 17 at Dunhuang, is also one of the best preserved and one that is clearly related to Sui and early Tang paradise or preaching scenes found on the walls of the caves themselves. Among the silk paintings, the closest parallel is the fragment of an Omitābah preaching scene from the Elliot collection (Banners, No.23). Several features seem to assure its early date: the composition itself; the colour scheme, both in the decoration of the canopy and throne and in the modelling of the figures; and the single surviving figure of a female donor in the lower left corner.</p><p>The painting is virtually complete, including a painted valance and the plain sewn-on silk border, except for part of the centre foreground. Its rich, yet delicate colouring, though faded, is in places extraordinarily well preserved and shows the full splendour of Buddhist painting in the High Tang period. Despite this great beauty of colour and form, the painting has rarely been reproduced before (Matsumoto, 1937, Pl. 58; Stein, Thousand Buddhas, Pl. VI, part only), and then only in monochrome. It is a fine example of a more developed paradise scene than Buddha Preaching the Law (Pl.7). In order to help the faithful to visualize the splendours of the Pure Land into which they could hope to be reborn, the depiction includes a growing retinue of attendants about the Buddha and a magnificent setting, with musicians below and pavilions above, representing the delights and beauties of the Pure Land. The main part of the assembly is gathered on a platform rising out of a lotus lake: here infant souls, newly reborn, are seen on lotus flowers joining in adoration (Pl.8-8). To either side of this assembly are narrow side scenes set in landscapes. These represent episodes from three of the nine parts of the Baden'sūtra. Each scene is identified by a car touch inscribed with the relevant part of the story, so that the painting could easily be used for the instruction of the faithful.</p><p>The main figure can probably be identified as Sāyemeni, although Omitābah, with Avalokitesvara and MagāSDāmapāpta, has also been suggested. His hands are in vitarka-mudrā, or mudā of the exposition of the Law, common to both Amitābha and Sākyamuni. Clearly, however, the entire painting is comparable to examples of “Preaching the Law” from caves of the early Tang period (e.g., Caves 103, 321, 329). In these the chief intent was to suggest the omnipresence of Buddha by constant repetition of the same scene. The type can be seen as a development from preaching groups on the walls of Sui caves at Dunhuang, where there are in general only three figures, the Buddha and two Bodhisattvas (cf. Cave 390). In the present painting, in addition to the Bodhisattvas representing the Mahāyāna, or Greater Vehicle, the presence not just of two monks representing the Hinayāna, or Lesser Vehicle, but of six in all seems to favour the identification of the central figure as Sākyamuni, the historical Buddha with whom they would be associated. Presumably there simply was not room to depict all ten of Sākyamuni’s historical disciples. In later, more developed representations of the Pure Land paradises, whether on silk or as wall paintings (e.g., Pl.8) the disciples are still fewer, with two-Ananda and Kāsyapa-characterized in appearance as young and old respectively. Here, on the other hand, there are no obvious formalized distinctions, but the figures, and especially their bald heads, are carefully studied and drawn.</p><p>The painter’s concern with rendering the forms of the shaven heads is clearly apparent (Pls.7-2, 7-3). At the same time there is a decorative aspect to the depiction of the faces in the somewhat stylized scheme of colour shading and white highlighting that seems to be used almost independently of the outer contours in ink. We may see here, and in other paintings at Dunhuang, a fusion of the “aesthetics of light” (Bussagli, 1963, pp.31ff), which was a feature of the art of the West, with the tradition of modelling through line that was an inherent characteristic of painting and allied arts in China. We should not, however, draw too rigid a distinction here, since the shading of colours was in fact also practised in China (e. g., in the handscroll Admonitions of the Court Instructress, attributed to Gu Kaizhi, in the British Museum, especially in the garments and drapery hangings) from the period of the Northern and Southern Dynasties onwards. Nor does the stylization of the colour shading imply that the style as a whole is fixed and derivative. On the contrary, when examined closely, there are many lively details which exhibit a freshness of approach. All of the subsidiary figures are varied in pose and expression. At the lower left, one Bodhisattva is seen in three-quarter view from the back (though with the face in profile). Among the monks, two of whom are partly hidden behind the trunks of the Bodhi trees, there are many varied expressions of the eyes. Their eyebrows are drawn initially with single curved lines, over which are numerous shorter strokes in grey ink. In most cases these strokes are also curved and parallel with the initial line, but in the monk on the far left these paler strokes cross it vertically to give him bushy eyebrows. Again, one monk has his mouth open and teeth showing as if he is chanting. Here the line between cheek and mouth, normally brought close to the lips by the fullness of the cheek, is elongated and drawn back (Pl.7-3). A close parallel to this can be seen in the wall painting showing a monk reading from a sutra roll (Cave 201; Dunhuang bihua, Pl.109). As a further confirmation of the early eighth century A.D. date of this painting, the wall paintings of the tomb of Princess Yongtai (A.D. 706; Tang Yongtai gongzhu mu bihua ji, Pl.4) provides another contemporary example. By the late eighth century, the convention has changed and the line between the lips ends in a gentle swelling; later still (in the tenth century) this is elongated and terminated by a sharply angled hook.</p><p>The concern with three-dimensional form, already noticed in the monks’ heads, extends to the composition as a whole, where the central figure is left almost free, while those surrounding him occupy relatively less of the picture area. Some are even partially obscured behind the trunks of the Bodhi trees supporting the canopy. Although all the figures have haloes, only those of the two lower Bodhisattvas are actually opaque. The transparency of the rest adds greatly to the feeling of space (cf. Cave 334). The painter has also used his discretion here with a nice sense of relative values: thus the same halo (that of the monk behind the tree trunk on the right) is transparent in order to reveal the monk who stands behind him, but opaque to the uninscribed cartouche above (Pl.7-2). The effect is to focus attention on the main figure, as well as to give the whole setting a certain measure of depth. This feature is a Chinese, rather than a Western, contribution. Among the earlier compositions recovered by Stein from Dunhuang, none is more remarkable in this respect than the great embroidery showing Sākyamuni Preaching on the Vulture Peak (Vol.3, Pl.1). There the figures of the two monks emerge as if from behind the Bodhisattvas on either side, leaving clear the rocky background of the central figure, and contributing not a little to the impressiveness of the whole composition. Later, in the tenth century particularly, the distinctions and relative importance of figures of the Buddha and his attendants seem to be lost, or rather forgotten in the need to fill the available surface evenly with colour and decoration.</p><p>To return to the painting, several further features distinguish it from others and serve to link it both with paintings in the caves and with possible parallels that must have existed in the capital, Chang’an, hundreds of miles to the east. The surviving donor (Pl.7-5), a young lady demurely seated with a lotus flower in her hand, clearly recalls in her neat hair and high-waisted dress the funerary figurines and wall paintings of court ladies from princely tombs of the very early eighth century near Chang’an. Her face and the dark black of her coiffure are admirably set off by a side bud from the stem of the lotus throne above her, and she holds a long-stemmed red flower with pairs of opposing leaves. Although only the top of the cap of the male donor is visible, plumes of smoke curling gently upward towards the central Buddha throne show that he originally held a hand censer. In the centre foreground, the space left and ruled (although never actually used) for a dedicatory inscription takes the form of a monumental stele of the type well known from the beilin in Xi’an, supported on a tortoise and crowned by intertwined dragons. Although the dragons are here replaced by a floral design of overlapping petals, this is manifestly the explanation of the semicircular cap, and there is even a rectangular space left, which on an actual stone stele would have served for the title in formal characters (Fig.15). Similar stelae for dedicatory inscriptions are also found in some of the wall paintings (e.g., Cave 335, dated A.D. 686), as well as in Stein painting 499 in New Delhi (Stein, Thousand Buddhas, Pl.XI), and are contributory evidence of reasonably close and frequent contact between Dunhuang and the capital, such as could only have occurred in the period before the area came under Tibetan control in A.D.781.</p><p>Among the wall paintings at Dunhuang, so far as can be judged from photographs and reproductions, preaching groups in Cave 329(Lo Archive, no.1361), Cave 103 and Cave 321 are the closest to this painting. In Cave 329, the Buddha’s right hand is in vitarka-mudrā, as in the Stein painting. The canopy above has a net fringe and cloud-like embellishments framed by the foliage of the two Bodhi trees. The lotus throne on which the Buddha sits, although not so embellished, has compressed petals similar to those seen in the Stein painting. Below it the space for the inscription may also be based on a monumental tablet with a capstone. Cave 321, high on the east wall above the entrance, has the group spread horizontally; the two monks both face in the same direction (Lo Archive, no.842). In both these groups the attendant Bodhisattvas, as well as the Buddha, have the tall horseshoe-shaped haloes, bearing some resemblance to the oval ones of the lower Bodhisattvas in the silk painting. There are similarities, too, in the shading, highlighting and delineation of the face of the preaching Buddha on the south wall of Cave 103 (Lo Archive, no.1229). There we find the same convention for the transition from the cheek to the mouth, already described for the chanting monk. This cave is generally dated to the period of the Empress Wu in the late seventh century A.D., and may serve to confirm the early eighth century date here attributed to Stein painting 6(Pl.7).</p><p>Other features also invite comparison with the wall paintings. These are the clouds above the canopy and those which decorate the petals of the Buddha’s lotus throne. The canopy clouds, ridden by apsarases scattering blossoms (Pl.7-6), belong to a long tradition stretching back, no doubt, to the earliest wall paintings of the Liang dynasty, long since lost at Dunhuang through the collapse of that part of the cliff that had contained the earliest caves. In this preaching scene, as in other paintings of early Tang date (Cave 329), the clouds are composed of separate plumes, each a different colour and delicately shaded. This formula was to be considerably simplified in the course of the ninth and tenth centuries A.D. at Dunhuang. The cloud plumes on the petals of the lotus throne give a similarly rich effect: they can be compared not only with similar decoration in the wall paintings (for instance the decorated halo and lotus petals of an eleven-headed Avalokitesvara in Cave 334) but with actual lotus pedestals of the mid-eighth century A.D. preserved in the imperial repository of the Shōsō-in, Nara, whose individual petals are richly painted in various colours (Shōsō-in no kaiga, Pls.109ff).</p><p>Before concluding these notes, it is appropriate to make a few comments on the construction of the painting, which is in ink and colours on fine silk. As with all the larger silk paintings, the size of the silk to a considerable extent determines the size of the finished panel. A single width of silk runs down the centre of the painting. The width of this piece is 53. 7cm. A second piece, cut down the middle into two equal halves, is sewn on, selvedge to selvedge, to the first piece. The cut edges on the sides of the painting should originally have been protected by a sewn-on border of doubled silk. In this case, however, the border has disappeared. We may infer from the fact that the half-widths are now only some 23. 7cm wide that about 3 cm on either side has also been lost. This assumption is confirmed by reference to the lotus thrones of the main Bodhisattvas, which need another centimetre or two to be complete. Nor is there anywhere any trace of stitching of the four borders. Along the top and left edges, however, about 1cm from the edge, an ink line has been ruled, and this may have marked the limit of the design when it was first laid out. It would seem that a certain amount of lateral compression was already necessary for the painter in order to fit in the many figures: note, for example, the rather vertical petals at the sides of the lotus thrones of the two main Bodhisattvas and the slight degree of asymmetry. Yet it is partly as a result of this asymmetry and the varied stances of the many figures that the painting is one of the most satisfying among those found at Dunhuang. One is left with the impression that here solutions to problems of representation were still being sought, rather than of rigid adherence to established prototypes.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，8世紀初</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高139.0cm 寬101.7cm</p><p>英國博物館,斯坦因繪畫6.Ch.liii.001</p><p>參見黑白圖版 15－17</p><p>這是敦煌第17窟中出土的繪畫中時代最早、保存狀態最好的作品之一，而且明顯與敦煌石窟壁畫中隋及初唐時期的淨土變和說法圖有密切關係。絹畫中，與它最接近的則是伯希和搜集品中的阿彌陀淨土圖的殘片 (《敦煌幡畫》圖23)。我們依據以下特徵將其定為早期作品：首先是根據它的構圖，華蓋、寶座的裝飾及表現諸畫像身體色彩的手法，以及畫面左下角女供養人像的表現形式等等。</p><p>雖然有人認爲主尊為阿彌陀佛，脅侍為觀音和勢至，但其主尊可以確認為釋迦牟尼，他的手勢為說法印，這是釋迦牟尼和阿彌陀佛共用的手勢。畫面結構與初唐石窟（比如103、321、329等窟）中所見的說法圖相似。這些說法圖的主要意圖，就是要通過同一場面的反復描繪，來宣示佛的無所不在。另外，此種形式是從隋代敦煌石窟壁畫中所見的只表現佛與二脅侍菩薩三尊的簡單構圖（比如第390窟）中發展而來。不過此圖中，除有大乘菩薩之外，還有代表小乘的比丘，這六個比丘也是我們將主尊定為釋迦牟尼佛的根據，他們歷史上曾隨侍過佛陀，與佛陀有密切的關係。可以假設只是因為沒有空間，而沒有把釋迦牟尼的十大弟子全部描繪出來。後來，隨著淨土變的發展，不管絹畫或是壁畫（如，圖8）弟子的形象還是出現的很少，只有阿難和迦葉作為年老和年輕的弟子的代表出現。另一方面，這幅圖並沒有獨特的風格，但是人物形象，特別是比丘的頭部，因觀察仔細而描繪逼真。</p><p>這幅畫畫家所要表現的顯然是對剃髮比丘頭部的圓潤（圖7－2，7－3）。與此同時，在描繪面部時使用了稍具形式化的高光，看起來似乎與黑色線描毫無關係，給人以裝飾性的感覺。此種技法在其他敦煌畫中也可見到，其在中國繪畫藝術固有技法——用線描進行立體描繪，又融入了西方美術的“光美學”（Mario Bussagli《中亞繪畫》，1963，p.31以下）。這裡沒有必要在兩者之間劃定一嚴格界限，事實上在中國，顏色勾勒是南北朝以來一直沿用的技法（例如，大英博物館藏相傳顧愷之所作的《女史箴圖》的衣褶部分）。另外，不能因說顏色勾勒方法已經是形式化了，就認為其整體風格也是固定化的，而沒有獨創性。恰恰相反，詳察其細部，可發現多處採用了新的表現方式。如，除主尊外，其他的畫像無論是姿態還是表情，都富變化。左下方的菩薩背朝外，身體稍往前傾（面向主尊）。有二個比丘的部分身體被菩提樹遮住，比丘的眼神各異。其眉毛則是先勾一條曲線，再用淡墨描出無數眉毛。雖然大部分眉毛稍有彎曲，卻基本與最初的曲線平行。最左邊的比丘淡淡的眉毛筆直，似“蚰蜒眉”。另外一個比丘張嘴露齒，神態像是正在吟誦。其他比丘臉頰和嘴間的線條緊挨嘴唇，只有細微的表現，而此比丘臉頰和嘴間的線條則拉長到下方(圖7-3)。與此極為相類的則是敦煌201窟壁畫中的誦經比丘（201窟；《敦煌壁畫》，圖109）。作為這幅畫斷為八世紀初的另一個確証，永泰公主墓壁畫（706年，《唐永泰公主墓壁畫集》，圖4）提供了同時代的例証。到了8世紀後半葉，繪畫方式有了變化，嘴唇之間線條兩端稍微變粗。再往後（10世紀）線條拉得更長，末端彎曲得很尖。</p><p>至於三維表現形式，我們已經注意到了比丘的頭部，並且這一方式已經滲透到整個構圖，而主尊形象突出，幾乎沒有受到畫面的限制，而圍繞其周圍的畫像則擁擠在狹小的空間裏，其中也有不乏被支撐華蓋的菩提樹樹幹遮擋而看不見其全身者。雖然諸尊均有項光，但除了下方的二菩薩項光不透明外，其餘則全部透明，這非常容易使人感覺到空間的深度（例如334窟）。</p><p>另一方面，畫家也謹慎而巧妙地處理了畫面的明暗配合：同一項光（右側樹幹後的比丘）是透明的，以表現站在其後面的比丘，項光上方與長方形空白處重疊部分是不透明的（圖7－2）。這種處理方法使人感覺到畫面相當有深度的同時，起到將焦點集中在主尊的效果。這完全是中國繪畫特徵，而非西歐畫法。斯坦因敦煌繪畫收集品中，這方面最引人注目的是刺繡靈鷲山釋迦牟尼說法圖（卷3，圖1）。二比丘似乎是從兩脅侍菩薩兩側探出身體，主尊清清楚楚地浮現在岩石重疊的背景中，給人以深刻的印象。此後，特別是到了10世紀，爲了在畫面上均勻地塗布色彩和裝飾，卻失去了或者說是遺忘了表現佛陀和隨眾之間的區別以及關連。</p><p>再回到這幅畫，該畫中還有若干明顯區別於其他繪畫的特徵，也可以與東部數百里外首都長安的石窟壁畫或者可能仍保存的類似作品聯繫起來。畫面中雖然只存留一手持鮮花端坐著的年輕女供養人（圖7－5），她整潔的髮型和高腰的衣服，使人很容易想起長安近郊發現的8世紀初王侯墓中的宮女壁畫和俑。女供養人正上方有菩薩乘坐的蓮華寶座，從蓮莖伸出的花蕾恰好在她頭上的位置，因而臉和黑髮格外顯眼。女供養人手持開有紅花的長莖草花，綠葉節節對稱。右下角的男供養人雖然僅存襆頭的頂部，但能清楚地看到向主尊寶座輕飄蔓延的香煙，可以想像他手持香爐。</p><p>中央前方雖然沒有被實際利用，但為了書寫題記而留了碑石形的空間。這與西安碑林著名的龜跌座和螭首碑額同一意思。上部的龍被重疊的花瓣替換了，顯然仍是一個半圓形的碑額，並且留下一塊長方形的空白處——在實際的碑刻中，這一處是用來撰寫正式碑文的地方（黑白圖版15）。敦煌壁畫（例如，335窟，686年）中都能看到同樣碑形題記，又如新德里國立博物館所藏的斯坦因搜集的繪畫499（斯坦因，《千佛洞》，圖11）。顯然，這些是吐蕃佔領該地的781年以前，敦煌和長安之間具有密切而頻繁聯繫的產物。</p><p>僅從照片和複製品上判斷，則敦煌壁畫中與此畫最為接近的有329窟（羅寄梅檔案No.1361）、103窟、321窟的說法圖。329窟的壁畫像該畫一樣，佛右手勢是說法印。上邊的寶蓋裝飾有帷帳及雲彩，其周圍被兩棵菩提樹葉包圍；佛的蓮華寶座在此圖中雖沒有精雕細琢，但重疊的花瓣與斯坦因繪畫收集品所見非常相似；另外下方寫銘文的地方是一塊拱頂石。321窟中，東壁入口處上部有一鋪水平排列的諸像，二比丘朝向同一方向（羅寄梅檔案No.842）。第329窟、第321窟也一樣，脅侍菩薩和佛陀的項光模仿該圖下方二菩薩的長馬蹄形項光。另外，第103窟南壁的說法圖中佛的面部的明暗、高光、輪廓等等均能看到與此圖類似的特點（羅寄梅檔案No.1229）。這裡我們還可以發現臉頰到嘴的表現如同上面提到的正在吟誦的比丘都運用了上述的同樣手法。一般認為該窟是7世紀末，即則天武后時代，據此將斯坦因搜集的本幅絹畫推測爲8世紀初的作品為更得當。</p><p>還可將該繪畫與壁畫的其他特徵相比較。即寶蓋上面的雲彩和裝飾佛蓮華座蓮瓣的雲彩是所作的嘗試。散花飛天（參照圖7－6）所乘的寶蓋雲沿襲了長期以來的傳統，無疑可以追溯到早期壁畫中北涼的作品。當然，北涼壁畫由於敦煌早期石窟所處斷崖的崩壞，在很早以前就已不存了。此幅畫也是和唐初的其他繪畫（329窟）一樣，雲被描繪成靈芝雲，並處處採用不同的彩色和美麗的渲染。其形式在敦煌9世紀到10世紀間已經比較單一的。裝飾蓮華座蓮瓣的靈芝雲也同樣很華麗，不僅僅與壁畫中的描繪是同一類裝飾（如334窟十一面觀音的項光和寶座），也可與保存在奈良正倉院8世紀中葉的香印坐（漆金薄繪盤）做比較。正倉院香印坐的蓮瓣是一片一片的，用各種顏色裝飾得很華麗（參照《正倉院繪畫》109圖）。 最後，再補充一下這幅絢麗的絹畫的製作。對於大幅的絹繪圖，由已經完成的畫面的大小可以推測其實際使用的絹幅。該繪畫的畫面中央使用了一幅寬有53.7cm的縱向絹。其兩側有兩塊大小相同的絹，它們的邊和邊分別與中央絹縫合在一起。繪畫兩端為了起到保護作用而將絹的兩層折疊縫合而成，可是這幅絹畫的邊已經丟失。現被切成一半的絹幅只有23.7cm左右，可以推測兩端分別缺了3cm左右。如果想完全看到脅侍菩薩寶座，那還需要1—2cm，由此也可以證明這個推斷。雖然從四邊的任何一處都見不到針眼，但沿著畫面右上方邊緣內側1cm左右的地方有一行墨線。這大概是畫家當初有意去顯示繪畫的外框。為了繪入更多的聖像，某種程度上需要將畫面上的物品變窄。如脅侍二菩薩的蓮華座兩端的蓮瓣被描繪成幾乎直立的，顯得不協調。但是，只有這種不協調和諸像位置關係有差距的表現才使我們認為該繪畫是敦煌繪畫作品當中的佳品之一。我們有這樣一個感覺，這幅畫表現的問題還需要進一步探討，並沒有建立一個的模型。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 8"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.12</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="R.1"><title lang="eng">Paradise of Sākyamuni, with illustrations of episodes from the Baoen-sūtra</title><title lang="chi-Hant">報恩經變相</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, mid-to late 8th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.177.6cm, W.121.0 cm</p><p>British Museum, Stein painting 12.Ch.liv.004</p><p>See also Figs.18-24</p><p>This painting demonstrates the way in which sutras were illustrated in the art of Dunhuang, both in the wall paintings and in those on silk, as it can be described as a bianxiang 變相,or illustration to the Dafangbianfo baoen jing 大方便佛報恩經.The concept of baoen, or the requiting of blessings received, is one that must have easily become popular in China, since it accorded well with Chinese traditional values of filial piety. In fact the story of Prince Sujāti is taken from the xiaoyang 孝養，or filial devotion section of the Baoen-sūtra. The subject is the duty owed by a child to his parents in requitement of the blessings received from them. The merit earned by such requitement could be much greater than the original blessings (Mochizuki, 1973-74,p.4551).In the present painting, the side scenes on the right side show Sujāti’s filial devotion, to the extent of sacrificing his own body to feed his parents in a time of crisis. At the same time, the splendours and delights of the Pure Land of Sākyamuni are shown in the centre.</p><p>The painting is virtually complete, including a painted valance and the plain sewn-on silk border, except for part of the centre foreground. Its rich, yet delicate colouring, though faded, is in places extraordinarily well preserved and shows the full splendour of Buddhist painting in the High Tang period. Despite this great beauty of colour and form, the painting has rarely been reproduced before (Matsumoto, 1937, Pl. 58; Stein, Thousand Buddhas, Pl. VI, part only), and then only in monochrome. It is a fine example of a more developed paradise scene than Buddha Preaching the Law (Pl.7). In order to help the faithful to visualize the splendours of the Pure Land into which they could hope to be reborn, the depiction includes a growing retinue of attendants about the Buddha and a magnificent setting, with musicians below and pavilions above, representing the delights and beauties of the Pure Land. The main part of the assembly is gathered on a platform rising out of a lotus lake: here infant souls, newly reborn, are seen on lotus flowers joining in adoration (Pl.8-8). To either side of this assembly are narrow side scenes set in landscapes. These represent episodes from three of the nine parts of the Baoen-sūtra. Each scene is identified by a cartouche inscribed with the relevant part of the story, so that the painting could easily be used for the instruction of the faithful.</p><p>On the right side, from the top downwards, are seven episodes from the story of Prince Sujāti (Fig.22). The top scene, showing an official in red bowing before a king, is accompanied by a caption introducing the king of Vārānasī and his minister Rahula, who had conceived traitorous ambitions against him. In the second scene “a spirit appears out of space and warns the prince” of the impending attack by Rahula’s troops. Subsequent scenes show the flight of the king, his wife and son by a ladder from the walls of the city and their journey, taking with them a bag of provisions. In the sixth scene, when these have been exhausted, Sujāti is seen interposing between the king, with upraised sword, and the queen, whom he is about to kill. At the bottom, Sujāti, his body covered in wounds, is left crawling by the roadside as the king and his wife continue on their way. For the remainder of the story, see the side scenes to Stein painting 1(Figs.34, 35). The left side is divided between two stories: from the top downwards five cartouches describe part of the story of the deer mother, in which a deer conceives after drinking water in which a rishi had washed his clothes (Fig.21). Her child is shown as a woman, twice seen walking around the rishi’s cave, with lotuses springing from her footprints (Pl.8-7). From the bottom, another three scenes give part of the story of the Good and Wicked Sons, also from the Baoen-sūtra. At the bottom is the king of Vārānasī with one of his wives. The middle scene shows the childless king in front of a shrine performing ceremonies of supplication, as a result of which two sons were eventually born and named after the characters of the king’s first and second wives. The third scene, above this, shows the fulfilment of the Good Son’s vow to fill the land with treasures. The inscriptions supply more detail than the painter was able to show in these scenes, and in particular the lowest caption refers to the Good Son’s fast and to his mother’s intercession with the king to allow him to enter the ocean and cull its treasures in fulfillment of his vow.</p><p>All of these scenes are set in landscape, with a few simple conventions to aid in the telling of the story. Thus the capital of the country of Vārānasī is represented by a city wall running across the narrow picture space, and a single pavilion, open at the front and with a flight of steps, serves both as the shrine where the king makes his vows (Fig.21, upper right) and as the setting, perhaps the palace, where a spirit appears to warn the king of his minister’s impending treachery (Fig.22,upper right).The other scenes are all appropriately set in landscapes which, by means of triangular slopes, zig-zag banks and flat spaces between, offer spaces for the incidents of the story. Some of the slopes, for example in the detail shown from the story of the deer (Pl.8-7), feature tall peaks and numerous plants and trees. The pointed forms of these peaks find counterparts both in the wall paintings and in some of the banners showing scenes from the life of the historical Buddha (Pl.39-1). Broad ink strokes are used to give further emphasis to the curved slopes and the vertical banks.</p><p>In this painting the donors too are represented at the foot of these side scenes: on the right a nun and a novice, and on the left a woman, named as the lady Meng, kneeling and holding an incense burner. Her modest attitude, demure headdress and high-waisted robe all suggest a date still in the eighth century A.D.</p><p>The architecture of the buildings above the paradise assembly reflects the appearance of Tang dynasty Buddhist temples, with a gatehouse and main hall on the central axis, connected by galleries to two-storeyed pavilions on either side of the main courtyard (Pl.8-3). The gateway itself is largely hidden by the Bodhi trees and canopy over the Buddha, but its great hipped roof, with the eaves seen from below and large “owl’s tail” finials, stretches across half the picture as a kind of canopy for the whole assembly. Beyond it, a raised and balustraded causeway leads to the main hall. This has just three bays. Simple brackets crown the columns, and straight struts provide additional support between them. The space within the hall revealed by the rolled-up bamboo screens is occupied by a low dais, beyond which is a painted screen.</p><p>Although the central hall is quite small, its relationship with the gateway gives it a good deal of prominence. Both are seen from below so that it almost appears with the latter as a tall, two-storeyed building, a much larger version of the two-storeyed side pavilions. The latter display the same sequence of dark lower roof, balcony and upper roof with dark ridges and acroteria, but they are seen from above. On either side of the main axis, the open galleries have white-painted walls with square wooden windows and doors open to an interior beyond; there are lotus pedestals, six in all, along the galleries, but no figures on them. Above the roofs, the Buddhas of the Four Directions rise on cloud supports. Finally, the platform from which the entire complex rises is lined with panels of tilework elaborately decorated with floral patterns.</p><p>The painting is endowed throughout with an extraordinary richness of colour in which dark and light are used to their best effect. Examples of the way in which the painter has achieved this can be seen in the main group of deities in the centre of the painting. Here, a black ground is used behind the figures, admirably setting off the rainbow hues of the haloes. Higher up, the black roofs of the gateway and side pavilions have a similar role. The haloes themselves are carefully orchestrated: among the lesser figures, the majority have plain colours (five blue, four green). They accord well with the prevailing tones in the whole painting. On them the petals (oblong or broad overlapping, respectively) are traced in fine white lines, now barely visible. The others (four with white cloud scrolls on a purple ground, and four with similar scrolls on orange and red) are evenly distributed to encircle the main figure. Only four are fully visible, while the others are partially obscured by the haloes of the three main figures. These in turn are far more elaborate. It is not necessary to describe them, as they are clear in the plates, but it may be observed that only that of the Buddha is adorned with a series of triangles appearing between the outer rows of petals. These triangles just touch to form a regular dentellation; in later paintings they are separated so as to appear more like barbed points, and their use gradually spreads from the main Buddha to the Bodhisattvas and eventually to lesser figures as well.</p><p>The figures of the two Bodhisattvas, their compassionate faces seen from the front but gently inclined towards the central Buddha, invite comparison with wall paintings of the early Tang, such as in Cave 322 (Dunhuang bihua, Pls.124-25). They retain a compactness of design although the richness of their adornments clearly indicates a somewhat later date for the painting on silk. In the foreground, the single dancing figure (Fig.20), poised between two garudas, sways and holds aloft long narrow scarves, striped in green and brilliant purple; these, too, are reminiscent of earlier wall paintings, e.g., Cave 220 (ibid., Pl.115). Bright colours such as purple and red are used in the garments of the minor Bodhisattvas and musicians, symmetrically disposed in the groups on either side.</p><p>The silk of which the painting is made up consists of one full width of 55.5cm, and two half widths of about 27 cm each. The resulting painted area is thus slightly wider than that of Pl.7, and of course much longer, but the main figures are very much smaller, principally as a result of accommodating the narrative scenes on either side. By the careful manipulation of scale, however, the artist has been able to avoid any feeling of crowding.</p><p>Finally, a feature which deserves special mention is the elegantly finished painted valance (Pl.8-2) and borders of flowers. The valance is elaborately made up with two double white streamers tied in symmetrical bows and dividing it into thirds. An actual example of such a valance, similarly divided by prominent streamers, is preserved in the Stein collection (Vol.3, Pl.8). Above the valance is a wide border of pairs of red florets edged in yellow with green and yellow leaf motifs. Similar but narrower borders with single florets separate the main paradise scene from the narrative side scenes. The present painted valance and the painted floral border above it are on a single separate piece of silk sewn onto the top edge of the painting.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，8世紀中晚期</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高177.6厘米,寬121.0厘米</p><p>英國博物館,斯坦因繪畫 12. Ch. liv.004</p><p>參見Figs.18-24</p><p>敦煌藝術中用壁畫或絹畫來表現佛經內容的繪畫，叫“變相”。此圖正是這種變相，即大方便佛報恩經變相。“報恩”的概念，正與中國傳統道德觀念中的“孝” 相符合，因此在中國很容易普及。事實上須闍提太子的故事即源自《報恩經•孝養品》，主旨講回報父母的恩德是子孫應盡的義務，回報父母的要比從父母那裏得到的多，是報恩中的美德（望月信亨《佛教大辭典》，1973-74，4551頁）。此作品右側邊緣表現的是須闍提太子的孝道故事，面對危機，將自己身體提供給父母解救饑餓。與此同時，中央則是描繪充滿光明歡樂的釋迦牟尼淨土。</p><p>此畫相對完整，依然保留著畫著的帷幕及四周縫製的素色絹邊，只有前景中間部分稍有損壞。雖然褪了色，但某些部分仍然保留了豐富濃重的色彩，顯示了盛唐時期佛教繪畫的壯美。盡管此畫顔色、形態都非常美，但至今爲止，卻很少有將其製成圖版介紹的（松本榮一《敦煌畫研究》，1937，圖58，斯坦因《千佛洞》，圖6，僅是局部），並且也只是單色圖版。這是比上圖（圖7）《樹下說法圖》有更大發展的淨土圖的絕好的例子。為幫助信徒能夠看到希望往生的淨土的壯麗，本圖描述了佛和周圍衆多的眷屬，下端的歌伎、上端的樓閣，構成了壯觀的場面，用以描繪淨土的歡樂與華麗。聖衆的大半集中于蓮池中的寶臺上，代表再生靈魂的化生童子坐在蓮花上合掌禮拜，（圖8－8）。在聖衆兩側狹窄的邊緣，描繪有山水爲背景的故事圖，《報恩經》所記載的九段故事，有三段被描繪於此。各場景內容可以據長方形榜題來確認，這樣這幅畫可以很容易地實現對信徒的教化。</p><p>右側邊緣，從上到下繪有七段須闍提太子的故事（參見Fig.22）。最上段描繪的是身著紅衣的大臣參拜大王，附有“波羅奈國大王和心生惡逆的大臣羅睺” 的標題。第二段是警告羅睺欲派兵馬襲擊的“虛空神祗的飛來”場面。與此相接的是大王、夫人和太子在城牆上架梯逃亡，以及攜帶食糧長途跋涉的場面。第六段是，食糧斷盡，大王舉起劍欲殺妃子時，須闍提太子橫插其間的場面。最下段描繪的是，受傷的須闍提太子留在道旁緩慢地爬行，大王和夫人則繼續旅程的場面。有關故事的剩餘部分，可以參看斯坦因繪畫1（參看Figs.34，35）。左側邊緣（參照單色圖版第21圖）分爲兩段故事，上方五段榜題記述《鹿母本生》的一部分，是鹿飲了仙人洗衣服的水而妊娠的故事（參看Fig.21)。鹿所産下的孩子長成婦人，用了兩個場面來描繪當她繞行仙人所住洞窟時，足下盛開了蓮花（參看圖8-7）。最下段表現的是《報恩經》中的善友太子、惡友太子故事的三個場面。下段中繪有波羅奈國王和他一位夫人，中間描繪沒有子嗣的大王在神殿前做祈願儀式，結果國王得到二個孩子，針對他們各自不同的性格，將第一夫人的孩子名爲善友，第二夫人的孩子名爲惡友。第三段是善友太子將財寶填滿國庫的誓願得到了實現的場面。長方形榜題上詳細記述著繪畫中未表示的內容，特別是最下段的榜題，記述著善友太子絕食、母后爲了使太子實現得到摩尼寶珠的誓願，勸解大王同意他赴大海。</p><p>所有這些場面是在山水畫間展開的，爲了使場面更易理解，多加有極其簡單的象徵性的事物。諸如把波羅奈國的國都描繪爲橫穿狹窄畫面的城壁，國王施願的神殿（參看Fig.21，右上角）、神祗警告大臣即將叛逆而出現的場所（參看Fig.22，右上角），大概是宮殿，統統用正面入口和一段臺階來表示。山水畫的其它場景設計也非常恰當，三角形山丘與“Z”字形岸邊之間的空間，用來安排故事情節。一些山丘，如《鹿母本生》的細部（參看圖8-7）中，山的尖頂、無數的草木都很引人注目。在壁畫和反映佛傳內容的幡畫（參看圖39-1）中均有不少極為類似的尖頂山。爲了強調山凹處和峭立的河岸等，採用了較粗的墨線。</p><p>此幅繪畫中，供養人像繪在兩邊緣最下端。右邊有比丘和比丘尼，左邊是“孟”姓的婦人，跪持帶柄香爐。從婦女恭恭敬敬的神態以及文雅的髮髻、高胸的衣裳等看，該繪畫的年代仍是8世紀。</p><p>淨土上方的建築物構造爲中軸線上的門和中堂、配于中庭兩端的二層樓等，都有回廊連接，體現出唐時期佛教寺院的外觀（參看圖8－3）。門前的大部分被佛上方的華蓋和菩提樹遮住，仰視狀態的軒和大鴟尾攏於屋脊的巨大屋頂，橫跨著畫面的大半部分，猶如是全體聖衆的華蓋一般。其上方描繪的是通向中堂具有勾欄的臺階。中堂有三間，柱頂有簡單的斗栱，中間可以望見表示進深的數根柱子。中堂前面的竹簾上卷，內部有須彌壇，其旁有繪畫的隔扇。</p><p>中堂極小，但從與之相連的門上卻感覺不出。因爲門和中堂都被描繪成從下往上仰視的形態，與宛如擴大了的兩翼的二層樓，看似是一體的建築物。這是因爲兩翼樓閣的的配色，一層和門樓的屋頂採用了相同的黑色，二層的勾欄配合中堂的勾欄，二層的屋頂和中堂的屋頂相同，都配有同樣帶黑邊的鴟尾。但在構圖上，樓閣卻是表現爲從上向下俯瞰的狀態。中軸線左右兩邊連綿的回廊，內側無圍牆，外側牆壁塗成白色，處處顯現有向內打開的方形木窗和門。回廊中擺放著蓮花座，共六個，上面並無乘坐者。屋頂上方，有代表四個方向的四方佛乘坐在雲彩上。最后，寶壇平地而起，上面貼有一層層非常美麗的花磚。</p><p>此繪畫巧妙地運用了顔色的濃淡對比變化，顯現出極其豐富的色彩，以達到最佳效果。仔細看畫面中央的一群聖像，便可窺見繪畫作者使用色彩的理念。諸尊背景採用黑色，使背光的繁多顔色更加顯眼奪目，上方的門樓和側樓屋頂所採用的黑色亦起著同樣作用。諸尊背光色彩也非常細心地考慮其相互之間的協調：小尊背光多爲單色（五例青色，四例綠色），整體畫面的色調和諧均勻。背光上用白線繪著絢麗的紋樣（橢圓形狀和寬幅的重瓣形狀），但由於已經脫落，現在幾乎無法辨認。其他小尊的背光（紫色底子上有白色卷雲紋樣的四例，橙色和赤色底子上有同樣卷雲紋樣的四例），等距離地環繞在主尊的周圍。其中，能看見全身的只有四尊，其他被主要的三尊背光遮住了一部分。三尊主尊的背光並不精致，圖版中可見背光明亮，無需詳細說明。值得注意的是如來背光外周連接著的三角形裝飾。三角形互相銜接，有規律地排列著。但隨著時代的後移，每一個三角形都獨立存在，形狀更尖，使用範圍也從如來依次擴大到菩薩和周圍的諸小尊。 脅侍的二菩薩深懷慈悲地面向前方，但略微傾向中央的如來，對比第322窟（參照《敦煌壁畫》圖124、125）等初唐時期的壁畫，從裝飾的豐富，簡潔的圖樣看，壁畫的年代不可能比絹畫晚多少年。前景中，在二隻迦陵頻伽之間，一位舞伎在空中舞動著綠、紫兩色飄帶翩翩起舞（參見Fig.20），這讓人想起第220窟（參見《敦煌壁畫》圖115）等早期壁畫中畫面左右兩側對稱的諸像，小菩薩或樂伎穿著鮮豔的紫色和紅色服裝。</p><p>此幅絹畫由一幅寬55.5cm的絹和兩幅寬約27cm的半幅絹構成。所以畫面比圖7稍寬，當然縱向更長。但兩邊插入了故事畫，主要部分的諸尊則變得略小。然而藝術家巧妙處理了比例關係，避免了擁擠的感覺。</p><p>最後要特別指出的一點是，極具雅趣的繪製的垂幕和花柄紋樣帶（參見圖8－2）。細心描繪的垂幕，配有兩根左右對稱的白色蝴蝶結飄帶，將整體分成三段。這種垂幕在斯坦因收集品（參見第3卷圖8）中存有實物，和這個垂幕一樣，有飄帶裝飾，把整體分爲三段。垂幕的上面有很寬的紋樣帶，紋樣是每兩朵有黃色邊緣的紅色小花，與綠和黃色葉子的組合。中央淨土圖與兩側故事畫的界限則是只有一朵同樣雅致的小花的窄幅紋樣帶。上部的垂幕和紋樣帶是繪在縫於畫面上端的另一絹子上。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 9"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.36</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san-Latn">vaidūryaprabha-sūtra</title><title lang="chi-Hant">藥師淨土變相圖</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Paradise of Bhaisajyaguru, with illustrations of episodes from the Bhaisajyaguru-vaidūryaprabha-sūtra</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.206.0cm, W.167.0cm</p><p>Stein painting 36.Ch.lii.003</p><p>See also Figs.25-28</p><p>Bhaisajyaguru, the Buddha of Healing, with his paradise in the East as a counterpart to the Western Paradise of Amitaabha, was, as Professor Soper has shown (Literary Evidence, p.173), a latecomer to the Buddhist pantheon. His two principal Bodhisattvas are modelled on those of Amitābha, but do not have the distinct personalities and individual popularity possessed by Mahāsthāmaprāpta and Avalokitesvara. Bhaisajyaguru himself seems to have evolved from a coalescing of two of his Bodhisattvas with similar names, and Soper suggests that his appearance, aided by a group of twelve yaksa deities, could have been a response to the healing miracles of Christ and the twelve apostles.</p><p>Nevertheless, Bhaisajyaguru enjoyed a period of great popularity at Dunhuang, to which both this painting and Pl.16 bear witness. The present very large painting on silk is the equivalent of some of the most complex, though even larger, paradise scenes on the walls of the Dunhuang cave chapels. Its wealth of detail and fair state of preservation have led to the inclusion of many details as colour plates in this book, in order both to give a fair idea of its appearance and to provide the opportunity of comparing it with the wall paintings. After the briefest of visits to Dunhuang in September 1981,and from published reproductions and the photographs of the Lo Archive at Princeton, I can only say that some of the closest resemblances, in both composition and individual details, are to be found not at Dunhuang itself but at the smaller Yulin group of caves with painted decoration at Wanfoxia, near Anxi. These similarities will be discussed below.</p><p>The whole composition is laid out just like the depiction of Sukhāvatī, or the Western Pure Land, corresponding to the description in the Wu liang shou jing 無量壽經, which speaks of seven rows of railings, with curtains and trees, seven lakes with golden sands and lotus flowers, music and singing birds, with Amitābha immeasurably bright and glorious in the centre. Here the Buddha is Bhaisajyaguru instead, but in all respects the depiction is modelled on the paradise of Amitābha. The railings and trees border the terraces on which the assembly appears, rising out of a foreground lake. Islands of golden sand, on which birds are displaying and singing (Pl.9-4), emerge from this lake, as do lotuses with tiny Bodhisattvas (Pl.9-8) and two more on which are naked newborn souls, still crouching in the foetal position. The main dancer, with flying ribbons and whirling scarves (Pl.9-3), is in the centre, immediately in front of the altar with its golden cakra on a golden tripod bowl. On either side of her, two infants also dance, and one of them plays on an hourglass drum. The other instrumentalists are seated. From the left they include the pipa 琵琶,or lute; qin 琴,or seven-stringed zither; pipa again; and konghou 箜篌,or vertical harp; from the right, xiao 簫, end-blown flute; sheng 笙,or mouth organ; dizi 笛子,or transverse bamboo flute; and wooden clappers. In front of the dancer, a kalavinka, or bird with human head and arms, plays the cymbals and completes the ensemble. Other birds originally stood in front of this one but are now lost. Like the painting as a whole, this orchestra represents a blend of Chinese and Western elements, since the qin was the Chinese musical instrument held in highest esteem, while the pipa, of Western origin, has always been regarded as a foreign instrument and associated with gaiety and dance.</p><p>Around the throne of the Buddha and the altar in front of it six kneeling figures make offerings (Pl.9-2).The two principal Bodhisattvas, Sunlight (on the right, holding a small standing figure who in turn holds the sun disc;Pl.9-11) and Moonlight (Pl.9-10), are surrounded by numerous other figures who include the four Lokapālas (Dhrtarāstra with lion-mask helmet alone recognizable by his lute;Pl.9-6), others with magnificent animal headdresses (phoenix, snake, dragon and peacock)and two demons, one of them holding a naked babe, a detail found also in the fragment Stein painting 178*(Vol.2,Pl.50).On the extreme left and right are standing triads of a Buddha and two Bodhisattvas, advancing to the railing of the terrace in welcome(Pls.9-8,9-9).Their scarves and stoles, particularly the long white sashes of the two Bodhisattvas holding offering bowls on which are flowers and a vase, are draped with conscious effect through and over the railings, in a manner that we shall see repeated in the banners featuring individual Bodhisattvas and Vajrapani(Pls.56-58).Below them on either side are side terraces, each with six of the twelve yaksa warriors who accompany Bhaisajyaguru(Pls.9-12,9-13).</p><p>Splendid buildings form a background to the assembly. Above them, on layers of red and blue clouds, appear the figures of Avalokitesvara with a thousand hands, and Manjusri with a thousand bowls, of which the larger each contain a dhyani-buddha seated on the cosmic mountain (Pls.9-5,9-6).These esoteric figures are mirrored below by two further forms of Avalokitesvara, Chintamanicakra(Fig.25)on the left and another only identifiable by the dhyāni-buddha in the headdress and the water flask held in one of the hands. They were each accompanied by four figures, one playing a pipa, another holding a lotus, the rest largely lost through the extensive damage to the lower edge of the painting.</p><p>The depiction of the Eastern Paradise is completed by the side scenes: on the right the Nine Forms of Violent Death (Pls.9-14,9-15,Fig.28)and on the left the Twelve Vows of Bhaisajyaguru (Fig.27). Not unnaturally the latter offered far less scope for imaginative illustration than the former. But like everything else in this paradise, the Violent Deaths bear a close resemblance to the Perils from which Avalokitesvara was the saviour, so that even here the contrived and derivative nature of Bhaisajyaguru and the overwhelming debt to Avalokitesvara and his spiritual father Amitābha are manifest.</p><p>The resemblance between this painting and those at the Yulin caves is most marked in the case of the Amitābha paradise on the south wall of Cave 25,already recognized as having paintings of the Middle Tang period of particularly fine quality (Wenwu,1956/10,pp.11-13). There are close similarities not only in the disposition and style of the figures but also in minor details such as the trees and birds. It is these features that are perhaps the most telling, since although the conservatism of art at Dunhuang and nearby ensured that the main features of large compositions were enduring, this cannot have been so with small details that allowed the painters greater scope for personal preference or the exercise of observation or imagination. Thus, to take some examples, we may notice in particular the two-storeyed pavilions on either side (Pls.9-5, 9-6). In both the silk painting and the Yulin Amitabha paradise, these pavilions are flanked on either side by trees, the foremost of which have foliage disposed in tiers that partly cover the lower roofs .Following the kind of formula already established in China by the period of the Northern and Southern Dynasties, these trees have a double trunk which divides close to ground level, with a dead snag half-way up the larger limb. An elaborately finished wooden kang with a vacant lotus throne almost fills the interior of the ground floor. On the upper storey some of the blinds in both paintings are still lowered, and others raised. On the left in the silk painting there is a charming glimpse of a gandharva or apsaras looking out, while another behind is raising the blind, head and shoulders concealed behind it. Across the painting at the same level a similar figure peeps around the corner of the building, and yet another has sat down on the balcony railing, holding on with both hands and leaning forward to avoid overbalancing. This figure, and perhaps the one rolling the blind also, finds an almost exact counterpart in the wall painting (Lo Archive, nos.3005-3006). All of them show a mastery of the convincing depiction of three-dimensional space as well as a nicety of observation of realistic details.</p><p>As to the birds, in the Amitābha wall painting of Cave 25,a kalavinka and a large bird are seen on the terrace to the right and left of the main Buddha triad. All are displaying with open wings; the birds resemble swans and appear to be white, but the one on the right curiously has a peacock tail. In the silk painting (Pl.9-1), this space is filled with additional figures of the much more numerous Buddha assembly. The kalavinka, still with striped wings and billowing cloudlike tail, finds a new place in front of the dancing figure (Pl.9-3), and the large swan-like birds, one of which (on the right) is damaged but can just be seen to have had a peacock tail, stand on the golden islands in the foreground lotus pool (Pl.9-4). The parrots of the wall painting have likewise flitted to perches on the railings nearer the front of the painting.</p><p>The architecture of the main buildings is among the most splendid of any of the silk paintings from Dunhuang, although not as elaborate as the still larger paradises from the wall paintings, for example, in Cave 172 (Dunhuang bihua, Pl.144). Nevertheless, the roof of the central gateway, immediately behind the Buddha, has triple tiers of brackets, with two slanting ang 昂,or cantilever arms, prominent and a third visible on close inspection at the corners, together with the round end of the eaves purlin. The intercolumnar supports are not easily visible at first but can be seen to be of confronting S-shape with elaborately foliated ends, rather than the archaic plain inverted V; they have not yet been replaced by further tiers of brackets as in the extant ninth century hall at the Foguangsi, Wutaishan. In the painting, this gateway has a single roof. Right behind it, in a paler red, can be seen the eaves of the first-storey roof of the main hall, clearly a free-standing structure. This is crowned by a terrace and a second roof of which only one corner is properly visible, due to the loss of a major section of the painting at this point. Just enough is visible to show that this roof has similar bracketing to that of the gateway, but lacks the slanting ang. A verandah runs from the gateway, turns behind the side pavilions, and apparently runs continuously behind the main hall, with extensions to right and left behind the drum and bell pavilions, suggesting an extensive series of courtyards. The interior walls are white, with green windows and a blue floor with tiled edging and tiled surround to the well of the courtyard. Here four Bodhisattvas stand on individual lotus pedestals. Further vitality is given to the lofty features of the architecture and the canopies by the long scarves of the apsarasas and the coloured plumes that support them in an aerial dance, winding in and out between the roofs and around the canopies. The white walls and the red columns are a constant theme; green ridges on dark blue or blue roofs alternate with blue ridges on green roofs to make quite clear the division of parts.</p><p>Turning to the side scenes, the resemblances with the wall paintings here appear perhaps not so much in terms of exact parallels in depiction as in the choice of scenes taken directly from daily life. We may take as examples a banquet scene from the Maitreya paradise on the north wall of Cave 25 at Wanfoxia (Lo Archive,no.3020) and scenes from the right margin of the silk painting such as the falconer with his hound—“When intent upon hunting, sports, women or wine, to have one’s strength and will stolen by a demon” (Pl.9-14,the Third Form of Violent Death)—and the eloquent death-bed scene with monks and laymen alike reciting the scripture of Bhaisajyaguru from yellow scrolls while the sufferer lies on a kang supported by his wife (Fig.28). All are vividly observed and appear as close reflections of contemporary life. As for the landscapes, resemblances can certainly be found, for instance in the overhanging cliff just within the main scene of the wall painting in the top right corner (Lo Archive, no. 3006) and the cliff from which a man is falling in the right margin of Stein painting 36(Pl.9-15). The landscape at the top of the right margin, with a tree-covered island in front of a steep valley, is outlined in ink, with shading above the contour lines, just as in the landscapes at the top of the Maitreya paradise in Cave 25 (Flying Devis, 1980, Pl.74).</p><p>Such close similarities are both evidence of the constant dependence of the Bhaisajyaguru paradise on that of Amitābha and a vivid reminder of how rapidly motifs in Buddhist art could spread and of the uses to which paintings such as the one under discussion could be put, since we must assume either that there were models brought from Dunhuang to serve as guides for the painters at Wanfoxia, or that the painters themselves, as is more likely, travelled there to carry out the work.</p><p>While preserving the same general proportions as some of the paintings already discussed above (Pls.7 and 8), this painting is much larger. This has been achieved by the use of three complete widths of silk each around 56 cm wide, so giving a total width that is half as large again as either of the above. This seems to have been the largest size of silk painting to have been produced at Dunhuang. Besides the present example,Pls.15,16,18 and 19 are all of similar dimensions, not to mention others in New Delhi and the Musée Guimet. Since the narrative side panels are only very slightly wider than in Pl.8, there is a much larger central area that enabled the painters to depict a more numerous assembly around the central Buddha and to give the whole scene an even more ambitious architectural setting. In addition, in the present case, a mandala-like appearance is given to the whole by the inclusion, in the upper and lower corners, of four deities from the pantheon of Esoteric Buddhism (Pls.9-5, 9-6,Figs.25, 26).</p><p>Finally, as regards the dating of the painting, although it has seemed appropriate to consider it in conjunction with the other paradise paintings of early ninth century date (such as Pls.8 and 11), it seems that it may in fact date from somewhat later in the ninth century. Without more detailed comparison with the wall paintings an exact dating is not possible, but the landscape details, in which the trees and their leaves begin to be reduced to a formula, and the new stiffness of the bright white sashes, elegantly twisting over the railings on the lotus pedestals, are evidence of the increasing mannerism that followed Dunhuang’ s isolation in the period of Tibetan domination and thereafter.</p><p>Note on kalavinka: In the Sanskrit text of the Sukhāvatī-vyūha, there is simply a list of birds: hamsa (goose),krauñka (curlew), mayūra (peacock) ,suka (parrot),sālika (mynah) and kokila (cuckoo).In Kumārajīva’s translation this list appears as white goose, peacock, parrot, mynah, kalavinka and gongming zhi niao 共命之鳥 (jīva-jīva, or bird with two heads.) In the paradise paintings from Dunhuang, swans, peacocks and parrots are readily identified; kalavinkas are represented more in the form of the Indian kinnara, or musician with the wings and legs of a bird and a billowing tail. A jīva-jīva, shown as a bird with two human heads, can be seen in Fig. 38. (Taishō Daizōkyō, vol. 12,no.366, p.247a.)</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高206.0厘米 寬167.0厘米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫 36. Ch.lii.003</p><p>參見Figs.25-28</p><p>與西方淨土阿彌陀相應的是藥師如來的東方淨土，如Soper教授所講的那樣（參見Literary Evidence p.173），是佛教萬神殿中較晚登場的如來。藥師的二脅侍菩薩也是仿效阿彌陀的，但不像阿彌陀的二脅侍菩薩觀音和勢至那麽具有鮮明的性格，也沒有那麽受歡迎。藥師如來似乎是基於藥王和藥上兩菩薩而成的。 Soper教授指出，以十二神將做眷屬的藥師佛的功能，可以與基督及十二使徒的醫療奇迹相比。</p><p>不過藥師信仰曾在敦煌地區極為流行，本圖和圖16則是見証。本圖所繪，作爲絹畫是非常之大，在構圖方面可與敦煌石窟壁畫中最複雜的淨土圖相匹敵，至於大小，壁畫則更大。對細部的描寫非常出色，保存狀態也好，所以在本書彩色圖版中刊載了很大一部分，使繪畫的各個局部最大可能地得到展現，這既有利於探討它出現的原因，也有利於與壁畫進行比較。筆者曾於1981年9月到敦煌作過短暫的訪問，依據出版的圖錄和普林斯頓大學羅寄梅檔案的照片資料，不是在敦煌石窟中，而是在比敦煌石窟規模要少得多的安西近郊萬佛峽榆林窟中，發現在構圖和細部的描寫方面與其極相近的淨土圖。關於那些類似之處，將於後面詳細討論。</p><p>整體結構的設置與西方淨土的刻畫是完全一樣的，西方淨土是根據《無量壽經》而形成的，經中說：七重欄楯，七重羅網，七重行樹，皆是四寶周匝圍繞。極樂國土有七寶池，池底純以金沙布地以及蓮花、音樂、唱歌的小鳥，阿彌陀如來坐在無量光明的淨土中央。在此圖中，除了藥師代替了阿彌陀如來，其餘的描繪均模仿阿彌陀淨土。聖衆站立的若干寶台被勾欄和樹木隔開，突現于前景的池中。金沙島上鳥兒展翅歌唱（圖9-4），蓮花漂浮在池中，载着小菩薩（圖9－8），有兩個以上的菩薩是以胎兒姿勢蹲坐的新生裸體幼兒。畫面中央的祭壇上，擺放着置於三足盤上的金色香爐。正中有挥動着飄帶、旋转着披肩跳舞的舞伎（圖9－3）。其左右有兩個跳舞的童子，其中一人拍打着胸前懸挂的鼓。其餘樂伎則坐着，左側依次演奏琵琶、七弦琴、琵琶、箜篌等樂器，右側依次演奏簫、笙、笛子、拍板等樂器。舞伎前方，人首鳥身的迦陵頻伽敲着鐃鈸，組成一個大合奏。其前面原來還應有一只鳥，現在已殘缺。畫面的整體印象是，這個樂隊融合了中西两方面的文化要素。琴是中國最受珍重的樂器，而琵琶是起源于西方，通常被看成是外來樂器，正是這些樂器造就了熱烈的舞蹈氣氛。</p><p>如來寶座的周圍以及祭壇的前方有跪着手捧供物的六尊菩薩（圖9－2圖）、二脅侍菩薩、日光菩薩（9－11圖，右手捧日輪圓盤的小立像）和月光菩薩（圖9－10），周圍則是包括四大天王（持國天王，可以從身著獅子兜、手持琵琶判斷。圖9－6）在內的其他諸像，如頭戴聖獸冠（鳳凰、蛇、龍、孔雀等）的諸像、二尊魔鬼像，其中一身懷抱裸體嬰兒，斯坦因繪畫（Stein painting)178(第二卷,圖50)的绢畫斷片中也有發現。左右兩端的寶臺上有一組一佛二菩薩立像，走近勾欄以示迎接（圖9－8，9－9）。其二脅侍菩薩的披肩和飄帶，尤其是手捧装花托盘的菩薩、手捧装寶瓶托盘的菩薩身上的白色的長飾帶，有意製成褶皺狀，穿過並垂懸在勾欄上。將菩薩或金剛力士作爲個體單獨描繪的幡畫中也有這種表現形式（圖第56－58）。三尊立像正下方的左右寶臺上，每側六尊神將，總共十二尊，護衛藥師（圖9－12，9－13）。</p><p>聖衆背後配有壯麗的建築物，上方描繪有乘坐赤、青彩雲的千手觀音和千缽文殊。其中有若干大缽，裏面是須彌山，佛坐在上面（圖9－5，9－6）。畫面下端也有兩處類似密教的圖像，左邊是如意輪觀音（參見Fig.25），右邊聖像從頭戴化佛寶冠、左手持淨瓶等標誌可以判斷是不空羂索觀音（參見Fig.26）。每像應有隨從四身，一身爲彈琵琶、一身爲手持蓮花，由於畫面下端已損，無法確認另外二身。</p><p>此東方琉璃光淨土因右側邊緣的“九橫死”（參見圖9-14，9-15，Fig.28）、左側邊緣的“藥師十二大願”（參見Fig.27）的故事畫而得以完整的體現。原本“藥師十二大願” 的想象空間沒有“九橫死”豐富，然而任何一幅藥師淨土圖中，所有“九橫死”都和觀音救助危難時的風格極其相似，所以藥師如來特性的形成深受觀音及其主尊阿彌陀如來的影響是顯而易見的。</p><p>此繪畫與榆林窟第25窟南壁已經被確認為中唐的特別優秀的阿彌陀淨土圖非常相似（參見《文物》1956年第10期11～13頁），不僅諸尊的佈局和風格，而且諸如樹、鳥等細部的刻畫也極其相似。之所以要特別舉出這一點，是因爲從敦煌及其附近的美術品中，主要畫面的表現方式已趨保守並有延續，而在微細的部分，則有充分的餘地以便畫家發揮自己的經驗、觀察力及想象力。如此，舉個例子，我們特別觀察一下兩端的二層樓閣（參見圖9－5，9－6）。無論是這幅絹畫還是榆林窟的阿彌陀淨土圖，樓閣兩側均植有樹木，幾叢茂密的樹葉遮住了下层楼的屋頂。這些樹木的處理方式承襲了南北朝就已經固定了的風格，樹幹離地很近開出兩叉，粗枝中間有殘枝。樓閣一層內，細心製作的木結構須彌壇幾乎填滿了一間房子，上面放置着無人乘坐的蓮花座。上層的簾子，兩幅畫中都是有些卷起，有些垂下。絹畫左側的樓閣中可以见到朝外看的乾闥婆或者天女可愛的身影，其背後另有一位正在卷簾，頭和肩遮隐在簾後。將目光平移到右邊樓閣，則可以看到從建築物後面側身探出同樣的像，而另一個則坐在勾欄上兩手扶著，身子向前傾斜，以保持平衡。在壁畫中也能見到大致類似的情景（參見羅寄梅檔案No.3005，3006）。這些足以說明說明畫家細部写實的細致入微的觀察力和三維空間的刻畫已經達到爐火純青的程度。</p><p>第25窟壁画的阿彌陀淨土圖中，阿彌陀三尊左右的寶臺上出現迦陵頻伽和大鳥各一組，每一組都展翅欲飛。鳥非常像天鹅，白色，右邊的鳥居然有奇妙的孔雀尾。而在此絹繪图中（圖9-1），這個位置則被多尊聖像占滿。迦陵頻伽的羽毛是條紋形，尾巴似波狀雲，位置則被挪到舞伎的前邊（參見圖9－3）。另外，天鵝一樣的大白鳥，其中一隻（右邊）已損壞，只留有像孔雀尾的站立在前景蓮池中的金沙島上（參見圖9－4）。在壁畫里，有鸚鵡飛落在畫面前方的勾欄上。</p><p>敦煌絹畫中主要建築雖不如敦煌壁畫中的建築壯觀，如第172窟壁畫中的淨土圖（參見《敦煌壁畫》圖第144）。不過，如來正後方門樓的屋頂，則清楚地見到三組斗栱中有二層昂，細細觀察則發現兩角斗栱也有三層的昂，連圓檁子的頂端都表現得很清楚。柱間蜀柱最初看到的是兩個相對的尾飾葉紋的“S”形而不是帶有古風的倒“V”字形。不過，它還沒有被五臺山佛光寺9世紀大殿中所見的跳出更深的斗栱所取代。此處繪的是門樓的單層屋頂。其正上方所見的淡紅色的軒，顯然是一個獨立建築物的底層。那建築物是圍繞著勾欄的二層樓閣，因爲這部分畫面大幅破損，只能看見一角。可看到其屋頂與門樓有同樣的斗栱組合，屋頂上見不到昂。從門延伸出的長廊，繞過兩翼樓閣的背後，一邊明顯通到中堂，另一邊則延伸到左右的鼓樓和鐘樓的後邊，體現出庭院的開闊。白色的內壁，綠色的窗戶，青色的地板，院落邊緣及水池四周貼磚。四身菩薩分別踏立於蓮花座上。更生動的是，在高高聳起的建築物、華蓋上面，有身著長衣的飛天在空中起舞，拖着長長的飄帶，在層層疊疊的屋頂間和華蓋中忽隱忽現。通常的白牆赤柱沒有變化，但爲了清楚區分屋頂，青色屋頂的邊緣採用綠色，綠色屋頂的邊緣採用青色，相互交替搭配。</p><p>再看邊緣部分，與壁畫有很強的的相似性，场景的刻畫都是直接取自現實的日常生活。我們可以用萬佛峽第25窟北壁彌勒淨土圖的宴會場面（參見羅寄梅檔案No.3020）做個例子，此繪畫右側邊緣的牽著獵犬的鷹獵者—— “打獵、競技、婦人、酒等，心力被鬼神所奪” （參見圖9－14，“橫死第三”）——富于表情的臨終時的場面、比丘和世俗男子好像在誦讀黃色經卷《藥師經》、病人臥在炕上被妻子攙扶著等場景，都栩栩如生，觀察的細致入微，是當時生活的真實寫照。至于山水，如壁畫上方右角半空中突起的懸崖（參見No.3006）和斯坦因繪畫36右側邊緣男子跳下的懸崖（參見圖9－15）等處，均可看出類似的地方。繪畫右側邊緣上端峻峭山谷前的樹木覆蓋的島嶼，是用墨色的線和晕染描繪的，與第25窟彌勒淨土圖（參見《敦煌飛天》圖74）上端所描繪的山水圖相同。</p><p>此繪畫和榆林窟壁畫如此相似，說明藥師淨土圖是仿照阿彌陀淨土圖的同时，也為正在探討的佛教美術的題材是如何迅速傳播與使用的问题提供了生動的资料。因為我們必須假定是敦煌粉本傳到萬佛峽作爲那裏畫家的底本，或者是敦煌畫家親赴那裏從事壁畫製作的。</p><p>前面已經討論過尺幅相當的兩幅繪畫（參見圖7，8），這幅畫則更大。它是用三幅幅寬爲56cm左右的絹子组成，整個畫面的幅寬比上面兩個作品寬約1.5倍。這可能是敦煌所製作的絹畫中最大的作品。與其大小大致相同的作品還有圖15、16、18和19，沒有將新德里國立博物館和集美博物館的作品列在裏面。邊緣故事圖的幅寬僅略大於圖8，所以中間部位極其寬闊，作者在那裏畫入衆多圍繞主尊的聖衆，還給整個畫面配上了雄偉的建築物。另外，此畫的上下四角還配有四尊密教萬神殿的神祗，使整個畫面具有曼陀羅式的氛圍（參見圖9－5，9－6，Figs.25，26）。</p><p>最後，關于此畫的年代。盡管該畫与9世紀初淨土變密切相關（諸如圖8、11），實際上這幅畫可能在9世紀稍後的時期內。如果不與壁畫進行詳細比較，則無法判断出正確的年代。觀察山水的細部，樹木、枝葉已經開始形式化，描繪蓮池的勾欄上优雅地纏着的白色綬帶的线条，顯出僵化的苗頭，使我們感覺到，這是吐蕃時期敦煌与世隔绝後，已經公式化了的現象。</p><p>注迦陵頻伽：在梵文《佛說阿彌陀經》，為一組鳥：鵝、麻鷸、孔雀、鸚鵡、八哥、杜鵑，鳩摩羅什譯為：白鵠、孔雀、鸚鵡、舍利、迦陵頻伽、共命之鳥（一鳥二頭）。在敦煌淨土畫中，天鵝、孔雀、鸚鵡非常容易識別。迦陵頻伽，在印度是一種妙聲鳥，有鳥的翅膀和腿，波浪狀的尾巴。共命之鳥，表現為兩個人頭的鳥，可參看Fig.38（《大正藏》，卷12，no.366,p.247a）。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 10"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.70</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Paradise of Amitābha, with illustrations of episodes from the Amitāyurdhyāna-sūtra</title><title lang="chi-Hant">觀無量壽佛經變相圖</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 1st half of the 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H. 168.0cm, W.123.0cm</p><p>Stein painting 70.Ch.xxxiii.003</p><p>See also Figs.29, 30</p><p>This Amitābha paradise is comparable in size to the Sakyamuni paradise of Pl.8 and in date to the paradise of Bhaisajyaguru (Pl.9). It is, however, markedly inferior both in quality of execution and in its present condition.</p><p>In the centre, his features difficult to make out owing to the fading of the colours and the deformation of the silk, sits Amitābha, with Avalokitesvara and Mahāsthāmaprāpta seated with legs pendent on either side. He is attended exclusively by Bodhisattvas. The standing figures at the sides can be compared with a fragment from Stein painting 222 (Fig.31) which, though considerably larger and probably somewhat later, is similar in composition (other fragments from this painting still await mounting). In front of the altar and the steps leading to it is a dancer’s platform with musicians. The less ambitious nature of the painting can be gauged from the fact that instead of the usual total of ten or twelve musicians, here there are only six, three on each side. Additional platforms rising out of the lotus tank in the foreground support two more groups of a Buddha with accompanying Bodhisattvas. In a charming vignette in the centre foreground, a single garuda plays the lute for a group of birds, two peacocks and two parrots (Pl.10-3). Piles of golden sand and red and purple lotuses rise from the water, but the infant souls, newly born to paradise, find room only on the steps leading to the lower terraces on either side.</p><p>The architectural detail of the buildings above has undergone a similar process of simplification. The pattern of gateway, main hall, two-storeyed side pavilions and connecting galleries is familiar, but the columns, railings and bracketing are all indicated by flat red lines on a white background with no attempt to define the floor spaces within the buildings. Above the main buildings, where the Buddhas of the Four Directions rise in groups of three above the whole, are two empty round pavilions that presumably correspond to the bell and drum towers seen in more ambitious paintings such as Pl.9, but which in this painting have been moved to the rear for lack of space at the sides.</p><p>The side scenes (Fig.29) are those normally found with depictions of the Western Pure Land of Amitābha, namely the legend of Bimbisāra and Queen Vaidehī (see also Pl.19 and Fig.41, where the soul of the rishi slain by Bimbisāra in order to obtain a son for his wife is shown as a white hare, according to one version of the story). Arthur Waley has explained how these scenes illustrate Shandao’s commentary to the Amitayurdhyāna-sūtra, rather than the sutra itself so that they represent an Esoteric doctrine, not mere narrative illustration. This doctrine is that of “contradictory causation”, whereby evil may lead to good:“thus if Bimbisara had not slain the rishi, the rishi would not have been reborn as Ajātasatru;and if the rishi had not been born as Ajātasatru, Ajātasatru would not have imprisoned his father (Bimbisāra), and if he had not imprisoned his father, his mother could not have visited him in prison...and so on, leading finally to the point at which Ajātasatru’s crime in imprisoning his mother leads her to call upon Buddha, and hence to her reception of the famous sixteen visions. Thus Bimbisāra’s wickedness in slaying the rishi ultimately produced a contradictory (i.e.a good) effect.” (Waley,1931,p.xxi.)</p><p>Even in this painting which uses fairly simplified means of representation, there seems to have been room for the expression of individual artistic variation, as in the strangely shaped banks of the side scenes, rather like the interlocking pieces of a puzzle, and also in the life-like birds (actually magically created visions, since there are no lower forms of creation in the Pure Land).</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀前半葉</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高168.0厘米 寬123.0厘米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫 70. Ch.xxxiii.003</p><p>參見Figs.29,30</p><p>此觀無量壽佛經變相圖的大小可以與圖8的《報恩經變相圖》相媲美，年代則與前面的《藥師淨土變相圖》（圖9）相當，然而其質地以及目前保存狀態都非常差。</p><p>中央部分，阿彌陀如來結跏趺而坐，二脅侍菩薩觀音和勢至善跏趺於如來兩旁，因褪色及絹子的變形，如來面容很難看清。佛的周圍均是菩薩。可與兩側立像菩薩進行比較的資料，有斯坦因繪畫222殘片（參見Fig.31）。盡管該繪畫尺寸比較大，時代略有些晚，但構圖還是有相似之處（這幅畫的斷片有多塊，仍待裝裱）。祭壇前邊的臺階通向舞臺，舞伎伴隨樂伎舞於臺上。該圖的畫面缺少激情，與通常的舞臺上有舞伎十或十二人相比，這裡每側卻只有三人，總計才六人。前景的蓮池上，左右伸出另外兩個寶台，承載着佛和隨侍的菩薩。在迷人的蔓葉花飾的前景中央，有一隻金翅鳥為二隻孔雀、二隻鸚鵡彈奏著琵琶（參見圖10－3）。池中現出金沙島以及浮出水面的赤色、紫色蓮花，化生童子則安置在下方兩側寶臺的臺階上。</p><p>上方建築物的細部也同樣被簡化。雖然保留了門樓、中堂以及兩層樓閣、長廊等建築，但把柱子、勾欄以及斗栱等均處理成平面，只在空白處用紅色線來表現，而且無意表現建築物內的空間。從中心建築物騰起的雲彩上面，有四方佛三身。建築物的上方，繪有圓形空殿兩座，相當於圖9所見到的鐘鼓樓。在這幅畫中因為兩邊沒有空間，而被移到後面。</p><p>邊緣的故事圖（參見Fig.29），與通常所見的阿彌陀佛西方淨土變兩側一樣，即頻婆娑羅王和韋提希夫人的故事（參見圖19及Fig.41，根據一個譯本，頻婆娑羅王爲求子而殺仙人，仙人的靈魂以白兔形像出現）。Arthur Waley認爲，這種場面是根據善導的《觀無量壽佛經疏》而不是經典本身，從而不僅是故事圖，也體現密教的教義。即把“惡”引向“善”的“否定因果”。“這樣，如果頻婆娑羅沒殺仙人，仙人則無法轉生為阿闍世；如果仙人沒有轉生為阿闍世，那麽他也不會把父親（頻婆娑羅）幽禁起來，如果他沒把父親幽禁起來，那麽他母親也不會去探訪幽禁中的父親……等等，最後，阿闍世所犯的幽禁母親之罪，促使母親（韋提希夫人）求見佛陀，由此使她接受著名的十六觀。這樣，頻婆娑羅殺害仙人的惡因而產生了完全相反的結果（善）。”（Waley,1931,p.xxi.）</p><p>此繪畫中表現方式相當簡化，然而仍有空間表現畫家的獨特藝術變化，如兩側故事畫中奇妙形狀的河岸，倒不如說像迷一樣的連環鎖，及好像是實物寫生的鳥（淨土中的創造物沒有規定的形式，實際上都是幻化出來的）。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 11"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.1</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Paradise of Sākyamuni, with illustrations of episodes from the Baoen-sūtra</title><title lang="chi-Hant">報恩經變相圖</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 1st half of the 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.168.0cm, W. 121.6cm</p><p>Stein painting 1.Ch.xxxviii.004</p><p>See also Figs.34, 35,38,72</p><p>Like Pl.8, this scene depicts the paradise of Sākyamuni with side scenes illustrating the story of Prince Sujāti. Sākyamuni, both hands in vitarka-,or preaching, mudrā, is seated between two Bodhisattvas above a dancer on a platform between two groups of musicians. Below them is the familiar lotus lake with golden islands on which stand a jiva-jiva——or bird with two human heads——on the left, and a kalavinka——with one head——on the right (Fig.38). These occupy only a limited space on either side, and the main part of the foreground is devoted to a second triad with a central Buddha, accompanied by a Bodhisattva and a monk. This Buddha has on his robe various cosmological emblems (Pl.11-3): the sun and moon on either shoulder, Mt. Sumeru on the breast, and to either side of that the figures of a four-armed god and of an ascetic seated on a tripod. Although Eiichi Matsumoto proposed that this Buddha should be identified as Vairocana, it is also possible that he represents Sākyamuni in his cosmic aspect. If so, this would illustrate the main thesis of the Lotus Sutra, in the course of preaching which the Buddha revealed that the master who appeared as Sākyamuni was in fact merely a corporeal manifestation of the eternal Buddha on earth and the embodiment of cosmic truth (cf:Ch’en, 1964, p.380).</p><p>The narrative of the side scenes, taken from the Baoen-sutra, begins at the top of the right margin (Fig.35) with successive scenes following one another and continuing upwards from the bottom of the left margin (Fig.34). The first scene shows the tutelary spirit of the palace appearing to give warning to the impending treachery of the minister Rahula, in revolt against his ruler. A ladder shows the escape of the king, his wife, and little son, Sujāti. At first they have a bag of provisions for their flight, but when these are exhausted Sujāti has to intervene and offer his own flesh to save his mother from being killed for food by the king. On the left, in the third scene, the parents take two of the last three pieces of flesh from Sujati and leave him to continue on their journey alone (Pl.11-4). When they have done so, Sujati gives his last piece of flesh to some wild animals, here represented by a white lion, who finally changes into his true shape as Sakra Devendra (the god Indra) and restores Sujāti to wholeness.</p><p>In style, several features of this painting appear to point to a date in the first half of the ninth century. The composition, although more elaborate than that of Pl.7 which we have seen to be related to early Tang preaching scenes in the wall paintings at Dunhuang, is still far from being as elaborate as those of the later Tang paradise scenes. In particular the architectural setting behind the main Buddha is confined to a single large pavilion, with a verandah just visible on either side. The three principal figures are left free and prominent, to the extent that the two monk figures between them are seen at a lower level, head and shoulders only. This still recalls, although by different means, the prominence given to the Buddha in the embroidery of Sākyamuni Preaching on the Vulture Peak (Vol.3,Pl.1), where the two monks stand behind the Bodhisattvas to leave the Buddha completely free. This uncluttered arrangement means that in front of the platform with the dancer and musicians there is room for the second group with a central Buddha, accompanied by a Bodhisattva and monk.</p><p>In the actual delineation of the figures, the robes hang in smooth and easy curves, undisturbed by sudden twists or turns. The haloes of the various Bodhisattvas and musicians, indeed that of the lower Buddha as well, are chiefly composed of patterns derived from lotus petals and executed in broad outlines. The harder, more geometric lines of later halo patterns can be contrasted to this. Similarly, the facial features and hands, particularly those of the principal figures, are executed with delicacy and subtlety, as well as with care. It is possible to compare a detail such as the face of one of the Bodhisattvas, with a similar face from a later painting (Stein painting 41, dated A.D.939, Vol.2, Pl. 17) in order to appreciate this. In general, the features are contained within the facial outline, although where a figure is in three-quarter view, the line of the upper eyelid may often project beyond the outline. This happens more often, if not invariably, in the paintings of the tenth century.</p><p>The landscapes of the narrative to either side follow a pattern familiar from the cave paintings as well. In general, the scenes seem to be linked in pairs, with a major element, usually a cliff or summit, appearing above the upper scene. Although the technique looks simple, with bands of red and green colour alternating and accented by ink to mark the folds and contours, it is used to advantage. There is often a triangular wedge or repoussoir to create a flat space for the episode, a longer slope set diagonally and returning to separate a pair of scenes, and a group of rocks with a predominantly vertical stance to close with a high horizon before the sequence begins again with a foreground scene on a flat setting. These vertical elements generally incorporate an overhanging cliff. Those at the very top on either side form peaks which are easily read as being larger or more distant, although in fact the trees that grow on them differ not at all from those lower down. The trunks of these trees are set well below the horizon line, while the foliage is silhouetted beyond it. The one building shown here is set at a diagonal, but the wall indicating the capital city of the country of Vārānasī runs straight across. Cartouches for the scenes, coloured red or yellow, alternate on the margins, with the topmost one centrally placed. Unlike in Pl.8, none of the cartouches is actually inscribed, probably because the story would be instantly recognizable and its episodes readily followed from the depiction. The large panel between the two groups of donor figures below (Fig.72) is similarly left blank, and we are left to conjecture whether such a painting was simply held in readiness for a commission, or whether the donor figures had become an essential part of the whole, not to be omitted even when there was no specific donor. Their demure attitudes, kneeling with joined hands, and the broad and slightly limp cap ribbons of the men serve to confirm that this painting dates from shortly before the middle of the ninth century; the donors of Fig.73 (dated A.D.864) are a close comparison.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀前半葉</p><p>絹本设色</p><p>高168.0 厘米 寬121.6厘米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫 1. Ch.xxxviii.004</p><p>參見Figs.34,35,38,72</p><p>與圖8一樣，中央是釋迦牟尼淨土，兩側邊緣是須闍提太子本生故事。釋迦雙手結說法印，於二菩薩中間結跏而坐。其下方舞臺上，一個舞伎在二組樂伎的伴奏下翩翩舞蹈。舞臺下方，左右兩側有常見的蓮池，池中各有金沙島，左側為共命之鳥——一鳥二人頭，右側為迦陵頻伽（參見Fig.38）。然而，兩邊蓮池所占空間很少，前景的主要位置被第二组以菩薩和比丘作脅侍以佛為中心的三尊像所占。佛的袈裟上裝飾著各種宇宙標志（參見圖11－3）：兩肩上的日、月，胸部的須彌山，兩側的四臂神像，以及坐在三足鼎上的苦行者。雖然松本榮一博士提出該佛可以確定為毗盧遮那佛，也可能是象徵釋迦牟尼佛的宇宙觀。如果是这樣，則是描繪《妙法蓮華經》主要思想的。佛在經文中宣說，作為世界之主出現的釋迦牟尼不僅是永恆居世的肉身佛，而且也是宇宙真理的化身（參見Ch’en,1964,p.380）。</p><p>邊緣部位繪的故事來源于《報恩經·孝養品》，由右上方開始（參見Fig.35）依序向下展開，轉到左側時，卻是由下往上展開（參見Fig.34）。第一幅場景是宮殿保護神降臨，警告國王逆臣羅睺起兵叛亂。下方描繪梯子的場面，是國王、夫人和須闍提太子逃离的情景。最初逃離時他們攜有一袋糧食，後来糧盡，國王欲殺夫人而食时，須闍提太子獻出自己身上的肉，解救母親。左側第三幅場景描繪的是，雙親帶著須闍提太子身上最後三塊肉中的兩塊，拋下太子，繼續趕路（參見圖11－4）。他們離去以後，太子将最後的一塊肉給了代表野獸的白色獅子，獅子變回原来的帝釋天形象，使須闍提太子完好如初。</p><p>據其風格上的幾處特徵，可以斷定該繪畫是9世紀上半葉的作品。構圖上，雖然比與敦煌壁畫中初唐時期的說法圖有關係的圖7更精致，但卻遠不及晚唐以後的淨土圖精致。尤其是主尊佛像背後的建築物背景，只限於一棟大型樓閣以及若隱若現的兩側翼廊。主要的三尊主像間，除了下方有僅露出頭和肩的二身比丘外，沒有任何眷屬，十分突出。這使人想起，在刺繡《靈鷲山釋迦說法圖》（參見卷三圖1）中，爲了突出佛陀，而將二比丘安排在菩薩背後站立，從而完全解放佛陀。這樣的安排意味著是為在有樂、舞伎的舞臺前的第二組三尊像一菩薩一比丘及所脅侍的佛留出寬敞的空間。</p><p>聖像的刻畫非常寫實，袈裟没有呈扭曲或反褶，而是緩和流暢地悬垂下來。諸菩薩、樂伎（譯者按：樂伎並無頭光）以及下方的佛的頭光，主要部分用粗線描绘出由蓮瓣派生出的纹樣。這種頭光的表現形式與後來僵硬的、幾何般的線條形成鮮明對比。同樣，對臉部、手部的描繪，特别是在主要像上，非常精致、敏銳、細心。或許也可以用一個菩薩面部細部與後世具有同樣面部特徵的菩薩繪畫（斯坦因繪畫41，年代939年，第2卷，圖17）作一比較，则更容易作出評價。盡管一個畫像面部侧向，出現上眼瞼線比面部輪廓線稍微突出的例子，總的來說，五官收攏于臉部輪廓線內。到10世紀時，突出輪廓線的表現手法更加普遍了。邊緣部分的故事圖中所見的山水表現手法，承襲了石窟壁畫的圖樣。總的來說，主要風景通常都是由出現在上方的斷崖或山脈等組成。盡管技法看似單调，但紅色和綠色帶子交互搭配，用墨描绘出山凹和輪廓，彌補了其缺陷。通常是用三角形或凸形創造一個平面，以便展開故事。一個長坡呈斜對角，然後折回，把兩個故事場面分開。一組岩石呈垂直姿態，構成一個高平面。如此形成層層平面。垂直的岩石一般具體表現為陡峭的懸崖。經常巧妙地运用三角形山脈和岩石作爲分界線。如，左下部迂回的長長的山坡，斷開兩個場景。其上面是不高的山丘鄰接垂直的懸崖，從而劃開了平坦的兩個場景。上面突出的斷崖也起著同樣的作用。繪於左右兩側最上端的山脈，遠遠大於下邊的山，看似是遠處的景色。上边的樹木大小和下邊的無差別，樹雖然從山脊長出，但其葉子極其繁茂，伸到了遠山上。這裡可以看到斜置的建築，代表波羅奈國都城的城墙橫切於畫面上。说明各場面的長方形榜題分別被塗成紅色和黃色，大部分交错分配在左右兩側，只有最上方的左右兩處在中央位置上。與圖8不同，長方形榜題裏没有題字。這恐怕是因爲對該故事非常熟悉，看圖即可很容易瞭解每一場景所講的內容。下方兩組供養人（參見Fig.72）之間大的榜題也是空的，這就使我們推測是因為這是等待定做的绘画，而空置題記欄，或者是假如没有特定的供養人，這種形式也是畫面中不可缺少的重要部分。合掌跪着的供養人端莊的舉止，男供養人的寬而略彎的帽翅等，都能證實該繪畫是9世紀中期稍前的作品。与Fig.73的供養人像（864年）極其接近。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 12"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.131</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san-Latn">Samantabhadra</title><title lang="chi-Hant">普賢菩薩像</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, late 8th-early 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.57.0cm, W.18.5cm</p><p>Stein painting 131.Ch.xivi.006</p><p>This painting in subdued colours on brown silk is one of the most beautiful paintings from Dunhuang. Although small in scale and properly belonging to the group of banners to be treated later in this volume, it is shown here because it shows to advantage stylistic features that are common to some of the larger paintings of relatively early date, in this case probably of the late eighth to early ninth century A.D.</p><p>The subject is one that is frequently depicted in wall paintings at Qianfodong, particularly during and after the period of Tibetan control (A.D.781-847). There seems little doubt that, although the headpiece and other accessories (cf. Pl. 28) for complete banners had already disappeared when the painting was found, this was originally a banner intended to be hung independently, probably with the Bodhisttva Mañjusri, closely associated with Samantabhadra during the Tang dynasty, on a similar banner.</p><p>The Bodhisattva sits in a relaxed pose on his vehicle, the six-tusked elephant, with hands in vara-mudrā. The elephant, advancing towards the right, turns to look back to the left, while the Bodhisattva faces the spectator squarely. One forefoot of the elephant is raised above its white-petalled lotus blossom. The other feet, each on its own red blossom, are firmly planted. Thus, although the composition is still, there is an implied or expected movement, which helps to give spatial interest to the narrowly vertical composition. This can be contrasted with the strong movement towards the centre seen in paintings such as Pl.23, dated A.D.864, and Vol.2, Pls.13 and 14, where Mañjusrī and Samantabhadra are each accompanied by a large advancing retinue, and where the canopies over each of them are seemingly blown back by the breeze created by their movement.</p><p>The subtle means by which the artist has given life to the whole composition are of course also present when we look at other details. Samantabhadra’s face is calm, framed by his dark hair of which two locks descend at the temples so that the generous curves of the full cheeks are set off by a gentle concavity at this point. The red lips, faintly outlined in pale ink, are divided by a dark ink line with rounded ends turned gently upwards, giving the effect of a slight smile and strongly contrasting, in its softness and roundness, with the abbreviated technique used for this feature from the end of the ninth century onwards. The shoulders and foreshortened arms are framed by long locks of dark black hair. A long, narrow white riband hangs in a continuous loop from either shoulder and down between the knees, following every curve of the underlying body and garments and so avoiding the stiffer and more symmetrical appearance of such scarves in later figures.</p><p>Despite the faded colouring of the painting today, enough remains to suggest that it was originally quite sumptuous. The lotus throne on which Samantabhadra sits seems to have had blue petals, and his outer robe is shaded in a purplish red in contrast to the strong bright red of the inner garment. The elephant, white with gentle modelling washes in pinkish flesh colour, has a splendid harness of dark brown leather edged in bright yellow. The painting was originally bordered, as with many of the banners, with dark brown borders down each side and a band of lozenges at the bottom.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，8世紀末—9世紀初</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高57.0厘米 寬18.5厘米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫131.Ch.xlvi.006</p><p>這幅繪在淡雅的黃色絹面的畫是敦煌繪畫中最精美的作品之一。盡管尺幅很小，本應把它歸入本卷後的幡畫組裡，之所以刊載於此，是因為它具備一些早期的大型作品的共同特徵，相當于8世紀末至9世紀初的作品。</p><p>這個題材在敦煌千佛洞壁畫中盛行，特別是在吐蕃占領時期（吐蕃占領年代，781年～847年）及以後。發現該繪畫的時候，盡管作為一個完整的幡所需的幡頭及其他附屬物等（參見圖28）已經遺失。它也許原來就是單獨懸掛的，也有可能是和文殊菩薩的幡配對掛在一起，唐代文殊菩薩與普賢菩薩聯系密切，也經常出現在一個幡上。</p><p>普賢菩薩悠閑地乘坐在他的坐騎六牙象上，兩手結著與願印。菩薩面向正前方，而大象身向右方，頭向左盼。大象的一只前足從盛開的白蓮上擡起，其餘則各自牢牢地踏在鮮紅的蓮花上。這樣，儘管構圖是靜止的，但此繪畫中隨處可見表现動感的暗示或願望，這使縱長狹窄的畫面结构具有空間感。這可與諸如圖23，年代864年，第2卷圖13、14等圖中，從畫面的兩端向中央強烈運動的表現形式相對比。众多眷屬伴随文殊和普賢行進，他们的行动卷起微風，諸尊頭上的華蓋在風中向後飄揚。</p><p>我們看一下其他細節，也可以發現畫家在構圖中爲增加生活氣息所採用的精妙手法。例如，普賢菩薩的面部文靜，面部邊緣的黑髮結成小串妝到鬢角處，形成淺凹，使人感覺下邊的臉頰鼓了出來。另外，紅色的唇以薄墨做輪廓線，閉著的唇界線拉著很長的濃墨，線兩頭稍呈圓形往上輕輕翹起，以示微笑。唇兩端的柔和的圓線，到9世紀末以後，逐漸被省略。兩肩以及爲了突出深度而略顯短的手腕背後，黑髮呈蕨爪狀垂下。細長的白色裝飾帶從頸部垂到膝間，隨著身體和衣著的曲線彎曲，沒有陷於後來所見的諸像天衣那樣左右對稱的死板模式。</p><p>現在雖然有所褪色，但從目前保留的情況可以推測當初它是一件非常華麗的作品。普賢乘坐的蓮花座花瓣原來是用青色賦彩的，菩薩的外衣採用偏紫的紅色來渲染，與內衣明亮的紅色形成強烈對比。大象是白色上加粉紅的膚色，使其顯得溫和，極有肉感。大象帶著黃邊的黑褐色的華麗皮製挽具。此繪畫原與其他幡畫一樣，周圍曾有邊框，現僅兩邊殘存有黑褐色邊框以及底邊的一根菱形帶。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 13"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.8</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san-Latn">Avalokitesvara (detail)</title><title lang="chi-Hant">觀世音菩薩像（局部）</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, late 8th-mid-9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.119.5cm, W.55.4cm</p><p>Stein painting 8.Ch.lvi.0016</p><p>See also Fig.36</p><p>Avalokitesvara is shown in three-quarter view, holding a sprinkler vase between the fingers of his right hand, and a spray of willow over his shoulder in his left. Despite the loss of the border and parts of the top and bottom of the painting itself, including a large part of the halo and the top of the head (Fig.36), the painting is generally in good condition. The damage to the halo was probably caused by the corrosive nature of the green pigment used. The top of the head of the “parent” figure of Amitābha can just be seen as all that remains of the headdress. To the left of the nose above the mouth, the damage extends some way into the face and there is some restoration on the backing silk, but the rest of the face is original, and was originally white, shaded with pink. The elegant token moustache and wisp of beard were probably originally green. An ink line, swelling at the right end, divides the lips.</p><p>The Bodhisattva’s long black hair, although not visible around the head, frames the shoulders on either side and ends in broad, swelling locks behind the elbows, with a smaller upturned lock on either shoulder. A green stole covers the shoulders and falls in parallel folds outlined in ink. Although these ink lines seem to waver, this is probably due to distortion of the weave, and the original appearance of these lines would have been smooth and flowing. Some idea of this may be gained from the appearance of the narrow white riband or sash hanging from the neck, which descends in an easy loop, swaying with the movement of the body and over the gathering of the stole at the waist. Underneath the stole, the crimson underrobe, orange-shaded skirt and white folds around the waist are all clearly distinguished.</p><p>The Bodhisattva wears a broad belt whose edges and buckle holes are a reddish brown, outlined in ink and highlighted in yellow. Apart from a single string of purple beads, the same combination of colours is used for all the other ornaments worn by the figure, from the earrings and pendants of the headdress to the breast pendant, the wrist bangles and the longer series of pendants hanging from a large central rosette. Both in form and colouring, this type of adornment for Bodhisattvas seems to have found favour over a long period at Dunhuang, and especially during the ninth century.</p><p>Painted as it is upon a single width of silk, the painting must originally have been considerably taller than it is now if we allow for the canopy above and the missing portion of the lower robes and feet on a lotus pedestal. The total height may thus originally have been about 150-160 cm, or close to the height of the large paradise scenes such as Pl.9. In the caves at Dunhuang and Yulin, large figures of Bodhisattvas can be seen flanking the paradise scenes, as for instance the figure of Avalokitesvara on the left side of the Maitreya paradise in Cave 25 at Wanfoxia (Warner, 1938, Pl.ⅩⅩⅩⅥ). It seems almost certain that the present painting, with Avalokitesvara in a similar stance and with a similarly placed cartouche, was intended to be hung next to a paradise scene. Indeed it could hardly have hung on its own.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，8世紀末～9世紀中葉</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高119.5厘米 寬55.4厘米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫 8.Ch.lvi.006</p><p>參見 Fig.36</p><p>側立的觀音像右手指間持淨瓶，左手握著搭在肩上的小柳枝。盡管周圍的邊框和畫面上下的一部分均已殘缺，以及大部分頭光和頭的頂部也不能倖免（參見圖36），總的來說保存狀態大致良好。頭光的損壞，大概是因爲所使用的腐蝕性較強的綠色顔料導致的。寶冠也基本完全遺失，僅能看見上方殘留的化佛頭頂。口的上方到鼻子左側都有傷殘，經過下襯絹子的修復。臉的其餘部分保持原樣，白色上面用粉色渲染，雅致的唇髭和一綹顎須原來大概是綠色的。嘴唇合閉處拉出很長的墨線，右端往上略翹。</p><p>菩薩長長的黑髮繞在頭上是看不見的，但能見到沿著兩肩下垂，在肘後變寬向上卷起，並在肩上結有小型的纓狀。綠色披肩搭在肩上，褶縐用墨線表現，平行下垂。墨線本應是光滑流暢的長線，看似的波浪狀，可能是由於織物扭曲所造成的。這一點，從頸部垂下的白色細長裝飾帶就能明白。那裝飾帶描繪的是隨著身體的動作搖擺曲線緩緩下垂，到腰部通過從左到右橫跨的外衣，下方呈環狀。綠色外衣裏著深紅色內衣，與用橙色暈染的裙和腰部白色衣褶等形成鮮明對比。</p><p>菩薩束寬大的腰帶，其邊緣和孔為紅棕色，輪廓用墨線上加黃色亮光。除了紫色小珠子串聯的首飾，從寶冠上的垂飾到耳環、胸前的纓絡、腕釧以及腹部大圓形飾物和下垂的長長飾物等等，該像的裝飾品都採用了上面的相同色調組合。菩薩裝飾品採用此種色調和形狀，是因爲這種表現方法很長一段時間在敦煌頗受歡迎，特別是9世紀尤爲流行。</p><p>這幅畫畫在單幅寬的絹上，如果我們考慮到頭上的華蓋、下方殘缺的裙裾和踏著蓮花座的足等因素，該畫當初無疑要比現在要高。原來的高度大約在150～160釐米，與圖9淨土變的尺寸接近。敦煌和榆林窟壁畫中，可見側立在淨土變旁的大型菩薩像。如，萬佛峽第25窟的彌勒淨土變相圖左側，繪有巨大的菩薩像（Langdon Warner ：Buddhist Wall-Paintings，1938，圖36）。由此可以確認，該繪畫與另一幅繪有相同姿勢、相同榜題的觀世音菩薩像懸挂於淨土變兩側。這幅畫確實無法單獨懸挂。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 14"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.25</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san-Latn">Avalokitesvara (detail)</title><title lang="chi-Hant">觀世音菩薩像（局部）</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, mid-9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.101.6cm, W.58.5cm</p><p>Stein painting 25.Ch.0091</p><p>See also Fig.37</p><p>Although very much faded, this painting of the Bodhisattva Avalokitesvara is very well painted and surely belongs to the ninth century. The Bodhisattva holds a willow spray in the right hand and a water vase in the left; from this vase there issues a tall waving spray with lotus buds and leaves, as well as small pairs of opposing leaves of a completely different kind. Clearly the artist had no personal knowledge of the appearance of a real lotus, or was more concerned to echo in his depiction the graceful benevolence of the figure in the sinuous curves of the stem. New leaves and flower buds succeed each other very much as successive landscape scenes were placed one above another in the side scenes to paradise paintings.</p><p>The Bodhisattva is seen full face, the body swaying slightly to his left, so that the left shoulder is brought slightly forward. All pigment has faded from the face, leaving only the ink lines contouring the main features. Behind the “parent” figure of Amitābha in the headdress, the twin branches of the topknot are seen; The rest of the hair falls behind the shoulders, with fanciful upturned locks here and more substantial swelled ends at elbow level. In this it is rather similar to Pl.13, but the stole, originally purple with a green lining, is narrower and reveals part of the upper left arm; beneath it is a red sash, rather than an underrobe, so that the lower torso is again partly exposed. The rippling edges of the stole, looped up near the shoulders and falling over the right arm or open to reveal the left, all display a lively appreciation of space and movement that can be contrasted with the stiffer formalization of the same motifs in, for example, Stein painting 22 (Vol.2, Pl.3).</p><p>At the lower right of the painting kneel two female donors, each holding a lotus (Fig.37). They too are of early or mid-ninth century type, to judge by the simple hairstyles. The painting has lost a certain amount at the bottom, as well as its borders, but appears to be almost complete at the sides and top. The cartouche in the upper left corner, like that in Pl.13, was left uninscribed.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀中葉</p><p>絹本设色</p><p>高101.6釐米 寬58.5釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫 25.Ch.0091</p><p>參見Fig.37</p><p>此觀世音菩薩像褪色嚴重卻是一件傑作，確實是9世紀的作品。菩薩右手持柳枝，左手提淨瓶，彎彎曲曲的長莖從瓶口伸出，莖上除蓮花蕾和葉子外，其他都是別類植物的小對葉。繪此畫的畫家也許沒見過真正的蓮花，也許是著意體現觀音的慈悲普及到彎曲的長莖。本幅畫中的樹葉和花蕾與淨土變相圖常常在邊緣繪製的連續山水畫非常場相像。</p><p>菩薩面朝前方，腰稍左扭，左肩往前突出幾分。面部顔色完全消失，僅存主要輪廓的線描。帶有化佛的寶冠的後面露出二個髮髻，頭髮垂於兩肩，並在肩部形成奇特的向上卷起的結，髮稍在肘的位置膨起。這髮型與圖13近似，而長衣當初是紫色，裏子爲綠色。其衣幅寬度大大縮小，露出部分左邊的小臂。長衣裏只穿著紅色帔帛，因此腹部也稍露在外。帔帛呈波浪形，柔和地從左肩懸落到右腕，剩餘的一部分搭在左臂上。這樣，此畫對動態和空間的處理使人感觉非常出色，比較而言，同一題材的繪畫，如斯坦因繪畫22（第2卷圖3），就顯得形式化而死板了。</p><p>畫面右下方跪有持蓮花女供養人像二身（參見Fig.37）。她們髮型簡樸，可以判斷是9世紀初或中葉的作品。邊框和畫面下部殘損相当嚴重，上部和兩側卻保存較完整。左上角長方形榜題也和前圖的情況一樣是空白的。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 15"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.35*</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Paradise of Amitābha, with illustrations of episodes from the Amitāyurdhyāna-sūtra (detail:Bodhisattva and attendants on Buddha’s left)</title><title lang="chi-Hant">阿彌陀佛淨土</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, early 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.173.5 cm, W.120.0 cm</p><p>Stein painting 35* . Ch.lvi.0034</p><p>See also Figs.39-42</p><p>In general form and appearance, this painting (see also Fig.39) somewhat resembles the Amitābha paradise already examined (Pl.10). Amitabha, with Avalokitesvara and Mahasthamaprapta, is seated in the centre. Numerous other Bodhisattvas are arranged in square formations around the two main ones, while two figures kneel and make offerings towards Amitabha from either side of the central altar table. Below, the musicians are seated, five in a row on either side. In front a dancer and a garuda appear on two separate terraces, diminishing in size. Additional triads of a Buddha and attendants appear on the side terraces. The marginal scenes are of the meditations of Queen Vaidehī, on the left, and the story of Bimbisāra, on the right (Figs.40,41). The whole painting is very much abraded and worn, and there are signs of a somewhat hurried finish, for instance in the architectural features at the top of the painting, where no effort has been made to give any depth to the side galleries, and where the bell and drum towers have been fitted in, placed over the side gallery roofs without any means of support.</p><p>The detail shown here is of Avalokitesvara, holding a lotus. It is this figure and that of his counterpart Mahāsthāmaprapta on the other side (Fig.42) which provide the main clue to the date of the painting, as unlike all the other figures in it, they are clearly influenced by non-Chinese models. Avalokitesvara, in lalitāsana pose and wearing diaphanous purple trousers and a sash, but otherwise naked above the waist, has an oval halo. Mahāsthāmaprāpta, holding a vajra, has a similar appearance, and both have locks of hair falling on the shoulders, a feature that we shall see in other paintings of the period of Tibetan domination at Dunhuang. In particular, these two Bodhisattvas can be compared with those who accompany Bhaisajyaguru in the very large painting of Pl.16, which is dated A.D. 836,towards the end of that period. Thus we may see transitional characteristics in the art of Dunhuang in the early ninth century, when the process of absorption of fresh sources of style and iconography was still continuing, and before the increasing isolation of Dunhuang from both China and the West led to a corresponding loss of vigour in the paintings of the Five Dynasties and Northern Song.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀初</p><p>絹本设色</p><p>高173.5釐米 寬120.釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫35*. Ch.lvi.0034</p><p>參見Figs.39－42</p><p>該繪畫（參見Fig.39）在形式和外觀上，與已經講過的《阿彌陀佛淨土》很相似（圖10）。中央部位做坐着阿彌陀，以及觀音和勢至。有很多小菩薩圍繞著這幾尊主像，排列成正方形。中央祭壇的兩側，有向阿彌陀跪着奉供物的二菩薩像。其下方的舞臺兩側，各坐一排五個樂伎。舞伎和迦陵頻伽的前方兩側配有兩個獨立的小型寶台，上面佈有一組佛及脅侍。左側邊緣绘韋提希夫人的“十六想觀”，右側邊緣绘“頻婆娑羅的故事”（參見Figs.40，41）。在嚴重殘損的畫面上，又有使人有匆匆忙忙完成的感觉。例如，以畫面上方的建築物來説，沒有著意表現回廊深度，鼓樓、鐘樓均無支撐點，看似直接蓋在回廊的屋頂上。</p><p>本圖版局部描寫中，觀音菩薩左手持蓮花。此像与对面對應位置上的勢至菩薩（參見Fig.42），为判斷該畫的年代提供了主要線索。即，這二身菩薩与其他像不同，明顯受了不同於中原圖像表現形式的影響。觀音身著紫色網狀袴和帔帛，穩穩坐著，上半身幾乎裸露，有橢圓形頭光。勢至持金剛杵，亦取同樣姿勢。兩者肩上都垂落像蕨芽形的頭髮，此在吐蕃時期的敦煌繪畫中常見。特別是，通过二菩薩的表現形式，與有836年纪年近于吐蕃末期的大幅作品（參見圖16）中藥師的二脅侍菩薩进行比較，我們可以認爲，該繪畫有接近9世紀初敦煌美術在過渡时期的特徵，还在繼續吸取式樣和圖像方面的新鮮事物，它是五代和北宋時期敦煌逐漸隔绝於中原和西方，導致敦煌繪畫喪失活力之前的作品。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 16"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.32</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Paradise of Bhaisajyaguru</title><title lang="chi-Hant">藥師淨土圖</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, Tibetan period, dated bingchen(A.D.836)</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.152.3cm, W.177.8cm</p><p>Stein painting 32.Ch.xxxvii.004</p><p>See also Figs.43-46</p><p>In spite of extensive damage to the lower half, this painting is one of the largest silk paintings from Dunhuang. It is also one of the most important because the central inscription in Tibetan and Chinese, although almost completely faded when first seen, can be read and does provide a date. This inscription (see below) had not been read when Waley catalogued the Stein collection, but has recently been revealed by infra-red photography (Fig.43) and published by Heather Karmay in her book on Early Sino-Tibetan Art. Her translation of the Tibetan part reads as follows:</p><p>In the year of the dragon, I, the monk dPal-dbyangs, painted in a group the images of Bhaisajyaguru; Samantabhadra; Mañjusri-kumara; a thousand-armed, thousand-eyed Avalokitesvara; Chintāmanicakra; Parina-tacakra etc., for the benefit of my health and to transfer the merit (?) (created by the act of painting, to all beings).</p><p>The Chinese inscription, in nine columns from left to right, repeats the substance of the Tibetan part, but is more specific as to date. More of the text can be made out than when it was published by Karmay:</p><p>建造畢</p><p>丙辰歲九月癸卯朔十五日丁巳</p><p>□共登覺路</p><p>□□□法界蒼生同</p><p>以此功德奉爲先亡□#</p><p>空羂索一軀</p><p>千眼一軀如意輸一軀不</p><p>一鋪文殊普賢會一鋪千手</p><p>敬畫藥師如來法席</p><p>Respectfully painted one group of Bhaisajyaguru on his dharma seat; Mañjusrī, Samantabhadra and their assemblies, one group; thousand-armed, thousand-eyed (Avalokitesvara), one group; Cintāmanicakra, one group; Amoghapāsa, one group; through this to acquire merit on behalf of his deceased (father and) mother...to be reborn in the Dharmadhatu ...together ascend the way of enlightenment. The year bingchen, ninth moon guimao, the first fifteen (days), the day dingsi, executed and completed.</p><p>This inscription is set in the very centre of the painting as it survives today, rather than below as with most of the silk paintings. Both the Chinese and the Tibetan texts agree in giving precedence to Bhaisajyaguru (Pl.16-3), who presides over the whole in the top centre, accompanied by two Bodhisattvas and a numerous retinue. For the rest, the text confirms what is already fairly clear from the painting. Below, on either side of the inscription, Samantabhadra and Mañjusrī are clearly recognizable by their vehicles (Pls.16-4,16-5), while at the bottom Avalokitesvara (Fig.46) in the centre can be seen to be accompanied on the left by one of his transformations, Cintamanicakra (Fig.45), with the missing figure on the right identified by the Chinese text as yet another form of Avalokitesvara, Amoghapāsa. The popularity of Mañjusrī and Samantabhadra in the period of Tibetan domination at Dunhuang is attested to by many wall paintings, and the great size of Avalokitesvara here demonstrates his popularity also. The painting is indeed identified as a mandala of Avalokitesvara by Waley, supported by Karmay, but I prefer the precedence which the dual inscription seems to give to Bhaisajyaguru. Perhaps this is not so much the paradise of the Medicine Buddha, however, as a composite reflecting the personal predilections of the Tibetan monk who commissioned the painting.</p><p>Not only the dual inscription in Tibetan and Chinese, but the painting itself reveals its Tibetan connections, for here in the same composition we find, as Heather Karmay has pointed out,“two quite different styles that existed side by side in Dunhuang. The first, in which the main body of the painting is painted, is in Chinese style, and the second, confined to the portrayal of the Bodhisattvas on either side of Bhaisajyaguru, may be directly associated with the group of Tibetan paintings [from Dunhuang].” In fact, of course, it is not so much two different styles as the integration of two different modes of depiction that we find here, since the actual means-line and colouring-is exactly the same for both types of figure. The initial drawing is in pale ink, still quite easily discernible in details such as the eyebrows. Over this is the white of the skin color, with slight shading in pink. Finally, outlines such as those of the eyebrows, mouth and major drapery lines are drawn again in a darker ink, or, in the case of the hands and fingers, ears and nose, in red. These represent common stylistic elements which are, I think, sufficient to show that the same artists were at work here. Where the figures differ is in their attitudes, in the configuration of their facial features, and in the clothes that they wear. The two chief Bodhisattvas above, lightly clothed in the Indian manner, are seated with one leg pendent, the body swaying to one side, the head not only inclined in the opposite direction but also lengthened on the one side and foreshortened on the other, while the hair falls in many small ringlets over the shoulders. This is in contrast to the demurely clothed figures of Manjusri and Samantabhadra below, although they also are seated with one leg pendent. They have almost symmetrical faces and long smooth locks of dark hair framing the shoulders and arms.</p><p>In some ways the painting appears to be midway between a mandala and the usual type of paradise painting with an architectural setting. There is a landscape background, clearly visible in the upper left (Pl.16-7) and originally in the right corner also. This can just be seen to have extended behind the central Buddha group also, and the latter is flanked by now-faded plantain trees. The space around is sparsely filled with flowering plants, but there are dividing lines of tiles also, suggesting a rectangular platform for the main group and dividing the middle assemblies of Manjusri and Samantabhadra from the triad at the bottom. Some of the most charming details are the small figures of flying apsarasas around the canopies of these two Bodhisattvas; in addition one attendant on either side holds a staff from the top of which flies a panelled banner with streamers. These two great assemblies, like the apsarasas and the smaller groups of sixteen and eighteen seated figures above them (Fig.44), are essentially supported on clouds which issue out of the landscapes above. All are shown advancing towards the centre. The triad below is static, dominated by the geometric forms of the multiple arms of Avalokitesvara and the great white red-bordered circles of the haloes of Cintamanicakra and Amoghapasa.</p><p>As explained by Karmay, the only bingchen year to fall within the period of Tibetan domination at Dunhuang corresponds to A.D.836. Among the sutra manuscripts also, those of this period which bear dates commonly lack any indication of the Chinese reign period, and are dated, as one might expect, by the cyclical combination alone. As the style, too, is manifestly of the ninth century, and the depiction of Manjusri and Samantabhadra not far removed from such a securely dated example as Pl.23, this date can be regarded as reliable and of considerable value in understanding the development of painting at this time.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，吐蕃佔領時期，丙辰年（836年）</p><p>絹本设色</p><p>高152.3釐米 寬177.8釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫 32.Ch.xxxvii.004</p><p>參見 Figs.43－46</p><p>儘管下邊大半部分已缺失，但該繪畫仍屬敦煌絹繪中超大型作品之一。說其重要是因爲在中央部位有吐蕃和漢文對照的題記，因為褪色，肉眼幾乎無法看清，但仍可識讀，並提供年代。Waley編寫斯坦因收集的敦煌繪畫目錄时，尚不能解讀此題記，而近年通過紅外線拍照才達到解讀的可能（參見Fig.43）。Heather Karmay在其著作《早期中原與西藏藝術》（Early Sino-Tibetan Art）中有介紹，她将吐蕃文解讀如下：</p><p>辰年，我，比丘dPal-dbyangs，繪藥師如來、普賢、文殊、千手千眼觀音、如意輪觀音、不空羂索觀音等諸像，爲了自身的健康並宣揚佛法（通過繪像普渡衆生）。</p><p>漢文題記是從左到右豎寫的，共九行，內容與吐蕃文重復，年代標記更爲明確。現在，此漢文題記比Karmay發表時解讀的更爲詳細。</p><p>建造畢</p><p>丙辰歲九月癸卯朔十五日丁巳</p><p>□共登覺路</p><p>□□□法界蒼生同</p><p>以此功德奉爲先亡□考</p><p>空羂索一軀</p><p>千眼一軀如意輪一軀不</p><p>一鋪文殊普賢會一鋪千手</p><p>敬畫藥師如來法席</p><p>這些題記，不像其他很多繪畫那樣記在下方，而是在現存畫面大致中央的位置上，因而保存至今。漢文和吐蕃文兩方題記一致推崇的藥師如來（參見圖16－3），随帶二脅侍和衆多眷屬坐于上部中央，統轄整个畫面。其他諸像雖然在畫面上均可判別，但題記更能幫我們確認。下方題記兩側是普賢和文殊菩薩，可以從他們的坐騎很容易做出判斷（參見圖16－4，16－5）。另，下段中央是千手千眼觀音（參見Fig.46），左邊伴有觀音變身之一的如意輪觀音（參見Fig.45），右邊残缺的像，通過漢文題记可以判斷是另一觀音變身：不空羂索觀音。吐蕃時期，敦煌地區流行文殊和普賢，從石窟壁畫的諸例也可證明。這幅畫中的觀音佔據了較大的空間，也可確認觀音的流行。Waley確認此畫為觀音曼荼羅，Karmay也支持這个觀點，而我是從合璧的文字題記中藥師如來的優越地位得到確認的。其實，此畫並不是完全按藥師淨土圖的形式製成的，恐怕是按照吐蕃僧人帶有個人喜好的要求而製作的作品。</p><p>不僅題記是吐蕃文和漢文合璧，繪畫表現上也有吐蕃化的成分。有關兩種形式的融合，我們也從畫面上可以看到。這一點正如Heather Karmay已經指出的，“……在敦煌，有兩種完全不同的形式共存。首先是繪畫的主要图像體現了完全中國化的形式，其次是在[敦煌]的一系列藥師的兩脅侍菩薩與吐蕃有緊密联係。”當然，實際上我們在這裏看到的，與其說兩種不同形式的共存，還不如說兩種不同圖像表現的統一。在兩種圖像中，線條和顔色均採用了完全一致的手法。比如可清楚辨认的眉的部分，用薄墨描下線；皮膚塗白色，用粉色薄薄晕染；施彩後，眉、口以及衣褶等均用濃墨描出，而手和指、耳朵等卻用紅色線。因爲兩种圖像都存在這種共同的表現方式，所以，可以充分肯定在該畫是由同一組畫家製作的。圖像表現不同的地方，體現在那些姿態上，即容貌和身上的衣裳的區別上。上邊的二脅侍菩薩著印度風格的輕衣，結半跏趺姿勢而坐。不僅身體向一邊扭，頭側向反面，頭的一側也顯得稍長，反側略短，有深度感。一方面，披在肩上的頭髮，髮梢形成小卷。這與下面同樣結半跏趺,姿勢端正的文殊和普賢的形成對比。文殊和普賢的面部幾乎是左右對稱的，頭髮長而平滑，可見多處結，從肩上懸到手腕。</p><p>該畫的內容，按慣例位置應在配有建築物的淨土圖和曼荼羅之間。左上部的風景（參見圖16－7）尚殘留，當初在右上部也應繪有同樣的風景。另外，藥師三尊和眷屬背後一帶也應繪有風景，月光菩薩左邊略微残留的阔葉植物想必是那風景構圖的一部分。其周邊的空白處分佈稀疏的花草，上方藥師三尊群體所乘坐的寶台、中段文殊以及普賢菩薩群體和下段三尊群體的分界線是排列的磚。此畫有很多富有魅力的細節，尤其引人注目的有圍繞文殊和普賢華蓋上空起舞的小飛天，以及文殊和普賢各有一位随從手握帶著流蘇的幡竿。文殊、普賢兩群體上方的由十六～十八身小型坐像組成的群體（參見Fig.44），像飛天一樣，乘着雲從上方飞來，他們看似是向中央前進。下段三尊是靜止的，以千手千眼觀音的衆手構成的幾何形背光、如意輪觀音和不空羂索觀音紅色邊緣的白色圓形背光，佔據了畫面的大半部分。</p><p>如同Karmay說明的那樣，吐蕃時期，敦煌與丙辰年相應的是只有公元836年。在佛經中，吐蕃時期通常不使用中國年號，而是使用干支來標識年代。風格上很明顯是9世紀的作品，文殊和普賢的表現方式與有確切紀年的彩色圖版第23圖《四觀音文殊普賢圖》無大差別。因此，判斷此作品中的紀年“丙辰”为836年是可信的。在研究吐蕃時期敦煌繪畫的发展上，它是極其重要的作品。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 17"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.50</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Amitabha with the Eight great Bodhisattvas (detail)</title><title lang="chi-Hant">阿彌陀八大菩薩圖（局部）</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, Tibetan period, early 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.95.0 cm, W.63.5 cm</p><p>Stein painting 50.Ch.0074</p><p>See also Figs.47-49</p><p>Although originally identified by Waley as Avalokitesvara, it seems more likely that the crowned central figure in dhyana-mudra is in fact his spiritual parent, Amitabha. There are clear references to the paradise of Amitabha in the geese standing on piles of golden sand in the lower part of the painting. Four of the Bodhisattvas, the two in the middle of either side, are labelled in Tibetan: they are Sarvanivaranaviskambhin and Samantabhadra on the right; Ksitigarbha and Manjusri on the left (Fig.47).Those above and below them should be Avalokitesvara (with a lotus )and Vajrasattva on the right; Maitreya and Akasagarbha on the left (Fig.48).</p><p>The figure of a female donor, very small, appears at the bottom (Fig.49), divided from the main area, as in other paintings of early date, by a band of lozenges. Blue was originally important in the colour scheme forming the patterned background, but it has now faded. (The same blue pattern is found in a banner on hemp cloth, Vol.2, Pl.40, and may be compared also to the printed frontispiece to the Diamond Sutra, dated A.D.868 [Vol.2, Figs.144-45].) In style the painting is very close to Pl.16 especially to the two Bodhisattvas in Tibetan style in that painting (Pl.16-2). This would seem to justify a date early in the ninth century.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代吐蕃時期，9世紀初</p><p>絹本设色</p><p>高95.0釐米 寬63.5釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫 50. Ch.0074</p><p>參見Figs.47－49</p><p>此幅畫原來Waley先生比定爲觀音菩薩，中央主尊頭戴寶冠、手結定印看起來更像阿彌陀如來更爲合適。畫面下部，金沙洲上站立的鵝，也可明顯看出是阿彌陀淨土圖。中段的兩側各二身菩薩，共四身，均有吐蕃文標識的名字，右側是除蓋障菩薩和普賢菩薩，左側是地藏菩薩和文殊菩薩（參見Fig.47）。它們的上下所繪的，右邊是觀世音菩薩（手持蓮華）和金剛手菩薩，左邊为慈氏菩薩和虛空藏菩薩（參見Fig.48）。</p><p>與早期的諸作品相同，畫面的下方用菱形的紋樣帶與主要部分隔開，其中有非常小的女供養人像（參見Fig.49）。在此圖中，底紋的青色是全圖的基本色調，但現在已全部褪色（第2卷圖40的麻繪中有同樣的青色底紋。有868年紀年的《金剛經》版畫，也能見到類似現象[第2卷,Figs.144-5]）。此圖在形式上與圖16相近，尤其與吐蕃式的二菩薩像（參見圖16－2）很相似，從這一點上也能判斷出此繪畫作品的製作年代在9世紀初。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 18"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.35</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Thousand-armed, Thousand-eyed Avalokitesvara</title><title lang="chi-Hant">千手千眼觀世音菩薩圖</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 1st half of the 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.222.5cm, W.167.0cm</p><p>Stein painting 35.Ch.lvi.0019</p><p>See also Figs.53, 54</p><p>This impressive painting, considered by Waley as one of the finest in the collection and by Matsumoto as a masterpiece of Tang Esoteric Buddhist painting, testifies to the increasing popularity of Vajrayana, or Esoteric Buddhism, during the period of Tibetan domination at Dunhuang. This influence has already been seen in the equally large paradise of Bhaisajyaguru (Pl.9) where thousand-armed forms of Avalokitesvara and Manjusri are found in the upper corners of the painting. A thousand-armed, thousand-eyed Avalokitesvara also appears as a principal figure in the other large Bhaisajyaguru painting (Pl.16), where this deity, together with Cintamanicakra, is specifically mentioned in the dedicatory inscription, dated in accordance with A.D.836. The popularity of Avalokitesvara, as well as the spread of Esoteric doctrines, ensured that there were many examples among both the wall paintings and the paintings on silk and other materials as well. Thus in the Stein collection, a painting on hemp (see Vol.2, Pl.40) with donors in early to mid-ninth century costume provides the closest parallel to this much larger silk painting. The two have an almost identical arrangement, although the hemp painting has far fewer elements. Another painting in which many of the same figures are repeated in the same positions in the standing Avalokitesvara of this type dated A.D.981 in the Musée Guimet, while several others are in New Delhi.</p><p>Avalokitesvara in the centre of the silk painting is magnificently portrayed. As the facial features and bare forearms and hands are painted in carefully shaded orange and flesh tones (Pl.18-2), with red or purple outlines, a shimmering circle is created by the outermost rows of countless hands, each with a single eye. Far larger forearms and hands, forty in number, each hand grasping an attribute or forming a mudra, weave a complex pattern around the figure. They are crowned by an extra pair of hands in anjali-mudra over the top. Green bracelets with blue jewels, and the blue colour of many of the attributes, form a leitmotif of the colour scheme, matching the luxuriant blue hair spreading over the shoulders of Avalokitesvara. A few of the attributes appear especially prominent: the white conch shell and vase on opposite sides, the sun and moon, the figure of a small Buddha and a pavilion near the top of the group. Avalokitesvara is represented with eleven heads and a single“parent”figure of his spiritual father, Amitabha, in his tiara. Below him a preta and a beggar stretch out their hands to receive sweet dew and the Seven treasures from the two hands which are in vara-mudra (Fig.54).</p><p>The essential elements around Avalokitesvara in the smaller painting on hemp (Vol.2, Pl.40) are, above,the Bodhisattvas of Sunlight and Moonlight, and below, two vajra-holding deities with flaming hair. In the middle on either side are Cintamanicakra and a kneeling Bodhisattva. All can be identified in the present silk painting also, but to them are added many more. At the top, to either side of Sunlight and Moonlight (Pl.18-9), are transcendent Buddhas of the Ten Directions, in groups of the Ten Directions, in groups of five (Pls.18-3, 18-4). Below them on the left (Pl.18-3) the adoring figure is labeled “Scattering Flowers” and is joined by another manifestation of Avalokitesvara, namely Amoghapasa, who rescues souls with his rope. Their counterparts on the right are Cintamanicakra and another adoring figure “Spreading Incense” (Pls.18-4,18-6). Below these on either side appear the Indian gods Brahma and Indra, taken into the Buddhist pantheon as protectors of the law, with their attendants, and beneath them Mahakala standing on the left and Mahesvara (Siva) on the right on a white-spotted blue bull and holding a child, symbolic of his role as creator (Pl.18-10).Below these again, these are still two large groups on either side above the flaming vajra figures. On the left the group is led by the Peacock King (Pl.18-7), accompanied by a Bodhisattva and a Devaraja, and two of the Four Guardian Kings, one of whom is identified by his lance and stupa as Vaisravana, Guardian of the North. His sister Sri Devi kneels in front of them. On the right, the group is led by the Golden-winged Bird King riding a phoenix (Pl.18-8), again with two of the Four Guardian Kings. Behind him are a Buddha and a woman, with two children (probably Hariti), while the figure opposite Sri Devi is a kneeling white-haired rishi holding a staff, the Rishi Vasu (Fig.53). His emaciated limbs and general bony appearance are comparable to a similar aged but four-armed figure in the southern niche of Cave 148 at Dunhuang, a cave said to be dated A.D.775.</p><p>In the centre, between these two groups, is a lotus pool (Fig.54). The stem of Avalokitesvara’s lotus thron rises from this pool, encircled by swirling waters and supported by two naga figures with additional serpent heads and serpent tails (Pl.18-5). Six other naga figures are also in the pool.Below it only parts remain of two more figures with flame surrounds, identified by the cartouches as Trailokyavijaya (“Subduer of the three Worlds”) and Vinayaka. It is clear from the dated paintings in the Musée Guimet (bannières, No. 101, dated 943 A. D., and No.103, dated A. D. 981) that this subject was still popular for nearly a century and half after the end of the Tibetan period at Dunhuang. Nevertheless, when considered from the point of view of style, the Stein painting must be considerably earlier. The tenth-century paintings are notable for their much greater degree of geometrical stylization, harsher colour scheme with strong contrasts of red and green, and of course the addition of prominent inscriptions and donors represented in large size. The need to rationalize the composition to take in these new elements has led to the elimination of others: the naga figures in the lotus pool have lost their snake headdresses by A.D.943, and the pool itself is barely recognizable behind the altar in the painting dated A.D.981.The Stein painting, on the other hand, presents an integrated composition in which the lower groups in particular range themselves around the pool and do not need cloud supports, as do the upper deities. This distinction is lost in the tenth century, when all the groups have stylised cloud supports. Far more subtlety is displayed as well in the articulation of the various figures. This is perhaps especially noticeable in the array of arms around the central deity: in contrast to the rigid attitudes of the arms radiating from the Guimet Avalokitesvaras, the arms, wrists and hands here are bent at different angles and interlace in a manner which is complex yet permits of no confusion. Finally, if we examine details of the facial delineation, we shall find an echo here of the same convention for the lips and mouth already described in Pl.7. Thus this painting and those at the Guimet (Together with images on paper such as Stein painting 167,see Vol.2,Pl.71)seem to come at opposite ends of both stylistic and iconographic development.</p><p>The painting is on three complete widths of silk, each about 55 cm wide. An unpainted margin about 5 cm wide has been left all around the edge. Remnants of the original sewn-on border, which may also have been stuck down, are clearly visible as a narrow strip at the extreme edge of the painted area. Enough remains of the bottom border to show that the painting is essentially complete and that there were no donors. In this it resembles some of the other larger earlier paintings such as P1.9. Perhaps the reason may be that such large and sumptuously executed paintings were not single works but part of a larger donation or commission. Clearly by analogy with the wall paintings, such paintings would not have hung alone; however, the question of the precise circumstances in which they were used has yet to be answered satisfactorily.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀前半葉</p><p>絹本设色</p><p>高222.5釐米 寬167.0釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫 35.Ch.lvi.0019</p><p>參見 Figs.53,54</p><p>此幅給人留下深刻印象的繪畫，Waley把它當作收集品中最精美的作品之一，松本榮一博士则認爲它是吐蕃時期密教在敦煌地區盛行時密教佛畫的代表作。密教的影響，已出現在與該繪畫大小相同的藥師淨土變相圖（參見圖9）中,那图的上邊兩角安置有千手觀音和文殊菩薩。千手千眼觀音在其它大型的藥師淨土圖（圖16）中是也作爲主要像出現的。在有相当于836年的“丙辰”紀年的題記裏，與如意輪觀音一起被提到。從這些觀音的流行和密教的普及上看，可以肯定不论是壁畫、絹繪，还是其他載體，都盛行这样的圖像表現方式。諸如斯坦因收集品中，有繪在麻布上的千手千眼觀音像（見第2卷圖40），此图中繪有身穿9世紀初至中葉時期衣裳的供養人像，與這幅大的多的絹畫極爲相似。儘管那图遠遠小於該繪畫，但畫面的安排方式幾乎是一樣的。集美博物館所藏有981年紀年的作品中央的千手千眼觀音被繪成立像，周邊繪由许多與他相同姿勢的小像。此外，新德里國立博物館也有几幅類似的作品。</p><p>佔據該繪畫中心的千手千眼觀音描繪的非常美（參見圖18－2）。臉部和從衣服中露出的前臂、手，皮膚的顔色用橙色和肉色細心暈染，而用赤或紫色描線。看似搖曳的背光外圈，由每一個都鑲著眼睛的無數手構成。背光內緣有巨大的四十隻手，每一隻手或持物或結印，使尊像周圍呈複雜的圖形。其頂部配有結合掌印的二隻手，綠色腕釧鑲著藍色寶石，手持的物品也大多施以藍色，這一部分的色彩是以青色爲基調，與覆蓋觀音菩薩肩膀的濃密的青色頭髮非常吻合。在衆多手持物中，有幾樣比較明顯，如白色貝殼以及和它對面的淨瓶。上方的日月、接近頂部的如來像和建築等尤爲醒目。頭部由十一面組成，寶冠上是化佛。觀音下方是餓鬼和乞兒，他們張開兩手等待，似乎要接受從結與願印的兩隻手中落下的甘露和七寶（參見Fig.54）。</p><p>前述小型的麻繪（第2卷, 圖40）上，圍繞觀音的主要諸像中，上方有日光菩薩和月光菩薩，下方是持金剛杵的二身怒髮鬼神，中段兩側則是如意輪觀音和單腿直跪的菩薩，都可以在本畫中找到。然而，本絹繪不僅包括了上面所有的內容，還增加了很多像。上邊的日光菩薩、月光菩薩（參見圖18－9）兩旁有十方化佛（參見圖18－3，18－4），每側有五身。畫面的左下方的供奉者標有“散花”二字，並排的是觀音變身之一，即通過羂索救濟衆生的不空羂索觀音（參見圖18－3）。右側相对的位置上，是 “塗香”與如意輪觀音（參見圖18－4，18－6）。其下兩側是本來為印度神的梵天和帝釋天，後被納入佛教護法神的萬神殿中，以及他們的眷屬。他們的下邊，左側站立著摩訶迦羅天，右側是乘白斑青牛的摩醯首羅天，懷抱可以象徵他的創造者身份的童子（參見圖18－10）。其下，左右兩側火頭金剛之上佈有左右兩組群像。左邊一組以孔雀王爲首（參見圖18－7），隨從有一尊菩薩、一尊天王以及包括四天王中的兩尊，兩天王中的一尊手托槍和塔，可以判斷是北方天的多聞天。他的姐姐功德天跪在這一群像前。右邊群體中是以金翅鳥爲首（參見圖18－8），隨從有四天王中的二身，其後是如來以及懷抱兩個童子的婦人（可能是訶梨帝母）。與功德天對稱的位置上，是手持錫杖跪着的的白髯老人婆娑仙（參見Fig.53）。他瘦骨嶙峋的手足和身軀，与據説是775年的敦煌第148窟南壁龕中的四臂老人形象相似。</p><p>這兩组群像中間，有蓮池（參見Fig.54），觀音的蓮花座的長莖從蓮池伸出，由頭戴蛇頭和蛇尾冠的二个龍王挑起，環繞著長莖有旋渦狀的五彩水（參見圖18-5），池中還有六個龍王。蓮池下方，是被火焰光圍繞的二身像，現只残留了一部分，通过榜題得知是頻那勒迦和畢那夜迦。根據集美美術館收藏的有紀年的作品（伯希和圖錄《敦煌幡畫和繪畫》篇圖版101，紀年943；圖版103，紀年981）可確認，吐蕃佔領結束後的近一個半世紀，敦煌地區仍繼續盛行這個題材。然而，從繪畫風格上看，斯坦因收集品的繪畫年代相對較早。集美美術館所藏的10世紀的作品中，格式化的幾何圖案較多，其紅、綠強烈對比的配色，題記和供養人像佔據的巨大空間等，都引人注目。爲了增加新的構圖要素，使表現方式合理化，有必要省略不重要的部分。所以，在有943年題記的作品中，蓮池上的龍王把蛇冠省去了；在有981年題記的作品中，蓮池本身也到了祭壇後，只能勉強認出。斯坦因這幅畫則不同，它似乎注重完整地表現畫面的下方，特別是蓮池周圍的諸像，沒有像上方的諸像那樣乘在雲彩上。而在10世紀的作品中，沒有此種區別，諸像均乘在模式化的雲彩上。另外，此畫中，諸像各部位的表現有細微差別，特別是圍繞主尊的手臂尤爲明顯。集美美術館的作品中，圍繞觀音的手臂呈放射狀，顯得極其僵硬。與此相比，此畫中的手臂和手腕及指尖的角度均有變化，相互交錯，但其組合一點也不混亂。最後，仔細觀察臉的細部則發現，嘴形的描繪所採用的手法，與已講過的圖7的手法是一樣的。由此看來，此畫與集美美術館等的繪畫（包括斯坦因繪畫167，第2卷圖71），無論是在風格上，還是圖像方面，都可認爲是兩個不同發展階段的作品。</p><p>該繪畫使用幅寬約55cm的三幅絹，四周均留空白約5cm，當初應該縫有絹邊，因爲畫面邊緣留有細小的紐狀痕迹。在下邊留有一部分的空白，從而可判斷該繪畫原本沒有供養人像。這一點如圖9，很像早期的大型畫面的作品。之所以這樣說，是因爲像這樣華麗的大型繪畫，不可能通過個人捐贈而形成，而是衆多供養人或者委託者的共同捐贈的産物。以壁畫爲例類推也能確定，這樣的繪畫不可能單獨懸挂。然而，有關此畫的使用場合尚未有滿意的答案。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 19"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.37</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Fragments of the Paradise of Amitabha, with illustrations of episodes from the Amitayurdhyana-sutra</title><title lang="chi-Hant">觀經變相圖斷片</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 8th- 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours and gold on silk</p><p>Original H. about 210.0 cm, W. about 177.0 cm</p><p>(see Fig.55)</p><p>Stein painting 37.Ch.00216</p><p>See also Figs.55-58</p><p>This Amitabha paradise must have been, when complete, resplendent with colour. Even now, although much less than half of it seems to have been preserved, the freshness of the colours is amazing, and can only be paralleled in some of the large paintings of the mid-to late tenth century in the Pelliot collection (Bannière, Nos.6,101,104). However, it is not like them in style. Indeed, considered from this viewpoint, it seems to exhibit features not easily identifiable with any of the other silk paintings in the Stein collection, and therefore demands careful attention.</p><p>As can be seen from the makeshift assembly (Fig.55), comprising all but the smallest of the fragments, the painting has the standard form of an Amitabha paradise, with side scenes of the Sixteen Visions of Queen Vaidehi on the right, of the story of Bimbisara on the left and of the Ten Sorts of Wickedness at the bottom. The entire picture space, comprising three whole widths of silk each approximately 59 cm wide, is enclosed by a painted border in brown on which is a series of separate scrolling stems in orange and red edged in yellow. No other painting has such a border, and by it we can recognize a fragment in the Pelliot collection (Bannieres, No.5) as also belonging to this painting, being part of the lower border and a narrative scene illustrating one of the Ten Sorts of Wickedness.</p><p>To return to the composition: while the central Buddha is almost completely missing, subsidiary Buddha groups, seated and standing, are visible on either side, making five Buddha triads in all, without counting the Bodhisattva triads above them. The latter are actually Avalokitesvara and Mahasthamaprapta, the chief Bodhisattvas attendant upon Amitabha, and it is worth examining these three chief figures in a little more detail.</p><p>Although Waley’s Catalogue states that the figures of Buddha and Avalokitesvara are almost intact, his descriptions show these to be the subsidiary seated Buddha triad on the right-hand side, in which indeed Buddha’s right hand is “held out at some distance from his side, in vitarka-mudra; left hand spread on knee”. In fact, close examination of the fragments (Fig.55) is needed to discover what remains of the main figures. From what can just be made out of the Buddha, he is seated on a gorgeously decorated lotus throne in the centre, wearing a red robe whose folds are delineated with fine gold lines. His right hand must have been held in front of his chest, for the elbow and a very small part of his forearm, with the exposed part gilt, can just be seen at the top edge of the fragment. Akalavinka, standing very upright with blue wings, can just be seen to the left of the throne; further up and to the left, set close to the floral border like the Buddha triads below, is a seated Bodhisattva who must be one of the two main attendants of Amitabha. This Bodhisattva is splendidly attired, with luxuriant black hair flowing in locks over his shoulders and down to his elbows, and billowing robes decorated with green and blue flowers and patterns in fine white lines. He is seated on a green lotus, again finely veined in white. His counterpart on Buddha’s left hand is only partly visible: the face is gone, but the left side of the head, left hand in vitarka-mudra, and his own left attendant are all clear (Pl.19-1). Again, rippling black hair falls on the shoulder; garlands of flowers cover all of the left arm save only the hand and the gold-decorated bracelet and armlet. The headdress is almost entirely in gold. It is adorned with a blue jewel over the ear and two red ones; above these another patch of red is in fact all that remains of the “parent” figure that identifies this Bodhisattva as Avalokitesvara.</p><p>The side scenes are separated from the main area by a broad band of scrolling leaves and flowers on a pinkish red ground (Pl.19-1). At the top, still within the main picture area, these bands are capped by a lotus flower with a glowing pearl (Fig.56). A different floral scroll is seen at the level of the orchestra on either side, as a complete wall behind the standing Buddha triads. This is not multi-coloured but instead is grey on black, giving a most handsome effect (Pl.19-2). This may be compared with Cave 148 at Dunhuang, dated to the mid-Tang period (A.D.775, according to the Lo Archive; see Dunhuang bihua, Pl.168), which has the same interwoven quality and bulbous ends to the leaves. Naturally there are parallels too in the scrolling foliage engraved in low relief on Tang stelae, and it seems possible that the use of monochrome on a vertical surface in the Stein painting was intended to convey ornament in relief on the high platform supporting the partitions.</p><p>Although the wall paintings furnish parallels for such a motif as the scrolling foliage, the style as a whole still presents some problems. Compared to other paintings, colour is used more abundantly for outlines, for instance the red lines of facial features. Also, there are intriguingly different halo types, which do not appear elsewhere. On the first question, the use of colour, the answer may lie partly in the astonishing degree to which this has been preserved, since the underlying preliminary sketches in ink are still almost entirely covered by the surface colour. Nevertheless, the impression remains of an art more Central Asian than Chinese in this aspect. The haloes too are extremely colourful. Plate 19-1, of Avalokitesvara and his attendant, illustrates this well. The Bodhisattva’s nimbus consists of overlapping bands of points, while the attendant’s, plain orange-red, is dotted with red. In the subsidiary triads, the decoration of many of the haloes has a pronounced clockwise movement, even that of the wavy type which, as normally seen at Dunhuang, is balanced on both sides, meeting at the top.</p><p>Looking at the facial features, the main outline takes in the style of the face and the chin in a single smooth curve, almost without any modulation at all. The mouth is a mere rosebud, with no subsequent accenting in ink. The eyes have a somewhat supercilious look with the upper lids down-curved and sharply angled at the corner of the eye. Some of these features, but not the last, appear related to the wall paintings from Bezeklik: note especially the tiny mouth and full-fleshed face, the prolific use of bright colour, and atypical halo patterns with a pronounced one-directional sense of movement (Andrews, 1948,Pl.ⅩⅦ). This is not to suggest that we shall find this painting to have been made outside Dunhuang; it is clearly Chinese and the characters in the cartouches to the side scenes might still be considered to be closest, in the series of manuscripts we have illustrated, to the eighth century of the Tang, but this painting does seem to illustrate a different current in the art of Dunhuang, with a substantial contribution from another center in addition to purely Chinese features such as the “Tang foliage”.</p><p>Perhaps the most vital clues of all are to be found, as always, in the side scenes, and particularly in the story of Bimbisara and Ajatasatru on the left-hand side. At the very top Ajatasatru is seen in his previous incarnation standing outside his hermit’s cell, a thatched conical hut with red wickerwork frame visible in the doorway (Pl.19-3). A tree stands beside it, and a winding wall leads from it to the hills that indicate its remote setting. These, and the even more impressive peaks of the next scene, when Ajatasatru has changed into a white hare fleeing from Bimbisara, are naturalistically drawn in brown, with darker shading and relief obtained by means of repeated long brushstrokes. There are areas of green on the level ground between the two scenes, and on a small high ledge. Apart from the larger trees near the hut, the prominent features and skylines of the hills are crowned with trees. These have bright green foliage massed over repeated horizontal ink strokes or over much broader, round-topped touches of the brush in the first and second scenes respectively. Both kinds also have serried ranks of red trunks. This kind of attention to details of structure and surface form in landscape, at Dunhuang at least, is characteristic of the eighth century (e.g., Cave 209,de Silva,1967,p.149). We may glimpse the painter’s skill also in the distinction he draws down between the inside and outside views of the prison where Bimbisara and Queen Vaidehi are confined. Just below the landscape scenes, they are seen inside, listening to a sermon; at the bottom, guards are seen outside the prison gate. The same crested bird roof finials recur (there is another in blue fully drawn with beady eye, toucan-like beak and a crest on the roof above the standing Buddha triad on the left), but there is no mistaking the inside and the outside views. There is liveliness and a very Chinese sense of movement and timing, too, in the figures of the two ministers Candraprabha and Jiva as they draw and trandish their swords to save Queen Vaidehi from Ajatasatru (Pl.19-4).</p><p>Such considerations seem to justify a date that is earlier, rather than later, among the silk paintings from Dunhuang-late eighth century even, rather than early ninth. But there does remain one important question that is difficult to resolve: while the painting is fragmentary, its condition is in fact better than almost any other. There are remarkably few signs of wear: even the border, where it is visible, seems quite intact. There is little sign of damage even along the lines where the three widths of silk must have adjoined. Rather, the divisions between fragments seem to run right through the very faces of principal figures such as Avalokitesvara, Mahasthamaprapta and the buddhas in the triads below them (Pls.19-1, 19-2). The central Buddha is missing altogether, yet nothing is missing on either side of these divisions. It is almost as though the painting had been deliberately destroyed before it was put away in the sealed chapel. Could it be that the divergent style of the painting, despite the splendour of its execution, was once held to diverge also from the proper iconographical rendering of the Western Paradise as it was understood at Dunhuang?</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，8～9世紀</p><p>絹本金粉设色</p><p>原高約210.0釐米 寬約177.0釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫 37.Ch.00216</p><p>參見 Figs.55－58</p><p>該觀經變相圖在完整的時候無疑使用了華麗耀眼的色彩。現在畫面已斷成碎片，然而在剩下不到一半的畫面上，其驚人的鮮豔顔色仍可與伯希和收集品中10世紀中葉到下半葉的大型作品匹敵（參照《敦煌幡畫》，圖6，101，104）。但在風格上，不僅與伯希和收集品有很多不同之處，還具備了不能和斯坦因收集品中的其他絹畫同日而語的種種特徵，因此不得不充分重視。</p><p>將小斷片拼合，試著復原其畫面（參見Fig.55）時，可以發現該繪畫的右側外緣部分是韋提希夫人的“十六想觀”，左側外緣部分是“頻婆娑羅的故事”，底部是“十惡人”，具備標準的觀經變相圖的形式。當初的畫面是三幅寬約59cm的絹連接起來的，邊緣是褐色底子上描有黃色輪廓線的赤和橙色唐草花紋的裝裱。這種描繪裝裱非常特殊，見不到其它更多的例子，所以可以確認，在伯希和收集品中有同樣此類裝裱的一個斷片（《敦煌幡畫》,圖5）也是該繪畫的一部分，是“十惡人”的故事和下端邊緣的一部分構成的。</p><p>回到構圖的話題，主尊幾乎完全殘損，其左右有三尊的坐像和立像，連同主像共六組。主像中的左右兩位應該是阿彌陀的二脅侍觀音和勢至菩薩，對於這三尊主像還需要詳細核查。</p><p>儘管Waley的目錄中對那些佛和菩薩像的描述幾乎是完美無缺的，他的描述只是關於右邊的輔助的三尊坐像，佛的右手確實是“往前伸，結說法印，左手展開放在膝蓋上”。爲了辨認剩下的有關主尊的部分，需要仔細分析殘片，並做很多拼合工作（Fig.55）。其結果，中央部位還是稍微再現了主尊的姿態。主尊坐在裝飾豪華的寶台上，有褶皺的紅色衣服裝飾華麗的金線做的邊。右手應該是在胸前舉起，施用金彩的手臂和手腕的僅一小部分殘留在斷片上端。青色翅膀的迦陵頻伽直立在寶台的左旁。其左上方，與飾有花草的紋樣帶連接的畫面的正下方，是一個與三尊佛同樣採取坐姿的隨侍菩薩，他無疑是阿彌陀如來主尊的脅侍菩薩之一。這一菩薩的裝束極其華麗，覆蓋肩膀的黑而豐滿的頭髮垂落到手臂，衣裳裝飾有綠和青色的花柄和美麗的白條紋。台座的蓮瓣塗了綠色，而葉脈則描成白色。與此對應的主尊的左脅侍菩薩只剩一部分，臉部已殘失，只有頭部的左側和結說法印的左手，以及他旁邊的小菩薩（參見圖19－1）還都完整地保留著。主尊左脅侍菩薩的黑髮呈波浪形垂落在肩上，左臂上挂滿花飾，帶著金腕釧和臂釧，僅露出手。寶冠也幾乎是金的，耳朵部分鑲著藍色和紅色的寶石。中央部分的紅色寶石上可看出有紅色小片，那是化佛的一部分，由此可確定此菩薩是觀世音菩薩。</p><p>紅赤底色上描着唐草花紋風格的花和葉子的寬花紋帶，將主畫面和邊緣部分隔開。花紋帶上部，有橫跨兩個領域，托著火焰寶珠的蓮花座（參見Fig.56。樂伎群左右的三尊立像背後有作爲屏障的花紋，繪的是另一種唐草花紋（參照圖19－2）。此圖用的不是彩色，而是在黑底上凸出灰色紋樣，顯得極爲緊湊。與此形式相同，而葉尖稍寬唐草花紋，在中唐時期的敦煌第148窟（據羅寄梅檔案為775年；參照《敦煌壁畫》圖版168）也可見到。同時，與唐代石碑中浮雕的唐草花紋也很相似，本圖所繪紋樣以垂直面單色表現，可能是要更好顯現支撐隔壁高臺上的浮雕。</p><p>儘管壁畫中可見類似的唐草紋，但有關整體的形式上還存在些疑問。與其它繪畫比較，輪廓線顔色的使用很顯眼。如，臉部輪廓線可以看出是紅色的線，頭光則用了不見於其他地方的奇特紋樣。第一點，從這些斷片保存狀態驚人的好，多少可以說明輪廓線的顔色問題。即，用墨在上描的線，現在再次塗後幾乎會完全被隱埋。然而即使那樣，仍殘留著與其說中國式還不如說是中亞風格的印象。背光的色彩極其豐富，在圖19－1中的觀音和脅侍，其觀音頭光的色彩成帶狀重疊，而旁邊脅侍的頭光是橙赤底色上散著紅色斑點。同時，主尊以外的三尊像的頭光多是右卷的旋渦狀，爲敦煌常見的波浪形，均衡地分佈在頂部兩側。</p><p>仔細觀察臉部表現，輪廓線没有间断，流暢的曲線從額頭一口氣描到下顎。口部只點了像是薔薇花蕾似的紅點，看不到墨線。上眼瞼下垂，使外眼角成尖角，顯出高傲的神情。此若干現象，即便不能肯定，但也可從中看出與伯孜克里克石窟壁畫的關係。特別引人注目的是，小小的口形，豐滿的臉龐，多處採用的明亮色彩，明確單一方向性的頭光花紋等（Andrews;Wall Paintings Bezeklik,Shrine iii,Pl.XVII）。但是，這並不提示該繪畫是在敦煌以外的地區製作的。本圖邊緣長方形榜題中的文字，與所講過的唐代8世紀的寫經字體接近。因此，該繪畫是，在純粹中國的唐代的唐草紋樣的形式上加上其他地域的因素，形成了敦煌美術的另一風格。</p><p>和其他作品一樣，邊緣部分有著最重要的線索。特別是左側的“頻婆娑羅的故事”（參見圖19－3）。最上段是作爲“阿闍世王的前世身”的仙人，站立在隱居的庵前。庵是圓錐形的草屋，房門是用紅色樹枝編的框架。其旁的一棵樹和庵下方向山谷彎曲延伸的圍牆，說明是邊境地區。此場景的山與用作隔離下一場景仙人的魂變成白兔逃出頻婆娑羅的山，都塗了褐色，用幾根長長的濃墨線描出了山的皺褶，顯得極爲真實。這兩個場景間的分界和小高山上塗有綠色，山脊和突起部、庵旁的大樹及許多樹也用了極其特殊的綠色。第一場景和第二場景的那些美麗的葉叢，杆用墨線表現，垂直畫成若干細條，上面用圓頭筆刷抹，出現了更寬的線。樹杆不是只用墨線來表現，還描了赤茶色線。可見到如此照顧風景的細部，至少是敦煌美術的8世紀的特色（參照de Silva:Chinese Landscape Painting p.149,第209窟）。同時，從下邊的頻婆娑羅和韋提希夫人被幽禁于監牢裏的場景，也可看到畫家爲了區分建築的內外側而所採用的手法之一端。上述的兩個連續場景，聽說法的兩個人立於屋子內側，下一場景的獄卒們則站在屋子外側。外邊以重復出現同一形式的屋頂的鴟尾（但淨土圖左邊的三尊立佛像上部的大屋頂卻與此不同，配有飾念珠般的孔和像鳥嘴一樣的青鴟尾），分別描繪建築物的內和外。爲了從阿闍世王的手中拯救韋提希夫人，月光和耆婆兩個大臣，一人手拔刀、一人揮刀的姿態，極爲生動，使人感到中國式的動感和空間感。</p><p>這樣看，此繪畫在敦煌出土的絹畫中無論如何是早期的作品，與其說是9世紀初的作品，還不如說是8世紀後半葉更爲正確。然而，還有一個重要的疑問未得到解決。即，該畫儘管斷裂嚴重，但和其他作品相比，其保留的狀態極好。畫面幾乎沒有殘損，就連磨損嚴重的邊緣部分也保持了原有狀態。該絹畫無疑是由三幅絹縫合而成，但沿著縫合處沒有見到損壞的痕迹。看其各斷片的斷裂處，切口基本在觀音、勢至和分佈于下方的三尊佛等主要尊像的臉部（參見圖19－1，19－2）。另外，主尊部分完全遺失，但兩側還留有相當一部分。這些現象說明，該繪畫在放入藏經洞之前，被有意撕裂的。儘管該繪畫是傑出的作品，卻幾乎切成碎片，也許是因爲它與敦煌通常理解的西方淨土相違而造成的。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 20"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.57</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Illustrations to the Vimalakirti-sutra</title><title lang="chi-Hant">維摩經變相圖</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, Tibetan period, late 8th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.140.0 cm, W.115.5 cm</p><p>Stein painting 57.Ch.00350</p><p>See also Figs.59-61</p><p>This painting represents one of the subjects that were most popular at Dunhuang, namely the visit of the Bodhisattva Manjusri to the layman Vimalakirti and their ensuing debate, as described in the Vimalakirti-sutra, of which several Chinese translations were available, the most likely one for the present painting being that made by Kumarajiva in A.D.406. There are three illustrations of the Vimalakirti-sutra in the Stein collection: the silk painting here, Stein painting 31* (Vol.2, Pl.53), which shows Manjusri alone, and Stein painting 76, a sketch of a complete composition, but split into several parts (Vol.2,Figs.86-88). Although the wall paintings at Dunhuang, as well as representations at Yungang, Longmen, and so on, testify to the great popularity of the Vimalakirti-sutra in China, there do not appear to be other versions on silk or paper. The painting shown here, although in a fragmentary state, is therefore especially valuable.</p><p>The majority of illustrations to the sutra (including apparently Stein paintings 31* and 76) are divided into two parts. In most of the wall paintings at Dunhuang, Vimalakirti and Manjusri are placed on either side of the entrance to the cave, where the worshipper would see them as he left. This arrangement doubtless both suited the narrower spaces available on the entrance wall and provided a proper subject for the faithful after contemplation of the paradise scenes on the main walls of the cave. In at least two of the wall paintings (Matsumoto, 1937, Pl.46) and in the present painting, however, the whole subject is presented in a single composition (cf. especially Cave 335, Chugoku Sekkutsu, vl.3, Pl.61).</p><p>The actual debate between Vimalakirti and Manjusri takes place in the middle of the painting, in front of the red brick wall of the city of Vaisali. Vimalakirti, his head turned towards Manjusri, is on the left, in a roofed and curtained bed. He is seated cross-legged in a relaxed position, his left arm perhaps supported on a rest and holding a fan. Manjusri is seated on a lotus throne under which is a square platform supported by lions (Fig.61). In front these are portrayed, as in Stein painting 31*(Vol.2, Pl.53), in the openings of a wooden stand, but beyond the receding side the lion appears to be outside this framework and standing erect instead of crouching.</p><p>Below Vimalakirti and Manjusri on either side, as well as the Four Guardian Kings and other Bodhisattvas, are the rulers and their attendants who have come to hear the debate. Those on the left side are more clearly visible, and obviously show a Tibetan king, or btsan-po, and his entourage (Pl.20-2). The king wears a robe with long sleeves and a collar with lapels folded back on either side, revealing several layers. On his head is the fluted turban of a btsan-po. Behind him an attendant holds a parasol, and in front two more, wearing wide turbans and long sleeves and collars trimmed with fur, lead the way. They resemble one of the figures in the scroll showing the contest between Sariputra and Raudraksa, from the Pelliot collection. Comparison can also be made with representations of Tibetan kings in Caves 158 and 159, both dating from the period of Tibetan occupation at Dunhuang (cf. Karmay, 1977). Other figures in the entourage recall the costumes of the foreign envoys in the wall paintings found in the tomb of Li Xian (Prince Zhang Huai) near Xi’an, of the early eighth century (Tang Li Xian mu bihua, Pl.25).</p><p>At the top of the painting, over the wall of the city of Vaisali, are other scenes connected with different parts of the Vimalakirti-sutra. In the center, accompanied by Bodhisattvas, is the Buddha. In front of him kneel five men, each of them wearing a three-pronged crown (indicating noble or princely birth) and holding a canopy. They represent the five hundred sons of elders who presented precious canopies to the Buddha and Bodhisattvas, as described in the opening chapter of the sutra. On close inspection these are seen to be supported on clouds which issue from the right hand of a small standing figure of Vimalakirti, who is seen at the extreme right and left. Thus they can be identified as some of the miracles performed by Vimalakirti in the course of the debate. At the left these manifestations include Mt. Sumeru, with the sun and moon (Pl.20-3), and three “lion thrones” which descend towards the assembly, representing the thirty-two thousand lion thrones magically provided by Vimalakirti for the assembly. On the right, the three bowls in front of the Buddha assembly indicate the fragrant rice, brought by nine million transcendent Bodhisattvas, again through the agency of Vimalakirti.</p><p>It is chiefly as an illustration of the sutra that this painting is of interest, since the artist displays no more than mere competence in skill. His range of colours is somewhat limited, and a majority of the figures are seen in identical three-quarter view, with full-fleshed faces and the top-knot of the hair appearing as an almost circular blob (for this feature, cf. also Bannieres, No.20, in the Musée Guimet). With it goes a lack of subtlety in compositional arrangement that is particularly noticeable when figures are seen close together in a large group.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，吐蕃佔領時期，8世紀末</p><p>絹本设色</p><p>高140.0釐米 寬115.5釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫 57.Ch.00350</p><p>參見Figs.59－61</p><p>該繪畫是敦煌繪畫中常見的題材之一，即根據《維摩經》，文殊菩薩探望 維摩居士，與維摩間辯論的內容。《維摩經》漢文譯本現有數種，該繪畫所據的底本最有可能是鳩摩羅什406年的譯本。斯坦因收集品中《維摩經變相圖》有三件：除了這幅畫外，還有斯坦因繪畫31*（卷2，圖53），僅畫了文殊菩薩，及斯坦因繪畫76，原本很完整的紙本墨畫，但現在已裂為幾片（卷2，Figs. 86－88）。雖然敦煌，以及雲崗和龍門石窟等處壁畫證明《維摩經》在中國的盛行，但在絹畫和紙畫中，沒見到根據其他譯本所描繪的作品。因此，這裏展示的繪畫雖然損傷嚴重，但是非常重要的作品。</p><p>絕大部分此經變相圖（當然包括斯坦因繪畫31*和76）是分兩個部分。絕大部分的敦煌壁畫中，維摩居士和文殊菩薩一般是處在洞窟入口的左右兩壁。參拜者離開時可以禮拜他們。這種佈置無疑是考慮滿足兩個方面的要求，一是爲了充分利用洞窟入口處的狹小壁面；二是在洞窟主壁畫淨土變之外提供另一種適當的題材供信徒禮拜。像這幅畫一樣在一個畫面上收入了兩個主要部分的，在壁畫中至少知道有兩處（特別是335窟，見《中國石窟·敦煌莫高窟》第3卷，圖61）。</p><p>實際上，維摩和文殊的辯論是在毘耶離城紅磚城牆前的畫面中央進行的。維摩坐在左側屋頂有帷帳的床上（參照彩色圖版20－2圖），面向文殊，悠然自得地盤腿而坐，左臂憑在几上，手持扇子（拂麈）。文殊則坐在獅子馱著的方形須彌壇上的蓮華座上（Fig.61）。須彌壇前木框裏所繪的獅子，與斯坦因繪畫31*（卷2，圖53）一樣，但後者的獅子是紋絲不動地蹲著，而本圖的獅子卻是站立的姿式，並且稍微地越出了框。</p><p>維摩和文殊的下方聚集著四天王和衆多菩薩外，還有聞訊趕來聽法的國王及其隨從。左邊的畫清晰可見，顯然顯示的是吐蕃贊普和他的隨從（參見圖20－2）。贊普身著翻領長袖禮服，顯出有很多層。頭戴的帽子似有凹槽的穆斯林頭巾。後面有侍者打著傘，前面有頭裹穆斯林頭巾、身著毛皮領的長袖袍子的兩人做向導。其中一人很像伯希和收集品《勞度叉鬥聖變》畫卷中所出現的人物。也可與有吐蕃佔領時期的敦煌第158窟、159窟壁畫中的吐蕃贊普做比較（參見Karmay,“Tibetan Costumes”，1977）。從隨從們的裝束可想到，西安近郊發現的8世紀初李賢（章懷太子）墓壁畫上的外國使節服裝（參見《唐李賢墓壁畫》圖版25）。</p><p>畫面上方，毘耶離城的城壁上描繪著《維摩經》其餘章節的場景。中央有菩薩脅侍的如來，其前是跪著的五個男人，頭戴三山冠（表明他們的貴族身份），各自捧著一頂華蓋。據該經第一品的記述，他們是代表五百長者子一起用華蓋供養佛和菩薩。仔細觀察，發現那些上方的諸像乘在雲端上，雲彩是從左右兩端的維摩小立像的右手升起的，這樣可以確認為維摩在進行辯論時出現的祥瑞的一部分。左邊部分是日月伴隨的須彌山（參見圖20－3）和三個向聽眾落下的獅子座，表現的是維摩居士爲聽法衆人用法力提供的三萬二千個獅子座。右方，佛前放著三只盛滿香飯的缽，這也是維摩居士為九百萬傑出菩薩所帶的食物。</p><p>該畫作爲經變畫，畫家最關心的是對《維摩經》的圖解，而並沒太多考慮技法。採用的顔色非常有限，大部分人物身子側立，面部圓潤，髮髻也幾乎呈圓狀（這種特徵也見於伯希和《敦煌幡畫》，圖20，收藏於集美博物館）。因爲缺乏精妙的構圖安排，特別是看成組的像時，這一點更爲明顯。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 21"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.62</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Contest between Sariputra and Raudraksa</title><title lang="chi-Hant">勞度叉鬪聖變</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.63.5cm, W.46.7cm</p><p>Stein painting 62.Ch.lv.002</p><p>Although it only shows two episodes from a longer story, this painting is of great interest as an example of the literary genre known as bianwen 變文, dramatized recitations by monks in return for donations from the faithful. They correspond to the bianxiang 變相，or pictorial illustrations of the sutras, of which most of the wall paintings in the caves, as well as those on silk, are examples.</p><p>The story of the contest between the Buddha’s disciple Sariputra and the heretic leader Raudraksa is told in the Xianyu jing 賢愚經，Sutra of the Wise and the Foolish, apparently a Chinese compilation of stories from the area of Khotan. The most famous illustration of the contest is the long scroll in the Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris, brought from Dunhuang by Paul Pelliot (Vandier-Nicolas, 1954). That is an illustrated roll with the relevant text written on the back behind each scene. Using it, the monk could read the text from the back as he held up the pictures for the audience to see. All six episodes of the contest are shown in it, although some prefatory scenes are missing at beginning.</p><p>The present silk painting shows only two episodes. Above, an elephant is seen standing in a pool with lotus leaves and flowers. To the lower right, Raudraksa can just be seen, kneeling and reeling backwards in astonishment as the elephant, miraculously created by Sariputra, instantaneously drinks dry the pool that Raudraksa had created by magic. A caption at the left reads: “in the pond there appeared thousand-leaved precious flowers”池中生千葉寳花,while a second caption continues (in part)“seeing the elephant of the Buddhists entering the pool”見佛家象入池.</p><p>The lower left corner of the painting, separated from the rest by the zig-zag bank of the pool, shows Raudraksa in the final episode of the story, falling to the ground in complete defeat. The depiction of his contorted frame is vigorous and energetic, recalling some of the figures of Lokapalas in the treatment of out-stretched hands and feet. Below the falling figure is a glimpse of a landscape in ink, with deer grazing in a rocky valley and trees. This is tiny in scale. Although it appears unrelated to the main scene, it seems quite possible that it was deliberately used to give the effect of huge scale to the main figures; according to the story, Raudraksa in the final contest himself took shape as a gigantic yaksa, but was defeated by Sariputra who personally repeated the miraculous transformations and apparitions of the great miracle of the Buddha at Sravasti.</p><p>Despite the evident fragmentary condition of the silk, the fact that an early episode (the second contest) and the final one are shown together makes it unlikely that this is a fragment from a larger painting showing the entire contest. More probably the major portion is complete here. The painting is certainly no later than the ninth century and according to Professor Akiyama, who considers it to be the earliest illustration of the story, may be as early as the mid-or late eighth century.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀</p><p>絹本设色</p><p>高63.5釐米 寬46.7釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫 62.Ch.lv.002</p><p>該繪畫僅僅描繪了長篇故事中的兩個情节，是文學領域中所謂的“變文”的極爲有趣的例子之一。“變文”是僧侶們接受佈施後作爲回報將經文用戲劇的形式演唱給施主聽的一種文學題材。與此相應的有“變相”，就是以繪畫形式表現佛經內容。除了絹畫，石窟壁畫中也有不少遺留的例子。</p><p>《賢愚經》是在于闐地區編纂的佛經故事集，該經記載著佛弟子舍利弗和外道首領勞度叉進行鬥法的故事。把該故事以繪畫形式表現出來的作品中，最有名的屬伯希和從敦煌帶回，現藏於巴黎國立圖書館的卷子本。該卷是畫卷的形式，有關說明文字記錄在各自場景的背面。僧侶高舉繪畫，讓觀衆觀看圖畫，自己讀背面的說明文字。雖然卷首的畫面多少有點損失，但鬥法的六個情节則完整保留下來。</p><p>該絹畫作品中，只描繪了其中兩個情節。右上部是站立在蓮池花葉中的大象，其下方依稀見到勞度叉的身影。繪的是勞度叉用幻術變出湧出的池水，舍利弗的魔力變出的大象瞬間将池水飲乾，因而甚感驚訝的勞度叉兩膝落地，幾乎暈倒。左上邊長方形中的文字是“水池中生千葉寶華”，接下來的部分在右下方長方形框中，它的左行是“見佛家象入池”。</p><p>齒形的池岸線隔開畫面左下方，這一部分描繪了故事的最後情節，遭到慘敗的勞度叉向地面墜落的畫面，這是“□…□出仰倒時”。對他扭曲身體的描繪非常生動有力，張開的手足仿佛是金剛力士像。勞度叉墜落的下方，僅殘留了一部分用墨描的在山間河岸吃草的鹿和樹林的風景畫。對這些風景的描繪都非常小，乍一看，似乎和主體部分毫無關係，但卻有使主體部分顯得更大的效果，是有意識的表現方式。故事中，鬥法的最終，勞度叉雖然變成個巨大夜叉的形態，但由於舍利弗的反復奇迹般變化和佛在舍衛城顯現的大神變，最終還是敗下陣來。</p><p>由絹的狀態看，明顯是由斷片組成的，但最初的情節（第二回鬥法）和最後的情節被繪在一起，恐怕此畫就是這样結束的，從而很難認爲此是一幅把全部情節都描繪出的大型畫的一部分。很明顯它不是9世紀以後的作品，秋山光和教授認爲它是《勞度叉聖變》最早的版本，推定爲8世紀中葉或後半葉的繪畫。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 22"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.20</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san">Sākyamuni Preaching on the Vulture Peak(fragment)</title><title lang="chi-Hant">靈鷲山釋迦說法圖（殘片）</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 8th-9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.95.9 cm, W.51.8 cm</p><p>Stein painting 20.Ch.0059</p><p>See also Figs.62-67, 112</p><p>The subject of this painting is an unusual one at Dunhuang, being found among the wall paintings only in Cave 72. Only the right arm of the central standing Buddha is now visible, outlined in ink and shaded in orange to give the impression of a golden colour. The arm is extended straight downwards with open palm and thumb and fingers closely pressed together. It is immediately recognizable as the gesture found in the Sakyamuni of the great embroidery shown in Vol. 3, Pl. 1, indicating that the subject is the sermon on the Vulture Peak, that is, the preaching of the Lotus Sutra. This is indeed confirmed by the rocky background and, among other birds in flight, an actual vulture perching on the top of the mountain above the canopy (Fig.66).</p><p>As the painting survives, only a little less than a quarter is preserved. This can be surmised from the construction alone, since a join in the silk runs down immediately behind the head of the monk, perhaps Sariputra as Waley suggested, who stands beside the Buddha. Following the usual make-up of a central whole width of silk with two half-widths, one either side, this means that the whole painting was originally very impressive, with the central figure of a standing Buddha, his body resplendent in its orange shading against the ornate mandorla and flame surround, set off by the dark rocks of the Vulture Peak, attended by a disciple on either side, and with narrative side scenes to the left and right. Something of its magnificence can still be seen from the sumptuous decoration of the petals of the lotus on which the monk stand: blue and orange seem to have been the dominant colours of the painting.</p><p>While the identification of the central Buddha allows us to refer to the embroidery (and the tiny embroidery, Vol.3, Pl.2) as well as to the image of Sakyamuni Preaching on the Vulture Peak found on a painting in New Delhi, other parts of which (Stein painting 51,Vol.2Pl.11) are in the British Museum, it is the narrative scenes at the side which link it to the wall paintings at Qianfodong. As suggested above, these narrative scenes cannot have been confined to the left side but must have been present on the right also. Of great interest is the fact that the standing image of the Buddha grasping his robe and with the right hand extended straight down is twice repeated in these scenes, to the lower left as a sculpture surrounded by a scaffold, with two men reaching out to the head, and near the top left outside a city wall as a free-standing image, towards which a monk stretches his left hand.</p><p>The explanation of these side scenes is made clear by the wall painting on the upper part of the south wall of Cave 72, which bears a series of inscribed cartouches that tell the story. Here the image of the Buddha, large and small, is shown many times in a landscape setting. In the centre of the wall Sakyamuni is shown with a large assembly; it is the scene to the right of this that chiefly concerns us here. The first image appears (Lo Archive, no. 072-7) at the top left of this part of the wall, with the caption: “The appearance of the iron(?) image from India” 鐵像從度印來現時. In the next scene to the right, the image is seen much larger, accompanied by apsarasas and disciples, but with the head missing. The inscription reads: “When the head was lost from the image of the Divine Countenance” 聖容像＃下去頭時. In the centre of the whole composition the image is shown again, this time with a scaffold erected around it, one figure climbing a ladder, two men half-way up the scaffold and four more at the top supporting the head of the image, which is still slightly tilted. The caption reads:“When they managed to get the original head of the image of the Divine Countenance and replace it as it was before” 却得聖容像本頭安置仍著時.</p><p>Further repetitions of the image, with narrative of other events, occur in the top right section of the wall painting, but the three scenes already described are those that are give some prominence, just as the scene of the replacement of the head by two men on a scaffold is clearly the principal event shown in the surviving part of the silk painting. Nevertheless, some other parallels may be attempted; for instance, just in front of the scaffold in the silk painting is a pavilion with a blue roof (Pl.22-2). A pavilion also appears in Cave 72, and next to it the inscription reads: “When the Lohan saw the Divine Countenance and recorded it on a tablet”羅漢見聖容碑記時. Unfortunately, available photographs from the cave (the entire lower half of the wall has in any case faded leaving only a single image visible) are not clear enough to identify the other scenes in the silk painting. These, besides the two wind or thunder spirits with their rings of drums, supported on clouds (Pl.22-2, Fig.67), include a rider apparently reviewing a troop of soldiers in armour (Fig. 65) and, higher up, a monk on a mule, followed by an elephant carrying a large number of scriptures (Fig.64). The whole painting is thus concerned not only with the central image of the Buddha in the act of preaching the most important Mahayana scripture, the Saddharma-pundarika, or Lotus Sutra, but with the transmission of both images and scriptures from India eastwards.</p><p>Since writing the above, the good fortune of a visit from M.Robert Jera Bezard has led to the identification of another substantial (H.72.0 cm, W. 28.0 cm) and important part of the same painting. On seeing Stein 20 he immediately recalled a fragment in the Pelliot collection with the same basic colouring (Bannieres, No.25). The piece in question (Fig.63) shows a Bodhisattva kneeling before an incense burner, described in the catalogue entry as being that which stood directly beneath the main image. Indeed a fragment of two multi-coloured petals of the lotus pedestal is just visible. There are numerous much smaller figures :a group of musicians, two groups of horsemen with pennants, five monks and another figure of some authority near them. These and the landscape setting already recall the Stein painting, but the most fascinating detail is immediately in front of the kneeling Bodhisattva, the head only of a Buddha, described as green in colouring (the statues in the London painting appear metallic in hue although no colour is actually left), seen on a rectangular plinth between two trees. There can be no doubt that the same story is represented, and I personally have no hesitation at all in believing this to be a part of the same painting, the figure of the Bodhisattva being almost directly below that of the large standing monk in the Stein painting (Fig.62). By this we can deduce that the whole painting was over 170 cm high and about 120 cm wide. There would have been space for many more scenes from the whole narrative as shown in Cave 72.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，8～9世紀</p><p>絹本设色</p><p>高95.9釐米 寬51.8cm</p><p>斯坦因繪畫20.Ch.0059</p><p>參見Figs.62－67,112</p><p>該畫的主題在敦煌非常罕見，石窟壁畫中也僅在72窟中發現一例。主尊的立像只殘留右臂，墨描輪廓，橙色暈染，顯示出金色光輝。手臂筆直下垂，手掌展開，手指緊並。看一眼就會立刻想起第3卷圖1的刺繡作品，即《法華經》中所講的《靈鷲山釋迦說法圖》中主尊的描繪。背景的山岩以及空中飛翔的鳥，其中還夾著停留在華蓋上方山頂的禿鷹（參見Fig.66）等則是更有力的證明。</p><p>該繪畫殘留部分不到整體的四分之一，这整體畫面只是通过比丘頭部正後方所見絹的綴接針眼推測的。如同Waley講的，佛旁站立的比丘大概是舍利弗。按慣例，中心是整幅絹子，兩邊再接缀半幅絹，当初应是一件很華美的作品，中央位置的立佛身上用橙色暈染，圍繞著絢麗的身光或火焰光，更加襯托出靈鷲山的暗色山岩。佛兩側各有一身弟子陪伴，左右兩側是故事圖。華麗程度，从比丘所站的蓮華座的豪华裝飾，亦可窥其一斑。整體畫面，依然以青、橙色爲主調。</p><p>主尊的身份，可以參考刺繡品（還有小型刺繡品，第3卷圖2）以及新德里國立博物館所藏的《靈鷲山釋迦說法圖》、大英博物館的其他藏品（斯坦因繪畫51；第2卷圖11）。而畫面兩側的故事圖，則與千佛洞的壁畫有聯係。如前所述，那些故事圖不僅應在左側，右側也應有描繪。非常有趣的是，左手執衣襟，右手筆直下垂的佛立像，居然出現兩身。一身在左下方的建築架中，有兩個男人貼近佛頭。另一身在左上端接近城壁外側的獨立像，旁邊站著舉起左手的比丘。</p><p>這些故事圖的情景，在敦煌第72窟南壁上部有榜題説明的壁畫中得到了更清楚的解釋。壁畫中，中央是釋迦，周邊圍著諸多聖衆，左右的山水圖中佈置了幾身大小不一的佛像。這裏，我們的問題主要在右半部展開的畫面。首先出現的是右半壁畫的左上方的佛像（參照羅寄梅No.072-7）。此場景的解說文是“鐵像從印度來現時”。右邊的佛像比這個佛像還大，頭部殘缺，伴隨著佛弟子和飛天，解說文是“聖容像（木+勿）下去頭時”。隨後中部出現的是被建築架圍起來的這一佛像。一個人爬著梯子，建築架半空有兩個男人，上面也有四個男人支着傾斜的佛頭。解說文是“卻得聖容像本頭安置仍舊時”。</p><p>壁畫右上方有若干身佛像，各自都有解說故事情結的榜題，特別引人注目的是上述三個場景，即建築架上的兩個男人進行佛頭修復作業，它們表現的顯然是此繪畫的殘留部分的主要事件。還可舉出若干相同的描繪，如該繪畫建築架正前方繪著青色屋頂的建築物（參見圖22－2），在第72窟中也可以見到，其解說文是“羅漢見聖容碑記時”。遺憾的是，手中所掌握的該窟照片（壁畫下半部全都很模糊，只見一身佛像），無法與此畫的其他部分做充分的比較。在此畫中，還可見到乘著雲彩，手持輪形大鼓的風神和雷神（參見圖22－2，Fig.67），有一隊騎馬著甲的士兵（參見Fig.65），在其上方有騎騾馬的僧侶及負載著經文的大象等（參見Fig.64）。從而，此畫中央描繪的說法佛，不僅僅與最重要的大乘經典《法華經》有關連，也與佛像和經典從印度東漸有關。</p><p>撰寫上文時，恰好M.Robert Jera Bezard來訪，確認了另一件可能是此畫的一部分重要的殘片（高72.0釐米,寬28.0釐米）。看到本圖，他立刻想起了在伯希和收集品中的同一色調的一件斷片（《敦煌幡和繪畫》，圖25）。在這個斷片中，一個菩薩跪在香爐前（參見Fig.63）。根據說明，香爐應該在主尊正下方的位置。實際上，這裏只能在上部窺到顔色豐富的蓮華座的兩片花瓣的尖端。另外，斷片中還繪有樂人一群、兩群騎馬人，比丘五人，以及諸多權貴人物等小像。這些人物和山水風景等的描繪，與斯坦因收集的作品也有關係，但最引人注目的是繪於跪姿菩薩正前方的佛頭，是用綠色描繪，用兩根樹夾起置於長方形的臺上（斯坦因此畫的顔色實際上幾乎完全脫落，但感覺像的顔色是金屬色）。伯希和收集的斷片，描繪的無疑是相同故事的一個斷片，我個人毫不猶豫地認爲，那是此圖的一部分，菩薩像應該連接於本圖大的比丘立像的正下方（參見Fig.62）。從以上的情況，可以推測全圖高170.cm,寬120cm以上，它應該像敦煌第72窟的宏大場景那樣，也有充分的餘地收進相當大的畫面。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 23"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.5</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san">Four manifestations of Avalokitesvara, with Samantabhadra and Manjusri</title><title lang="chi-Hant">四觀音文殊普賢圖</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty ,dated 5th year of Xiantong 咸通五年(A.D.864)</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.140.7 cm, W. 97.0 cm</p><p>Stein painting 5.Ch. lv.0023</p><p>See also Figs.71, 73</p><p>Until the recent identification of a date on Pl.16, this was thought to be the earliest dated painting in the Stein collection. The subject testifies to the great popularity of Avalokitesvara at Dunhuang, as well as to that of Manjusri and Samantabhadra. Each of the Bodhisattvas is identified by a cartouche, without whose help it would be impossible to distinguish the four in the top row. For instance the third from the right is labeled “Great Merciful, Eleven-faced Guanshiyin”, although like the rest he has just the single figure of Amitabha in his headdress (Pl.23-3). Nevertheless, this Bodhisattva seems to have attracted the special devotion of one of the donors, who has added his own name in the space left in the cartouche.</p><p>While the four Bodhisattvas at the top all wear garments and adornments in “Indian” style, though modified to adapt to Chinese taste, particularly in the long underrobe falling in symmetrical folds of reddish pink down to the feet, the figures of Manjusri and Samantabhadra appear entirely in Chinese style (Pl.23-2). Especially in the attendant figures of Bodhisattvas holding triple umbrellas, the initial under-drawing in ink shows clearly beneath the flesh colour of features such as the face and hands. Details such as the mouthline, ending in a swelling upward turn (Pl. 23-4, Fig.71), the eyebrows and nose were re-emphasised in darker ink after completion of the colour work, usually without the spontaneity and swiftness of the under-drawing, but with a more careful weighting of line to accent the contours. The dark hair falling from the shoulders can easily be seen to have been painted at this stage as well, and here too the under-drawing in outline only can be seen beneath.</p><p>The haloes display just a few basic types, with wavy “rainbow” haloes alternating with ones featuring double cloud spirals in the upper row of figures. The same cloud type is used for the standing Bodhisattvas below at the sides, those in the centre having green overlapping petals, also found in the centre of the mandorlas behind Manjusri and Samantabhadra. The latter also have cloud patterns on their haloes, and the painted motif is found only in the outer ring of their mandorlas. There is thus a pleasing symmetry and unity in the painting, which extends even to the contrast between upturned and downturned petals in the pedestals of the upper figures. The predominance of gentle curves and spirals in the halo decorations contrasts with those of later periods when even minor Bodhisattvas sport the more geometric or pointed halo motifs.</p><p>At the bottom of the painting, in the centre between the single monk and three laymen on the right, and the two nuns and two women on the left, is the cartouche which dates this work (Fig.73), reading from right to left:</p><p>一爲當今皇帝二爲本使□</p><p>三爲先亡父母及合□□□</p><p>無之灾障□□</p><p>咸通五年□</p><p>First, on behalf of the present Emperor; second, on behalf of his envoy... third, on behalf of his departed parents and all his family...May they (escape) both earthly disasters and obstacles to salvation. Hsien T’ung [Xiantong] 5th (year) [A.D.864]. (Trans. Waley, 1931,p.10.)</p><p>This inscription and the donors themselves are shown in a separate narrow register at the bottom of the painting, divided from it by a band of lozenges. Mary Fong (1972) has compared them with other donors of the second half of the ninth century in Cave 85 (dated 867) and Cave 107 (dated 872) at Dunhuang. As Waley has noted, the ladies wear just a single comb in their hair without any of the hairpins common at a later date.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，咸通五年（864年）</p><p>絹本设色</p><p>高140.7釐米 寬97.0釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫5.Ch.iv.0023</p><p>參見Figs.71,73</p><p>近年，考證彩色圖版第16圖的年代時，曾把該繪畫看作是斯坦因搜集的敦煌畫中年代最早的作品。此繪畫的主題證明觀音、文殊和普賢在敦煌都深受歡迎。菩薩的名字通過榜題中記錄的像名可以確認，如果沒有榜題，就無法識別上段的四身菩薩。例如，右邊第三尊像（參見圖23－3）記爲“大悲十一面觀世音菩薩”，但却與其他三身像一樣，寶冠上只有一個化佛。儘管這樣，這位菩薩似乎凝聚著一個供養人特殊的信仰之心，他在榜題的空白處寫了自己的名字。</p><p>上段的四觀音身上的袈裟和裝飾品，全都是迎合中國的喜好而改變了的印度風格。特別是布滿紅粉色縐褶、左右對稱直垂到腳的長裙，是其典型的例子。與此相對，下方文殊和普賢的衣裳完全是中國風格的（參見圖23－2）。其他諸像，尤其是持三層傘蓋的脅侍菩薩，能清楚看到其面部和手的顔色下面有底稿的墨線。邊端稍顯膨脹的唇線（參見圖23－4，Fig.71）以及眉、鼻等的線，都是在上完彩色後再用濃墨描繪成的，但這種線條幾乎無例外地沒有底稿線那樣的自然流利，只是爲重視強調輪廓而谨慎運用的手法。從兩肩垂下的黑髮也是後來用濃墨塗的，可見到輪廓的底稿線。</p><p>頭光的表現多少使用了基本的型式。上段諸像的頭光，是波浪虹狀紋和雙雲旋渦紋交替搭配。下段兩端的立像菩薩用著同樣的雙雲旋渦紋，內側菩薩的綠色頭光有重疊的花瓣，在文殊和普賢背光的中心部分也可見到同樣的紋樣。文殊和普賢的頭光也有雙雲旋渦紋，只有背光的外緣部分是別樣的，使用了像劍一樣帶尖的紋樣。此畫中保持了令人舒適的左右對稱的統一性，這些還涉及到上段，諸像的蓮華座，兩端的二身是仰瓣，中間二身的則是向下的重瓣等的表現中。頭光的花紋主要是由平穩的曲線和旋渦卷構成，與後世小菩薩的頭光都變成了幾何圖樣或尖銳花紋成對比。</p><p>畫面最下段為供養人像（參見Fig.73），右邊是一比丘和三俗世男子，左邊是二比丘尼和二婦人，中央有從右往左豎寫並有紀年的題記：</p><p>一爲當今皇帝二爲本使□</p><p>三爲先亡父母及合□□□</p><p>無之災障□□</p><p>咸通五年□</p><p>與上部畫面間有花紋帶隔離的題記和附有各自名字的供養人像，被繪在最下段的細帶狀的部位。Mary Fong(1972)試著將此畫與9世紀後半葉的敦煌第85窟（867年）及第107窟（872年）壁畫中的供養人像做了比較（博士論文）。Waley的敍述也涉及到這方面，注意到婦人們頭髮上只是插著一把梳子，沒有使用以後作品中常用的簪子。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 24"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.3</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san">Two Avalokitesvaras</title><title lang="chi-Hant">二觀世音菩薩圖</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, mid-9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.147.3 cm, W. 105.3 cm</p><p>Stein painting 3.Ch.xxxviii.005</p><p>See also Figs.75</p><p>This painting is one of the grandest of those attesting the popularity of Avalokitesvara with individual devotees at Dunhuang. In iconography it is very similar to Pl.13, but with two figures of the Bodhisattva instead of one alone. In addition, the inscription gives us clear details of the wishes of those who had this painting made. It is placed in the very centre of the painting, between the two Bodhisattvas who face each other in virtual mirror-reverse. In fact, the inscription itself (see below) is also so divided, and consists of two inscriptions, each starting from the middle (Fig.75). The top of both is damaged so that a character or two is missing from the top of every line. In addition, a small piece from the top right half of the inscription has been mounted at the top left. Nevertheless, most of the wording can be made out, as follows, beginning with the right half and starting from the centre:</p><p>Avalokitesvara Bodhisattva. The disciple of pure faith, Yiwen, on his own behalf, having fallen [into the hands of the Tibetans], that he may return to his birthplace, made and dedicated with undivided heart...-you and the female disciple Juehui toehui together made an Avalokitesvara Bodhisattva first that her deceased father and mother may be reborn in the Pure Land ...[may escape] the Three Ways and be granted birth in the Pure Country and soon ascend to the World of Buddha, dedicated with undivided heart.</p><p>The left half of the inscription, in five lines beginning again from the centre, reads in similar fashion:</p><p>□□三塗承生淨國早(早)登佛杲(界)一心供養</p><p>□□憂婆姨覺惠同修觀世音菩蕯一爲先亡父母神生淨土</p><p>□番□得歸鄉敬造一心供養</p><p>□觀世音菩蕯清信弟子溫義溫爲己身落</p><p>□觀□世□音□菩□蕯清信弟子□義溫爲己身落</p><p>□番□得□歸鄉敬造一心供養</p><p>□□永安寺老宿慈力發心敬畫觀世音菩蕯爲過往父</p><p>□□三早過佛界一心供養 信弟子男永安寺律師義</p><p>□溫一心供養 信弟子兼技術子弟董文員一心供養</p><p>[Avalokitesvara Bodhisattva]. The disciple of pure faith [Yi] wen on his own behalf, having fallen [into the hands of the Tibetans] that he may return home, made and dedicated with undivided heart. Cili, elder of the Yong’an temple, piously and reverently painted Avalokitesvara Bodhisattva, on behalf of his departed father ...three, that he may soon pass into Buddha’s world, dedicated with undivided heart. The disciple of faith and son Yiwen, master of the Vinaya in the Yong’an temple, dedicated with undivided heart. The believer and performer Dong Wenhai dedicated with undivided heart.</p><p>In spite of the difficulties caused by the misalignment of part of the inscription and the missing characters, some facts emerge fairly clearly from it. Each of the two Bodhisattvas has a separate dedication, and in each case this seems to be divided, with two lines of larger characters first, followed on the right by two lines and on the left by three lines of smaller characters. We may perhaps take it that the chief donor and the principal wishes are recorded in the larger characters, and that other associate donors and their wishes are recorded in the additional lines to the right and left. The wording of the main inscriptions is then practically identical; and the donor in each case seems to be the same person. According to Professor Fujieda (personal communication ) the character “luo”(fallen) seems in each case to invite completion with the character “fan”, as in other inscriptions in the caves themselves, referring to the Tibetan control of this district, and the principal wish is undoubtedly the very Chinese one of a desire to return home. This seems to take precedence over the remaining wishes expressed on behalf of deceased parents, that they may escape rebirth in the Three Evil Ways (as animals, demons, or hungry ghosts) and may instead be reborn in the Pure Land or in the World of the Buddha.</p><p>According to Professor Fujieda’s theory, this would mean that the painting could be dated with some certainty to the period from A.D.781 to 847, before the restoration of Chinese control. This also seems possible from the point of view of style. The two Bodhisattvas, each in three-quarter view, mirror each other to the extent that, save for details such as the shape of the nose, they are distinguished only by their attributes and by the colour of the stoles that cover their shoulders. The figures are both solidly planted on their lotus pedestals, with rather large feet, their bodies swaying very slightly forward at the waist. The depiction is characterized by great precision of brushwork in the fine ink outlines of the main features, with schematic colour shading for the exposed areas of flesh .There are close resemblances to the single depiction of Avalokitesvara of Pl.13, but it could be suggested that Stein painting 3 is slightly later, since the ribands hang more stiffly and the lines of the faces appear also somewhat harder.</p><p>Although the painting shows two figures side by side, and might therefore have been expected to be made up also of two widths of silk, this is not in fact the case. There is a broken area right down the centre of the painting due to folding, but the method of assembly is precisely the same as that of other paintings of the same size, with a full width of silk in the centre, onto which are sewn two half-widths. The left figure has been mounted somewhat too high and the hands would originally have been directly opposite each other: a touch of yellow and two leaves from the flower held by the left figure can be seen on the right and indicate its correct position.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀中葉</p><p>絹本设色</p><p>高147.3釐米 寬105.3釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫3.Ch.xxxviii.005</p><p>參見Fig.75</p><p>此畫是說明觀音信仰在敦煌佛教徒間盛行的代表作之一。此圖與圖13的觀世音菩薩像極其相近，只是在這裏不是一身，而是兩身。并且有願文，明確表达了捐献此畫的人們的祈願。願文在繪畫中心，在面對面像是照鏡子的兩身菩薩中間的位置上。願文（見下）本身分兩部分，分別從中間行開始書寫（參見Fig.75）。上部的絹子有些損壞，每行上部的一個字均已丟失，第二個字也有缺損。左側上端所見的小斷片，原應是右側上部的願文。不過，大部分文字還可以讀出。</p><p>右半願文的大意如下：</p><p>清信弟子溫義，雖然落入吐蕃手，但爲了自身能歸鄉，敬造觀世音菩薩，一心供養。……</p><p>優婆姨覺惠也修造觀世音，第一是爲了亡父母能轉生於淨土，……（可能脫落）三道接受轉生淨國，爲提早進入佛界，一心供養。</p><p>左半的願文，也是從中間行開始書寫，概括在五行裏。</p><p>清信弟子義溫，雖然落入吐蕃手，但爲了自身能歸鄉，敬造觀世音菩薩，一心供養。……</p><p>永安寺的老宿慈力爲了亡父發心敬畫觀世音菩薩。……（三）爲了提早入佛界一心供養。</p><p>作爲信徒和兒子的永安寺律師義溫……一心供養。信徒兼伎術子弟的董文員一心供養。</p><p>題記行款不齊，況且文字缺損，很難解讀，但通過以上詞句，可以明確幾個事實。二身菩薩各持有奉獻名，無論哪一段，前二行的字都是大的，隨後接下來的右側的二行和左側的三行是用小字記錄的。可以看出，大字記錄的主要供養人名及其祈願，而輔助的供養人及其祈願則在左右，是次要記錄。主要的願文寫的全都相同，供養人（右半的是溫義，左半的是義溫）也是同一人。據藤枝晃教授指教，“落”字，與此地區在吐蕃統治時期各石窟所見到的題記一樣，兩處均與“番”連用。出於當時中原人情感中不可動搖的“歸故鄉”的願望，歸鄉在祈願文中作爲主要的記錄，優先於亡父母不轉生三道（畜生道、羅刹道、餓鬼道）而生淨土的供養話語。</p><p>根據藤枝晃教授的觀點，此畫應是唐朝恢復對敦煌的統治權以前，即781年至847年間製作的。這點也可從圖畫的形式來推斷。七三開結構的二身菩薩，除了鼻子形狀等細部的表現外，只有手持物和肩上的天衣顔色不同，其餘表現都是像照鏡子一樣面對面對稱的姿態。二身像的腳均稍大，穩穩踏在蓮瓣上，腰部稍扭向前。在描法上，皮膚所使用的暈染技法和顔面細部細墨線的精密描寫都非常顯眼，與圖13的觀世音菩薩像非常相似。頭部飾帶的線條顯得有些呆板，臉部線描也有幾分僵化，所以本圖的菩薩時代稍晚。</p><p>從並列的二身像上看，雖然可能會並排使用兩幅絹子，但實際情況不是。畫面中央是折疊導致的破損；絹子的縫合使用的是和其他同尺寸的絹繪完全一樣的縫合方法，即畫面中央用了一幅絹子，其左右各綴接了半幅絹。圖畫在粘裱時左邊像被貼在稍微高的位置上，本來雙方的手應並排在同一高度：左邊像手持黃色花和兩片葉子這一細節，在右邊有相應的部分，指示了它原來應在的位置。</p><p>□□三塗承生淨國早(早)登佛杲(界)一心供養</p><p>□□憂婆姨覺惠同修觀世音菩蕯一爲先亡父母神生淨土</p><p>□番□得歸鄉敬造一心供養</p><p>□觀世音菩蕯清信弟子溫義溫爲己身落</p><p>□觀□世□音□菩□蕯清信弟子□義溫爲己身落</p><p>□番□得□歸鄉敬造一心供養</p><p>□□永安寺老宿慈力發心敬畫觀世音菩蕯爲過往父</p><p>□□三早過佛界一心供養 信弟子男永安寺律師義</p><p>□溫一心供養 信弟子兼技術子弟董文員一心供養</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 25"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.48</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Unidentified Christian saint (detail)</title><title lang="chi-Hant">身份不明的景教人物圖（局部）</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.88.0 cm, W. 55.0 cm</p><p>Stein painting 48.Ch. xlix.001</p><p>See also Figs.76</p><p>This figure is of great interest since although it is depicted in three-quarter view in very much the same way as some of the paintings of Buddhist Bodhisattvas, even to the gesture of the right hand, this appears to a Christian, perhaps a Nestorian, saint (see also Fig.76). A cross, each arm terminating in bead-like extensions, appears both in the headdress of the figure and hanging form the necklace he is wearing. In his left hand he holds a long staff. He wears a red stole with a yellow lining, over a robe which has faded to a greenish colour very similar to that of the background silk.</p><p>Two minor features suggest that this painting dates from the end of the ninth century: the narrow flame border of the halo and the configuration of the mouth, which has a slight downward return to the ends of the ink line between the lips. Further confirmation of a possible Christian identification of the figure appears on close examination of the face, as there is a fairly thick moustache and a slight beard, both in red and quite different from the curling moustaches, generally in green, of Bodhisattvas such as Pl.13.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀</p><p>絹本设色</p><p>高88.0釐米 寬55.0釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫48.Ch.xlix.001</p><p>參見Fig.76</p><p>此像如菩薩像中所常見的那樣，為四分之三身像，右手的姿势也很相似，但表現的是基督教，或許是景教的聖者（參見Fig.76）。冠飾和項鏈都有邊緣為水滴狀的十字架。聖者左手持長杖,身披黃色襯裏的紅色披肩，其下著綠色衣服，但已褪色，與背景顔色相近。</p><p>頭光有細小的火焰帶，閉合的唇線拉著墨線，兩端稍往下翻卷。這兩個微小特徵說明此畫是9世紀末以後的作品。細查臉部描寫，相當密的鬍子和稀疏的鄂鬚都是赤茶色的，與彩色圖版第13圖的觀世音菩薩通常捲曲的綠色鬍鬚完全不同，從這一點可肯定此像表現的是基督教聖者。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 26"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.28*</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san">Avalokitesvara as Succourer in Trouble</title><title lang="chi-Hant">大悲救苦觀世音菩薩像</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, dated 3rd year of Dashun 大順三年(A.D.892)</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.83.3 cm, W. 63.1 cm (including border)</p><p>Stein painting 28*. Ch. xx. 005</p><p>See also Figs.74,77</p><p>This modest painting epitomizes the thoughts of those who offered it and who are portrayed below. Although the artistic standard of the execution is at best moderate, it is clear that it amply satisfied them. It still has a colourful border of damask printed by the jiaban 夾版 (Japanese: kyokechi) technique (see Vol.3). A cartouche at the upper left bears the dedication “with whole heart” to Avalokitesvara as Succourer in Trouble. Around the canopy appear small figures of Bodhisattvas offering bowls of flowers, and musical instruments tied with ribbons, reminiscent of those seen in paradise paintings, for example Pl.19. Avalokitesvara himself with a “parent” Buddha in his tiara and a third eye on his forehead is seated on a lotus throne that rises on a tripod base out of a lotus pool whence also emerge other lotuses, some on long leafy stems framing the Bodhisattva on either side.</p><p>The inscription below, dated in the third year of Dashun (A.D.892), identifies the principal donors, the monk Zhigang and the nun Shengming, and states that the painting is offered on behalf of deceased nuns and clerics, in perpetual dedication. The two donors are seen on either side of the inscription, the monk with a hand censer, the nun holding a dish and accompanied by two more nuns (Fig. 74). On the left, behind the monk, are a lay man and woman. They are of great interest since the coiffure of the lady, with a comb and a single hairpin, shows the transition from the plain garb of the early ninth-century donors to the ever more elaborate headdresses, generally with several long hairpins, common in the tenth century. A stylistic transition is visible here too, moving away from the earlier relaxed position, with hands in lap (e.g., Pl.7-5, and Cave 329,Dunhuang bihua, Pl.126) to a stiff repetition in which all the donors lean slightly back at the same angle, their hands all raised high in front of the chest. Only some thirty years earlier, in Stein painting 5 (Pl.23 and Fig.73), the stance of the donors is markedly more upright, and the hairpins have still not made their appearance. In this last painting, as in the one shown here, the outer garments of the donors are of a warm brown colour, without the strong contrast of black outer robe and yellow or white inner lining that is exploited in the stereotyped donors of the tenth-century paintings.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，大順三年（892年）</p><p>絹本设色</p><p>高83.3釐米 寬63.1釐米（含邊緣）</p><p>斯坦因繪畫28*.Ch.xx.005</p><p>參考Figs.74,77</p><p>此幅高雅的繪畫似乎凝聚了繪于下段肖像中供養者們的意願。藝術水準充其量是中等水平，而供養者們大概十分滿意。畫上，殘留著夾纈染的花邊飾，上部左邊的榜題上寫着表示對救苦觀音“一心供養”的獻辭。華蓋周圍可見手捧花盤的二身雲上菩薩和結著彩帶的樂器，使人想起圖19的淨土圖。觀音寶冠上戴著化佛，額上有第三隻眼睛，坐於蓮華座上，而蓮華座乘在置於蓮池外側三腳的壇基上。從蓮池伸出葉子繁茂的長莖，環繞菩薩立於兩旁，莖端盛開美麗的花朵。</p><p>下段的題記中記有大順三年（892年）的紀年、供養人沙門智剛和尼勝明的名字外，還記述了已故的比丘尼施捨此畫爲永世供養的事迹。上述二個供養人像在靠近題記兩邊，比丘右手持帶柄香爐，比丘尼則兩手捧盤。比丘尼背後又有兩個比丘尼。隨比丘背後有世俗的男人和婦人（參見Fig.74）。這些像中可見幾處有趣的特點。首先婦人梳子外還插有一個簪子，這可窺到9世紀初的供養人簡單的髮飾，正向10世紀盛行長簪子的華麗髮飾過渡的跡象。另外，供養者姿勢也有變化，畫中的人物沒有早期作品中把兩手隨意放在膝上的姿勢（參照圖7－5以及《敦煌壁畫》圖126，329窟），而是全都把兩手舉於胸前，以同一角度向後傾斜的姿勢不自然的排列著。比它僅僅早30年左右的圖23的《四觀音文殊普賢圖》中，供養人是筆直而坐（參照Fig.73），也沒有簪子。有供養人像的圖，此畫是本卷中最後一例，供養人像的外衣呈暖褐色，不同於10世紀供養人一律穿著對比強烈的黑色外衣加黃色或白色裏子。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 27"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.31</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san">Tejaprabha Buddha and the Five Planets</title><title lang="chi-Hant">熾盛光佛并五星圖</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, dated 4th year of Qianning 乾寧四年 (A.D.897)</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.80.4 cm, W. 55.4 cm</p><p>Stein painting 31.Ch. liv.007</p><p>See also Figs.79-81</p><p>This is a happy instance where the painting is not only dated, but also represents one of the rarest of the subjects of Buddhist art. The title, “The Buddha of Blazing Light and the Deities of the Five Planets”, is given in the donor’s inscription, as well as the date (Fig.80). Although various literary references to Tejaprabha Buddha accompanied by nine or eleven luminaries are known, only three actual paintings survive: this one, a painting on the south wall of the entrance corridor leading to Cave 61 at Dunhuang itself and a hanging scroll of the Yuan period in the Boston Museum of Fine Arts (Tomita and Tseng, 1961, Pl.21). Cave 61 may be dated to the early Northern Sung period, soon after the middle of the tenth century. It is well known for its magnificent series of donors, including a princess of Khotan, and for its paintings of Wutaishan as well as numerous paradise assemblies. The multiple images of Buddha on its ceiling are closely related to stencils preserved in the Stein collection (Vol.2, Pl.78). The paintings in the corridor, according to Stein, are by a hand far more skilled in composition and drawing than that which executed the present silk painting. Nevertheless, with its earlier date, and because of the rarity of the subject, this is still a very important work.</p><p>The composition is considerably simpler than that of the wall painting, not to mention the one in Boston, and is confined to the principal figures of the Buddha and of the five planets only, all supported on the same multi-coloured clouds. Rays of light radiate from the Buddha, symbolizing his power to subdue adverse influences from the planets. Eiichi Matsumoto (1937, pp.338ff) has shown how the figures of the latter correspond almost exactly with the descriptions of them in the Fan tian huo luo jiu yao 梵天火羅九曜. Proceeding anticlockwise from Tejaprabha himself, who is seated on a cart drawn by an ox advancing to the left (in the entrance corridor of Cave 61, the whole composition suitably takes the form of an extended procession), these planetary figures are described in the text as follows: Mercury, as a woman with a monkey in her headdress, holding brush and paper (Pl. 27-2); Jupiter, as a high official, with blue robes and a boar headdress, holding flowers and fruit (Fig. 79); Saturn as a Brahman, with an ox headdress, holding a pewter staff (Pl.27-4); Venus, with a cock in her headdress, in white mourning robes, playing a stringed instrument (pipa)(Pl.27-5); and finally Mars, shown as a heretic, with donkey headdress, four-armed and carrying weapons and blades (arrow, bow, sword and trident) (Fig.81).The wall painting is damaged but clearly included are these five, with the sun and moon and the two dark stars Rahu and Ketu taken from Indian astronomy, for a total of nine luminaries. In addition, groups of figures representing the twenty-eight constellations appear above the procession, and also small circular medallions, originally twelve in number, within each of which is depicted one of the Western signs of the zodiac.</p><p>An elaborate set of altar vessels drawn in ink and originally richly gilt, is displayed on an altar at the front of the cart, with a valance and an embroidered cloth falling over the ox in the shafts. The face of the Buddha and other exposed areas of his body were originally also gilt. The gilding on the face shows clear signs of having been renewed, and the ink lines of his countenance have also been redrawn, being much darker than those of the other figures, and giving him a more fully fleshed countenance. It is very noticeable that the mouthline ends in a distinct hook, after the fashion of the tenth century (Pl.27-3); in the other figures this line is straight or ends in a slight swelling. It thus seems more than likely that the painting was refurbished at some time in the first half of the tenth century. At the top of the painting, a broad strip of purple silk shows that it was once mounted as a hanging scroll. Although this strip is sadly now only 11.5 cm high, when described by Stein in Serindia it measured 2 ft 61/2 in, or about 75 cm. when found it had already lost the lower mount; nevertheless, it must originally have been an impressive picture and was perhaps actually intended to be carried in procession, as the treatment of the subject itself seems to imply.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，乾寧五年（897年）</p><p>絹本设色</p><p>高80.4釐米 寬55.4釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫31.Ch.liv.007</p><p>參見Figs.79－81</p><p>此圖不僅有紀年，以主題來説中也是佛教美術中最珍稀的作品之一，是難得的範例。“熾盛光佛並五星”這一畫題與紀年同時記錄在供養題記中（參見Fig.80）。經典中有種種有關伴隨九曜和十一曜的熾盛光佛的記載，但繪畫實際只存有以下三件，即本絹繪、敦煌第61窟洞口南壁的壁畫及波士頓美術館藏元代的挂幅（參照K.Tomita and H.C.Tseng:Portfolio of Chinese Paintings圖版21）。從于闐公主等華麗的供養人隊伍，以及由衆多聖衆構成的淨土圖和五臺山的描繪等知道，敦煌61窟的壁畫是北宋初期，即10世紀中葉稍後製作的。而繪於天井上的諸多如來像與此收藏品中收的紙樣（參照第2卷圖78）有密切關係。據斯坦因講，無論是構圖還是線繪，壁畫都比本圖熟練。但是，此畫年代早，主題罕見，是很珍貴的作品。</p><p>波士頓的作品暫且不論，將此畫和壁畫進行比較，此畫的構圖比壁畫簡單得多，只由主尊熾盛光佛和五星組成，都乘同樣的五彩雲。熾盛光佛放射着巨大光芒，象徵震懾的力量。據松本榮一博士講，五星的表現與“梵天火羅九曜”的記載大体是一致的（參照《敦煌研究》338頁之後）。熾盛光佛所坐雄牛牵的車朝向左，五星在車的周圍按照逆時針方向依次排列（第61窟洞口的則全部是按行列形狀整齊排列）。婦人形象的，頭戴猿冠，手持紙、筆的是“木星（北極星）”（圖27－2）；官人形象的，身著青衣，戴豬冠，手捧花和水果的是“水星（歲星）”（Fig.79）；婆羅門形象的，戴牛冠，手持錫杖的是“土星（土宿星）”（圖27－4）；婦人形象的，戴鳥冠，著白色練衣，彈奏琵琶的是“金星（太白星）”（圖81）；外道形象的，戴馿馬冠，四隻手持武器（矢，弓，劍和三叉戟）的是“火星（南方荧惑星）”（Fig.81）。壁畫雖有所損壞，但能確認除了這些五星和日月外，還有從印度天文學借来的羅睺星和計都星兩顆暗淡的星，合起来是九曜。此行列的上方可见表示二十八宿的诸像,以及代表十二宮的小圓形裝飾，最初當是聚齊了十二個宮，但畫面只殘留了一部分。</p><p>牛車前方的祭壇上，擺放著一套精美的祭器。它們用了墨描，當初可能是用了金色暈染。祭壇周邊圍著垂幕，刺繡的桌布垂到駕轅的雄牛背上。熾盛光佛的面部和身軀當時也是金色的，現在面部的金色經過再次塗抹。眼睛和鼻子等的線描也有修改的痕跡，比起其他像显得濃重，面容更加生動。特別是嘴角突出了10世紀的描繪法，呈鈎形，很显眼（參照圖27－3）。其他像的唇線筆直，或兩端稍上翹。因此，判斷此畫是10世紀前半葉著手完成的更準確。繪畫上端殘留的寬幅紫色絹，說明它是曾當作挂幅來使用。可惜的是，現在上端的絹只有高11.5釐米的帶，而斯坦因的發掘報告書《西域》中記載約有75釐米。下端的装裱在當時發現時已經丟失。雖然如此，此畫在當時是極爲富麗的，並且很可能在實際使用中，就是挑掛在畫中所描繪的遊行隊伍中的。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 28"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.120</idno><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.134</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Two banners</title><title lang="chi-Hant">幡（完整）</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, late 9th century A.D.</p><p>Left: Bodhisattva (see also Pl.55)</p><p>Right: Vajrapani (see also Pl.59)</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>Left: H.172.5 cm, W. 18.0 cm</p><p>Left: H.187.5cm,W. 18.6 cm</p><p>Stein painting 120.Ch.0025</p><p>Stein painting 134.Ch.004</p><p>These are two of the best-preserved of the so-called banner paintings from Dunhuang, since they have survived almost complete, with headpieces, side and tail streamers and weighting boards.</p><p>Taking first the Bodhisattva, and leaving aside the question of identification, which is not easily determined, it is interesting to consider the construction of such a banner, as it is in some respects different from that of the larger votive paintings. The painting itself, on a narrow piece of silk, comprises not only the figure but also a narrow ink border on either edge, a band of lozenges below and a painted valance above; these serve as a kind of frame. In this example the triangular headpiece was of a separate piece of silk, now perished or lost, with a pale pink border sewn on its outer edges. At the apex is the original hanging loop. Along the base of the headpiece, originally covered by the silk but now revealed, is a bamboo splint used as a stiffener. This is wound with scraps of red and blue coloured silk threads, running obliquely in opposite directions and so enabling the rest of the banner to be sewn onto it without risk of slipping. A similar piece of bamboo stiffens the lower end of the painting and from it in turn hang four silk streamers, each decorated with a single wavy stem with alternate leaves and flower buds. These are painted in silver. At the bottom all four streamers are fixed in a wooden board, by means of a slit in which they are held by another splint of bamboo. The board itself, coloured red, is similarly decorated in silver with a central flower flanked by leaves.</p><p>Two side streamers are attached to the top stiffener so as partially to cover the edges of the painting. Their ends hang free. These ends are of grey silk, sewn onto a longer ribbon of green. As will be seen in Vol.3, scraps of silk were always saved and used as parts of votive materials at Dunhuang. Here there seems to be an aesthetic motive as well since the grey ends of the streamers correspond nicely with the beginning of the silver-decorated tail streamers, while the green part frames the painting.</p><p>The Vajrapani banner has also the triangular piece of silk from the centre of the headpiece. The suspension loop has a red cord, also apparently original, inserted through it. The lower part consists of a single piece of indigo-dyed silk, with two slits cut almost to the top. The edges of the resulting three streamers have been rolled and finely sewn to prevent the silk fraying. The silk has a shiny appearance, and is also wavy, the latter due simply to long storage rolled round the weighting board. The board is decorated with three floral motifs.</p><p>Such banners look very similar front and back, since the silk is of a single thickness and the painting can be seen from both sides. That they were meant to be so seen is easily shown since the triangular headpiece is frequently made from a folded square of silk, giving a double thickness and having a separate painting on each side. There are also a fair number of banners more cheaply made out of linen or paper, both of which were opaque: all of these are painted on both sides with similar figures (Vol.2, Pls.41-46). It is therefore likely that the paintings were not hung on a wall but in some place where they could twist and turn freely. In fact the wall paintings show banners hanging from the tops of pagodas or high canopies (e.g., Cave 220, see Flying Devis, 1980,Pl.52); and on occasion, as in two of the Stein paintings showing the Bodhisattva Guide of Souls (Vol. 2,Pls. 9, 10), the banner is hanging from a hook at the top of a staff. Such a hook is actually mentioned in the inscription to Stein painting 216 (Vol. 2, Pl.32), one of the banners of exceptional length, dated A.D.956; the donor “respectfully (caused to be) painted this forty-nine feet banner in one strip. This banner suspended on high from a dragon hook ... twisting about and flapping in the wind like a bird in flight, like the coloured [hangings] in the Western Apartments of the Palace.”(Waley, 1931,p.187.)</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀末</p><p>左：菩薩像（參照圖55）</p><p>右：金剛力士像（參照圖59）</p><p>絹本设色</p><p>左：高172.5釐米 寬18.0釐米</p><p>右：高187.5釐米 寬18.6釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫120.Ch.0025</p><p>斯坦因繪畫134.Ch.004</p><p>這是敦煌幡畫中保存最完好的其中兩幅，它們的幡頭、邊、幡尾和最下端的墜板都完全保留下來。</p><p>首先看菩薩幡，把菩薩不易考證的身份放在一邊不說，來考察幡畫的構造是很有趣的，因爲它有些細節不同于大的還願畫。這個畫在一條狹窄的絹帶上畫像，不僅有菩薩像，兩側還有細細的墨色的鑲邊，下邊綴加菱形花紋帶，上邊是著色的短帷幔，起到了邊欄的作用。在這個樣品中，三角形幡頭外沿縫著粉色邊布，是單獨的一塊絹，現在已經毀壞或遺失了。在三角形的尖上是原來的吊環，在幡頭的基部是一個用作加固物的竹夾板，原來覆蓋著絲織品，現在已經露出來了。有一個裂口帶著染成紅色和藍色的絲綫，斜著滑到了相反的方向，所以使幡旗可以被縫在上面以免滑落。一個同樣的竹板加固了畫的底座，從那裏依次垂下了四條絲帶，每條絲帶上裝飾著一個單獨的波浪形的杆莖，其上交替排列著樹葉和花蕾。這些都畫在絲織品上，在幡尾，全部絲帶被固定在一個木板上，木板本身被漆成紅色，同樣附有銀飾—葉子包圍著中心的花朵。</p><p>兩邊的絲帶系在頂部的加固物上，所以部分地遮住了畫的邊緣，它們的尾部是灰色的絲織品，沒有挂任何東西，被縫在一個較長的綠絲帶上。就像即將Vol.3中看見的那樣，在敦煌壁畫中，絲織碎片，常常節約下來用作還願的部分材料。這裏似乎也帶有美學的目的，因爲絲帶的灰色尾部很好的和銀裝飾的絲帶尾部開始部分相配，同時綠色部分框住了圖畫。</p><p>金剛力士像的幡頭中央同樣也失去了三角形的那塊絲織品，吊環中插著一個紅帶，很明顯也是原來的，其下部是一片單獨的藍靛染的絲綢，鉸開兩個口，形成了三個下垂的帶子，卷起來以防止零亂，絲綢的外表閃光，幷總是波浪形的，後者只是簡單地因爲長期地卷在一塊重木板上保存而導致的。這塊木板裝飾以三個花紋。</p><p>這樣的幡的正反面看起來非常相似，因爲絲綢只有一層，兩面都可以看見圖像，它們刻意被設計成容易看見，因爲三角形的頭幡由折叠的絲織品製成，具有雙層的厚度幷且每一面都是不同的畫面。還有很多的幡畫製作廉價，由亞麻布或紙製成，它們都是不透光的：兩面的圖案是相同的，(Vol. 2,Pls,41-46).這是因爲這些幡畫幷不是懸挂在墻上，在有些地方它們能够捲起來或自由翻動，事實上壁畫顯示幡畫懸掛在寶塔頂部和高的華蓋(例如：220窟，敦煌飛天，1980，Pl 52)；甚至象斯坦因收藏的兩幅畫中的《引路菩薩圖》(Vol.2 Pls. 9, 10)那樣，幡畫從某個物體頂部的勾子上懸掛下來。這樣的勾子在斯坦因收藏的畫216中已經被提到---該畫繪于西元956年，它的長度超乎想像，捐獻者分別在一條帶子上繪出了這個49英尺長的幡畫。這個幡畫從一個龍形的鈎子上垂下來，在風中捲曲、飄轉，就像鳥兒在飛翔，像西宮的彩色懸挂物一樣，(Waley, 1931,p. 187.)。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 29"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.95(1)</idno><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.95(2)</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Scenes from the Life of the Buddha: the Farewell; the Departure of Chandaka; the Search</title><title lang="chi-Hant">佛傳圖斷片:別離；尋找</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 8th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.18.5 cm, W. 19.0 cm (upper part)</p><p>H.14.0 cm, W. 19.0 cm (lower part)</p><p>Stein painting 95.Ch.lxi.002</p><p>See also Fig. 85</p><p>Originally this banner had four scenes, all set in a continuous landscape and punctuated by blank cartouches set on one side or the other. This organization resembles that of the marginal scenes accompanying the paradise paintings: the diagonals formed by the slopes of the landscape serve to divide one scene from the next and provide space for the action or events depicted. Generally it seems not to have been necessary to inscribe the cartouches, presumably because the story would have been well known to the viewers already.</p><p>The upper section takes up the story of Prince Sakyamuni’s life after his departure from his father’s palace. He is shown bidding farewell to his groom, Chandaka, and his horse, Kanthaka. The occasion is clearly an emotional one for all three, as the groom and the prince both raise their sleeves to wipe away their tears, and the horse also kneels and seems overcome. Immediately above them, an isolated group of distant mountains shows that was the topmost scene shown on this banner. Immediately below, the landscape continues with Sakyamuni, still wearing his three-pronged princely crown, more composed and seated on a ledge while Chandaka and Kanthaka can just be seen descending the valley opposite. The lower part represents the search for the prince by five messengers sent by his father Suddhodana. As the landscape continues below and there is the top of a fourth cartouche, there must have been a fourth scene at the bottom of the banner.</p><p>The messengers are shown as riders, in bright costumes and caps with flowing ribbons. This scene in particular, with the riders in a landscape setting, recalls wall paintings of the early eighth century such as have recently been recovered from princely tombs near Xi’an, especially the scenes of polo playing from the tomb of Zhang Huai 章懷 (Tang Li Xian mu bihua, Pls. 15-23).</p><p>Despite a certain summary quality in the painting which leaves one in no doubt that the painter was merely following a model (confirmed by the fact that an almost identical group of riders can be seen in another banner illustrating these episodes from the Stein collection now in New Delhi (Stein, Thousand Buddhas, Pl.XII), there is considerable interest in the depiction of the group and in the many flowering trees, beloved of Tang painters. The bright colours used for such motifs as the rocks show the kind of colour scheme that knew later fame as the blue-green style, traced back to Li Sixun 李思訓and his son at the Tang court in the late seventh and early eighth century.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代（8世紀）</p><p>絹本设色</p><p>上部斷片 高18.5釐米 寬19.0釐米</p><p>下部斷片 高14.0釐米 寬19.0釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫95.Ch.lxi.002</p><p>參考Fig.85</p><p>本幡原畫有四個場景，全部設置在一個連續的風景畫中並且在其間插入空白的長方欄作爲場景分隔。這樣的組織畫面類似于淨土圖邊緣部分的故事圖，風景畫的斜綫組成對角綫來劃分一個場景和另一個場景，同時也爲活動和事件的文字說明提供空間，通常這好像不一定需要文字描述的，也許是因爲觀衆對這個故事已經非常熟悉而顯得沒有必要了。</p><p>上部的場景以悉達多太子離開他父親王宮的故事爲開始，畫中表現他告別馬夫車匿和愛馬犍陟的情景，這個場景顯然對於他們三者都是很動情的,因爲馬夫和太子都舉起衣袖擦去眼淚，愛馬也不勝傷感的硊倒在地，就在他們的上面一群獨立的遠山顯示了這是幡畫的最高部位。緊接其下畫面繼續描寫悉達多太子還是戴著他的通天冠，努力控制他的情緒坐在岩石上，車匿和犍陟眼看著消失在山谷裏。較低部分表達了太子的父親淨飯王派出五個使者。查訪太子的情况，因爲風景畫往下延續，幷且殘留有第四個長方框的上部,可知原來有第四個場景在幡畫的底部。</p><p>使者被表現爲騎馬者，穿著亮麗的衣服和帶流蘇的帽子。這個場景尤其是畫中的騎者，使人聯想起八世紀早期的一些壁畫，例如最近發現的西安附近的王室墓葬，尤其是章懷墓中的馬球遊戲的場景（唐麗仙墓壁畫，Pls, 15-23）。</p><p>那些作畫者繪畫時僅僅依據一個模式，這一點被這樣的事實證明---在新德里的斯坦因收藏品中可以看到幾乎完全相同的一群騎馬者。盡管如此，唐代畫家仍然熱愛這種繪畫方式，他們對于描述在很多開花的樹下的人群傾注了極大的熱情。明亮的顔色用于表現諸如岩石這樣的主題，這類顔色系統就是後來知道的所謂藍綠風格，這可以追溯到七世紀晚期至八世紀早期唐朝宮廷畫師李思訓父子。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 30"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.96</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Scenes from the Life of the Buddha: Dipamkara’s Prediction; Old Age, Sickness and Death; the Conception</title><title lang="chi-Hant">佛傳圖: 燃燈佛預言；三苦；入胎</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.60.0 cm, W. 16.5 cm</p><p>Stein painting 95.Ch.lv.009</p><p>This very handsome banner, one of a pair, the other of which is in New Delhi (Ch.lv.0010, Stein, Desert Cathay, vol.Ⅱ, Pl.Ⅵ; Serindia, Pl.LXXIV), shows four scenes one above the other, clearly divided by broad bands of the same colour as the side borders. This arrangement for the successive episodes of a narrative, as an alternative to their depiction in a continuous landscape setting, parallels the alternatives that were open to a painter depicting narrative in a horizontal format such as the handscroll or the registers of a wall painting. Cartouches for the possible inscription of explanatory labels appear alternately on either side. The New Delhi banner exactly matches this arrangement so that it seems likely that the two hung together as a pair or on either side of a central painting.</p><p>The scenes begin at the top of the banner (Pl. 30-1). In the first scene, a Buddha (Dipamkara?), accompanied by two attendants, touches the head of a young hermit. Although the identification of the characters is not possible, the intent is clear as a prediction that a future existence the youth will be reborn as Sakyamuni. The second scene shows several figures or perhaps the same one successively as an old man supported by a boy, on his sick bed, and finally in death, while his soul flies up to paradise represented by buildings in the sky. The third scene (Pl.30-2) shows a palace courtyard with one building open to reveal the sleeping figure of Queen Maya, the mother of Prince Sakyamuni, while a figure on a white elephant appears on a cloud from above. This represents the conception of the Buddha. The last scene shows the queen’s confinement, with her attendants keeping watch outside the closed pavilion where she lies.</p><p>In style, the architecture with its slender and elegant features, the columns ruled as fine straight lines, is close to the architecture of the side scenes, illustrating the story of Prince Ajatasatru, in the wall paintings of Cave 25 at Yulin. Among the paintings on silk, apart from others of the banner paintings showing the life of Buddha, the side scenes of Pl. 9 are probably the closest. This would suggest a date in the middle or second half of the ninth century.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀</p><p>絹本设色</p><p>高60.0釐米 寬16.5釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫96.Ch.lv.009</p><p>這個非常漂亮的幡，是一對中的一個，另一個藏在新德里(Ch.lv.0010, 斯坦因, Desert Cathay, vol.Ⅱ, Pl.Ⅵ; Serindia, Pl.LXXIV)，顯示四個場景一個在另一個的上面，明顯地被同色寬帶作爲邊界分隔開來，這個故事的連續情節的安排，是連續的風景畫描述中的一種排列方式，畫家也可以選擇用另外一種表現方式以，比如用手寫卷或者用壁畫的方式。長方形的題簽作爲描述的標簽交替出現在每一邊，新德里的幡正好配上這個布局,所以它好象兩個懸掛在一起作爲一對或者在中央畫面的兩邊。</p><p>這個場景從幡頂上開始(Pl. 30-1)，在第一個場景，描繪的是有二個侍者的燃燈佛手摸年輕修行者的頭。雖然這個角色的身份不太可能，但目的很明顯在於預言未來這個年輕人將再生爲釋迦牟尼。第二個場景顯示了幾個人或者同一個人，被一個仆童扶坐起來的老人,在他的病床上最後死去，他的靈魂最後飛向天堂。第三個場景（Pl.30－2）顯示了宮殿敞開的部分，露出太子的母親摩耶王后睡覺的畫象，其上有一個坐在白象上的幼兒身姿，代表著釋迦牟尼的“入胎”。最後是摩耶王后生産的場面，牆壁圍起的産房外，她的隨帶侍女守候在她所躺的華麗宮殿之外。</p><p>從風格上,畫面的建築帶著纖細和優雅的特征，柱子被設計成優美的直線，與這些建築類似的是榆林第25窟的壁畫中描述的悉達多王子的故事，在這些絹畫中，除了一些佛傳圖外，彩色圖版中的第9圖邊緣部所見到的描繪，恐怕最接近該作品。從這一點可推斷該畫應該是9世紀中期或9世紀下半葉的作品。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 31-1"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.91</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Scenes from the Life of the Buddha: Buddha’s Birth and First Steps</title><title lang="chi-Hant">佛傳圖斷片:入胎；誕生；九龍灌頂；七步</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.37.0 cm, W. 18.8 cm (upper part)</p><p>H.31.0 cm, W. 19.0 cm (lower part)</p><p>Stein painting 91 and 89.Ch.0039, Ch.xxii.0035</p><p>These two fragments were originally joined as a single banner of four scenes, disposed however in a continuous setting rather than in separate frames as in the last example. The top scene, although more summarily depicted, will be recognized as the same as the third in that banner, namely the conception of Sakyamuni, when he appeared to Queen Maya as a child riding a white elephant. The second scene proceeds immediately to the actual birth. This still preserves elements of iconography common to the earliest surviving depictions of the event, for instance at Amaravati in the first to second centuries A.D. Although there the child himself is not shown, the ladies attendant on the queen hold out a cloth to receive him (Barrett, 1954,Pl.Ⅷc).</p><p>Queen Maya and her attendants are shown as aristocratic Tang ladies, with the rather full figures and plump faces associated with Emperor Minghuang’s favourite in the late eighth century; they wear a large chignon with ornaments but none of the long pins that become common in the early tenth century.</p><p>The third scene shows the washing of the new-born prince by nine dragons in the Lumbini Garden. Sakyamuni stands on a kind of Sumeru pedestal, and the nine dragons are combined into a single cloud within which they are not in fact individually distinguished at all (Pl.31-3). Similarly, in the last scene, showing his vow and the seven steps, the latter are shown by just three lotus tracks in addition to the one he stands on, thought up to seven by the three in the sky above him. The whole depiction of this banner is somewhat cursory, with simple colours used for the landscape and an avoidance of elaboration.</p><p>The top of the banner is lost, but at the bottom the bamboo stretcher can just be seen; this, when found, had fragments of brown silk streamers.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀</p><p>絹本设色</p><p>上部斷片高37.0釐米 寬18.8釐米</p><p>下部斷片 高31.0釐米 寬19.0釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫 91.Ch.0039</p><p>斯坦因繪畫89.Ch.xxii.0035</p><p>這兩個碎片原來是拼成四個場景的單獨一幅畫，但是就象在最後的例子中一樣，它已經處理成一個連續的場景。最高處的場景，雖然是總結性的描述，在人們記憶中與第三種完全相同，就是釋迦牟尼的胎兒期，即他顯示爲一個孩子乘坐白象走向摩耶王后。第二場景即進行到實際的出生，這對於早期的事件描述保存著通常的聖象成分，比如從一世紀到二世紀中在Amārāvati的例子。雖然孩子自己並沒有出現，王后的侍女拿出一塊布來接納他。(Barrett,1954, pl.VIIIc )（注：原书名 D.E.Barrett;Sculptures from Amārāvati in the British Museum.London,1954.）。</p><p>摩耶王后和她的侍女表現爲唐代貴族婦女，豐滿的形體和面部爲八世紀晚期的唐明皇所喜愛,梳著帶有裝飾的很大的髮髻，但是沒有一個長的別針---這在十世紀早期變行很流行。</p><p>第三個場景表現在藍毘尼園中九龍爲新生王子進行洗禮，釋迦牟尼站在須彌壇形狀的臺子上。九條龍被繪成一朵雲，以致無法分辨各自的形狀，類似地，在最後一個場景，表現他的誓言和行七步，下一個顯示了三朵蓮花，還有一朵是佛站在上面，另外還有三朵在天空中他的頭上，所以事實上變成了七朵。整個幡旗的描繪都很粗略，使用簡單的顔色，避免過分裝飾。</p><p>幡畫的上端已經遣失了，可以看見底部的竹支架。剛剛發現它的時候，還有棕色絹的幡腳的斷片。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 31-2"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.89</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san">Scenes from the Life of the Buddha: Buddha’s Birth and First Steps</title><title lang="chi-Hant">佛傳圖斷片:入胎；誕生；九龍灌頂；七步</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.37.0 cm, W. 18.8 cm (upper part)</p><p>H.31.0 cm, W. 19.0 cm (lower part)</p><p>Stein painting 91 and 89.Ch.0039, Ch.xxii.0035</p><p>These two fragments were originally joined as a single banner of four scenes, disposed however in a continuous setting rather than in separate frames as in the last example. The top scene, although more summarily depicted, will be recognized as the same as the third in that banner, namely the conception of Sakyamuni, when he appeared to Queen Maya as a child riding a white elephant. The second scene proceeds immediately to the actual birth. This still preserves elements of iconography common to the earliest surviving depictions of the event, for instance at Amaravati in the first to second centuries A.D. Although there the child himself is not shown, the ladies attendant on the queen hold out a cloth to receive him (Barrett, 1954,Pl.Ⅷc).</p><p>Queen Maya and her attendants are shown as aristocratic Tang ladies, with the rather full figures and plump faces associated with Emperor Minghuang’s favourite in the late eighth century; they wear a large chignon with ornaments but none of the long pins that become common in the early tenth century.</p><p>The third scene shows the washing of the new-born prince by nine dragons in the Lumbini Garden. Sakyamuni stands on a kind of Sumeru pedestal, and the nine dragons are combined into a single cloud within which they are not in fact individually distinguished at all (Pl.31-3). Similarly, in the last scene, showing his vow and the seven steps, the latter are shown by just three lotus tracks in addition to the one he stands on, thought up to seven by the three in the sky above him. The whole depiction of this banner is somewhat cursory, with simple colours used for the landscape and an avoidance of elaboration.</p><p>The top of the banner is lost, but at the bottom the bamboo stretcher can just be seen; this, when found, had fragments of brown silk streamers.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀</p><p>絹本设色</p><p>上部斷片高37.0釐米 寬18.8釐米</p><p>下部斷片 高31.0釐米 寬19.0釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫 91.Ch.0039</p><p>斯坦因繪畫89.Ch.xxii.0035</p><p>這兩個碎片原來是拼成四個場景的單獨一幅畫，但是就象在最後的例子中一樣，它已經處理成一個連續的場景。最高處的場景，雖然是總結性的描述，在人們記憶中與第三種完全相同，就是釋迦牟尼的胎兒期，即他顯示爲一個孩子乘坐白象走向摩耶王后。第二場景即進行到實際的出生，這對於早期的事件描述保存著通常的聖象成分，比如從一世紀到二世紀中在Amārāvati的例子。雖然孩子自己並沒有出現，王后的侍女拿出一塊布來接納他。(Barrett,1954, pl.VIIIc )（注：原书名 D.E.Barrett;Sculptures from Amārāvati in the British Museum.London,1954.）。</p><p>摩耶王后和她的侍女表現爲唐代貴族婦女，豐滿的形體和面部爲八世紀晚期的唐明皇所喜愛,梳著帶有裝飾的很大的髮髻，但是沒有一個長的別針---這在十世紀早期變行很流行。</p><p>第三個場景表現在藍毘尼園中九龍爲新生王子進行洗禮，釋迦牟尼站在須彌壇形狀的臺子上。九條龍被繪成一朵雲，以致無法分辨各自的形狀，類似地，在最後一個場景，表現他的誓言和行七步，下一個顯示了三朵蓮花，還有一朵是佛站在上面，另外還有三朵在天空中他的頭上，所以事實上變成了七朵。整個幡旗的描繪都很粗略，使用簡單的顔色，避免過分裝飾。</p><p>幡畫的上端已經遣失了，可以看見底部的竹支架。剛剛發現它的時候，還有棕色絹的幡腳的斷片。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 32"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.99</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Scenes from the Life of the Buddha: the Bath in the Lumbini Garden and the First Steps, together with the Seven Treasures of the Cakravartin</title><title lang="chi-Hant">佛傳圖:佛七寶；九龍灌頂；七步</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.65.5 cm, W. 19.0 cm</p><p>Stein painting 99.Ch. 00114</p><p>This banner has no formal separation of the scenes, but two scenes from the life of Buddha are combined with the depiction above of the Seven Treasures of the Cakravartin (see the notes to Pl.40 below, for a complete list of the treasures).</p><p>The depiction of the Bath in the Lumbini Garden and the First Steps is some-what more elaborate than is the case in Pl.31, but is essentially quite similar in style. The heads of the naga spirits are gathered together in a black cloud and can clearly be seen as Chinese dragons (Pl. 32-3). There is a token landscape setting to the whole composition, with a scattering of flowering plants, two trees behind the infant prince in the bath scene, and the foliage of another tree at the top of the painting. Below, the ladies surround the infant as he stands on a lotus pedestal. One of them holds out a towel as if ready to dry him, a motif reminiscent of the swaddling cloth held by Indra and Brahma in early representations of the birth (e.g., at Amaravati, 1 st-2 nd century A.D., cf. Barrett, 1954, Pl.Ⅷc). Although each of the figure groups as a whole is stationary, the attitudes of the individual figures are quite varied, with some of them seen from behind and in contrapposto, reflecting Tang interest in figure painting and the long experience of painters in China with groups of figures, now revealed by the excavation of wall paintings in tombs near Xi’an.</p><p>The space above the Life scenes in this banner is occupied by a subject that is also found on another banner (Pl. 40), as well as in other paintings from Dunhuang (Bannières, No.6). Here the figures and the symbols appear supported by clouds, with trees just visible in the background, so that it would seem that they are not just a separate representation, but appear as manifestations on the occasion of the events portrayed below. Among them the general carries a banner with characters zuo yi jiang 左一將, “First General of the Left”, that is, “the best general”, since the left takes precedence over the right in Chinese ranks. He thus corresponds well with the canonical list of the Seven Treasures (see Pl.40). He also carries a shield which is decorated in large squares of colour in similar fashion to the silk banners without decoration (Vol.3, Pl.10). The horse has a red mane and tail as with the scenes of the prince’s Farewell (Pls.29 and 38). The spirals of the clouds were first drawn in white and a pale colour, then denser colour was used to provide firm outer contours and to break up the white in a feathered effect. This technique seems to have been first used in the High Tang in the wall paintings (cf. Cave 205, Dunhuang bihua, Pl.149), but here the feathering of the white seems to extend much further around the spiral than in such early examples. The depiction is directly comparable with the painting in the Pelliot collection, where the Seven Treasures are shown along the lower margin (Bannières, No. 6).</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀</p><p>絹本设色</p><p>高65.5釐米 寬19.0釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫99.Ch.00114</p><p>此幡沒有場景的嚴格的分隔，但佛的兩個生活場景與上部的Cakravatin的七寶的描寫聯合起來(見第40頁下面的附注，那裏有一個珠寶的完全單子)。</p><p>對藍毘尼花園中的“灌頂”和“七步”的描寫，無論如何比圖31的描繪有更多裝飾，但從本質上是非常相似的風格，九龍的頭在黑雲中聚集在一起，可以清楚的看出是中國的龍形。在整個構圖中散布著一些開花的植物，在灌頂的場景中兩棵樹在嬰兒王子的後面，畫的頂部有另一棵樹的樹葉。在下面，婦女圍繞著站在蓮座上的嬰兒，其中一個婦女拿著一塊毛巾好象准備將他擦幹淨，這個主題使人想到了早期生育的代表梵天和帝釋天手拿著包裹嬰兒的布。(例如, Amaravati, 1 st – 2 nd century A.D., cf. Barrett, 1954, Pl. VIIIc).雖然作爲一個整體的每個畫象都是固定的，但因爲他們姿勢不同，顯得是活勸的，其中一些從後面看並且in contrapposto，舆西安附近挖掘出來的墓葬壁畫中發現的人群畫相比較,反映了唐代在人物畫的興趣和人群畫像的較長的發展經歷。</p><p>就像敦煌其它圖畫中出現的那樣，在此幡畫生活場景的上面被一個在加一幡畫出現的同一主題占據。這裏的人物和一些圖案都被雲彩圍繞，背景中有樹,所以看起來不是獨立的場景，而是下面描寫的事件場景的顯現。在人群中有一人舉著幡，上面寫著“左一將”——“左边的第一长官”，即最高长官，因为在中国排位中尚左，即左边的位置尊于右边的位置。这很好地吻合了教義規定的七宝名单的排序(见圖40)。他也带了一个盾，上面装饰着大块的色彩，与没有装饰的绢幡畫的风格很相似（卷3,圖10）。馬的紅鬃和紅尾馬就象王子辭別的那個場景(圖29、38)。螺旋形的雲首次被畫成白色和暗淡的色彩，使用濃厚的顔色以提供堅固的外部的輪廓，以打破白色，形成羽毛的形狀，這種技術似乎最先應用於盛唐的壁畫（參照《敦煌壁畫》圖版149，205窟），但這裏白色的羽毛似乎比早期的延伸更多，形成螺旋狀，這種描繪直接與伯希和收藏的繪畫相比較，在那兒七寶被表現在低的邊欄上。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 33"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.94(1)</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Scenes from the Life of the Buddha: the Simultaneous Births</title><title lang="chi-Hant">佛傳圖斷片:諸獸誕生</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.18.0 cm, W. 19.0 cm (upper part)</p><p>H.24.0 cm, W. 20.0 cm (lower part)</p><p>Stein painting 94. Ch.xxii.008</p><p>See also Fig. 86</p><p>These fragments of a banner (see Fig. 86), as pointed out by Stein in Serindia, are clearly from the same series as those shown in Pl.31 and Pl.41, characterized by the use of opaque white pigment that has tended to flake away, and by simplified landscape forms—low hills—separating the different scenes. A charmingly domestic touch is added by the lady, with the rather full figure and costume associated with the Tang, who is milking the cow.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代（9世紀）</p><p>絹本 设色</p><p>上部斷片 高18.0釐米 寬19.0釐米</p><p>下部斷片 高24.0釐米 寬20.0釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫94.Ch.xxii.008</p><p>參考Fig.86]</p><p>這些幡畫的碎片(見Fig. 86)，正如斯坦因在《西域》中指出的---很明顯來自圖31 和圖41中表現的相同的系列，使用不透明的白色顔料來顯示這一特徵，而白色顔料已經脫落了。用簡單化的風景——低矮的小丘——分隔不同的場景，一個身著唐代服裝的擠牛奶的豐滿婦女，使畫面增加了令人陶醉的家庭氣息。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 34"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.90</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Scenes from the Life of the Buddha: seated Buddha; Sākyamuni in Discussion; the Iron Targets</title><title lang="chi-Hant">佛傳圖斷片：坐佛；釋迦牟尼講論時；鐵靶</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 8th or early 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.42.5 cm, W. 17.5 cm</p><p>Stein painting 90. Ch. xlix.006</p><p>This fragment and the next evidently belong to the same series, with each scene framed and divided from the next by a striped band with individual florets.</p><p>The upper section must have been the top of the banner and was a seated figure of the Buddha with hands in abhaya- and vara-mudrā. There is no accompanying cartouche, as in the remaining scenes, which are inscribed in a neat regular script. The centre scene shows the boy prince seated on a couch, engaged in discussion with the doctors of military science and of literature (one holds a scroll and another an official tablet). Of the lowest scene only the top half is preserved, but this is enough to show that it represented Sākyamuni’s prowess in contest; a similar scene of the iron target drums lined up is to be found in the series of scrolls of the Kako genzai inga-kyō in Japan. Sākyamuni alone was able to pierce them all with his arrow. The competition, along with Sākyamuni uprooting a tree with his bare hands, is also shown in one of the Stein banners now in New Delhi.</p><p>Both the actual painting and the writing of the captions accompanying each scene in this and the next banner are very well done, in marked contrast to the summary execution and careless hand visible in another pair of banners with individually framed events (Figs. 82 and 83). There the composition seems to follow an archaic formula, with the figures stiffly distributed in the picture area, with little movement or indication of depth. In the present paintings, on the contrary, the figures are grouped so as to make quite clear their individual relationships, and architectural features are used to advantage in establishing a spatial setting.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，8世紀～9世紀初</p><p>絹本设色</p><p>高42.5釐米 寬17.5釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫90.Ch.xlix.006</p><p>這個碎片和下一個很明顯屬于同一系列，每個場景是都分別被框起來,用一個由花朵形連成的條紋帶隔開。</p><p>上面的部分一定是幡的頂部，是佛的坐像。兩手結施無畏印和與願印，沒有下面接續的兩個場景中的那種工整楷書書寫的題箋。中心場景表現少年太子坐在一個椅子上，正在和武功和文學先生進行討論（一個手握卷軸，另一個手持笏），最下面的場景只殘留上半部分，但這足以表現出它代表釋迦牟尼在戰鬥中的英勇，鐵鼓形的靶子---在日本的《過去現在因果經》卷軸中也有相同的場景，釋迦牟尼可以獨自用劍刺穿他們。這個比賽連同釋迦牟尼空手拔樹場面一起，在現存的新德里斯坦因收集品的幡畫中也有表現。</p><p>此幡和下一幡的每個場景的繪畫本身及其相應的文字說明都做得非常好，與另一對幡的獨立的框起來的事件（參照單色圖版第82圖，第83圖）——演奏的簡略繪畫和潦草筆迹相比，有顯著的區別。那個構圖似乎根據一個古老的公式，人物像被僵硬地分配在畫面裏，幾乎沒有動感或立體感。相反，在現在的繪畫中，人物都被聚在一起，人物關系清楚明瞭，對建築物的描繪也有立體感。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 35"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.88</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Scenes from the Life of the Buddha: the Four Encounters; Old Age and Sickness</title><title lang="chi-Hant">佛傳圖斷片：四門出游：老年和疾病</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 8th or early 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.37.5 cm, W. 17.7 cm</p><p>Stein painting 88. Ch. lv.0016</p><p>By its clear relationship with the preceding banner, this fragment, showing two of the Four Encounters (all four-Old Age, Sickness, Death, and the Religious Life-are shown on another banner in New Delhi), implies the existence of an orderly series of banners, presenting the events of Sākyamuni’s life in sequence.</p><p>Much care was taken in the execution: unlike the inscriptions on many of the votive banners, the characters in the cartouches are neatly written, of a standard size and well chosen to fill the space available exactly. The style of the figures and of the architecture echoes this care. In both banners the architecture is drawn with slender elements, although not yet so attenuated as that of the side scenes of the south wall of Cave 25 at Yulin, where the columns have become truly pencil-thin. The figures and Sākyamuni’s horse are compact and beautifully organized within the space available. Although the overall impression, from colouring and setting, is very different from that of Pl.38, an examination of such details as the fine delineation of the bony structure of the horse’s head and the accurately drawn harness reveals a close similarity. The initial impression distinguishing the two may have much to do with the subjects: here and in Pl.34 it is the civilized and orderly background of the prince’s sheltered life in the palace of his father that is shown, while his new life as a religious ascetic begins in the untamed surroundings of the wilderness, allowing the artist full scope for the depiction of a grandiose landscape with crags and cliffs (Pl.38).</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，8世紀～9世紀初</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高37.5釐米 寬17.7釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫88.Ch.lv.0016</p><p>根據它與前一幡的明顯關系。這個斷片，表現了四門出游中的兩個(四門包括：老年、疾病、死亡和出家——在新德里的另一幡畫中有表現)，暗示著一個有秩序的系列幡畫的存在，表現了釋迦牟尼生活事件的連續性。</p><p>該畫制作精細，不象很多還願畫的那樣，長方形題簽的尺寸計算的恰好能收入文字，字的大小整齊，人物和建築也和字同樣細致。在兩個幡畫中的建築被畫成纖細的線條，雖然沒有榆林第25窟南壁的邊緣部分那樣纖細——那裏的石柱已經變成真正的鉛筆那樣細。人物和馬簡潔漂亮，畫面安排恰到好處。雖然全部的印象從顔色到布局，與圖38的幡有很大的不同，但對一些細節的分析，比如對馬頭健美結構和對馬具的精確繪畫都顯示出二者的相似性。最初分辨二者也許只能依靠主題，這兒和圖34是教化的有次序的背景，王子在他父親的王宮裏，過著受庇護的生活，那兒是在沒有開發的野外環境中開始的苦行僧的宗教新生活，使得藝術家有機會用懸崖峭壁來描繪氣氛磅礴的風景畫。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 36"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.98</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Scenes from the Life of the Buddha: the Pleasures of the Palace; the Great Departure</title><title lang="chi-Hant">佛傳圖:宫廷生活的欢樂；偉大的轉變</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.50.0 cm, W. 20.0 cm</p><p>Stein painting 98. Ch. xlix.005</p><p>This banner consists of two scenes only, each as usual accompanied by a cartouche, left blank. Although it displays no great sophistication, the depiction is engagingly direct, and not without a touch of humour.</p><p>At the top, Sākyamuni is seen seated on a dais in the centre, with his wife Yasodharā in the side verandah. Before them is a dancer, in Chinese costume with long sleeves and cloud-toed shoes, accompanied by musicians and two kneeling figures. The scene represents Sākyamuni’s life of pleasure in his father’s palace, while that below shows his departure by night. This scene takes place between the walls of the palace. Guards can be seen in front, carrying banners; other banners seen over the upper wall indicate the presence of more guards, and two are within the walls. All wear scale armour, and all save the one in the gateway make the gesture of cupping one hand to their ear, to catch the sound of the unseen departure. One indeed is seen stretched out as if asleep, but still making this gesture. Above the palace Sākyamuni rides his horse, each hoof supported by a kneeling figure to muffle the sound. The scene marks Sākyamuni’s departure from the palace to the life of austerities and would probably have been followed by a farewell scene with his horse and groom, as in Pls. 29 and 38.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代（9世紀）</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高50.0釐米 寬20.0釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫98.Ch.xli.005</p><p>此幡僅包括兩個場景，每個按慣例有一個長方形題簽，但沒有文字。沒有運用很複雜的手法，表現質樸，並且還有些許的幽默。</p><p>在上部，可以看見太子端坐在中央的講臺上，他的妻子耶輪陀羅在旁邊的走廊裏，在他們前面是一個舞者，穿著中國服飾，長長的衣袖，腳尖繡著雲彩的舞鞋，還有伴有一群樂師和兩個跪著的人，這個場景表現太子在父親王宮中的歡愉生活。下面的畫面表現他的深夜出走，這個場景發生在宮牆之間，前面可以看見衛兵，擡著幡，宮牆之上還能看見旗，暗示還有更多的衛兵，其中兩人在牆中間。他們全部穿著鱗片狀的甲胄，留下一人在門口，其他的衛士一手捂住耳朵，以捕捉看不見的出走的聲音，其中一個直躺在地上好像已經睡著了，但仍然保持著這個姿勢。在宮殿以上，太子騎著他的馬，每個馬蹄都被一個跪著的人托著以消音。這個場景標志著太子從王宮向苦修生活的轉變，也許還應該接繼上與他的坐騎和馬夫告別的場景，正如圖29和圖38中所見的那樣。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 37"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.85(1)</idno><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.85(2)</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Scenes from the Life of the Buddha: Suddhodana sends messengers; the Search; the Farewell; the Return of Chandaka and Kanthaka</title><title lang="chi-Hant">佛傳圖斷片：淨飯王派出使者；搜尋；告別；車匿和犍陟回歸</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.31.0 cm, W. 19.5 cm (upper part)</p><p>H.21.5 cm, W. 20.0 cm (lower part)</p><p>Stein painting 85. Ch. xxvi.a. 003</p><p>Although set in a single frame with no divisions other than the landscape elements, this banner represents four episodes following Sākyamuni’s flight from his father’s palace. At the top, King Suddhodana is just visible issuing instructions to four men who stand bowing at the right. The king is seated cross-legged on a dais, behind a low draped table. His gesture, and particularly the exaggerated flouncing of the sleeves, resembles that which we shall see in the underworld kings of Stein painting 80 (Vol. 2, Pl.63). His position of authority and his anger contrast with the contrite, downcast attitudes of those who receive his instructions.</p><p>Immediately below, three horsemen, carrying pennants, are seen riding through a hilly landscape. In the same landscape, at a point where the banner is unfortunately separated, Sākyamuni is shown bidding farewell to his horse and groom. The horse, Kanthaka, kneels as in the other representations of the Farewell (Pl. 29), almost prostrate with his head stretched out along the ground. Finally, in the last episode, Kanthaka has returned to the palace: one lady examines the empty saddle, and another wipes her tears away with her sleeve. Chandaka stands off to the left since there turn of the riderless horse is the poignant centerpiece of this scene.</p><p>Both the narrative and the style find a continuation in Pl. 39, which Kiyohiko Munakata has described as follows, dating it sometime in the tenth century: “The representation follows the conventional structural systems of showing complex rock forms, the brushwork is unmistakably that of the ‘sparse’style. The strokes are those of changing width, having the emphasis of calligraphic strokes. More important is the way the strokes break the rigid outline system, not being precisely connected to each other.” (Munakata, 1965, p.46.) Dating apart, this is an excellent analysis of the style. It may be possible to show parallel developments in the figure painting of the late ninth century, for instance in banner paintings of individual Vajrapāni, where the ink strokes also break up the outlines and are not connected to each other. This banner, when found, had lost most of its accessories but still retained three streamers of bluish green silk. They had been detached and sewn on again with grass, according to the description in Serindia.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>上部斷片 高31.0釐米 寬19.5釐米</p><p>下部斷片 高21.5釐米 寬20.0釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫85.Ch.xxvi.a.003</p><p>這個場景唯一的分隔只有風景，這個幡代表了釋迦牟尼逃離他父親王宮之後的四個片斷情節。在頂部，可以看見淨飯王正在對弓腰站在右側的四個人發指示，淨飯王盤腿坐在講臺上的低矮桌子之後，他的姿勢，尤其是誇張的飾以荷葉邊裝飾的袖子，使人聯想到曾經在斯坦因幡畫80中見過的地獄之王。他的權威位置和他的憤怒與那些接受他訓斥的人的悔罪與沮喪的態度，形成了強烈的對比。</p><p>緊接其下，可以看見三個騎馬的人舉著小旗，在山坡上騎行。在同一個畫面上幡很不幸在某一點上被撕裂。太子正在與他的馬和馬夫告別，這個馬，犍陟，象其它象征告別的那樣跪著（參照圖29），頭部直躺在地上，幾乎在跪拜他。最後一個片斷，犍陟已經回到王宮，一位女士正在檢查他的空馬鞍，另一位用衣袖擦去淚水。車匿遠退到了左邊，因爲沒有騎者的歸來的馬是本場景的傷痛的最重要部分。</p><p>這個故事和形式都在圖39中找到了延續，Kiyohiko Munakata已經被描繪成跟隨者，它的時代應該在十世紀的某一時期，“表示跟隨傳統結構系統表現複雜岩石形式，畫家的筆法准確無誤地是稀疏的形式。線描強調肥瘦清晰的書法樣的技法，輪廓線只是間斷的連接”。（宗像清彥 博士論文）（注：The Rise of Ink-Wash Landscape Painting in the T’ang dynasty.Princeton,1965,p.46.）關於年代姑且不論，有關形式卻是出色的分析，很可能顯示了9世紀晚期諸像繪畫的並行發展，例如各別的金剛力士像的幡畫中，輪廓墨線也有中斷，並沒有相互連接在一起。這個幡在最初發現時，已經丟失了它的大部分配件，但是仍然保留了三個青綠色絹的幡腳。根據《西域》中的描寫，它們被拆開又被草縫上了。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 38"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.97</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Scenes from the Life of the Buddha: the Farewell; the Cutting of the Locks; the Life of Austerities</title><title lang="chi-Hant">佛傳圖：離別；剃髮；苦行</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 8th- early 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.58.5 cm, W. 18.5 cm</p><p>Stein painting 97. Ch. lv. 0012</p><p>This banner, almost perfectly preserved in spite of the fact that all its accessories are lost, is the pair to a banner in New Delhi, showing the Great Departure and King Suddhodana’s subsequent examination of the women and gaolers (Ch.lv. 0011, Stein, Desert Cathay, vol. Ⅱ, Pl.Ⅵ). The subjects of the British Museum banner follow immediately after these episodes, and represent the Farewell, the Shaving of Sākyamuni’s head, and his Life of Austerities. All these scenes are set in an orderly landscape of exceptional completeness and great beauty. The three episodes are shown in succession from the top downwards, but the landscape is course built up from the bottom, where Sākyamuni is shown in meditation on a rock, clad only in a red dhoti, his arms and upper body naked and already emaciated.</p><p>The scene is set on a green slope, with groups of small trees and steep valleys on either side. The outer contours are drawn in ink, with ink wash and orange wash helping to accent the recesses. This space is closed by a thick diagonal beyond which lies another flat plateau, edged on the left by a strong zig-zag series of banks, and overhung on the right by a cliff wholly executed in ink and ink washes. The enclosed space so defined is closed off at the rear by a triangular hill crowned with flowering trees, and on the left by the blank cartouche, originally coloured yellow, through which a white ground now appears. The symmetrical slopes of the hill open up to form a ridge leading to the top, and beyond this appear clouds.</p><p>The farewell scene at the top again takes place on a plateau, this time marked by a shallow zig-zag bank running across the picture. Sākyamuni is seated on the same rock as in the central scene, but here it is seen from the left. Chandaka and Kanthaka in front of him kneel beneath a double or triple layer of steep green tree-clad slopes, undercut by fissured cliffs. To the right, the flat ground opens out, with trees and gentle slopes, to a stretch of water, distant blue hills and piled-up clouds.</p><p>This one painting thus combines most of the possible arrangements of major landscape motifs. In particular the most vivid impression is of the mode later known to Guo Xi 郭熙 as shenyuan 深遠, “deep distance”, with a high cliff to one side allowing a view across a flat area into the far distance. It is a highly successful and uniquely Chinese formula, naturally used to great advantage to form much larger narrtive sequences in landscape on the walls of the cave chapels.</p><p>As to the date, although it is tempting to go back to the eighth century by reason of the high artistic standard and such details as the flowering trees, perhaps a safer clue is provided by a detail such as the elegantly tied and twisting white sash of the attendant divinity in the hair-cutting scene; compare the sashes of the Bodhisattvas at each side of a paradise such as in Pls. 9-8 and 9-9. A mid-ninth century date thus seems to be possible, although an earlier one should not be excluded.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，8世紀～9世紀初</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高58.5釐米 寬18.5釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫97.Ch.lv.0012</p><p>盡管其配件全部丟失了，但該幡還是被幾乎完整保存下來了，這與現存新德里的一幡是一對，表現了偉大的轉變和國王淨飯王隨後對獄卒們和婦女的審問(Ch. lv. 0011,斯坦因, Desert Cathay,vol. II, Pl. VI),大英博物館藏有一幡主題緊接其後，表現了告別、剃髮和他的苦行生活。所有這些場景都被順序安排成特別完整和雄偉美景的畫面，三個片斷從頂部一直向下，當然風景由下部開始建立。在那裏表現太子在一塊岩石上沉思，只纏一條紅色腰布，他的手臂和上半身都在裸露著，因爲饑餓瘦骨嶙峋。</p><p>這個場景安排在綠色的山坡上，坡上有大片小樹林，兩邊是陡峭的山谷。外面的輪廓用墨畫，借助墨和橙色來強調隱密處，這個空間被一條下面的躺在另一個平坦高原的粗的對角線分割開，一條非常彎曲的河岸在它的左邊，右邊有一個懸崖——完全用墨和墨水處理，圍起來的空間明示它在尾部由一個飾以開花的樹的三角形山丘來分隔，左邊的長方形題簽原來是黃色的，現在看起來已經沒有顔色了。對稱的山丘斜坡向上形成一個通向頂部的山脊，更遠處有雲彩。</p><p>頂部的告別場面又一次發生在高原，這次的標志是一個淺淺的、彎彎曲曲的河岸流涇畫面，太子坐在岩石中，處於場景的中央，但也可以從左邊看到他，車匿和犍陟跪在他的前面，下面是兩三層的陡峭的覆滿綠樹的山坡，不幸有一些裂痕,降低其價值。到了右邊，平坦的地面敞開著，有樹和緩坡，延綿的水，遠處的青色小丘和層層疊疊的雲。</p><p>這幅畫結合大多數主要山水畫，主題的可能的布局，尤其最強烈的印象是對後來郭熙産生影響的“深遠”的風格。一個很高的陡崖在一邊，使視線通過一段平坦的地帶後帶進很遠的距離，這是極高的成功的和獨特的中國風格，很自然地提高了在石窟壁畫的大型故事圖中的山水畫的效果。</p><p>至於時代，雖然由於高的藝術水平和這比如開花的樹這些細節來看，可以證明它們是8世紀的作品。然而，也許一個更安全的線索——由一個細節比如在剃髮的場景中優雅地捆劄並搓鉸的白色綬帶的隨從的神情，比較在天堂中菩薩像每一邊的綬帶（參照圖9－8、9－9）,該畫的時代大概應該定在九世紀中期，雖然也不能排除更早一些的可能。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 39"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.100</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Scenes from the Life of the Buddha: Thunderstorm; the Life of Austerities; the Bath in the Nairañjanā River</title><title lang="chi-Hant">佛傳圖：雷雨；苦行；尼連禪河水浴</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.69.0 cm, W. 19.3 cm</p><p>Stein painting 100. Ch. xxvii. 001</p><p>See also Fig. 84</p><p>The scenes in this banner appear to follow after those of Pl.37. As in that banner, several episodes of Sākyamuni’s life are shown in a sparse landscape setting. At the top, the Five Companions are shown attempting to protect themselves from a thunderstorm, represented by a storm god within a ring of drums, supported on a purple cloud spiraling out of the distance near a high peak. The scene must represent the physical hardships undergone by Sākyamuni during his period of austerities; he himself is seen in the next episode, emaciated and seated in meditation in a rocky cave, with high crags on either side in a balanced composition. In front of the cave are two stags lying at ease. As Waley has suggested, these are also there to suggest the undisturbed nature of his retreat, and his own immobility. Lastly, the lowest scene shows Sākyamuni still emaciated and naked save for a loincloth, grasping a willow branch to emerge from the Nairañjanā River, with the aid of a spirit who appears above on a cloud.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高69.0釐米 寬19.3釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫100.Ch.xxvii.001</p><p>參考Fig.84</p><p>該幡的場景緊接那些37幡中場景。在此幡中幾個生活片斷被表現在一個稀疏的山水畫設置中。在頂部，五個男人企圖在雷雨中保護自己，雷雨由一個在鼓圈裏的雷神來代表，它源於遠處螺旋形昇起的一片紫雲。這個場景代表太子在他的修行期間其身體經歷的苦難。在下一個片段可以看到他自已，瘦骨嶙峋地坐在岩洞裏冥思，很高的懸崖分布在兩邊成爲一個平衡的構圖，洞穴的前面有兩只牡鹿很自在地躺著。正如Waley所指出的，這也暗示著他隱退之後沒有打擾自然，以及他自身的紋絲不動。最後，最下部的場景表現太子仍然很瘦弱而且只裹了一塊腰布，在一個雲端之上的神靈的幫助下，抓住柳條浮出了尼連禪河。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 40"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.93</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">The Seven Treasures of the Cakravartin</title><title lang="chi-Hant">佛七寶圖</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.62.5 cm, W. 20.0 cm</p><p>Stein painting 93. Ch. xxvi.a. 004</p><p>This banner follows a format similar to those depicting events from the Life, and, as we have seen (Pl.32), the Seven Treasures are also on occasion shown alongside those events. As defined by Alice Getty (1962,p.194), the Seven Treasures are:</p><p>1, the golden wheel believed to fall from heaven on the investiture of a ‘Wheel King’, symbol of Perfection of the Law; 2, a precious stone (māni),symbol of the accomplishment of wishes; 3, a royal consort (a noblewoman) symbolizes the ‘calming caress’; 4, the best horse (a white horse), symbol of prompt success in the acquisition of the qualities of the Buddha; 5, the best elephant, as bearer of 84,000 sacred books, symbolizes the infinite propagation of the religion; 6, the best treasurer (civil offcer), who by his generosity removes poverty, and by his justice assures the well-being of people; 7, the best leader (military chief), who with his sword of wisdom repels the enemies.</p><p>As can be seen from the paintings, the content as the order may vary slightly. Here, as in the Pelliot painting (Bannières, No.6), the Treasurer is replaced by a rectangular coffer; in Pl.32 both the Treasurer and the Coffer are shown, and the precious jewel is not separately represented, so that the total is still seven. It almost seems that the Chinese predilection for symmetry is the decisive factor, especially in the Pelliot painting where the Wheel is flanked by the Consort and the General, then by the Elephant and the Horse, and finally by the Coffer and the Jewel.</p><p>seven blank cartouches accompany the treasures, which are set in a minimal landscape. The style is quite similar to that of Pls.36, 37 and 39.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代（9世紀）</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高62.5釐米 寬20.0釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫93.Ch.xxxvi.a.004</p><p>此幡與我們所見的圖32中的那些描寫事件的幡採用相似的形式。七寶也不時出現在那些事件的旁邊，根據Alice Getty的定義(1962,p.194)，七寶是：</p><p>1．金輪寶，被認爲是從天堂裏“輪王”授權儀式上墜落下來的，象征著法律的完美。</p><p>2．神珠寶，象征著完成願望。</p><p>3．玉女寶（以貴婦人形象表示），象徵寧靜的愛撫。</p><p>4．白馬寶，代表快速成佛。</p><p>5．白象寶，因爲馱著84000冊宗教書籍，象征著無窮的宗教傳播。</p><p>6．主藏臣寶（以文官形象出現），以他的慷慨消除貧困，用他的公正確保人們的幸福平安。</p><p>7．主兵臣寶（以將軍形象出現），用他的智慧之劍擊退敵人。</p><p>象畫中可以看見的那樣，內容和順序可能會有稍微的變化。這裏，象在伯希和畫中一樣，主藏臣寶被換成了一個矩形箱子。另外，圖32中文官和矩形箱子同時出現，並且珍貴的珠寶不是單獨的表現，所以總數仍然是七。好像中國人對對稱的偏好是決定性因素，尤其是在伯希和畫中，那裏輪子被放在武將（主兵臣寶）和貴婦人（玉女寶）的側邊，接著是白馬寶和象寶，最後是矩形箱子和珠寶。</p><p>七個題箋伴隨著珠寶，都没有文字。這些珠寶放置在非常粗略的山水畫中。這種風格與圖36、39的幡近似。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 41"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.92</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Scenes from the Life of the Buddha: Suddhodana dispatching a messenger; the Search; the Return of the messenger</title><title lang="chi-Hant">佛傳圖：淨飯王派遣使者；尋找；信使返回</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.77.5 cm, W. 19.0 cm</p><p>Stein painting 92. Ch. xx. 008</p><p>As Aki Uyeno has pointed out (1970,p.12), the floral border on the triangular headpiece, actually a continuation of the same silk as the main scenes, corresponds with that of Pl.31.Like that painting, this one originally was furnished with brown silk streamers, now separately preserved. The colouring of the landscape-dividing motifs, also, suggests that this painting formed part of the same series as Pls. 31 and 33, and that the subject is again the life of the prince. In this cave the top scene represents Sākyamuni’s father, Suddhodana, sending out a messenger to find his son. In the centre the messenger is seen galloping through the hills on his quest, reporting back empty-handed below. This last scene also features musicians to represent some of the pleasures of palace life, and an enclosed garden with lotus tank, bamboo and pavilion (with an unidentified object, perhaps a casket or a dais, inside) to represent its amenities.</p><p>Throughout the painting the white pigment has suffered considerable loss, but otherwise the colours are strong and well preserved.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高77.5釐米 寬19.0釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫92.Ch.xx.008</p><p>正如Aki Uyeno 指出的那樣(1970,p.12)，三角形幡頭上的花邊，事實上就是主要場景的同一絹的延續。與圖31的幡一樣，就像圖畫中的一樣，這個最先飾有棕色絲帶，現在被單獨存放著。這個山水畫分割主題的顔色，暗示了這畫構成了象圖31、33同屬一個系統，而且這個主題又是王子生活的一部分。這個洞的頂部場景代表釋迦牟尼的父親淨飯王派出使者尋找他的兒子，在中間場景可以看見使者在山丘上到處急馳,不斷尋找，下面是使者空手而歸彙報情況。最後一個場景仍然以樂師爲特征表現宮廷生活的歡愉，一個有蓮花池的院子，竹和亭子(內有不明物，也許是小箱或者講臺)以表現它的環境。</p><p>通觀整體畫面，白色顔料已經脫落很多，但其他色彩保存良好。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 42"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.136</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san">Bodhisattva with cintāmani</title><title lang="chi-Hant">菩薩像</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, late 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.71.0 cm, W. 17.5 cm</p><p>Stein painting 136. Ch. lv. 0026</p><p>See also Fig. 87</p><p>Numerous Bodhisattvas, some differing only in detail, are preserved in both the Stein and the Pelliot collections. As they hung from a triangular headpiece, they could twist and turn, to be seen from either side. The close similarities between such figures have led to the suggestion that they may have been traced from the same original. In some cases paper stencils must have been used: one actually found at Dunhuang and now in New Delhi is described as being of a Bodhisattva, with all the details drawn in, leaving a border at the edge, and the main parts then cut out (Stein Serindia, Ch. 00425,p.999). Such a stencil was clearly quite different from the pricked pounces preserved in the British Museum (Vol.2, Pls. 78-80) and was probably more suitable for transferring a design to silk.</p><p>The present painting is very close to Stein paintings 122 and 125* (Fig. 94 and Pl.43). The chief impression gained from it is that of the opaque, bright colours, and of the continuous black ink outlines of the drapery. Especially prominent is the white of the narrow sacrificial thread and of the knotted sash, twisting and turning over the petals of the lotus pedestal. The outlines are precise and unbroken. By the use of contrasting colours, e.g., red for the outer border of the sleeves and green for its lining, they tend to divide the drapery into alternate narrow strips of colour, a mannerism that will be carried even further in the wall paintings of the Song and Yuan, for example in the fourteenth-century paintings of the Yonglegong 永樂宮. The figure of the Bodhisattva is heavy and majestic. The Samantabhadra of Pl.12 is altogether more approachable, partly as a result of its softer outlines, partly because of its more restricted use of colour and of line that is more descriptive of the underlying form than assertive of a prescribed pattern. A period of as much as a century may lie between the execution of the Mañjusrī and that of the present Bodhisattva and its companions.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀末</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高71.0釐米 寬17.5釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫136.Ch.lv.0026</p><p>參考Fig.87</p><p>斯坦因和伯希和的收藏中保存了很多菩薩像，只是細節上有一些差異，當它們從一個三角形的幡頭垂下來，可以旋轉和翻動，兩面的內容都可以看見，這種極大的相似性在這樣的肖像之間暗示著他們原先的出處是一致的，在一些場合中，一定是使用了紙印模：一個在敦煌發現的，現藏新德里，被描寫成的菩薩所有的細節都畫出來，在邊上留了一條邊界，其主要部分被切掉了(斯坦因,《西域》,Ch. 00425,p.999)。這樣的印模很明顯與大英博物館收藏的pricked pounces有很大區別，更適合用於把圖案印在絲綢上。</p><p>現在的畫非常接近斯坦因的畫122和125(Fig.94、圖43)，從中得到的主要印象是不透明的，明亮的顔色，以及布料的連續的黑色墨外沿線，尤其突出的是白色的很窄的，作爲奉獻的絲線和打結的綬帶，紐結和翻轉在蓮花座的花瓣上，外沿線是精確的和連續的，運用對比的顔色，例如衣袖外邊沿線用紅色，衣袖本身用綠色，他們企圖把布料分成顔色變化的窄條，這種特殊的風格到了宋元的壁畫就更加明顯，例如14世紀永樂宮的繪畫，菩薩像厚重而且宏大。而圖12的普賢菩薩像卻容易親近的多，一部分是因爲它的輪廓不那麽鮮明，一部分是由於它使用了更少的色彩和線條，比僵化的規定形式更加靈活，由於沒有使用固定的模式，使他的身體更清楚地表現出來。那幅普賢菩薩像和本圖的菩薩像等之間，約有一個世紀的間隔。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 43"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.125*</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Bodhisattva with censer</title><title lang="chi-Hant">手持香爐的菩薩像</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, late 9 th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.68.2 cm, W. 19.0 cm</p><p>Stein painting 125*. Ch. i. 005</p><p>In this painting, particularly in the crimson V-shaped stole with its alternating half-florets of green and white. The effect was added to, though not in any systematic fashion, by the headpiece, now kept separately, part of which is of brilliant red silk damask.</p><p>This banner is one of those that provide clear evidence for the use of stencils, since the Bodhisattva is identical, but in reversed pose, to that in Fig. 94. No doubt the fact that the outlines were obtained in this manner partly accounts for their unwavering precision. The figure of the Bodhisattva stands firmly; but the tassels of the canopy above are agitated in a manner more usually reserved to emphasise the sideways movement of Bodhisattvas such as Mañjusrī and Samantabhadra. Unusually also, the cartouche is here filled with a floral spray in yellow. Along with paintings such as the Bodhisattva of Pl.56, this banner must date from the later part of the ninth century.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀末</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高68.2釐米 寬19.0釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫125*.Ch.i.005</p><p>唐代佛教畫師在明亮裝飾效果方面的興趣，在這幅畫中立即變得明顯起來，尤其是交替出現綠色和白色半圓形花紋的赤紅色V字形天衣。現在被單獨存放的幡頭,其中一部分就是明亮的紅色綿緞製成的。</p><p>此幡是那些爲運用印模提供明顯證據的幡畫的其中一個，因爲這個菩薩像與Fig.94的菩薩完全相同，只是上下顛倒了。毫無疑問用這種方法獲得的形狀部分地說明瞭它們毫無偏差的精確。菩薩像穩穩地立著，但華蓋上面的穗被吹動，在某種意義上更多地常常用于强調菩薩的左右運動，比如文殊菩薩和普賢菩薩。長方形題簽運用了較罕見的手法---用黃色花的螺旋來填充背景，對照圖56那樣的菩薩像的描繪手法，這個幡一定屬於9世紀後半期的作品。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 44"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.125</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san-Latn">Ksitigarbha</title><title lang="chi-Hant">地藏菩薩像</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.58.0 cm, W. 18.5 cm</p><p>Stein painting 125. Ch. i. 003</p><p>See also Figs. 88, 90</p><p>Those Bodhisattvas already examined are not easily identifiable, due to the absence of distinguishing attributes. Except for the lack of a “parent” figure in the headdress, they might easily be identified as Avalokitesvaras. Only one Bodhisattva, however, wears the patched robe and shaven head of a monk, namely, Ksitigarbha. In this painting he is identified in the accompanying cartouche: “Praise to Ksitigarbha Bodhisattva.”</p><p>Ksitigarbha, although hard to trace in Indian mythology, became extremely popular in China, as the many depictions of him among the Dunhuang banners testify (several from the Pelliot collection as well as those shown here from the Stein collection). He is represented with closely shaven head, as here, or as the patron of travelers, with a hood covering the head, as in some of the tenth-century examples. Youngsook Pak has analysed the significance of the Ksitigarbha cult in her inaugural dissertation (1981) for the University of Heidelberg. According to her, numerous Dunhuang manuscripts exist of the extremely short Dicang pusa jing 地藏菩薩經, which describes Dicang or Ksitigarbha looking down on those suffering in purgatory, and instructs that those who write out his sutra or recite his name will be reborn in the Western Paradise. Thus Ksitigarbha, no less than Avalokitesvara, can be seen to be closely connected with the cult of Amitābha.</p><p>It should be noted here that the cartouche was accidentally inscribed on the back of the painting, so that the characters appear in reverse and are partially obscured by the opaque colour of the cartouche. The outlines of the figure are, on the other hand, crisp and clear, and comparison with Pl. 45 shows that this is the front of the painting, with the kasāya hanging from the Bodhisattva’s own left shoulder.</p><p>The headpiece of this banner is preserved with it. An ancient repair using large overcast stitches is visible at the height of the canopy about the Bodhisattva’s head. The centre of the headpiece is of a silk dyed with flowers in pink and green. On the reverse the headpiece was lined with plain sage-green silk. The hanging loop inscribed with a character hua 華 and parts of the dark blue side streamers are also preserved separately.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高58.0釐米 寬18.5釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫125.Ch.i.003</p><p>參考Figs.88,90</p><p>上述菩薩不容易被區分，如果不具備足夠的識別特徵，就很難斷定具體是哪一位菩薩。假設寶冠上配有化佛時，他就很容易被認定是觀世音菩薩。只有一個菩薩很容易被識別，身著由很多布片縫成的衲衣，頭部如僧侶般剃髮的像，無疑就是地藏菩薩。</p><p>雖然在印度神話中很難找到地藏菩薩的蹤迹，他在中國卻非常有名，正如一些敦煌幡畫中對他的描寫所證明的(一些來自伯希和收藏，而且斯坦因的收藏中也有顯示)，在這裏他表現爲剃著頭作爲旅行者的神，頭上戴著兜帽，就像一些十世紀的例子，朴英淑女士在海德堡大學的博士論文中(1981)，分析了地藏菩薩的意義。根據她的分析，很多敦煌手稿中存在簡短的《地藏菩薩經》，它描寫地藏菩薩俯視那些在煉獄中受難的人們，並且指示那些抄寫《地藏菩薩經》、誦讀他的名字的人，將會轉生到西方淨土。這樣，可見地藏菩薩與觀音菩薩一樣，都與阿彌陀信仰緊密結合。</p><p>應該在這裏指出長方形題簽也會偶爾被繪在幡畫的背面，所以文字出現了顛倒，並且因爲題簽不透明而部分變得很不清晰。另一方面畫像的外形是明快而清晰的，與幡45相比較表現出這是畫的正面，有袈裟從菩薩左肩垂下來等圖案的一面是幡的正面。</p><p>幡頭也一起保存下來了，菩薩頭部的華蓋上有舊時的密密的大的針腳的丁，華蓋中心是用花染成粉色或綠色的絹，相反的幡頭是樸素的灰綠色的絹。吊環上記有“華”字，而深蓝色幡尾已經脫落並且單獨保存著。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 45"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.118</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san-Latn">Ksitigarbha</title><title lang="chi-Hant">地藏菩薩像</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.63.7 cm, W. 17.0 cm</p><p>Stein painting 118. Ch. lxi.004</p><p>The Bodhisattva, his patched robe covering both shoulders, turns towards the right, his hands forming almost the identical gesture of Fig. 88, but holding a sprinkler vase. The shaven parts of the head, chin and upper lip are blue. The features are altogether Chinese, and convey an impression of benevolence and compassion through the gentleness of the curves. The hands are partly outlined in red. Lines of small white dots across the right shoulder and falling from the left seem to mark the passage of a narrow stole which, however, does not obscure the brightly coloured patches with their wavy ink lines, reminiscent of the moiré patterns formed when light passes through two layers of textile. In some areas the silk seems to be left without any colour, as in the background to another painting of Ksitigarbha, holding a cintāmani and altogether more robust, wearing an ordinary robe in strong contrasts of green and red and pale blue (Fig. 93). This last painting also outlines parts of the hands in red, and despite their outward differences, the two must be close in date, probably towards the end of the ninth century.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高63.7釐米 寬17.0釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫118.Ch.lxi.004</p><p>此菩薩將衲衣披在兩肩上，面向右前方，雙手的姿勢幾乎與Fig.88的相同，只是多了一個淨瓶。剃了髮的頭，下顎和上唇塗了藍色，相貌特征完完全全是中國人，以柔和的曲線傳達出慈悲和哀憐的神情。雙手的部分輪廓線用紅色。從右肩斜向下到左肩有一條由白色小點組成的線，好像記錄了這段窄的綬帶，鮮豔的顔色搭配他們墨色的波浪線，無論如何都是明顯的，暗示當光線透過兩層織物時形成了雲紋綢(moiré patterns)，某些局部地方絹上已經看不出任何顔色了，就象另一個地藏菩薩的背景——他手持寶珠，更加健壯魁偉，穿著普通的紅、綠、淺藍強烈對比的袈裟。最後一幅畫的手的部分的輪廓線仍然使用紅色，盡管外表有區別，但他們的時代非常接近，很可能都是9世紀晚期的作品。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 46"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.101</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san-Latn">Bodhisattva</title><title lang="chi-Hant">菩薩像</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, early 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.44.5 cm, W. 14.5 cm</p><p>Stein painting 101. Ch. lvi.008</p><p>This plate and the following two show some of a series of ten banners (the remainder in New Delhi, several illustrated in Matsumoto, 1937, Pls. 201-02) with features that obviously represent some of the non-Chinese characters of the art of Dunhuang, and may in fact relate to the art of Khotan or of Western Tibet.</p><p>All of these banners share certain characteristics: the Bodhisattvas stand with feet close together, the legs almost straight with no articulation at the knee. The upper half of the body is naked save for a shawl with floral motifs (in one of them it has been knotted around the thighs instead). All wear a tightly wrapped dhoti with the end falling from the waist to fill a narrow space between the legs. They wear a three-pronged golden tiara, with elongated halo behind and ring-lets of black hair falling behind the ears and over the shoulder, as in some of the other figures associated with the Tibetan period at Dunhuang. Some have brief inscriptions in Tibetan.</p><p>Stein and Waley both drew attention to similarities with the miniatures of a Nepalese manuscript of the eleventh century at Cambridge (Foucher, 1900-05, Pls. Ⅳ-Ⅵ) owing its origins to the eighth-and ninth-century Buddhist art of Bengal. A more recent and convincing case has been made, however, by Gerd Gropp (1974, p.94) whose reconstruction of paintings from Balawaste has allowed him to attribute this group to the art of Khotan. He draws particular attention to the clumsy execution of the feet and legs, as typical also of the Bodhisattvas with naked upper torso from Balawaste. The striped clothing also exhibits some of the same textile patterns. In his view, the paintings found at Dunhuang must be somewhat later than those at Balawaste (dating from the sixth century onwards), and the rosettes along the top edge of Pl.48 need to be compared with those found in Temple 9 at Bezeklik, of the eighth to ninth centuries A.D.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀初</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高44.5釐米 寬14.5釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫101.Ch.lvi.008</p><p>此畫和接下來的兩個圖表現了十個幡的系列中的一部分，其餘的在新德里，其中幾件收錄於松本榮一氏(1937,圖201-02)很明顯這些不是中國特色的敦煌藝術，事實上可能與于闐或者吐蕃藝術有關係。</p><p>所有幡畫具有共同特徵：菩薩雙腳並攏站立，腳幾乎是筆直的，看不出膝關節。上半身裸露，只披了稍加花紋的天衣（其中一個只是在大腿上打結來代替天衣）。全都穿了裹得很緊的腰布，腰部的末端從腰部垂下位於兩腿之間的部分，他們像吐蕃時期敦煌畫中常見的諸像一樣，戴著金色通天冠，黑色卷髮從耳後垂到肩上，頭後面的光環向四週發著光。一些地方可見吐蕃文的短句。</p><p>斯坦因和Waley都注意到劍橋大學藏的尼泊爾古文書中的小型畫像與這些菩薩像的相似性，並把它們的起源歸結於8、9世紀孟加拉地區的佛教藝術。Gerd Gropp (1974,p.94) 還找到了一個更近、更有說服力的證據，他重親恢復了Balawaste的畫之後認爲這些畫就是于闐藝術，它尤其關注對腳和腿部的笨拙處理，這種方法在Balawaste的赤裸著上身的菩薩像中也很常見。該畫的條紋布料也顯示了一些在那些紡織品中的共同圖案。根據他的觀點，敦煌發現的畫無論如何一定晚於Balawaste的畫(其時代是六世紀以前的)，而圖48頂部邊上的玫瑰花飾需要與那些在伯孜克里克第9窟發現的成於公元8、9世紀的花紋作比較。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 47"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.102</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Bodhisattva with lotus (Padmapāni?)</title><title lang="chi-Hant">菩薩像（莲华手菩萨？）</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, early 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.51.0 cm, W. 14.0 cm</p><p>Stein painting 102. Ch. lvi.003</p><p>This Bodhisattva follows the same canon of proportions as the one just discussed, tall and slender but with a slightly thick-set appearance nonetheless because of the lack of articulation, and wearing the same closely wrapped dhoti and flowered stole. The most noticeable Central Asian feature is the shape of the face, which like another figure from Qizil described by Mario Bussagli, obeys “the Indian principles of foreshortening laid down in the handbooks on wall painting, in particular in the principle of ksayavrddhi, or ‘increase and decrease’. The face of the figure is turned to the left; the receding parts of the face are contracted, the more visible parts enlarged, the former obeying the law of ksaya, the latter that of vrddhi. The two parts [are] divided by a line passing through the ridge of the nose and the tip of the chin (these being salient features and therefore highlighted).” (Bussagli, 1963,p. 32.) The same principle can be seen at work in the main Bodhisattvas attendant upon Bhaisajyaguru in Pl.16-2, which is dated A.D. 836.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀初</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高51.0釐米 寬14.0釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫102.Ch.lvi.003</p><p>此菩薩像描繪的與上圖菩薩像比例相同，仍然沒有顯示膝關節，緊緊纏著腰布，著花紋樣的天衣。身體細高，格調稍顯稠密。臉部表現極具顯著的中亞特徵。Mario Bussagli以下講述有關克孜爾出土像时所指出的恰與之符合：“以壁畫作模本，可辨認出是以增減法則做基礎的印度式透視法。此像轉向左方的臉部，向外的一面大，而向裏的一側則繪的狹小，遵從了前者是‘增’後者是‘減’的法則。這兩個部分被鼻梁和下顎尖的連接線隔開，爲了更加明顯使用了高光”（參照Painting of Central Asia p.32）。依照與此相似規則的繪畫，還有紀年爲836年的圖16的藥師脅侍菩薩（參照圖16－2）。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 48"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.103</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san-Latn">Bodhisattva Vajrapāni</title><title lang="chi-Hant">金剛菩薩像</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, early 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.55.0 cm, W. 14.5 cm</p><p>Stein painting 103. Ch. lvi.002</p><p>This banner is the most impressive of the three (Pls. 46-48). The Bodhisattva, holding a small vajra in his right hand, faces the spectator squarely. The left hand, palm outwards, seems to caress one of the curving lotus stems at his side. Above him, instead of the hanging textile drape of the other banners, is a splendid floral border. His striped dhoti is smoothly wrapped around each leg, and a white-flowered scarf is tied in a generous knot on the right hip. The colour of his body is a greenish bronze. His eyes, quite horizontal, are almond-shaped, bright white with black pupils. This feature above all gives the figure its Indianizing appearance, and one might make the comparison with bronze figures with the eyes inlaid in silver (see, for instance, the eighth-century bronze Buddha from Phyang monastery, Ladakh, reproduced in Singh, 1968,p.53). Bright white is also used for the yajñopavīta, or sacrificial thread worn by the Bodhisattva-in sculpture these too on occasion may have been inlaid in silver. Such features support the theory that this group of paintings may be related to the art of Khotan.</p><p>All three of these banners and presumably those in New Delhi from the same group differ in construction from the rest of the Dunhuang banners. They are on a grey silk with a balanced close weave, while the majority of the paintings are on a more open silk, with warp threads running in pairs. They are also much narrower than the usual width of the other banners, and both edges are hemmed with a strip of silk binding, instead of being merely painted with a dark brown pigment as is commonly seen. Finally, all three of these banners show a selvedge on the lower end. These facts seem to imply a different origin for the silk itself, and a different tradition of making the banners, the figures being at a right angle to the warp instead of in line with it. It does therefore seem possible, from technical as well as stylistic evidence, that these paintings were executed elsewhere and brought to Dunhuang, rather than being executed there under the influence of models from further west. It is very noticeable that none of the banners (including the group in New Delhi) has a cartouche for characters, even those that are in fact inscribed in Tibetan.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀初</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高55.0釐米 寬14.5釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫103.Ch.lvi.002</p><p>此幡是同一系列的三件（圖46～48）中給人印象最深的作品。右手上放著小形的金剛杵，面向正前方。左手掌向前，手指執旁邊的蓮華莖。上方不像其他幡的幕，而是描繪著精美花紋的邊飾。從腰到腳的部分順滑的纏繞著細軟的布，身著布滿小花紋的天衣，鬆軟的繋在腰的右方。身軀被塗成青銅色，眼睛扁長呈杏仁形，純白眼底點著黑瞳。這種眼睛的表現方式更是印度式，可以與眼部嵌銀的金銅像（如，參照M.Singh;Himalayan Art.London,1968.p.53收錄的Phyang寺的8世紀金銅像）做比較。而且不僅是眼部，有的菩薩裝飾帶也是白色的，在雕刻作品中用嵌銀來表現那些部分也有很多例子。這種特徵成爲這一連貫的繪畫與和闐美術有關聯的有力證據。</p><p>在新德里國立博物館的同一系列的幡恐怕也是那樣的，這三件幡的製作不同于敦煌其他幡。這三件採用經緯均勻質地細密的鼠灰色絹，而其他大部分的幡則採用只有兩根經線質地粗糙的絹。絹幅遠比其他幡狹窄。幡兩端的邊兒通常只是用黑褐色顔料繪出，而這三件則用細絹布縫的。而且此三件幡的任何一件，布的織邊在畫的下端。以上的不同點說明，不僅絹的生産地不同，幡的製作習慣也不同，菩薩像不是沿著經線，而是和經線成直角。因此，無論風格上還是技法上，與其說這三件幡是在敦煌受西方影響時製作的，還不如說在其他某一地方製作，帶到敦煌更爲妥當。這些一連竄的幡中（包括收藏在新德里國立博物館的），雖然有吐蕃文的記錄，但無一例有長方形題箋，這也是值得注意的。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 49"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.104</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san-Latn">Avalokitesvara</title><title lang="chi-Hant">觀世音菩薩像</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, early 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.65.0 cm, W. 18.0 cm</p><p>Stein painting 104. Ch. xlvi.001</p><p>This painting and Stein painting 113 (Fig. 97) also display strong Indian influence, particularly in the facial features and in the stance of the figures. As Stein wrote of the superior version of this banner, now in New Delhi (Serindia, Pl. LXXⅧ): “whole figure expressive of dignity, scorn, and rapid movement, drapery following sweeping lines of the limbs.” (Ibid., p. 1008.)</p><p>The face is seen in profile, but the body is in a strong contrapposto, seen in three-quarter view from the back, the hips thrust forward and the shoulders leaning back. Every part of the figure seems to be involved in these rhythms: the left hand is bent back and twisted outwards; the right, which holds a lotus bud, is also twisted as though to support the ornament enclosing the chignon of hair, and even the ear is exaggeratedly bent.</p><p>Despite the markedly Indian appearance, the execution is probably Chinese. Note in particular the stylized orange and red folds of the skirt, and the scarf, although it was once blue and not white as in Bodhisattvas of Chinese type such as Pl. 56, describes similar twists and turns as it falls to the ground by the lotus pedestal. Finally the cartouche, although blank, is a characteristically Chinese touch.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀末</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高65.0釐米 寬18.0釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫104.Ch.xlvi.001</p><p>此像和Fig.97的菩薩，特別是面貌和身體的姿態，明顯受到印度的影響。新德里國立博物館保存有此種畫像的更好的作品（參照《西域》圖78.Ch.i.002( 原為LXXVIII)）。關於新德里的作品，斯坦因記述“整體威嚴氣派，衣物順著腿的行動表现的褶子，使人感到敏捷的動作。”（《西域》p.1008）。</p><p>臉是側向，身體卻大大傾斜扭曲，露出脊背，臀部向前突出，肩則後提。身體的所有部分都好像配合著此規律，左手向後擰伸到下方，右手掌上放著蓮蕾，舉在後上方，像是托著束髮的髮飾。另外，耳朵也誇張地折曲。</p><p>雖然此像具有印度風格，但顯然是在中國製作的作品。特別要注意的是，衣裳上加入橙色和紅色的格式化褶子。天衣是青色的，而不是圖56中國式菩薩所穿的白色天衣，兩位菩薩天衣彎轉扭曲的形式非常接近，且都順著蓮座垂到地面。而空白的長方形題箋，也是中國式的。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 50"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.124</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san-Latn">Avalokitesvara</title><title lang="chi-Hant">觀世音菩薩像</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, late 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.56.5 cm, W. 16.5 cm</p><p>Stein painting 124. Ch. 00113</p><p>See also Fig.89</p><p>This Bodhisattva exhibits certain resemblances with Pls. 46-48, already discussed as perhaps emanating from the Khotan region. The similarities are in the proportions-rather straight legs, large or clumsy feet, and arms long in relation to the height-and also in the way the end of the dhoti hangs straight down between the legs. The figure seems altogether too large for the space available (even the halo is obscured by the striped border above). Nevertheless other characteristics such as the extensive use of ink, both for the under-drawing in the figure and for the final outlines of the drapery, suggest a Chinese hand.</p><p>Some minor features point to a date in the second half of the ninth century. The ink line separating the lips is slightly swollen at each end, but with the tip of the brush re-emerging; and over the shoulders, behind the hair, an orangered shawl makes an arbitrary double loop on either side. This kind of loop, with streamers reaching to the elbow, can be seen clearly in a painting dated A.D.864 (Pl. 23-3), but evidently it was already well established by then. It may have been intended to show the bow tied centrally at the nape of the neck (Pl. 55).</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀末</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高56.5釐米 寬16.5釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫124.Ch.00113</p><p>參考Fig.89</p><p>此菩薩原先的講述是從和闐地方帶回的作品，與圖46-48的菩薩像有相似點。體型比例的相似點是：腿線大致筆直，腳龐大粗笨，与身高相比，兩臂過長這種體型特徵，而且腰布的端頭垂落于兩腳間。像的描繪占滿空間，只是在此畫中似乎過於龐大（頭光和上方的邊飾重疊在一起）。然而，在其他方面，如像的底线和衣紋的勾勒均頻繁使用墨線等，顯示了中國的製作特徵。</p><p>多處細部的表現具有9世紀後半期的特徵。拉出唇線的墨線兩端稍微脹粗，其下方用筆尖拉出短細線。兩肩的頭髮背後，有用橙紅色描出一直垂到肘的隨意環繞的披肩等。這種裝飾與紀年爲864年的圖23《四觀音文殊普賢圖》的四觀音像（參照圖23－1，23－3）趣味同樣，所以可認爲此時已經確立了這種表現形式，圖55中的菩薩從脖頸垂下的蝴蝶結趣味也一致。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 51"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.130</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san-Latn">Avalokitesvara</title><title lang="chi-Hant">觀世音菩薩像</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.45.0 cm, W. 18.0 cm</p><p>Stein painting 130. Ch. lv.0032</p><p>At first glance this painting appears to have much in common with the last (Pl. 50). Waley’s comment was: “This is one of the few paintings in the collection which seems to be the product of an artist, not a mere workman. The colouring is particularly successful.” We can indeed see how the colour shading and highlighting is accurately and carefully applied, and highlighting is accurately and carefully applied, and features such as the eyebrows were originally green within their sharp ink outlines. The hair is done in long blue strokes framing the shoulders on either side and reinforced by ink lines closer to the neck. The hands, initially drawn in ink, are outlined in red and also have colour shading and highlighting. Rich dark blue is used for the edges of the stole and the lower border of the dhoti, whose end falls in distinctive curves to below the feet. The legs marked by the symmetrical curves of the robe, are straight, and the feet large, as in Pls. 46-48, but by no means clumsy or ill-proportioned. I hesitate to venture a possible date for the painting: the high quality invites an early date, but the smooth ellipse of the face and the matching curves of the torso point to the mid-ninth century.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高46.0釐米 寬18.0釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫130.Ch.lv.0032</p><p>乍一看，此畫有許多與上一圖觀世音菩薩像相同的要素。據Waley講，“這是斯坦因搜集的敦煌畫中不單是工匠，而是由正式的畫家製作出來的極少數作品之一。其色彩非常出色。”事實上，如果細細觀察則發現，對色澤的明暗或高光的使用精確而仔細，尖尖的眉毛的墨綫輪廓線間加了綠色。頭髮是青色，沿著兩肩長長垂下，脖頸附近加了墨線以突出力度。而手是先用墨作底線，賦彩後再用紅色勾勒，並加入色暈和高光。天衣和腰布下端的邊緣使用藏藍色，腰布的底端描出獨特曲線，下垂至腳間。兩腿上，裳的褶子左右對稱，和彩色圖版第46～48圖的諸像一樣，儘管腿線筆直兩腳巨大，但完全察覺不出粗笨或者比例不當。判定此畫的年代稍有困難，良好的質量顯示出它可能年代較早，但卵形的臉和均衡的上半身曲線等，符合9世紀中葉作品的特點。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 52"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.137</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san-Latn">Mañjusrī</title><title lang="chi-Hant">文殊菩薩像</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.39.5 cm, W. 14.5 cm</p><p>Stein painting 137. Ch. xxvi.a.007</p><p>According to Jin Weinuo (personal communication), this painting can be dated by such features as the disposition of the feet and the sword, characteristic of Esoteric Buddhism, to the period of Tibetan domination at Dunhuang. Its affinities with the group of banners already described and thought to be related to the art of Khotan (Pls. 46-48) are evident. The Bodhisattva wears a similar kind of three-pointed tiara, with a high chignon of hair and thick ringlets falling on the shoulders. The sacrificial thread is heavily dotted with opaque white. In the construction the warp threads run across the banner instead of vertically. Nevertheless, unlike the banners of Pls. 46-48, the weave is the more open one typical of most of the Chinese paintings from Dunhuang, with the warp threads grouped in pairs. Similarly, some elements in the presentation appear close to the banners in Chinese style: the presence of an unfilled cartouche, the borders painted brown, and the lozenge border with individual flowers. A similar painting of Mañjusrī is New Delhi (Waley, 1931, p.298).</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高39.5釐米 寬14.5釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫137.Ch.xxvi.a.007</p><p>據金維諾先生個人的觀點（私下交流），根據腳的位置以及具有密教特色的劍的描繪等來看，此像是吐蕃佔領時期的敦煌繪畫。也明顯與前述與于闐美術有關連的一組幡畫（圖46-48）類似。文殊菩薩頭戴類似通天冠的冠，發結高高聳起，濃厚的卷髮垂落在兩肩上。瓔珞上嵌滿密密麻麻的白點。本畫絹布使用的經線為橫向而非縱向，但質地與圖46-48不同，基本與以敦煌的中國式繪畫的幡相同，織紋粗大，使用兩股經線。同樣，空的長方形榜題、焦茶色的邊緣、下端菱形中各配一朵花的邊飾等，表現方法的若干因素，極接近中國風格的幡。</p><p>類似的文殊菩薩像在新德里國立博物館也有收藏（參照Waley《敦煌畫目錄》298頁）。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 53"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.109*</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san-Latn">Bodhisattva (Ratnapāni?)</title><title lang="chi-Hant">菩薩像（宝手菩萨？）</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.41.0 cm, W. 18.5 cm</p><p>Stein painting 109*. Ch. lv.007</p><p>See also Fig.100</p><p>This painting and Fig.98 are from the same hand, and display some “Indian” characteristics although it seems likely that they were executed at Dunhuang. The Bodhisattva, holding a cintāmani in both hands, is of a golden colour, visible in the face, torso and through the transparent covering with small floral motifs around the legs. His companion in Fig.98 is coloured red in the same manner. Both have long sacrificial threads originally decorated with triple rows of bright white dots, and scarves falling in symmetrical folds on either side and filling the space between the legs. All these features seem to bespeak influence from the West. Figure 99 is also of this group.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高41.0釐米 寬18.5釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫 109.Ch.lv.007</p><p>參考Fig.100</p><p>此圖和Fig.98屬同一畫群，雖然看起來是在敦煌製作的，但表現出一些印度的特徵。菩薩兩手捧著火焰寶珠，臉和上半身施用金彩，透明的撒花的衣料之下的腿部也有金彩。與此相應的Fig.98中的像也是同樣的表現手法，只是身體的色彩是紅的。兩像的瓔珞上均有三行白點，綬帶有左右相稱的褶子垂在兩腿間。這些表現可能是受西方的影響。Fig.99的《觀世音菩薩像》也屬這一畫群。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 54"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.141</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san-Latn">Mañjusrī</title><title lang="chi-Hant">文殊菩薩像</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.66.0 cm, W. 24.8 cm</p><p>Stein painting 141. Ch. 0036</p><p>As Arthur Waley wrote in his Catalogue (p. 153), this painting is “completely Indian in style”, so much so that he both suggested that the origin of the karashishi, or “Chinese lion”, should be sought in India rather than China, and also looked for a possible Indian alternative to Mañjusrī as the Bodhisattva. Comparison, however, with another banner in the Pelliot collection shows how intimately the Chinese and Indian modes were connected at Dunhuang in the ninth century. The banner in question shows Manjusri riding on a lion (Bannières, No.126). The lion is portrayed in very similar fashion in both paintings, the main difference being that in the Pelliot painting he does not have an attendant and his mane is green only and not of several colours. It is the Bodhisattva figures alone who present a total contrast, the one in Paris being Chinese in type, with a rather heavy figure largely concealed by ample draperies, as opposed to the almost sultry Bodhisattva with diaphanous purple garments and abundant jewelry of the Stein painting.</p><p>These similarities and differences confirm what we have already seen in paintings such as Pl.16, namely that Indian and Chinese modes of depiction, particularly for figures such as those of the Bodhisattvas, flourished side by side at Dunhuang and may even have been executed by the same painters, following different models.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高66.0釐米 寬24.8釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫141.Ch.0036</p><p>如Waley在《敦煌畫目錄》（153頁）中所述，“該繪畫風格完全是印度式”，由於此種印象太突出，他把本是唐獅子的起源追溯到印度。但是，比較伯希和收集品中所藏的幡，則很清楚地看到，9世紀的敦煌，是中國和印度兩種風格緊密結合的。用於比較的幡，描繪的是乘獅子的文殊（參照伯希和圖錄《敦煌的幡和繪畫》篇圖版126），其中獅子的姿態與本圖非常相似，但也有一些不同之處，比如沒有陪伴隨從，鬃毛只是綠色而不是多彩的。菩薩像本身形成了鮮明的對比，伯希和收集品的像是中國式的，全身幾乎被肥大的衣服包裹，感覺很穩重。與此相比，本圖的像是全身散滿寶石的裝飾品，著網狀薄透的紫色袴和天衣，確實很有肉感。</p><p>這些類似點和不同處，如在已述的圖16的《藥師淨土圖》中所見的那樣，可以確認在敦煌，特別是對菩薩像等的表現上，印度式和中國式手法的使用是同樣盛行的,甚至存在一個作家使用不同的模本，畫兩種方式的可能性。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 55"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.120</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Bodhisattva with glass beaker (for complete banner, see Pl.28)</title><title lang="chi-Hant">菩薩像（參照圖28）</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.58.0 cm, W.18.0 cm</p><p>Stein painting 120. Ch.0025</p><p>Because it has survived almost intact, this banner has already been presented in Pl.28 to introduce the construction of banner paintings. Here it is interesting to note the way in which the painter has approached the problem of showing a figure from the back. The main part of the figure is in three-quarter back view, much as the Bodhisattva of Pl. 49, but with the head turned even further and seen in profile. As occasionally in other Dunhuang paintings, the side view of the face presents a single outline from forehead to mouth, with the nose seen beyond this. The rear view of the shoulders also enables us to see how the hair, seen framing the shoulders of very many Bodhisattvas, divides at the neck into two large locks, falling from a chignon behind the tiara. Other details of the painting similarly reveal the disposition of the robes. The long white scarf in front, so prominent in many of the banners (such as Pl. 56) is just visible, draped over the lotus petals.</p><p>The Bodhisattva holds a glass beaker, evidently moulded and cut in large dimples in the same fashion as that held by the Bodhisattva of Pl. 56, but with an everted instead of an incurved lip, and containing a lotus blossom. Such glass vessels, as explained in the notes to Pl. 56, were probably imports from Iran.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高58.0釐米 寬18.0釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫120，Ch.0025</p><p>此幡基本保留了完整的原型，爲了介紹整體结构，已經在圖28中展示。這裏再次舉出此圖，是想把目光转向畫家描绘像的背面所採用的手法上。圖中的菩薩為四分之三身的背面像，與圖49的菩薩像相似，但頭部還要向后，露出臉的側面。它采用了從額到嘴一筆绘出，其侧向露出鼻子的表现手法，在其他敦煌畫中有時也可看到這種手法。兩肩部分展示的也是背部，所以可看清在其他繪畫中常見的覆蓋菩薩兩肩的頭髮，實際上是從寶冠後面的髮髻垂落的，在頸項處分成兩大缕。其他細節部分，也顯現出了衣服的表現。在多數幡畫中明顯的長而白的綬帶（例如，參照下一圖的菩薩像），在此畫中仅仅搭在蓮華座上。</p><p>此菩薩右手持琉璃缽，與下一圖菩薩所捧的器皿一樣有大波紋的彫飾。只是器形不像下一圖那樣邊口內縮，而是向外側敞開，內插有蓮花蕾。這種玻璃容器，正如下一圖的解說中所述，大概是從伊朗引進的。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 56"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.139</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="eng">Bodhisattva with glass bowl</title><title lang="chi-Hant">菩薩像</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, late 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.81.5 cm, W.26.3 cm</p><p>Stein painting 139.Ch. 001</p><p>At first glance this handsome Bodhisattva, slightly aloof, restrained and dignified in pose, seems a far cry from the Vajrapāni of Pl. 58, but in fact the two are closely related in style and date, although they do not match exactly.</p><p>The face of the Bodhisattva seems already to exhibit the kind of full-fleshed features that will be seen in the Song, if anything slightly masculine rather than the feminine ideal portrayed in the Tang. There is a remnant of colour shading around the eyes and neck, but the principal means of depiction are ink lines. Although much slenderer than the ink lines used for the Vajrapāni, when examined closely, for instance those of the nose and the outline of the face, they prove to be short and discontinuous blunt strokes of the brush, exactly parallel to the more exaggerated strokes of Pl. 58.</p><p>In both figures much play is made of the knotted white scarves around the waist that fall to the lotus pedestals. These are in opaque and brilliant white, with very firm outer contours of ink. Other scarves in this painting use colour to obtain effects of transparency, and this interest is likewise seen in the rendition of the large dimpled bowl on his upturned right hand. Not only can parallels be found for this in the wall paintings (e.g., the transparent cintamani held by a Bodhisattva in Cave 15 at Wanfoxia, Lo Archive, no. 2445), but an actual example of such a glass bowl is to be found in the treasures of the Shōsō-in (Shōsō-in no garasu, Pl. 1), and it is similar to glass bowls excavated in Iran. It is not at all surprising that such precious examples from the trade along the Silk Road should have been incorporated into the iconography of Buddhist art at Dunhuang.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀後半葉</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高81.5釐米 寬26.3釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫139.Ch.001</p><p>此美麗的菩薩像，有略顯高傲、感情壓抑的威嚴姿態。乍一看，好像與圖58的金剛力士像相差甚遠，其實，兩者在風格和創作年代上都關係密切。</p><p>此菩薩的面部不是唐代崇尚的女性化風格，而是有某些男性風格，已經具備了宋代像的豐潤容貌。眼睛周圍以及脖頸還能辨出色彩暈染的痕迹，而基本用墨線描繪。此像的墨線比圖58的金剛力士像還細，詳細觀察則發現，如鼻線和臉部輪廓線等不是一筆拉下來的，而是運用了短筆連接的方法，同一筆法，在圖55的金剛力士像的描繪上更爲誇張。</p><p>兩個像的白色綬帶效果都非常好，塗著不透明的亮白色，用墨將輪廓清楚的描出，打結的綬帶纏在腰閒，之後垂到蓮花座上。爲顯示天衣的透明感，在色彩上下了功夫。朝上反轉的右手掌捧著的大琉璃缽的表現，也可窺出在刻意顯示透明感。在壁畫中也能見到與此類似的透明器物的描繪（例如，萬佛峽第15窟裏，有手持透明淨瓶的菩薩。參照羅寄梅No.2445）。另外，在正倉院的御物（參照『正倉院のガラス』圖版1）和伊朗出土品中可見玻璃碗的實物。因此，敦煌佛教圖像中，採納這些絲綢之路交易往來的貴重物證，也不足爲奇。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 57"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.123</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san-Latn">Vajrapāni</title><title lang="chi-Hant">金剛力士像</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, late 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.64.0 cm, W. 18.5 cm</p><p>Stein painting 123.Ch.xxvi. a. 005</p><p>See also Fig. 101</p><p>This striking banner has four bottom streamers of dark blue silk and side streamers of bluish green and plain green, but there is no weighting board. The bottom streamers and one side streamer are stamped with motifs of flowers and insects, as is the side streamer of Pl. 62; the plain green streamer may be a replacement.</p><p>Even more than in Pl. 58, the network of colour modelling, here executed in “acrid pink”, makes an extraordinary impression. It covers all the exposed areas of flesh, even the face and hands, not only to suggest the musculature of the torso but also to reinforce the demonic appearance of the face. Stein’s description in Serindia comments on the extreme nature of this “meaningless latticework of a coarse pink”. In fact it should probably be seen as having its own rationale, used for demons (see, for example, the crouching figures beneath the feet of the Lokapālas, as in Pl.63, as opposed to the quietly schematic method of colour shading and highlighting earlier used for the Buddha and Bodhisattvas, for example in Pl.7). Naturally, the same convention can be easily found in the wall paintings, the best example being of royal and other mourners in the famous parinirvāna scene of Cave 159 (late eighth or early ninth century); another in the same cave, using colour only without ink outlines, is seen in an attendant of Mañjusrī (Dunhuang bihua, Pl.174). A dated example is seen in the painting of Tejaprabha Buddha and the Five Planets (A.D. 897,Pl.27), and may support a late ninth or even early tenth century date for the present painting.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀末</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高64.0釐米 寬18.5釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫123.Ch.xxvi.a.005</p><p>參見Fig.101</p><p>此五彩繽紛的幡，底部是藏藍色絹做的幡腳，鎮板已遺失，側面一邊是青綠、另一邊是綠色的幡尾。底部幡腳和側面的幡尾映出花和蟲子花紋，這和圖62幡兩側的幡尾一樣。無花樣的綠色幡尾可能是後補的。</p><p>此像顯示肉感的網狀描繪使用的濃豔的粉色，遠比下一圖的金剛力士像給人的印象強烈。包括臉部和手，網狀覆蓋了身體所有暴露的部分，不僅使人聯想到肌肉組織，也增強了鬼神的表情。斯坦因在《西域》中也對這肉感的極端的表現做了評價，“無意義的劣等粉色格子文樣”。實際上，這些是爲鬼神或者邪鬼想出的方法（參照圖63廣目天腳下蹲的地鬼例子，與早期作品中佛和菩薩的溫和圖式的明暗和高光相對應，參照圖7）。當然，在壁畫中也多有運用同一手法的作品，最好的例子，可以舉出第159窟（8世紀末～9世紀初）有名的涅槃圖所描繪的國王們及其他哀悼者們，以及同窟的不用墨綫、直接上彩的文殊脅侍（參照《敦煌壁畫》圖版174）。另外，有紀年的作品，可以舉出《熾盛光佛和五星圖》（897年，圖27），它可作爲把本圖繪制年代看作是9世紀後半葉乃至10世紀前半葉的依據。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 58"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.132</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san-Latn">Vajrapāni</title><title lang="chi-Hant">金剛力士像</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, late 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.79.5 cm, W. 25.5 cm</p><p>Stein painting 132. Ch. xxiv. 002</p><p>By its similar size and in features such as the ink outlines and colouring, this banner has to be seen as a match to the Bodhisattva with a glass bowl of Stein 139 (Pl. 56), and so provides a valuable point of reference between the two subjects. It is, however, unlikely to be from the same set, as the two paintings have different borders and are painted on silk of a slightly different weave.</p><p>The painting has been the subject of an excellent article by Toshio Nagahiro (1964), who drew attention to the identical pose with flexed muscles, firmly planted heel and clenched toes, seen in a rubbing from the Qianxiang an 千祥庵 at Luoyang dated A.D. 700, and another Vajrapāni figure partially preserved at the Dayan ta (Great Gander Pagoda) 大雁塔 in Xi’an, and of similar date. Both of these examples used continuous line contours, sensitively modelling the articulation of figural motifs such as the face or the knee. In this and similar paintings, on the other hand, short disconnected lines with considerable variation in width are used, attaining an exaggerated effect without bothering about the underlying forms. There can be no doubt about the popularity of the stance for such Vajrapāni. There are two fine sets of four, probably dating from the tenth century and executed in ink alone, in the British Museum and British Library (Vol.2, Figs. 93, 94). The same pose can be seen in the famous woodcut frontispiece to the Diamond Sutra dated A.D.868 (Vol.2,Fig. 144). Four grey silk damask streamers, now separately preserved, originally brought the total length of the banner to just over 2 metres.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀末</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高79.5釐米 寬25.5釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫132.Ch.xxiv.002</p><p>從墨線和色彩到尺寸和絹的顔色來看，該幡可能與圖56手持琉璃瓶的菩薩像極爲相配，兩者存在密切的關係。不過二者可能並非屬於一組圖像，因爲它們有不同的邊幅，所用絹布的織法也不同。</p><p>長廣敏雄先生就此繪畫爲主題發表過優秀論文（1964年），其中先生注意到金剛腳尖緊繃，兩腳跟用力踏地。在久視元年（700年）紀年的洛陽千祥庵的拓本中也有與此相同姿勢的金剛力士像，在西安大雁塔裏也殘留了大致同時代的相同像的一部分。這兩個相同的例子中，描線順暢沒有停頓，像的臉和膝蓋等重點部位的描繪上精確地按照底稿的模型。與此相比，斯坦因收集品中的本圖以及類似的繪畫中，使用短的有間斷的綫，基本遵照底稿但進行肥瘦的改變，起到了誇張的表現效果。可以說這裏反映了有關金剛力士像流行。大英博物館和大英圖書館分藏的，大約爲10世紀的二組四塊墨繪的像（參照第2卷Fig.93、94），和有咸通九年（868年）紀年的《金剛經》的有名的封皮上的木版畫（參照第2卷Fig.144、145）中，也可見相同姿態的像。本幡原有的四條灰色絲緞幡腳與主幡分開保管，如果加上它們，該幡的長度會在2米以上。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 59"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.134</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san">Vajrapāni (for complete banner, see Pl. 28)</title><title lang="chi-Hant">金剛力士像（整個的幡參見圖28）</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, late 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.67.5 cm, W. 18.6 cm</p><p>Stein painting 134.Ch. 004</p><p>This painting has already been shown as a complete banner in Pl. 28 together with the Bodhisattva of Pl. 55. A similar figure in New Delhi (Stein, Serindia, Ch.i.006) is also preserved complete, with only minimal differences such as the mouth being open to show the teeth, and the side streamers blue instead of green. Even the lozenge border at the bottom has the same colours in the same places.</p><p>The fact that this is one of a series of a almost identical figures also emerges when one examines the depiction itself, which is far less vigorous than such an example as Pl. 58. The contrast can be seen in the modelling: although colour shading and ink outlines are used in both paintings, here they are used rather tamely and conventionally, in contrast to the bold effects obtained in Pl. 58. Again, both paintings feature a halo ringed with flames: in many cases such flames simply form a decorative outer border or edging to the halo, but in Pl. 58 they serve to break the geometric outline and appear to be blown by the fury of the figure, now within the circle and now outside it. In the present banner and its match in New Delhi, the flames all lie inside the circles and have lost their vitality. The differences illustrate levels of skill among the painters, since all were very probably executed in the same period of the late ninth century.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀末</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高67.5釐米</p><p>寬18.6釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫134.Ch.004</p><p>此幡全圖已經和圖55的菩薩一同刊載在圖28中。與其相似的幡則收藏在新德里國立博物館（斯坦因《西域》，Ch.006），也保存完好。除張口露牙，兩側的幡尾不是綠的而是青色等方面的細微差別外，底部菱形邊緣的顔色和位置均相同。</p><p>事實上，檢視該畫本身即可發現其是大致相同的系列幡畫中的一件。那些像的描繪，與圖58的金剛力士像相比，缺少活力。其不同點首先體現在肉感的表現上。雖然雙方都是用明暗和墨線表現肉感，但本圖的表現卻很雅氣，符合體型，與上一圖力大無比的強悍感成對比。兩者均伴有火焰光，但表現有差異。大多時候，火焰是單獨在頭光的外緣部或者一角上，與此相對，上一圖的金剛力士像中，宛如是被像的威猛所震動，至使內外都有火焰在燃燒。而本圖的像和新德里國立博物館中的相同形式的像，火焰只在圓形裏面，失去了生氣。這些繪畫都被認爲是9世紀後半葉同期製作的，因此這種差別是由畫家個人才能的差距造成的。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 60"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.126</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san-Latn">Lokapāla</title><title lang="chi-Hant">天王像</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, late 8th or early 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.60.0 cm, W. 18.5 cm</p><p>Stein painting 126.Ch.0095</p><p>In several ways this Lokapāla is rather different from the majority of those in the collection, and may perhaps be dated somewhat earlier than the rest. The figure is entirely human, without the demonic attributes of most of the guardian kings. He steps lightly forward on a cloud, with slender figure and light armour. The face is very carefully delineated in ink and shaded in pink, the hands likewise and clasped together in añjali-mudrā. He wears no helmet, but the collar of his coat of mail, apparently of stiffened leather coloured blue outside and red inside, rises high to protect the neck. Beneath the oblong leather scales of the coat, an undergarment of red splendidly embroidered with large flowers can be seen. Other flowers, arranged as florets with four circular petals on the arms of a cross, can be seen on the sleeves and lower part of the skirt. This floral pattern was done in white with yellow petals. White was used as the final colour in the painting. It has survived particularly well where it has been applied over another colour, for example the white lines on the blue leather edging to the armour, and over the orange inner edges of the same. Where the same white was merely applied straight onto the silk, it has practically all come away. Only a few scales on the greave of the right leg show that originally all the leather scales of the armour were bright white, with the vertical edges of each scale in ink and the horizontal overlaps in blue like the leather edgings.</p><p>Of considerable interest is the fact that at the bottom of the painting the artist has experimented with sketches of three faces in three-quarter view, two of them in red outline alone, the largest in ink with a little colour added to the lips.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，8世紀末～9世紀初</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高60.0釐米 寬18.5釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫126.Ch.0095</p><p>此天王像有很多方面與該收集品中的大部分天王像存在差別，大概年代也比那些作品稍早。此像的外觀完全是一個普通人物，沒有大多天王像所具備的魔神特點。像的瘦身裹以輕的鎧甲，輕盈地走在雲上。臉用墨線描出，賦了粉色暈。以同樣手法描出的兩手，結著合掌印。沒有戴盔，而是把鎧甲的領子立的很高保護著脖子。領子是硬皮革，表層是青色，裏層染成紅色。沒有長方形鱗片的鎧下，露出刺繡精美的大花紋紅色內衣。袖和衣裙是用白和黃色描出的十字形四瓣花的另一種小花紋樣。白色是最後塗上的，特別是重疊於其他顔色上的部分，如鎧甲邊緣的青色革和鎧甲裏子的橙色邊緣上描的白色，很多保留下來。同樣的白色，直接塗在絹上的部分卻已基本脫落。但右腳脛骨的一部分白色仍保留至今。可以窺見鎧甲原來所有的鱗片是美麗的白色，每一片的豎線是用墨色，橫線用和鎧甲邊緣相同的青色勾勒出來的。</p><p>有趣的是，畫面最下邊有畫家試畫的三個草圖。其中兩個只用朱線，另一最大草圖則用墨線描繪，唇上稍加顔色。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 61"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.106</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san">Virūpāksa, Guardian of the West</title><title lang="chi-Hant">廣目天像，護衛西方</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.45.5 cm, W. 16.0 cm</p><p>Stein painting 106. Ch.xlix. 007</p><p>Both Virūpāksa in this banner and Dhrtarāstra in the following one are magnificently attired but kingly rather that demonic in their appearance and thoughtful rather than threatening. The figures on which they stand, too, are supportive and recognizably human rather than cringing long-haired demonic types. The manner of their depiction with short thick and thin lines is similar to that of the Vajrapāni of Pl. 58 which Nagahiro (1964) has contrasted with the even, continuous lines characteristic, even for figures such as a Vajrapāni, of the early eighth century. Following his argument, a date in the middle or late ninth century seems possible.</p><p>In Stein’s opinion this banner belonged to the same series as that of Dhrtarāstra in the following plate. The two are technically similar, unlike most of the banners, in having a selvedge at the bottom, so that the warp is horizontal instead of vertical. They also have similar sage-green streamers.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高45.5釐米 寬16.0釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫106.Ch.xlix.007</p><p>此廣目天像幡畫和下一圖的持國天，有漂亮的裝飾，與其說是鬼神，不如說有王者風範更合適，與其說威赫不如説是智慧。兩者腳踏的地鬼都被踏扁，不是長髮的魔鬼形象，而是表現理解和支持的人類。描法是使用連接肥瘦不一的短線，近於圖58的金剛力士像的描法。關於此描法，長廣敏雄先生（《東方學報》1964年）講，只有8世紀前半葉的金剛力士像才使用無停頓的順暢線描。因此，根據先生的論點，該畫是9世紀中葉或者後半葉的作品較爲妥當。</p><p>斯坦因將此幡看作和下一圖持國天的幡屬同一系列的作品。兩者的技法相似。與其他所有幡的區別的，還有來自下端的織邊，經線和畫面是水平走向而非垂直走向。再者，兩個都有同樣的青綠色幡腳。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 62"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.129</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san">Dhrtarāstra, Guardian of the East</title><title lang="chi-Hant">持國天，護衛東方</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.40.5 cm, W. 15.5 cm</p><p>Stein painting 129. Ch. xxvi. a. 006</p><p>The Lokapāla here very impressive in spite of the small size of the banner, which has lost all its accessories, but preserves its lower border of flowers in lozenge panels intact. Dhrtarāstra, holding the bow and arrow which identify him as the Guardian King of the East, stands solidly in the centre, turning to the spectator’s left. His feet are supported by a tousle-headed, one-eyed, snaggletoothed demonic figure naked from the waist up and drawn with short thick-and- thin lines of ink that are comparable to those used in the Vajrapāni paintings such as Pl. 58.</p><p>The predominant tones of the painting are the yellow of the scale armour and the red of its leather borders. Around his waist the Lokapāla wears a tiger skin, similar to that worn by the fragmentary figure of Fig. 110. White originally played a major part in the painting, but as usual has come away where it was applied directly on the silk, and is only really bright in a few places such as the one open eye of the supporting figure, and the eyes and horns of the animal mask above the belt. Perhaps a better grade of white was used for these accents. The ink outlines were strengthened after the application of the colour; but this was not done consistently, and in some places, such as the red trouser of the demon below, the ink lines are fainter. At the moment it is not clear whether these fainter lines of ink beneath the colour are the under-drawing, or the final ink lines applied from the other side, which could mean that the colours were applied first, using a stencil, and the details and contours added later on both sides.</p><p>Some features of the painting may be explained by reference to the very similar banner of Virūpāksa in New Delhi (Stein, Thousand Buddhas, Pl. XXⅦ) and to the splendid wall painting of the same king in the Yulin caves (Warner, 1938, Pl.XIV), which must date before A.D. 901, when a visitor left an inscription beside him. All three representations are shown in similar poses and with the same armour, but the function of the animal mask in clasping the belt is clearer in these other examples than in the British Museum banner, where the lower jaw has been omitted.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高40.5釐米 寬15.5釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫129.Ch.xxvi.a.006</p><p>雖然是小型的幡畫，卻是一件給人印象深刻的作品，附屬品全部遺失，只留下菱形中配飾花紋的完整的下端邊飾。從手持弓箭知道此天王像是東方的守護神，即持國天。兩腿基本是拉開架式站立在中央，上體略向左方扭。雙腳踏此亞咧嘴的獨眼卷毛地鬼，該鬼用腰以上赤裸的姿勢支撐著持國天。此地鬼採用了與圖58的金剛力士像同樣手法的線描。</p><p>此畫的主色調爲，鎧甲鱗片用的是黃色，鎧甲的邊革使用紅色，腰上圍著虎皮。在Fig.110的多聞天像（斷片）中也見到相同的表現。白色原為重要的色調，直接塗在絹子上的部分照例已脫落，不過現在地鬼睜著的眼、腰帶上獸飾的眼和角等處，仍保留著閃亮的一部分。可能這些地方使用了比其他部分更高質量的顔料。輪廓線賦了彩後，用墨描出。但不是全部使用此法，在若干個地方，如地鬼紅色褲子線條墨色較淡。這些暗淡的墨線，是因上面加彩後變得淡薄的底樣呢，還是從裏面加入的線呢，現在無法說清。也許是首先敷上顔色，然後從輪廓線兩側加描細部。</p><p>與此畫非常相似的有新德里國立博物館的幡畫廣目天像（斯坦因《千佛洞》，圖27）以及精美的榆林窟廣目天像可資參考。通過榆林窟廣目天旁邊的題記，知道是901年以前製作的（Warner，Buddhist Wall-Painting1 Pl.14）。不與它們相比較，該繪畫中也會有不確切的部分。這三身廣目天像是相同的姿勢、同樣的鎧甲，但相比腰帶的獸飾，本圖中省去下顎，而那兩例卻完全齊備，其功能表現得更爲明白。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 63"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.108</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san">Virūpāksa, Guardian of the West</title><title lang="chi-Hant">廣目天像，護衛西方</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.64.5 cm, W. 17.5 cm</p><p>Stein painting 108.Ch.0010</p><p>See also Fig.102</p><p>Although the bottom streamers of sage-green silk are now separately preserved, this banner when found was complete except for the weighting board and still makes a splendid impression with its wide headpiece of thin rose-coloured silk and side streamers of green silk with flowers, birds and insects in dark blue or possibly silver. The suspension loop is of a thick silk with a pattern in green like MAS 858 (Vol. 3, Pl. 6). The painted area has narrow red edges with small florets in white. The Lokapāla and the demon he stands on are almost perfectly preserved, a large piece of bright blue silk having been tacked behind the top of the painting to prevent it falling apart. Whit the purple cloud rising to form, as it were, a canopy above the halo, the painting is close to two paintings of Virūpāksa’s eastern counterpart, Dhrtarāstra, from the Pelliot collection (Bannières, Nos. 193, 194).</p><p>As considered by Stein in Serindia, the Lokapāla paintings in the collection (twenty-four in all, including those in New Delhi) were divided into two categories, those with features relating them to the more “Indian ”of the Bodhisattva banners, such as Pl. 62, and those more Chinese, such as the present banner (Stein, Serindia, pp. 939-41, 1032-33). In actual fact, despite some differences, the whole group is fairly homogeneous and simply presents a range of types. All may be regarded as being painted at Dunhuang, rather than having been brought there from elsewhere.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高64.5釐米 寬17.5釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫108.Ch.0010</p><p>參照Fig.102</p><p>發現此幡時，除了缺少鎮板外，形狀還很完整，現在底部的黃綠色幡腳被單獨保存。薔薇色薄絹的大型幡首和綠色絹底上，用藏藍色或銀泥描繪着花、鳥、蟲等兩側的幡尾等，至今仍給人華麗的印象。吊環與MAS858（第3卷圖6）包經卷的布相似，由綠色花紋的厚絹做成。畫面的兩側加了紅底上撒滿白色小花紋樣的細邊飾。廣目天和腳下的地鬼大體保存完好，繪畫上部從內側安了大塊亮青色的絹子，此補修可使繪畫不易脫落。頭光上方騰起紫色雲彩，看似華蓋。從這種表現看，此畫與伯希和收集品中的兩件持國天近似（參見《敦煌的幡和繪畫》篇圖版193、194）。</p><p>在《西域》中，斯坦因把收集品中的天王像（包括新德里國立博物館的部分，共有24件）分爲兩類（參照《西域》，p.939-941,p.1032-1033），即與“印度式” 對應的圖62等菩薩幡畫群，及與“中國式”對應的本菩薩幡畫群。其實，虽然多少有些差別，但大體上都屬同一性質，可以說只是各類型的不同展現而已。因此所有的都不應是從別處帶入的，而應該是在敦煌製作的。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 64"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.137*</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san">Virūpāksa, Guardian of the West</title><title lang="chi-Hant">廣目天像，護衛西方</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9 th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.43.5 cm, W. 18.0 cm</p><p>Stein painting 137*. Ch. 0035</p><p>Although it has lost all its accessories, this banner remains quite impressive and is finely drawn: note the alternate red and black lines of the beard and the shaded white of the leg-coverings tied around the knees. Of the supporting figure below, only the sparse red hair remains, enough to show that it was one of the cringing demon types probably modelled in colour washes alone. Virūpāksa’s jewelled scabbard rests directly on the demon’s head. In the facial delineation of the king, the sharply angled mouthline suggests a late ninth - century date for the painting.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高43.5釐米 寬18.0釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫137*.Ch.0035</p><p>此幡儘管沒有留下一件附屬品，但從其細緻的描繪，可以看出是一件震撼人心的佳品。用墨線和朱線两色交替描繪的髯，膝蓋以下以帶子結紮用白色暈染的長綁腿，都很引人注目。下方地鬼淩亂的紅毛髮只殘存一小部分，但僅從其色彩，便足以反映出其所描繪的下蹲惡鬼的形象。廣目天用鞘上鑲嵌寶石的刀壓住地鬼的頭。從唇線呈銳利的特點來看，該繪畫是9世紀後半葉的作品。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 65"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.138</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><title lang="san">Vaisravana, Guardian of the North</title><title lang="chi-Hant">多聞天像,護衛北方</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.50.5 cm, W.17.5 cm</p><p>Stein painting 138.Ch.lv.0018.</p><p>Other paintings of Vaisravana, complete with his retinue of attendants, are included in Vol. 2 (Pls. 15, 16). Here he is shown alone in similar fashion to the other guardian kings and is recognizable by the stupa poised above his right hand. He wears sandals and stands upon a supine demon with yellow hair. Below, a small strip remaining from the lozenge border has been incorrectly mounted too close to this figure. Above, a brown cloud can just be seen to have hung above the halo, which, as usual with these figures, is plain green with a darker green edge, against which the upward-floating ribbons of the headdress are displayed to advantage.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高50.5釐米 寬17.5釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫138.Ch.iv.0018</p><p>有侍者隨從，形象表現完整的多聞天（毘沙門天）像，收錄於第2卷（圖15、16）中。這裏和其他天王像一樣只表現一身，因右手托著寶塔，由此可確定他是多聞天。腳穿涼鞋，踏著仰臥的黃髮鬼。下端是粘貼補著菱形邊飾的斷片，由於裝裱時的失誤，與像的距離過於狹窄。上方頭光之上突出的部分，殘留少許茶色雲。頭光按照此種像的慣例，塗著淡綠色，只是邊緣括以濃綠色。從寶冠上飄起的白色絲帶，清晰地浮現在頭光背景上。</p></note></msItem></msContents></msDescription><msDescription n="Vol. 1 Plate 66"><msIdentifier><settlement>London</settlement><repository>The British Museum</repository><collection>Stein Collection</collection><idno type="current">1919,0101,0.69</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="1"><msItem n="1"><title lang="san-Latn">Lokapāla (fragment)</title><title lang="chi-Hant">天王像（斷片）</title><note lang="eng"><p>Tang dynasty, 9th century A.D.</p><p>Ink and colours on silk</p><p>H.63.0 cm, W.67.0 cm</p><p>Stein painting 69.Ch.liv.003</p><p>Although fragmentary, this painting shows how splendid the finest paintings at Dunhuang could be. The width is likely to have been 75 cm or more, and so the whole figure must have stood over 2 metres high. Compared to the smaller banners painted with the help of stencils, more individual attention has been paid to details, both as regards the outlines and modelling and in the final colouring.</p><p>The Lokapāla, from the arrow he is carrying, is probably Dhrtarāstra, Guardian of the East. His face is outlined in thick heavy ink lines, but these are subsequently almost lost beneath the luxuriant growth of beard flowing in smooth lines almost like a magnetic field from the ends of the mouth, chin and temples. The items of his apparel correspond to those of other guardian kings, but are more gorgeously decorated, as in the rows of scale armour, each of a different colour, the borders of embroidered flowers, and the splendid blue jewel worn at the neck.</p></note><note lang="chi-Hant"><p>唐代，9世紀</p><p>絹本設色</p><p>高63.0釐米 寬67.0釐米</p><p>斯坦因繪畫69.Ch.liv.003</p><p>此畫雖然是斷片，但能如實地說明在敦煌創造過多麽精美的繪畫。其幅寬是75釐米或者更寬，整個立像的高度無疑會超過2米。與利用模板的小型幡畫相比，此畫無論線描、樣式還是色彩，都非常細緻周到。</p><p>從此像手持矢看，可能是東方的守護神，即持國天。臉部輪廓用生硬粗糙的墨線來描繪。而嘴邊、下顎以及鬢角處似磁場，吸住無數流利柔和線表現的豐滿鬍鬚，幾乎將它們隱埋。身上穿的衣物本身與其他天王像基本無差別，只是表現極爲華麗，每段鎧甲鱗片分別塗不同的顔色，刺繡花紋的邊飾、嵌青色寶石的美麗首飾，裝飾非常豪華。</p></note></msItem></msItem></msContents></msDescription></body></text></TEI.2>
