<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title lang="eng">Tun-huang Popular Narratives (The Story of Wu Zixu)</title><author id="VM">Victor Mair</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher><pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace><date>1983</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>PRINTED BOOK</p><bibl><ref target="Mair_1983">123-150</ref></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc>Translation</projectDesc><editorialDecl>Converted into TEI XML by Maude Croucher on 2007. Imported to 4D on
                13/06/07 by Sam van Schaik.</editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><head><p>Translation of the Story of Wu Zixu, a transformation text from Dunhuang. For
                copyright reasons, we can only reproduce 28 pages of this translation here. For the
                full version, please consult Mair_1983: 123-165.</p></head><body><msDescription n="1" type="VM"><msIdentifier><idno type="current">Or.8210/S.328</idno><idno type="unknown">T1-28</idno><idno type="current">Pelliot chinois 3213</idno><idno type="current">Pelliot chinois 2794</idno><idno type="current">Or.8210/S.6331</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><msItem n="Whole text"><title lang="eng">The Story of Wu Zixu</title><q lang="eng"><p>Of old, when the Zhou Dynasty was on its last legs, the six
                                braves began to contest among themselves and the eight barbarians
                                vied with each other in invading the realm. In the south, there was
                                King Ping of the Kingdom of Chu who, reposing in benevolence,
                                exercised a civilizing influence over his people. There were
                                attendant upon the King's court ten thousand principalities. His
                                charismatic sway spread afar, enabling him to exercise a commanding
                                influence over the sundry states.</p><p>For external affairs, he
                                sponsored a deliberative body called the 'Bright Terrace' and, for
                                internal matters, he ascended the palace throne. He pacified the
                                area to the south as far as the Gate of Heaven; his northernmost
                                frontier pass was at Huaihai; his frontiers to the east went as far
                                as the sun and moon; to the west, his borders were the Buddhist
                                kingdoms.</p><p>He opened up mountains and rivers to correct the
                                earth's axis and adjusted the twelve semitones so as to
                                differentiate yin and yang. When he mounted the throne, it brought
                                stability to the Imperial Gate; when he shook the Yellow Dragon
                                standard, his assistants came to him. The six dragons sent down from
                                heaven good fortune; the symbols of earth betokened auspicious
                                harvests.</p><p>Neither did the wind make the branches of trees
                                rustle nor did the rain break up the clods of earth. The avenues,
                                boulevards, streets, and roads, neatly and impressively laid out,
                                were broad and level. Indeed, he had made a name for himself that
                                would last ten thousand generations.</p><p>The Prime Minister of Chu
                                was surnamed Wu and named She. Possessed of literary and military
                                ability, he was dedicated to preserving the altars of Chu. He held a
                                three-foot long sword in his hand and entrusted his emotions to his
                                six-foot frame. Ten thousand nations willingly received his
                                commands. He was honest and straightforward in conduct, and faithful
                                and true to ceremonial usages and rules. His opinions were as lofty
                                as the wind and the clouds; his heart was as hard as iron and steel.
                                Of constant purpose and unfailing assiduity, he was attentive both
                                morning and night.</p><p>Wu She served his ruler with dedication as
                                his ideal. Through obedience, he enabled his ruler to be successful.
                                But, if even the monarch were tyrannous, Wu She would rebuke him
                                without regard to his superior status.</p><p>Now, Wu She had two
                                sons who were in the service of their lord. The younger was called
                                Zixu and the elder, Zishang. The one was serving in the kingdom of
                                Liang and the other in the state of Zheng. Both were loyal and
                                far-seeing men.</p><p>The Crown Prince of Chu was a grown man but
                                had not yet taken a wife. The King inquired of his officials, 'Who
                                has a daughter worthy of being the Prince's consort? We have heard
                                that, "if a country be without an heir-apparent, half of the land
                                will be barren. Though the flowing springs of the Eastern Sea flood
                                a tree with their plentiful waters, if the tree have no branches,
                                half of it will be dead." The Crown Prince represents half of the
                                majesty of the kingdom, but he has not yet taken a wife. What do you
                                think?'</p><p>The Grand Minister Wei Ling addressed the King,
                                saying, 'I have heard that Duke Mu of Qin has a daughter aged
                                sixteen who is surpassingly beautiful. Her eyebrows are like the
                                waning moon, her cheeks like concentrated light, her eyes like
                                shooting stars, her face as colourful as a flower. Her hair is seven
                                feet long, her nose is straight and her forehead square, her ears
                                like pendant pearls. Her hands hang below her knees, her ten fingers
                                are slender and long. I would hope that Your Majesty issue
                                directives whereby marriage arrangements be made on behalf of the
                                Prince. If things can be worked out to satisfy Your Majesty's
                                wishes, it would be a splendid event in whose glory all nations
                                could share.'</p><p>So the King sent Wei Ling to solicit the Duke of
                                Qin's daughter. After Wei Ling had returned with the girl, the King
                                summoned him and said, 'I have troubled you to make this long
                                journey and to brave wind and frost.'</p><p>When the King saw how
                                beautiful and charming the girl was, he suddenly became filled with
                                a wolfish, tigerish desire. Wei Ling craftily played upon the King's
                                feelings: 'I would have Your Majesty take her for your own Imperial
                                concubine. We can seek elsewhere for the Crown Prince. There are
                                beautiful girls without number. How could this be an offence against
                                the Ideal?' When the King heard Wei Ling's words, he was happy
                                beyond measure. He forthwith took the girl from Qin as his
                                concubine. For three days, he stayed in the inner palace and did not
                                hold court.</p><p>Wu She was furious when he heard this and, not
                                cowering before the thunder and lightning of the King's majesty,
                                with his hair all dishevelled, he went straight before the palace.
                                Risking the royal displeasure, he straightforwardly reproved the
                                King.</p><p>The King was startled and apprehensive.<lg>'Has there
                                    been an unfavourable omen?' he asked.</lg>'Today I have seen you
                                act so unscrupulously,' answered Wu She, 'that I fear for the
                                ruination of the kingdom. If the country should undergo a rebellion
                                and its ministers abandon it, would that not all be attributable to
                                the Duke of Qin's daughter? You gave her to your son as a bride but
                                then took her yourself as a concubine. Will not contesting like this
                                with your son for a wife bring you opprobrium before Heaven and
                                Earth? This has made chaos of our laws and overturned the rules of
                                propriety and good custom. I must reprove you for I fear that it is
                                going to be difficult to preserve our country's altars!'</p><p>At
                                this, the King's face went pale with shame. Humiliated in the
                                presence of his ministers, he shot back, 'Has the Prime Minister not
                                heard this saying: "Set plans are not to be discussed; spilled water
                                is hard to recover." Things being what they are, do not reprove me
                                again!'</p><p>Wu She felt that the King, without principle, had
                                taken the Qin girl as his own concubine. Not cowering before the
                                thunder and lightning of the King's majesty, he risked the royal
                                displeasure by straightforwardly reproving: 'Your Majesty is the
                                lord of ten thousand men and commander of sundry states. How could
                                you have received so credulously the words of Wei Ling?'</p><p>'If
                                your heart of filial piety can indeed swiftly relieve my distress,
                                this soul of mine, suspended above Hades, can avoid having to depart
                                from the world.'</p><p>When Zishang, far afield, received this
                                summons in his father's letter, he wept grievously and, intending to
                                beg the King of Zheng to save his father, he went to see him. 'My
                                father has been imprisoned by King Ping,' he said. 'In a letter from
                                afar, I have been ordered to return. I do wish to save my father,
                                but there is really nothing I can do...I hope that you will think of
                                some plan for me.'</p><p>'Your father has been severely punished and
                                is being detained in a large prison.. A messenger from afar has
                                brought this letter which says that his crimes may be remitted. If
                                you do not save your father from the consequences of his error, how
                                can you be called a filial son? You must depart at once! There is no
                                point in considering the matter further.'</p><p>Zishang then bid
                                farewell to the King of Zheng and made a rapid journey through the
                                night to the Kingdom of Liang to see his younger brother, Zixu.
                                After telling him in detail the content of the letter, Zishang said,
                                'Now King Ping has acted without principle. He has received
                                credulously the words of a deceitful minister and im prisoned the
                                person of our father. It being his purpose to be ruthless, I have
                                come this long way to call upon you to go with me. The exigencies of
                                the situation do not permit us to tarry for any length of time. I
                                would hope that you pack your things at once.'</p><p>Hearing these
                                words of his brother, Zixu realized, even though he was far from
                                Chu, that his father was being held. From close consideration of the
                                details of the matter, he concluded that the letter was, in all
                                probability, a forgery. So he answered his brother: 'King Ping,
                                being without principle and believing the words of a treacherous
                                minister, has imprisoned our father and intends to execute him.
                                Inasmuch as we two brothers are abroad, he is tormented by the
                                possibility of revenge later on and so has had this letter written,
                                pretending it is father's. Because we are so far away, he rashly
                                thinks that he can deceive us. Given these circumstances, it is
                                sufficiently clear that, if we go to Chu to save our father, then we
                                too will certainly be slaughtered. This express letter and the
                                command it lays upon us are surely but a monstrous pretext intended
                                to bring us brothers back. And, when we get to Chu, we will
                                certainly be implicated along with our father. We cannot embark upon
                                this journey. If we do, we shall be like dull-witted birds thrashing
                                about in a net or fish from a fountain swimming in a
                                kettle.'</p><p>'Go back, now,' continued Wu Zixu, 'and relate
                                everything that I have said. As for my roughness toward you just now
                                please do not take offence at it.'</p><p>When the messenger heard
                                these words, he returned at once to Chu and, tying himself up with
                                rope, went to see King Ping. He informed the King, saying:</p><lg><l>'I received your order to act as express messenger;</l><l>Day and night I ran, passing through many lands.</l><l>South of Kuai Ji Mountain, I caught up with him,</l><l>But, pulling out his sword, he thought to behead me.</l><l>Your servant cowered before the sword in Zixu's hand,</l><l>Zixu feared that both of us would end up dead.</l><l>Each distrusting the other, neither approached the other,</l><l>Word by word across the distance, he explained his case.</l><l>"Turn back and report these words of mine to your King Ping:</l><l>I shall forthwith raise troops and take vengeance for my
                                    father!"'</l></lg><p>Upon hearing this, the Emperor of Chu struck the steps leading to his
                                throne and shouted angrily, 'What an insolent and petty person! How
                                comes it that we endure his existence? "How is an inch-long blade of
                                grass fit for measuring heaven? Can one thin strand of hair hope to
                                withstand the hot coals of a stove? Zixu's words are sheer madness
                                and not even worth our notice. They are but wild verbiage thrown
                                upon the wind. There is no necessity for us to pay them any
                                heed.'</p><p>The King of Chu then called Wu She and Zishang out of
                                jail and had them sentenced and punished. When Zishang was about to
                                die, he looked up to heaven and, sighing, said, 'When we were in
                                Liang, I did not follow my brother's advice and so have come all
                                this way only to die with my father. What can I do now? Alas!
                                Nothing! Beyond this, what more know I to say? After I die, may my
                                brother live on and, if a way be opened by heaven, may he avenge our
                                father by slaying Chu!' No sooner had he completed these his dying
                                words than they killed him. Father and son were slaughtered at the
                                same instant.</p><p>The King of Chu issued a proclamation.
                                Accordingly, Zixu was to be treated in accordance with the terms of
                                the proclamation which read: 'In re the rebel Zixu, a servant of the
                                Kingdom of Liang. His father was in service to Your Ruler but,
                                unable to remain loyal and circumspect, he plotted against the
                                altars of our state with cruel rapacity. Zishang, a servant of the
                                Kingdom of Cheng, was executed together with his father at the same
                                time. There only remains Zixu who has fled and, as of this moment,
                                has not been apprehended. Whoever can capture him and turn him in
                                will be given a reward of a thousand catties of gold and enfeoffed
                                with the income from a thousand households. Whoever gives him
                                shelter will face the usual punishment provided by law, videlicet,
                                first the offender will himself be beheaded and this will be
                                followed by the extermination of his entire clan. Should any
                                arresting officer exercise leniency, he will be relieved of his
                                office and brought to prosecution. Your King should be kept
                                constantly informed and the offender escorted, in fetters, to the
                                capital.'</p><p>The proclamation having been put in circulation, a
                                water-tight dragnet went into effect. Each province and district was
                                informed and public notices were posted on the highways and roads.
                                Thorough searches were made in every village and ward so that no one
                                dared to shelter Wu Zixu. Rather, greedy for the rich reward, they
                                vied with one another in their pursuit of him.</p><p>Zixu walked
                                until he came to some wild mountains where, placing his hand on his
                                sword and sighing, he sang this sorrowful song:</p><lg><l>'Full of anger, a long, drawn-out sigh escapes me:</l><l>How lamentable for a brave man to be wronged and in peril!</l><l>The net of heaven is all-embracing, the road is cut off,</l><l>Leaving me afraid and with nowhere to take refuge.</l><l>Thirsty, tired, and without food to fill my stomach,</l><l>Companionless I wander in this unending wilderness.</l><l>Afar, I hear the mighty wind-swept waves of the
                                    river-barrier;</l><l>The soaring mountains reach to the very heavens.</l><l>No boat there is midst the desolate islets of this remote
                                    place;</l><l>How then shall I get to the southern shore?</l><l>If it should happen that High Heaven go against human
                                    feeling,</l><l>I'll not escape having difficulties in this place.</l></lg><p>His sad song finished, Zixu resumed his forward progress. Trusting
                                his karma and in accordance with conditioning causes, he reached the
                                River Ying. The wind came to brush against his ears bringing with it
                                the sound of silk being beaten. Wu Zixu was hesitant to press
                                forward and so stood in hiding.</p><lg><l>Zixu, have come to the side of the River Ying;</l><l>Thirsty, tired, and starving, it is difficult to go forward.</l><l>Afar, I hear the sounds of the beating of silk in the air,</l><l>Cringing and crouching, I come suddenly to a standstill.</l><l>I am afraid there may be someone hidden here -</l><l>Stealthily, I draw myself into the shade of the trees.</l><l>Long and sober reflection tells me I need not be afraid;</l><l>Ever so stealthily, I peep through the trees.</l><l>Beside the river-ford, there are no men -</l><l>I see only a nimble, shapely girl beating silk.</l><l>A hundred times, she lowers her head and peers into the
                                    water;</l><l>A thousand passes, her jade wrists dance over the waves.</l><l>At once, I want to rush forward and beg food of her;</l><l>But my heart is full of doubt and irresolution.</l><l>Daring neither to advance nor retreat, I quickly reconsider;</l><l>Though hesitant, I wish to go away meekly at once.</l></lg><p>The girl who was beating silk in the water suddenly raised her head
                                and saw a man rushing wildly, his spirits crazed, and with a starved
                                look on his face. Because he was wearing a sword at his waist and
                                running, she knew that it was Wu Zixu. Full of sympathy, she said to
                                herself: 'I have heard that, "for a single meal given him in the
                                mulberry grove, Ling Zhe propped up the chariot". "The Yellow
                                Sparrow which was given a salve to heal its wounds requited the
                                donor with a gift of white jade bracelets." Though I have kept
                                myself chaste, pure, and undefiled, it is fortune which has granted
                                me this meeting with a gentleman here by the waterside as I beat my
                                silk. True, our home is not well-provided but why should I grudge
                                him this one meal?'</p><p>She walked slowly up the bank, and called
                                out, 'Traveller, won't you stop a while? Where do you come from, my
                                good swordsman? Of what kingdom are you the paragon? You have a
                                spirited appearance and a lofty manner. What urgent business have
                                you to be hurrying on this long journey, companionless, glancing
                                about in fear, and distraught in spirit? Judging from the look on
                                your face, your heart must harbour something for which you are
                                seeking. If you are not a knight-errant who cherishes a grievance,
                                then it must be that you are being pursued by King Ping. My home,
                                though poor, is hospitable and I make bold to offer you a meal. How
                                would you like that? I hope you will condescend to bend your path
                                this way.'</p><p>'I am a man of Chu,' replied Wu Zixu, 'and hold the
                                position of envoy of the Kingdom of Yue. Recently, because I was
                                appointed to present tribute from Yue, I journeyed westwards to the
                                King of Chu. On my way back, I met together and planned defence
                                matters with the two kingdoms of Liang and Zheng. Riding in a
                                chariot drawn by stout horses, I had gone as far as a small river
                                when I was attacked by fierce thieves but was fortunate enough to
                                come out of it alive. Today, climbing mountains and crossing ridges,
                                I have exhausted my provisions. Having heard in the air the sound of
                                your silk-beating, I looked everywhere for its source. Appearing
                                thus, I must present a rather sorry figure. And I am afraid I shall
                                be unable to return within the time set by the King. So I am indeed
                                in a great hurry. Now how can I get through to the road which leads
                                to Kuai Ji? I beg of you only the right direction: I dare not expect
                                any food!'</p><p>'I have heard a saying of the ancients,' said the
                                girl, 'which wasn't spoken vainly. "When one's affection is gone,
                                there's no keeping him from his purpose; but a broken bowstring can
                                still be rejoined." It is obvious which way your course leads. Yet
                                seeing you glance behind and look ahead, your anxious face stained
                                by the wind and dust of far-off rivers and mountains which you have
                                had to cross, I am so bold as to hope that you'll not reject my
                                humble offer of a meal:</p><lg><l>From the beginning, I have always lived in Nan Yang District;</l><l>Aged sixteen, the glow of my face is like soft, bright silk.</l><l>As I beat the silk, my red rouge reflects in deep pools;</l><l>The lotus flower floating on the water is no match for my
                                    beauty.</l><l>My guest has come like a boat floating over the sea;</l><l>At dusk, the birds return to roost, fearing the close of day.</l><l>Should you not reject this humble offering, I pray you try your
                                    best to make a meal of it.'</l></lg><p>Zixu wanted to continue on his journey at once but, again and again,
                                she earnestly begged him to stay. It being truly difficult to
                                disregard human kindness, he squatted down right there by the
                                waterside and began to eat. He stopped short after three mouthfuls,
                                thanked the woman, and wanted to set forth at once. Again, he was
                                persuaded by the maiden to eat his fill.</p><p>Now more deeply
                                indebted than ever, he began to tell her of his cares. He answered
                                her thusly:</p><lg><l>'I am none other than Wu Zixu;</l><l>Escaping from Chu, I flee to Wu in the south.</l><l>Because I fear pursuit and capture by King Ping,</l><l>I travel at night over desolate roads.</l><l>Your gracious gift of a meal is more than enough to fill my
                                    hunger;</l><l>How will I ever be able to repay you?</l><l>My body has regained lightness and strength, my eyes
                                    brightness;</l><l>And so, taking leave of you, I wish to set out on my long
                                    road.</l><l>An exile cast out of his native place,</l><l>I am this very moment harried by King Ping.</l><l>Be so kind as not to let others know I have been here;</l><l>I pray you understand my feelings.</l></lg><lg><l>When Zixu had finished speaking, he went forward on his way;</l><l>The girl cried out bitterly and wept aloud:</l><l>'Wanderer so mournful, I truly worry for you,</l><l>Crawling in the face of death yet craving life.</l><l>You've had a meal from me but that seems not to be enough;</l><l>A woman cannot satisfy a hero's heart.</l><l>Although you solemnly rejected my offer,</l><l>The embarrassment which you have caused me is not light
                                    either.'</l></lg><p>She paused to restrain her sobbing and wipe her tears:</p><lg><l>'Your countenance has suddenly become haggard with care.</l><l>If, later on, you are taken by those who pursue you,</l><l>You will certainly say, "It was that woman who brought on my
                                    troubles."</l><l>"Thirty years old, never before having talked to a man",</l><l>I live together with my mother in our neighbourhood.</l><l>The graceful, charming glow of the face you see before you,</l><l>The faith and chasteness of a virtuous woman - all cast away in
                                    vain.</l><l>My Lord Wu,' she called out, 'do not doubt me!'</l><l>Then clasping a stone, she threw herself into the river and
                                    died.</l></lg><p>Zixu turned round and looked from afar; Having a fond regard for the
                                maiden, he was filled with sorrow. Far off, seeing her clasp the
                                heavy stone and leap to her death in the river, Involuntarily, he
                                cried out against this injustice.</p><lg><l>As the waters of the Ying relentlessly swallowed up her last
                                    traces,</l><l>Wu Zixu wept and, his grief doubled, sighed sadly:</l><l>'If, in the future, I should rise to high rank,</l><l>I will certainly give a hundred pieces of gold for her tomb.'</l></lg><p>When Zixu finished weeping, he resumed his forward progress. The wind
                                and dust seared his face; swirling dust darkened the sky. His nerves
                                strained to the breaking point, Wu Zixu suddenly reached a deep
                                river. Its waters were so deep they seemed to have no bottom and its
                                banks were so far apart it seemed to be endless.</p><p>He climbed
                                hills and entered valleys, following winding mountain streams to
                                their sources. When dragons and snakes blocked his way, he would
                                draw his sword and rush forward. When his path was full of tigers
                                and wolves, he would draw his bow at once. When hungry, he dined on
                                wild grasses midst reeds: thirsty, he supped from flowing springs
                                neath towering cliffs. A hero incensed and out for vengeance regards
                                death as but a sleep.</p><p>Suddenly, he came upon a house which
                                stood in a valley. He quickly knocked at the door and begged for
                                food. There was a woman who came to answer the door. Having
                                recognized from afar the sound of her brother's voice, she knew even
                                at a distance that it was Zixu. With concerned words and affection,
                                she comforted him and asked what trouble he was in. Zixu, his lips
                                sealed, spoke not a word. Realizing that her brother had been
                                thirsty and in want for a long time, she took a gourd which she
                                filled with rice and fixed, to go with it, a salad of bitter-tasting
                                endive and chicory.</p><p>Zixu was wise enough to apprehend what it
                                was his sister had in mind. Thinking carefully, he explained to
                                himself: 'The gourd filled with rice stands for bitterness within
                                and sweetness without; using chicory and endive for a salad is to
                                match bitterness with bitterness. Taken together, she must mean to
                                send me off at once. I'm to go away at once and cannot tarry
                                longer.'</p><p>And so he said goodbye and was about to leave when
                                his sister asked, 'Now that you are setting out again, where do you
                                intend to take recourse?'<p>'To the Kingdom of Yue,' answered Zixu.
                                    'Our brother and father have been murdered and I must avenge
                                    them.'</p>The sister embraced her brother's head and, not daring
                                to cry aloud, choked and sobbed until she was hoarse. 'Alas!' she
                                sighed as she threw herself on the ground and struck her breast.
                                'How painful! How cruel! What sins we must have committed in former
                                lives to have been thus orphaned and aggrieved!</p><lg><l>'Over the vast reaches of time, what sins were there,</l><l>That we should now be so ungrateful to our parents?</l><l>Although we, in our persons, may be wealthy and honoured,</l><l>Father in the south and son in the north, we are scattered.</l><l>Suddenly, I recall our father and older brother when they were
                                    alive,</l><l>And it causes every inch of my vitals to rend.</l><l>Today, my younger brother is going away, I know not where,</l><l>Leaving me here to bear my grief alone.</l><l>Now more than ever I am bereft of a place to devote my love;</l><l>Oh, would that I could bring an end to my existence!'</l></lg><p>Zixu took leave of his sister, saying,</p><lg><l>'Take good care of yourself.</l><l>There's no need to weep and streak your face with tears.</l><l>Our father and older brother have been unjustly slaughtered;</l><l>In my heart, a raging fire burns with intensity,</l><l>Today there is no place for a man of spirit beneath the sun!</l><l>The brave man's heart is knotted with deep and bitter
                                    resentment.</l><l>If the day should come that heaven open a way to me,</l><l>I swear I will catch King Ping of Chu alive-</l><l>Wrench out his heart, chop him to bits.</l><l>Wipe out his clan to the ninth degree.</l><l>If I do not accomplish all of this,</l><l>I swear I'll not return to my native place.'</l></lg><p>As soon as he had finished with these words, he set out towards
                                the south. He had walked a little more than twenty furlongs when his
                                eyes began to twitch and his ears to tingle, so he immediately drew
                                a diagram on the ground to make a divination and he saw by it that
                                his sister's sons were coming after him. He sprinkled water on his
                                head, inserted a piece of bamboo beneath his waistband, and put his
                                wooden shoes on backwards. He drew the diagrams for 'Earth's Door'
                                and 'Heaven's Gate' and then lay down in the rushes where he chanted
                                the following incantation:</p><lg><l>A plague upon him who catches me;</l><l>Death to him who pursues me; Swiftly,</l><l>swiftly, in has leges.'</l></lg><p>Zixu had two nephews, Zian and Ziyong. When they returned home, they
                                saw where someone had been eating and knew that it must have been
                                their uncle, Zixu. Disregarding the deep sympathy which their mother
                                held for him and with ill intent, they at once set out in hot
                                pursuit, thinking the while, 'If we gain audience with the Monarch
                                of Chu and receive a reward, we'll certainly be able to achieve high
                                rank. The rebel has come to our door today. There shouldn't be any
                                trouble catching him.'</p><p>When they had walked about ten
                                furlongs, they rested by the side of the road. Ziyong had a slight
                                understanding of yin-yang and so drew a diagram on the ground and
                                made a divination. It revealed their uncle had water on his head
                                which certainly meant that he had fallen by the side of the river;
                                there was a piece of bamboo at his waist which meant that his grave
                                was in a wild place; he wore his wooden shoes backwards which meant
                                that, wandering aimlessly, he was not making any forward
                                progress.</p><p>In accordance with these signs, they felt that he
                                must have died and so did not resume their search. 'There's no more
                                in it for us,' they said. 'Let's go back home.'</p><p>Zixu crouched
                                down to look at his magic markings and saw that his nephews had
                                broken off their pursuit. And so he ran on and on through the starry
                                night without stopping.</p><p>In a valley, once more he came upon a
                                house. Its walls were extraordinarily stately. As the farm stood off
                                by itself quite alone, there was no one anywhere around it. Not
                                ashamed of being such a big, husky fellow, he knocked at the gate
                                and begged for food.</p><p>Zixu knocked at the gate and proceeded to
                                beg for food;</p><lg><l>His wife took on a serious expression and came out to answer.</l><l>When she saw quite clearly that this was her own husband,</l><l>She wanted somehow to express that she recognized him.</l><l>But the wife stood there apart and carefully considered;</l><l>She dared not go forward - she dared not approach him.</l><l>Instead, with all proper civilities, she greeted her husband;</l><l>Her tearful voice choked with grief, she asked him politely:</l><l>'I dwell here in these wild and desolate confines;</l><l>Neighbourless on all four sides, alone I have settled.</l><l>From whence have you come, my good man, to this place,</l><l>Your face filled with sadness and a look of hunger?</l><l>Reduced to nervous trembling you seem frightened of someone;</l><l>You cringe and withdraw timidly while begging for food.</l><l>Although I have kept myself secluded in the fastness of my
                                    rooms,</l><l>You give me the vague impression of being familiar.'</l></lg><lg><l>'I am a man of Chu, sent to fill a distant mission;</l><l>Crossing hill after hill and dale after dale, I was returning
                                    home.</l><l>On the way I became lost and, as though in a stupor,</l><l>Wandered about until I unwittingly came to this place.</l><l>My native borders are far away at the western end of the sea;</l><l>Distant they are and separated by three great rivers.</l><l>Just now, I impulsively and rudely barged in on you;</l><l>It was really too rash of me, so I turn myself away.</l></lg><lg><l>'Milady is very forgetful and so has mistaken me;</l><l>Nor do I recall having ever met you, good lady, before.</l><l>Now I should like to set forth towards the east of the river,</l><l>And hope that you will be so kind as to point the way!'</l></lg><p>His wife then composed a poem with the names of medicines its theme
                                and, by means of it, asked him a series of questions:</p><lg><l>'I, Belladonna, am the wife of a man named Wahoo,</l><l>Who early became a mandrake in Liang.</l><l>Before our matrimony-vine could be consummated, he had to go
                                    back,</l><l>Leaving me, his wife, to dwell here ruefully alone. The mustard
                                    has not been cut, the flaxseed bed remains unvisited -</l><l>Hemlocked in here without any neighbours, I raised my head and
                                    sighed for my Traveller's Joy:</l><l>"Parsley, sage, rosemary, and thyme -</l><l>I "pray that he'll forget me not!"</l></lg><lg><l>Gingerly, I hoped, but I recently heard that the King of Chu,</l><l>Acting without principle and unleashing a bitterroot heart,</l><l>Slaughtered my pawpaw and brother-in-law with a jalap! jalap!</l><l>Clovered with shame, weak as a wisp of straw,</l><l>And arrowhead-swift, my husband fled with fear as a dog
                                    would.</l><l>Quick as a periwinkle, he became a fungative,</l><l>And hid amongst the stinkbushes;</l><l>But hiding became a hell-of-a-bore.</l><l>He seemed like a jackal pursued by horehounds;</l><l>Laudanum almighty, how he hopsed and hyssopped like a
                                    jackinthepulpit!</l><l>When I think of it, bittersweet tears stain my bleedingheart;</l><l>I am arti-choked with antimony.</l></lg><p>At nightshade when I sleep, it's hard to endure till the morning's
                                glory; I recite his name all day until my tongue curls up like a
                                sliver of cypress. His voice, begging balm, so ingenuous entered my
                                ears; Drawn by aniseedent causes, I dillied up to the visitor, And,
                                seeing it was my long orrised honeysuckle whom I mint at the gate,
                                Sloed down my steps to a hibiscus pace. And then I saw your
                                toothwort smile; It reminded me of my husband's dog's tooth violets.
                                Borax you don't remember me but, no madder what caper you're up to,
                                I'm willing to lay out my scurvy Butter and Eggs.'</p><p>Zixu
                                answered in the same cryptic vein:'Potash! Nitre am I this fellow
                                Wahoo whom you speak of, Nor am I a fungative from injustice. Listen
                                while I tell you the currant of my travels. I was born in Castoria
                                and grew up in Betony Wood; My father was a Scorpio, my mother a
                                true Lily-of-the-valley. Gathering up all of my goldenrod and
                                silverweed, This son of theirs became a Robin-Run-Around. Rose Hips
                                was my low-class companion, Nelson Rockyfeldspar my uppercrust
                                chum.</p><p>Together with them, I waded Wild Ginger Creek, And
                                caught cold in its squilling, wintergreen waters; Saifronly, of the
                                three of us, I found myself alone. Day after day, my lotus-thread
                                hopes dangled tenuously; My thoughts were willows waving in the
                                wind. All alone, I climbed Witch Hazel Mountain; How hard it was to
                                cross the slippery elms and stone roots! Cliffs towering above me, I
                                clambered over stoneworts and rockweeds; Often did I encounter
                                wolfsbanes and tiger thistles. Sometimes I would be thinking of soft
                                spring beauties, But suddenly would meet up with a bunch of
                                pigsheads; My thoughts would linger over mid-summer vetches, Yet I
                                could never see an end to my tormentils. So I reversed my steps,
                                feeling compelled to spurry back; Fennelly, I arrived here. I grow
                                goatsbeard, Not dog's tooth violets. Methinks you've scratched a
                                fenugreek but found no tartar, So furze tell me what you mean and
                                don't make such a rhubarb.'</p><lg><l>The wife then replied: 'Do not be in such a hurry, for your road
                                    is a long and distant one.</l><l>'And even supposing we have never before met,</l><l>What harm is there in my mistaken identification?</l><l>I am a daughter of the wealthy Gongsun family;</l><l>Fittingly matched with a gentleman, I served him faithfully.</l><l>My husband, surnamed Wu, held a high position in government;</l><l>As a young man, he traveled a thousand miles to serve his Lord,
                                    the King.</l><l>From the time he left, he sent no letter, not even a word;</l><l>Thinking of him, my heart grows so sad that I nearly expire.</l><l>The way is long and dark - I feel so isolated and forlorn;</l><l>I am not used to being separated for such a long time.</l><l>My once rosy cheeks have lost their former hue - how haggard and
                                    wan they are;</l><l>Fondly I recall him, but the tears, oh when have they ever
                                    stopped?</l><l>So many years thrown away in vain, keeping watch in these empty
                                    rooms,</l><l>Who could survive again the beauteousness, the fragrance of
                                    Spring?</l><l>Day and night, the damsel in her tower feels charm's glow
                                    fading;</l><l>And it's all because her wandering man is serving in Liang.</l><l>Languidly, she goes to the front of the courtyard to gaze at the
                                    moon;</l><l>Then, full of sorrow, returns to her bed to embrace the marriage
                                    pillows.</l></lg><lg><l>Even a message by carrier pigeon would still not get through;</l><l>The frontiers on the horizon are separated by a long, long
                                    road.</l><l>She tries to weave at her broken loom but feels too
                                    disheartened;</l><l>Her painted brows are embarrassed to face the dresser mirror.</l><l>She dotes on the chattering magpies in the grape arbour,</l><l>And cherishes the pair of swallows which roost in the white jade
                                    hall.</l><l>You, in not' recognizing me, are behaving like Qiu Hu;</l><l>And I, unwillingly, play the role of his neglected wife.</l><l>Seeing in your mouth that set of beautiful teeth,</l><l>I feel quite certain that I know from this who you are.</l><l>Never would I grudge you a meal, coarse fare though it be;</l><l>I hope that you will stop here a moment - be not so hurried.'</l></lg><lg><l>Having been recognized, Zixu declined her offer,</l><l>With deceitful, wily words, he evaded her thusly:</l><l>'Don't, my lady, recklessly interfere in my affairs,</l><l>There are many men who resemble each other.</l><l>Your husband's surname is Wu and he occupies high office.</l><l>I come from a poor family and dwell on the grassy plains.</l><l>If I should happen to meet your husband, I'll pass on the
                                    word,</l><l>And, with reason, will exhort him to return to his home.</l><l>Now, because I have urgent business, I must go east of the
                                    river;</l><l>I cannot tarry here with you another day or night.'</l></lg><p>His wife realized he was planning some important undertaking and so
                                did not dare further disturb him. According to custom, she gave him
                                provisions and saw him off, as was proper.</p><p>Zixu, having been
                                recognized by his wife, said no more. 'I am a man,' he thought, 'but
                                before I had reached my goal, was recognized by this woman. Yet can
                                I allow such a small matter to defeat me in the performance of this
                                great duty of mine?' And so, hero that he was, Wu Zixu carried a
                                stone as he walked and, with it, knocked out his teeth.</p><p>By
                                day, he was guided by the sun and at night by the stars. He ran on
                                without stopping until he came to the north bank of the River Wu.
                                Afraid that there might be someone concealed there, he slunk
                                stealthily among the reeds. Hand resting on his sword, he sighed as
                                he sang this sad song:</p><lg><l>'Vast are the river's waters - its waves rise up and up,</l><l>To the sky they boil - or sink lower and lower.</l><l>The flying sand is so dense that it covers up the Milky Way;</l><l>The chill wind whips up the waves and howls destructively through
                                    the forest.</l><l>White grasses cover the vast expanse of wild fields and
                                    plains;</l><l>Green willows stand in lines droopingly on both sides of the
                                    river.</l><l>Crows and magpies intermingle as they peck about for food;</l><l>Fishes and dragons jump here and leap there in grand
                                    disarray,</l><l>Otters sport in the water and hold playful contests of speed.</l><l>A thousand times over, I involuntarily sigh;</l><l>Suddenly recalling the unjust slaughter of my father and
                                    brother,</l><l>I at once feel a burning pain in my heart and bowels.</l><l>Thinking of my sworn hatred, I gasp with pain and sorrow:</l><l>Though we meet today, I would make no renunciation.</l><l>My life may well end in the deep waters of this river;</l><l>Whether I live or die all depends on what happens tonight.</l><l>I do not shirk the thought that my bones may sink in these
                                    waves;</l><l>The oath of vengeance for my father and brother must never be
                                    broken.</l><l>There is always the wind by which the firmament bends the
                                    grasses;</l><l>And, still yet, the mighty transforming power of all the
                                    deities.'</l></lg><p>When his sad song was ended, he walked to the edge of the river and
                                gazed into the distance. All he could see was the broad expanse of
                                its waters; how could he ever get across it? He stretched his neck
                                out from amidst the reeds and, turning his head from side to side,
                                saw that all was silent. His eye met no one out sailing in a boat
                                nor was there anyone on a raft. All he could see were river crows
                                starting out from the banks and egrets contesting in flight, fishes
                                and turtles crisscrossing the surface, cormorants and wild swans
                                gliding about in profusion. He saw, too, long islands here and there
                                on the vast breadth of the river, waves spreading across its coves,
                                dark mists rising, black clouds descending. Trees pressed close upon
                                the worn banks, the moon shone upon a solitary peak. Dragons
                                trembled and turtles were startled; globe-fish stirred up
                                ripples.</p><p>If one has strayed from his native place, he climbs a
                                high mountain and thinks of home; a traveller on a raft guides
                                himself by Orion and Lucifer. Wu Zixu spent one night on Min
                                Mountain seeming as a tiger or wolf prowling around. The river
                                rushed by, sounding like drums beating and horns blaring, but there
                                was not a single boat in which to cross it. He had passed two
                                further nights there hiding amidst the reeds when, at last, he saw
                                someone on the waves. He was singing a ballad as he plied his oars.
                                In his hand, he held a reel and hook and was evidently a fisherman.
                                Wu Zixu emerged from the reeds and called out to him: 'You there in
                                the boat, sir, holding the fishing hook! May I trouble you for a
                                moment to come to the bank so that I may have a word with you?
                                Please do not turn from this trouble. I would be most grateful if
                                you would be so kind as to pay me some heed.'</p><p>The fisherman,
                                hearing him call, right away tried to find where the voice was
                                coming from. Suddenly, a man appeared out of the reeds and so he at
                                once rowed his boat to the shore. He reeled in his line and - no
                                longer paddling or poling - let the boat drift along on the current.
                                As he rocked to and fro, the fisherman sang 'Soothing Breezes',
                                using it to ask a series of questions:</p><lg><l>'Where is it you wish to go today, my good man? On the distant
                                    shores and inlets of this river, I see no other travellers in
                                    boats;</l><l>Nor do you have any companions, so lonely you are.</l><l>Perhaps you are like drifting tumbleweed,</l><l>Stranded here alone on these desolate islets and shores?</l><l>If you're hunting for a boat or ferry,</l><l>You won't find any at all in this place.</l><l>But if you're not put off by my rudeness,</l><l>I request that you tell me fully what's on your mind.'</l></lg><p>I have heard,' answered Wu Zixu, 'that "men may know each other
                                through virtue and learning just as fish look towards each other in
                                the rivers and lakes." Your humble servant is a traveler. Dare I
                                vainly think up words of deception? Because of a small matter which
                                must be attended to promptly, I need to make my way south of the
                                river. As a person, I am rather inept but I do hope, sir, that I
                                will have the good fortune to receive your understanding. If you
                                will be so kind as to ferry me across the river, my gratitude would
                                be so great that I would even give my life for you. If you cannot
                                agree to this, I will naturally give up the idea
                                altogether.'</p><p>'Just now,' said the fisherman, 'as I scrutinized
                                your face and examined your appearance, I observed that you were
                                different from the ordinary sort of person. I can tell what is on
                                your mind; you need not further clarify yourself. I have heard that
                                "he who can distinguish between good and bad men is himself not base
                                and he who can distinguish between good and bad jade shall not be
                                wanting"; "Duke Mu of Qin prompted gratitude with his gift of wine";
                                "the one who was eloquent gained sole command of the three armies";
                                "he who presented an empty cage received a bounteous reward". I see
                                that you have been distressed for many days and that you have been
                                thirsty and in want for a long time. You cannot cross the river on
                                an empty stomach. Allow me to fix a meal for you. The trip from here
                                to my house and back is a little over ten furlongs. It may take me a
                                while to return, so please don't be suspicious.'</p><p>'All that I
                                seek,' said Wu Zixu, 'is a boat to ferry me across the river. I
                                wouldn't dare expect any food!' 'I have heard,' replied the
                                fisherman, 'that "the unicorn, when it gets food, can travel a
                                thousand miles in a day; the phoenix, when it gets food, can soar
                                across the four seas".' He had scarcely finished these words when he
                                beached his boat and set out towards his house to get some food.
                                Zixu had heard what the fisherman said and so watched the boat for
                                him. But he reflected to himself, 'This man told me that he was
                                going home to get some food but I wonder whether he might well not
                                have gone to call someone to come and arrest me.' So he abandoned
                                the boat, went over to the reeds, and hid among them.</p><p>In no
                                time at all, the fisherman returned to where the boat was. He
                                brought with him a jug of fine wine, five catties of fish, ten thin
                                pancakes, and was carrying a container of rice. When he got to where
                                the boat was, the gentleman of the reeds was nowhere to be seen.
                                There was only the empty boat which had been drawn up on the shore.
                                The affectionate regard in which he held Wu Zixu caused the
                                fisherman to feel deep disappointment at this and so he called with
                                a song:</p><lg><l>'Oh, gentleman of the reeds!</l><l>Why have you gone into hiding?</l><l>Come out here so I can have a look at you;</l><l>After all, I don't have any bad intentions.</l><l>There's no need to doubt or worry;</l><l>Don't make things doubly difficult. I have brought back a meal
                                    expressly for you;</l><l>Why don't you come over here and eat it?'</l></lg><p>When Wu Zixu heard the boatman speak these words, he knew that he was
                                not ill-intentioned and so came out from the reeds. He was
                                embarrassed by the trouble he had put the man to in going to get the
                                food, so he went forward to meet him and offered his humble
                                apologies. Thereupon, they spread out the meal, and the two of them
                                ate together. The fisherman then struck up the oars at once and
                                rowed out as far as the middle of the river. Zixu, having had his
                                fill, thought to himself: ' "Whoever receives one meal from another,
                                is indebted to him to that extent; whoever receives two meals from
                                another must exert himself on his behalf."'</p><p>So he presented
                                the jade disc which he carried in his bosom to the boatman. The
                                latter, worried that dusk was coming on and anxious to go forward,
                                would not accept the gift. Zixu was worried that the fisherman may
                                have considered this token of his gratitude as being too little and
                                so took off his precious sword and offered it, too, as
                                recompense.</p><p>The fisherman stopped rowing and, turning around,
                                answered him: 'Don't be so rash! You really ought to think it over
                                carefully. How could the small favour of a single meal be worth so
                                much? Men in trouble,though they be as different as fish are from
                                turtles, flock together; when the going is rough, people as
                                different as dragons are from snakes willingly cohabit. The King of
                                Chu is out to get you and the one who succeeds in capturing you will
                                be rewarded with a thousand pieces of gold. Anyone who harbours you
                                will be executed and his family annihilated.</p><p>In the first
                                place, I am not greedy for the heavy reward the Sovereign is
                                offering. And, in the second place, I do not run from the
                                possibility of being sentenced and executed. You wish to present
                                your precious sword to me, but how could even it be a match for what
                                King Ping has to offer? Keep your precious Excalibur to protect
                                yourself, and your jade disc from Jhing which will serve to fulfil
                                what you hold dear. Later on, if you should rise to high place and
                                attain great wealth, do not forget that we once met. I rebuke myself
                                for having grown old so early and for having met you so late. As for
                                the matter of the sword and jade disc, please do not again try to
                                leave them with me. If you wish to vindicate my sentiments, it will
                                not be necessary for me to refuse your offer again.'</p><p>When Zixu
                                saw that the man would not accept his gifts, he began to feel
                                increasingly uncomfortable. 'I am afraid,' he thought to himself,
                                'that the boatman belittles these tokens of my gratitude because
                                they are too poor and too few. And that, even though they are
                                precious things worthy of a lord or king. What more can I do?' Then
                                he threw the sword into the river. It shot forth a spirit-like glow,
                                sparkling brightly as it thrice sank and thrice came to the surface
                                with a great gush and then hovered above the water. The god of the
                                river far off heard the sword's roar and, tremulously, he roiled the
                                waters in a great and frothing frenzy. The fish and turtles were
                                thrown into a panic and burrowed into the mud. Dragons raced along
                                the waves and leaped out of the water. The river god held up the
                                sword in his hand and, frightened, told Wu Zixu to take it
                                back</p><p>After the sword had left the water, the fish and turtles
                                began to skitter about again. All was as bright and pure as the rays
                                of the sun and moon; the mountains and forests glistened. The clouds
                                parted, and the river fog lifted; mists scattered, and the vapours
                                rolled back. The trees along the bank seemed to have lined up to
                                welcome a visitor, the river wind to be seeing off a guest. One
                                could see, far off, egrets standing beside sand bars in the fading
                                evening light, and making ready to return to their nests in the
                                forest. Along the river banks, there were no boats for hire to be
                                seen. Out on the water, there were no companions for our two
                                passengers. All that was visible was a solitary mountain across a
                                vast expanse of water.</p><p>Wu Zixu turned back to gaze at his
                                homeland and, wiping away the tears which dampened his shirt, felt
                                deeply disturbed at heart. They had crossed the better part of the
                                river and were about to reach the south bank so Wu Zixu inquired of
                                the boatman: 'What is your surname and name? In what province and
                                district is your native village?' 'I have neither surname nor name,'
                                answered the fisherman, 'and have long lived here with the river my
                                only companion. I pole across the quiet shores and tie up my boat in
                                deep pools. Today, two outlaws meet -what need is there to speak of
                                names? You, sir, are the Gentleman of the Reeds and I the Man in the
                                Boat - that is all we need know about each other. When you become
                                wealthy and honoured, you must not forget me.' 'There will never be
                                a time when I shall forget this aid which I have received from you,'
                                said Wu Zixu. ' "Even a wounded snake which is treated with medicine
                                can repay its benefactor!"'</p><p>'When you continue your flight
                                today,' asked the fisherman, 'in which kingdom do you intend to seek
                                    refuge?'<p>'I intend to seek refuge in the Kingdom of Yue,'
                                    answered Zixu.</p><p>'So you're going to Yue -,' the fisherman
                                    said. 'The Kingdom of Yue and Chu get along well with each other
                                    and have never been engaged in military conflict. I am afraid
                                    that if you go there, they will arrest you and extradite you to
                                    Chu so the vengeance which you hold in your heart would never be
                                    achieved. But if you take refuge in the Kingdom of Wu, the
                                    sailing would certainly be much smoother. The King of Wu has
                                    constantly been at odds with Chu. The two kingdoms do not get
                                    along well together. Wu has had numerous campaigns against the
                                    Kingdom of Chu and, furthermore, has no able ministers.
                                    Obtaining your services would be extremely important for
                                    them.'</p><p>'How can I get the Kingdom of Wu to accept my
                                    allegiance?' Wu Zixu asked the boatman.</p><p>'When you get to
                                    the Kingdom of Wu,' said the boatman, 'enter the market place of
                                    the capital, daub your face with mud, and make your hair
                                    dishevelled like that of a wild man. Then go running swiftly,
                                    now to the east now to the west, and cry loudly three
                                    times.'</p><p>'Please be so kind,' said Zixu, 'as to explain all
                                    this.'</p>'Daubing mud on your face,' said the boatman, 'means
                                that, though you are defiled without, you are pure within. Crying
                                loudly three times and running swiftly east and west means that you
                                seek an enlightened ruler. Standing in the market place with your
                                hair dishevelled then makes sense, does it not? Though not a sage, I
                                have had a lot of experience.'</p><p>Zixu received his instructions
                                and bowed gratefully to the fisherman. Fearing that he might meet up
                                with the Chu envoys, he could not remain there any longer but set
                                out as soon as they reached the shore. After they parted, he sobbed
                                until he was hoarse. It was like 'the four fledglings each flying
                                their own way' or 'the three thorns being separated'. Thus he left
                                the fisherman and went towards the south. But, because of his tender
                                regard for the fisherman, Wu Zixu's grief was unceasing. As he
                                turned his head to look back across the distance, he suddenly saw
                                the fisherman overturn his boat and die. Conscience-stricken by this
                                final favour of the fisherman, Wu Zixu sobbed and 780 wept
                                mournfully without cease and then sang this sad lament:</p><lg><l>'The great river's waters, oh, they stretch on and on without
                                    end;</l><l>The clouds and waters, oh, they seem to join together!</l><l>How painful! How very painful! 'Tis difficult to endure.</l><l>How bitter! How very bitter! Injustice upon injustice!</l><l>From of old, leavetaking has been a part of human existence;</l><l>Life, death, wealth, and honour are all dependent on heaven.</l><l>What have I done to make my teacher hold such resentment against
                                    me,</l><l>That he should capsize his boat in the middle of the river?</l><l>His boat bobs up and down on the waves and then sinks beneath
                                    them;</l><l>I sing of the wrong he suffers - how keen and deep the pain
                                    is!</l><l>It is as though my sad heart were being sliced in pieces by a
                                    sword:</l><l>As I go on my way, I cannot suppress the tears which stain my
                                    collar.</l><l>I look towards Wu but, alas, I cannot reach there;</l><l>I think of my native kingdom and my heart is filled with
                                    grief.</l><l>But if I meet a wise ruler, garnering rank and success,</l><l>I will display to the full this hero's heart of mine!'</l></lg><p>His sad song finished, Wu Zixu once again resumed his forward
                                journey, all the while sick at heart. Now that our hero was
                                isolated, how greatly did he falter! He had served his ruler
                                faithfully and truly for nine years. He had been lax neither in the
                                morning nor at night. In paying his morning respects, he was never
                                remiss. Now that he had encountered such ill-luck, he knew of no
                                words further to express his feelings. The anger in his heart which
                                speech could not convey welled up in his throat. Such was his karma,
                                such his fate - and both depended on heaven.</p><p>Wu Zixu climbed
                                mountains and sprang over ridges, crossed rivers and followed
                                streams. He sought to go forward, but often his way was blocked. And
                                going back, of course, was out of the question. Hungered by his
                                exertions, he felt his life in a whirl. 'King Ping,' he cried out,
                                aggrieved, 'you are too cruel!'</p><p>His sword in hand, Wu Zixu
                                walked on and on until he came to some wild and desolate mountains.
                                There, the rock walls shot ten thousand feet into the sky. A tangled
                                mass of bamboos and creepers interpenetrated the earth. Far off, he
                                saw dodder hanging from the pines on the mountains with their dark,
                                steep cliffs. Wolves and tigers came and went, and hundreds of birds
                                filled the air with chirping. Thinking of his native land, Wu Zixu
                                sang this song:</p><lg><l>'What weighs on my mind is how long, oh, how long the road
                                    is;</l><l>Crossing rivers and lakes, I shall enter the domain of Wu.</l><l>My father and brother among the shades, I know not where;</l><l>Alone, and plagued by anxiety, I have been chased away.</l><l>A wandering hero am I who follows his karmic fate;</l><l>Life and death, riches and honour - all of these are
                                    inconstant.</l><l>King Ping perversely accepted the words of Wei Ling,</l><l>Trusted a slanderous flatterer, struck down the honest and
                                    true.</l><l>Thoughts of my homeland, oh, bring grief which is hard to
                                    forestall;</l><l>Facing rivers or climbing mountains, my passions are without
                                    let.</l><l>The ruler of Chu has a penchant for buxom grace and narrow
                                    waists;</l><l>Inside his palaces, many beauties are starving to death.</l><l>The daughter of Duke Mu of Qin has a face that is like jade;</l><l>Sweet sixteen she is - her face glows soft as a peach, bright as
                                    a plum.</l><l>When he beheld her beauty, he took her in as his concubine;</l><l>Is this any way for a lord and ruler of men to behave?</l><l>Since fleeing, I have felt constant sorrow in my heart;</l><l>I have been left alone and without any recourse.</l><l>To travel by day would be like seeking a way to ghosthood,</l><l>So I step in shadows or hide: but I range the whole night
                                    long.</l><l>When shall my deeds be inscribed in stone on Mount Yan?</l><l>Until then, my temples greying, I forge through dust and
                                    brambles.</l><l>I fear nor east nor west nor to resist great cold -</l><l>Only thirst, fatigue, and the passage of wild places.</l><l>Would that I could safely attain the goal which lies ahead;</l><l>May my path be not impeded but flow freely as a brook.</l><l>If, in the Kingdom of Wu, I meet a wise ruler,</l><l>I shall raise an army and, posthaste, behead Wei Ling.'</l></lg><p>His sad song finished and his heart filled with heroic passion, he
                                turned his back on the Qu passes to the north and began climbing
                                south towards Kuai Ji Mountain in Wu. It so happened that he came
                                upon a day when the sky was dark, full of clouds black as pitch. He
                                strayed from the road and went running back and forth trying to find
                                it, but the mountain forests compelled him to halt. Flocks of
                                strange birds milled about, wolf packs and bands of tigers prowled
                                everywhere. The birds cried raucously and the beasts roared angrily.
                                Suddenly, the fear in his heart clearly evident, he pulled out his
                                sword and went forward.</p><lg><l>From out of its sheath, light springs forth;</l><l>Filling the wild with a spirit-glow.</l><l>It holds within the moon and sun,</l><l>The Dipper and its seven stars.</l><l>The hero's heart burns with sorrow;</l><l>A thousand soldiers he shall not fear!</l><l>Should King Ping ever capture me -</l><l>My mission not yet brought to rest -</l><l>Or if I should be arrested,</l><l>A hundred to one I shall die.</l><l>Stealthy my steps, cautious my tread -</l><l>I hold my breath and keep silence.</l><l>The wind blows and stirs the grasses,</l><l>Swiftly I go into hiding.</l></lg><p>His sword song completed, Wu Zixu again went forward. North, he
                                crossed Guang Ling and south he climbed Kuai Ji. The passes and
                                fords were closely watched. The provinces and districts increased
                                their surveillance. Militiamen were everywhere and there were
                                continual replacements of guards. Keeping himself carefully hidden,
                                he went forward a step at a time.</p><p>Before many days had gone
                                by, he reached the Kingdom of Wu. In exact accordance with the
                                instructions of the fisherman, he dishevelled his hair and entered
                                the market place, daubed mud on his face, cried wildly three loud
                                shouts, and went running swiftly east and west. At that moment, a
                                minister of the Kingdom of Wu happened to be riding through the
                                marketplace on horseback. He noticed Wu Zixu's extraordinary
                                appearance and unusual gifts as well as his six-foot frame and,
                                knowing that he would make a worthy minister, went running to inform
                                the King of Wu. 'Just after leaving your august presence,' he said,
                                I was passing through the market and there I saw a gentleman from
                                another land. His face was smeared with mud and he appeared wild;
                                his hair was dishevelled and he cried out pitifully as he ran back
                                and forth from east to west. I looked on from the side, examining
                                him closely. From my scrutiny of his appearance, I am convinced of
                                his worth. I should hope that Your Majesty inquire into the matter
                                thoroughly and have him detained. He must certainly be a
                                knight-errant who harbours an injustice.'</p><p>When the King of Wu
                                heard these words, he was pleased and, gathering together his
                                ministers, opened his pearl curtains, and spoke of his dream: 'Last
                                night at the third watch, I dreamed that I saw a worthy man entering
                                my realm upon which my body grew light and my person grew strong so
                                that I could not prevent myself jumping about with joy. Would you,
                                my ministers, carefully discuss this and explain for me whether it
                                portends ill or good?'</p><p>When the hundred officials heard these
                                words of the King, they danced and laughed gleefully all at the same
                                time. 'Peace!' they sang out together. 'Long live the King!' they
                                exclaimed with one voice. 'The dream shows that the six-foot
                                gentleman in the market place is superbly fitted to your heart. All
                                of your ministers who are present are overcome with joy.'</p><p>The
                                King of Wu forthwith ordered an express messenger to go into the
                                market place and summon this worthy minister-to-be. 'Inform him on
                                my behalf,' said the King, 'that although I have not previously been
                                acquainted with him, I do wish to meet him and that, when he sees me
                                face-to-face, he may express his ambitions.'</p><p>As soon as the
                                messenger received these verbal orders, he galloped directly into
                                the market place. There he saw Wu Zixu and repeated to him entirely
                                the verbal orders of the King of Wu. Zixu respectfully received the
                                King's mandate and, not daring disobediently to delay, immediately
                                followed the messenger. When they reached the King of Wu's palace,
                                Wu Zixu went down with his face to the ground. He sobbed and moaned
                                until his voice became hoarse and it was long before he rose. The
                                King of Wu knew that it was Zixu and sympathetically inquired of
                                him: "The King of Chu did not accept loyal admonishment but
                                perversely listened to the words of a sycophantic minister. He
                                unjustly murdered your father and brother. How could he be so
                                bitterly cruel? The sorrow which he caused is beyond description.
                                Such awful pain! Who could have borne it? For you to have crossed
                                mountain walls and river barriers and to have plodded long distances
                                through wind and cloud to come so far to such a small and narrow
                                kingdom as my own must have caused you great suffering.'</p><p>Zixu
                                waited for quite a while and then, smoothing down his hair, spoke:
                                'Your servant's father and brother were not attentive in the service
                                of their lord and so they were executed by the monarch of Chu. And
                                I, instead of continuing the family traditions, abandoned my father
                                and left my ruler to flee as fast as I could run. I have heard that,
                                "when a kingdom is about to perish, calamities and disasters occur
                                in great profusion just as when a tree is on the verge of snapping,
                                wind and frost press upon it". He who is destitute finds it
                                difficult to stand firm. Faced with such distressing circumstances,
                                I was unable to distinguish black from white; snake and dragon
                                became hopelessly confused. I wished to cut my throat and die but
                                was ashamed to see my ancestors in the nether world. Therefore, I
                                have placed myself in the hands of a wise ruler like yourself in the
                                hopes that you might understand the workings of my heart. Having
                                grown up in a humble house and dwelling in the grassy wild, I am
                                incapable of serving or supporting a ruler. It would be my great
                                fortune to be accepted on your rolls!'</p><p>'My kingdom,' replied
                                the King of Wu, 'is of narrow compass and is lacking loyal and
                                honest men. In wishing to establish you as a minister, I realize
                                that this is to compromise your integrity. But I hope you will not
                                feel that it is something disgraceful.'</p><p>'I am a small person,'
                                said Zixu, 'an unworthy recipient of your great favour. To be
                                accepted on your rolls is already an exceptional act of kindness
                                bestowed upon me. But further to be raised to office is something I
                                dare not, in the end, accept. To do so would be to incur the death
                                penalty for my presumption!'</p><p>'What do you think?' the King of
                                Wu asked those to his left and right. All of the ranks of ministers
                                sang out their approval, saying, 'Your Majesty has such great
                                influence that even this man from another land has placed himself at
                                your disposal. Make him your helpmate and Minister of State and the
                                entire country will exclaim together: "Long live the
                                King!'"</p><p>As a minister, Zixu showed determination and moral
                                fortitude. Never was he lax in his thinking. Morning and night he
                                strove, single-mindedly serving his ruler all the while. His speech
                                was not offensive; his words were informed with agreeableness. Men
                                came to him in great numbers from far and near, talented officials
                                appeared in abundance. Heaven's soldiers were not mobilized, and the
                                war horses' whips were stayed. Those on the four borders all showed
                                their allegiance, all the eight directions were settled and
                                submissive. No man-made disasters occurred, no natural calamities
                                arose. The people were joyful and sang songs along every road just
                                as in the time of Yao and Shun. Everyone proclaimed: 'Our ruler is
                                possessed of a benign influence. Lofty is the sacred sun, revivified
                                are heaven and earth!'</p><p>After Zixu had governed the country for
                                one year, the wind blew so softly that it scarcely rustled the
                                branches and the rain fell so gently that it broke not the clods of
                                earth. After he had governed the country for two years, the
                                granaries over-flowed with abundance. All under heaven was peace and
                                prosperity. Clerks gave up their greed for pelf, officials left off
                                their tyrannous ways.</p><p>When he had ruled the country for three
                                years, the six barbarians expressed friendliness, and the ten
                                thousand principalities all threw in their lot with Wu. After he had
                                governed the country for four years, the Dragon of Good Prospect
                                visited the land in answer to the auspiciousness of the day and the
                                Red Sparrow came carrying in its beak a letter. Spirit-fungi grew
                                side by side while portentous grain grew multiple spikes. Ploughmen
                                gave way over questions regarding where to lay the boundary lines
                                between fields. And no one picked up articles which had been lost by
                                others on the highways. The three teachings flourished side by side
                                and the city-gates never had to be closed. There were no more
                                summonses or forced labour: people worked for themselves.</p><p>When
                                Zixu had governed the country for five years, the sun and moon
                                doubled their brilliance. In the markets, there were fixed prices.
                                Cats and mice lived together in the same holes. Rice and wheat were
                                carefully weighed out to the last hundredth of an ounce and the
                                jails had no prisoners. Everyone vied to proclaim the harmony of
                                ideals between the King and his minister. Their praise spread far
                                and near.</p><p>Indebted to the Minister Wu Zixu for his
                                achievements, the common people all visited his gate and announced:
                                'We wish, on behalf of Minister Wu, to wage war upon
                                Chu.'</p><p>Seeing all of these brave men voluntarily enlist, Zixu
                                did not dare to make them his private preserve. Instead, he informed
                                the King of Wu: I am but a small person who has been the recipient
                                of your bountiful favours. Before I have established any merit, how
                                dare I let ambition stir my heart? I consider that I am of no
                                ability and so, when all is said and done, dare not be
                                presumptuous.'</p><p>I have heard,' replied the King of Wu, 'that
                                "one prepares for old age by bringing up a child and anticipates the
                                time when one will be decrepit by accumulating good deeds". Last
                                year I had thought to commission you to carry out your vengeance but
                                was concerned that the spirit of vengeance had not yet sufficiently
                                developed in you. The peace and prosperity of these years are all a
                                result of your efforts. If you do not now avenge the wrong done to
                                your father and brother, how can you be called a filial son? The
                                time is perfect for our kingdom to raise troops and attack
                                Chu.'</p><p>And so the King issued a mandate which called for all
                                the brave men in the land to help Minister Wu wreak his vengeance.
                                The text of the mandate read as follows: 'Whereas the father and
                                brother of Minister Wu were wilfully slaughtered by King Ping, it is
                                our desire today [19] to levy an army which has heaven on its side
                                for the purpose of punishing Chu and we do thereby call upon our
                                devoted subjects to enlist in this venture. If there be among you
                                any who will risk his life by following the army into battle, he
                                should come to enlist with the greatest urgency. We shall, at the
                                outset, present heavy rewards. The decorations and emoluments
                                conferred will not be light. If there are any such brave and valiant
                                men, come quickly and present your responses to this our
                                plea!'</p><p>Once the mandate had been issued and made known to all
                                those far and near, they came severally to sign up, competing with
                                one another to be the first to respond to the call. The War Office
                                selected, screened, picked, tested, examined, and measured until it
                                had come up with a superior fighting force that could decisively
                                conquer at a distance of a thousand miles. Among its men, there were
                                those capable of bending the bar of a door, tossing timber about,
                                picking up huge square beams with their hands, jumping high in the
                                air while clasping heavy stones, and shooting an arrow through seven
                                layers of armour.</p><p>After the proclamation had been displayed
                                for seven days, 900,000 crack troops were enlisted. Rewards of
                                crimson silk and inducements of green silk were made, each being
                                presented in lots of one thousand bolts. The recruiting officials
                                led them outside the city-wall where the ranks were made to stand as
                                straight as a formation of wild geese. The King of Wu then saw his
                                soldiers lined up south of the city and proceeded at once to
                                entertain and cheer these brave warriors.<p>'Today,' he inquired of
                                    Wu Zixu, 'we wish to attack Chu. How many soldiers should we
                                    use?'</p><p>'For the present, we'll need ten thousand soldiers,'
                                    was Zixu 's answer.</p><p>'Won't ten thousand soldiers be too
                                    few?' asked the King.</p><p>'I have heard,' replied Zixu, 'that
                                    "when a man is determined to die, a hundred others are no match
                                    for him. And, if one hundred work -together with one mind, they
                                    range at will anywhere under heaven."</p>' I feel otherwise,'
                                said the King of Wu. 'Only if you lead 900,000 men will you be able
                                to attack Chu.'</p><p>The King of Wu then established Wu Zixu as the
                                Generalissimo and Commander of the Army, as well as Chief of
                                Mobilization. In accordance with the precepts of the Son of Heaven,
                                he was to avenge his father by wiping clean the injustice he had
                                suffered.</p><p>Thereupon, there was a mass slaughter of cattle and
                                sheep and a feast was set up south of the city. There were a
                                thousand casks of wine and ten thousand catties of meat. It was all
                                divided equally, there being no rank when it came to eating. The
                                King of Wu went outside the city-wall to send Wu Zixu off. 'Sir, you
                                need only do your best,' said the King, 'and be cautious on your
                                forward march. With heaven's mercy, you will certainly be able to
                                carry out the vengeance you hold in your heart. Furthermore, I have
                                nothing to worry about in my kingdom. So you, sir, should not fail
                                the souls of your father and brother in Hades. Return promptly as
                                soon as your business is completed. Do not give me cause for
                                concern.'</p><p>'Today,' Wu Zixu replied to the King of Wu, 'as I
                                lead this army on a punitive expedition against Chu, there is no
                                doubt but that the result will be a gratifying one. I should hope
                                that Your Majesty will not worry and fret over me on my distant
                                journey. I expect that, before much time has passed, the affair will
                                be completed and I shall return with the army. For this, I shall be
                                grateful unto death!'</p><p>When Wu Zixu had finished his farewell
                                to the King, he launched the troops at once. The sound of forty-two
                                large drums rumbled across the sky, the strident blare of thirty-six
                                horns swept the earth. For a hundred furlongs to the side, the
                                mountain forests shook with the creaking and rumbling of heavy carts
                                and horses.</p><p>The vanguard, whose role was to take prisoners
                                alive, was the first to take to the road. Like clouds, the formation
                                spread out in all four directions, making a sound which carried
                                across the whole of the wild, open plains. The powerful cavalry
                                charged ahead pell-mell; the brave soldiers leaped forward
                                ferociously. By leaps and bounds, they had soon gone a thousand
                                furlongs, looking like so many scales on a fish. Rank after rank
                                they came, like the wings of wild geese. Lined up shoulder to
                                shoulder, their long lances stood as erect as a forest of trees
                                piercing through heaven. Restlessly, they strung their bows - palm
                                next to palm - and bent them till they arched like crescent moons.
                                White banners fluttered like falling snow and the battle swords
                                glistened like frost. When their crossbows were released, thunder
                                raced across the sky. When they pulled out their swords, the blades
                                howled in the air.</p><p>The General of the Army issued orders so
                                all-embracing that not even a drop of water could have slipped
                                through them. The Commanding Officer-in-Charge's directives were so
                                strict that even a bird would have had trouble flying around
                                them.</p><p>There was such an-overwhelming sea of soldiers and
                                horses that they stretched out every which way for several hundred
                                furlongs. With clanking golden armour and flashing silver saddles,
                                bounding over hill and forest, they rushed forward tumultuously.
                                Foxes and rabbits raced away in fear. Startled, dragons and snakes
                                outdid each other in scurrying out of sight.</p></q></msItem></msContents></msDescription></body></text></TEI.2>
